<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bed trick</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16082982</id>
    <revision>
      <id>923875342</id>
      <parentid>909316528</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-31T10:29:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot III</username>
        <id>35936988</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Moving [[:Category:Literary techniques]] to [[:Category:Narrative techniques]] per [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2019 October 22#Category:Literary techniques]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7836" xml:space="preserve">{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
The '''bed trick''' is a plot device in traditional literature and folklore; it involves a substitution of one partner in the sex act with a third person (in the words of [[Wendy Doniger]], "going to bed with someone whom you mistake for someone else"). In the standard and most common form of the bed trick, a man goes to a sexual assignation with a certain woman, and without his knowledge that woman's place is taken by a substitute.

==In traditional literature==
Instances of the bed trick exist in the traditional literatures of many human cultures.&lt;ref&gt;Wendy Doniger, ''The Bedtrick: Tales of Sex and Masquerade'', Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; It can be found in the [[Old Testament]]: in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] Chapter 29 [[Laban (Bible)|Laban]] substitutes [[Leah]] for [[Rachel]] on [[Jacob]]'s wedding night, as Jacob discovers the following morning. Other examples range throughout the Western canon (several occur in [[Arthurian legend|Arthurian romance]], as well as in Chaucer's "[[The Reeve's Tale]]") and can be paralleled by instances in non-Western cultures.&lt;ref&gt;Geert Jan Van Gelder, ''Close Relationships: Incest and Inbreeding in Classical Arabic Literature'', New York, I. B. Tauris, 2005; pp. 145–6 and ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Renaissance==
For modern readers and audiences, the bed trick is most immediately and most closely associated with [[English Renaissance theatre|English Renaissance drama]],&lt;ref&gt;Marliss C. Desens, ''The Bed-Trick in English Renaissance Drama: Explorations in Gender, Sexuality, and Power'', Dover, DE, University of Delaware Press, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; primarily due to the uses of the bed trick by [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] in his two dark comedies, ''[[All's Well That Ends Well]]'' and ''[[Measure for Measure]]''. In ''All's Well That Ends Well'', Bertram thinks he is going to have sex with Diana, the woman he is trying to seduce; Helena, the protagonist, takes Diana's place in the darkened bedchamber, and so consummates their arranged marriage. In this case, the bed trick derives from Shakespeare's non-dramatic plot source, the ninth story of the third day in the ''Decameron'' of [[Boccaccio]] (which Shakespeare may have accessed through an English-language intermediary, the version in [[William Painter (author)|William Painter]]'s ''Palace of Pleasure'').&lt;ref&gt;Anne Barton, Introduction to ''All's Well That Ends Well'', in: ''The Riverside Shakespeare'', G. Blakemore Evans, general editor; Boston, Houghton Mifflin, 1974; pp. 499–500.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Measure for Measure'', Angelo expects to have sex with Isabella, the heroine; but the Duke substitutes Mariana, the woman Angelo had engaged to marry but abandoned. In this case the bed trick was not present in Shakespeare's sources, but was added to the plot by the poet.&lt;ref&gt;Anne Barton, Introduction to ''Measure for Measure'', in: ''The Riverside Shakespeare'', pp. 545–6.&lt;/ref&gt;

(Related plot elements can be found in two other Shakespearean plays. In the final scene of ''[[Much Ado About Nothing]]'', the bride at Claudio's wedding turns out to be Hero instead of her cousin, as expected; and in ''[[The Two Noble Kinsmen]]'', the Wooer pretends to be Palamon to sleep with and marry the Jailer's Daughter.)

The two uses of the bed trick by Shakespeare are the most famous in the drama of his era; they were emulated by more than forty other uses, however, and virtually every major successor of Shakespeare down to the closing of the theatres in 1642 employed the plot element at least once.&lt;ref&gt;William R. Bowden, "The Bed Trick, 1603–1642: Its Mechanics, Ethics, and Effects," ''Shakespeare Studies'' 5 (1969), pp. 12–23.&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the bed trick in [[Thomas Middleton|Middleton]] and [[William Rowley|Rowley's]] ''[[The Changeling (play)|The Changeling]]'', in which Diaphanta takes Beatrice-Joanna's place on the latter's wedding night, is probably the most famous instance outside of Shakespeare. Rowley also provides a gender-reversed instance of the bed trick in his ''[[All's Lost by Lust]]'', in which it is the male rather than the female partner in the sexual pair who is substituted. (Male versions of the bed trick are rarer but not unprecedented; a classical instance occurs when [[Zeus]] disguises himself as [[Amphitryon]] to impregnate [[Alcmene]] with the future [[Hercules]]. Similarly in Arthurian legend, [[Uther Pendragon]] takes the place of [[Gorlois]] to impregnate [[Igraine]] with the future [[King Arthur]].)

Multiple uses of the bed trick occur in the works of Thomas Middleton, [[John Marston (poet)|John Marston]], [[John Fletcher (playwright)|John Fletcher]], [[James Shirley]], [[Richard Brome]], and [[Thomas Heywood]].&lt;ref&gt;Desens, p. 11 and ff.&lt;/ref&gt; Shakespeare employs the bed trick to yield plot resolutions that largely conform to traditional morality, as do some of his contemporaries; in the comic subplot to ''[[The Insatiate Countess]]'' (c. 1610), Marston constructs a double bed trick in which two would-be adulterers sleep with their own wives. Shakespeare's successors, however, tend to use the trick in more sensational and salacious ways. In Rowley's play cited above, it leads to the mistaken murder of the substituted man. Middleton's ''[[Hengist, King of Kent]]'' features an extreme version of the bed trick, in which a woman is kidnapped and raped in darkness, by a man she doesn't realise is her own husband.

==Post-Renaissance==
After theatres re-opened with the start of the [[English Restoration|Restoration]] era, the bed trick made sporadic appearances in plays by [[Elkanah Settle]] and [[Aphra Behn]],&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Copeland, ''Staging Gender in Behn and Centlivre: Women's Comedy and the Theatre'', London, Ashgate, 2004; pp. 43, 71–6.&lt;/ref&gt; and perhaps reached its culmination in Sir [[Francis Fane (dramatist)|Francis Fane's]] ''Love in the Dark'' (1675); but in time it passed out of fashion in drama.

Modern critics, readers, and audience members tend to find the bed trick highly artificial and lacking in credibility (though scholar Marliss Desens cites one alleged real-life instance of its employment in Shakespeare's era).&lt;ref&gt;Desens, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also, of course, by modern standards, a form of [[rape by deception]].

==Some other bed-trick plays==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*''[[Blurt, Master Constable]]''
*''[[The English Moor]]''
*''[[The Family of Love (play)|The Family of Love]]''
*''[[A Game at Chess]]''
*''[[The Gamester]]''
*''[[Grim the Collier of Croydon]]''
*''[[The Lady of Pleasure]]''
*''[[Love's Last Shift]]''
*''[[The Marriage of Figaro]]''
{{col-2}}
*''[[A Mad Couple Well-Match'd]]''
*''[[The Novella (play)|The Novella]]''
*''[[The Parliament of Love]]''
*''[[The Queen of Corinth]]''
*''[[The Wedding (1629 play)|The Wedding]]''
*''[[The Widow's Tears]]''
*''[[The Witch (play)|The Witch]]''
*''[[The Wonder of Women]]''
*''[[True Lies]]''
{{col-end}}

==In other media==
In [[Richard Strauss]]'s 1932 opera ''[[Arabella]]'', Zdenka/Zdenko, the daughter consigned to live as a boy because of family finances, contrives to pretend she is her sister Arabella to sleep with Matteo, with whom she is secretly in love.

The bed trick can be seen in [[Eliza Haywood]]'s novel ''[[Love in Excess]]''.

The bed trick is used in [[Roald Dahl]]'s story ''[[The Great Switcheroo]]''.

A variation of the bed trick can also be seen in the movie ''[[Revenge of the Nerds]]''.

The ''[[Family Guy]]'' episode "Peter-assment" features a farcical and unwieldy variation, with Peter hiding Quagmire and Mort under his clothes to have sex with his boss Angela.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Measure for Measure}}
{{All's Well That Ends Well}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:William Shakespeare]]
[[Category:Narrative techniques]]</text>
      <sha1>1d5t5li47hk2wjkv6xibc602okrg288</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
