<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mayanism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2296754</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931197467</id>
      <parentid>926142416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-17T15:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 3 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="23590" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Collection of New Age beliefs}}
{{more citations needed|date=December 2012}}
{{New Age beliefs sidebar}}
'''Mayanism''' is a non-codified eclectic collection of [[New Age]] beliefs, influenced in part by [[Pre-Columbian]]  [[Maya mythology]] and some folk beliefs of the modern [[Maya peoples]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Alexander|1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hoopes|2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Adherents of this belief system are not to be confused with [[Mayanist]]s, scholars who research the historical [[Maya civilization]].

Contemporary Mayanism places less emphasis on contacts between the ancient Maya and [[lost lands]] than in the work of early writers such as [[Godfrey Higgins]], [[Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg]] and [[Augustus Le Plongeon]], alluding instead to possible contacts with [[extraterrestrial life]].  However, it continues to include references to [[Atlantis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Jenkins|2009|pp=304–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notions about extraterrestrial influence on the Maya can be traced to the book ''[[Chariots of the Gods?]]'' by [[Erich von Däniken]], whose [[ancient astronaut theories]] were in turn influenced by the work of [[Peter Kolosimo]] and especially the team of [[Jacques Bergier]] and [[Louis Pauwels]], authors of ''[[Le Matin des magiciens]]''. These latter writers were inspired by the [[fantasy]] literature of [[H. P. Lovecraft]]&lt;ref&gt;Colavito 2005&lt;/ref&gt; and publications by [[Charles Fort]].  However, there remain elements of fascination with [[lost lands|lost continents]] and lost civilizations, especially as popularized by 19th century [[science fiction]] and [[speculative fiction]] by authors such as [[Jules Verne]], [[Edward Bulwer-Lytton]], and [[H. Rider Haggard]].

Mayanism experienced a revival in the 1970s through the work of [[Frank Waters]], a writer on the subject of [[Hopi]] mythology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Waters|1963}}&lt;/ref&gt; His ''Book of the Hopi'' is rejected "as largely ersatz by Hopi traditionalists".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Paper |first= Jordan |title= Native North American Religious Traditions: Dancing for Life |year= 2006 |publisher= Praeger |isbn= 978-0275990978 |page= 38}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, Waters was the recipient of a [[Rockefeller Foundation]] grant to support research in Mexico and Central America.  This resulted in his 1975 book ''Mexico Mystique: The Coming Sixth World of Consciousness,'' a discussion of [[Mesoamerica]]n culture strongly colored by Waters' beliefs in [[astrology]], [[prophecy]], and the lost continent of [[Atlantis]].{{sfn|Waters|1975}}  It has gained new momentum in the context of the [[2012 phenomenon]], especially as presented in the work of [[New Age]] author [[John Major Jenkins]], who asserts that Mayanism is "the essential core ideas or teachings of Maya religion and philosophy" in his 2009 book ''The 2012 Story: The Myths, Fallacies, and Truth Behind the Most Intriguing Date in History.''{{sfn|Jenkins|2009}}

Mayanism has gained renewed vigor due to [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] nonfiction by authors such as [[Erich von Däniken]], [[Zecharia Sitchin]], and [[Graham Hancock]], whose theories range from invoking [[ancient astronauts]] and other [[extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrials]] from outer space to revivals of the idea that ancient peoples from [[lost lands]] brought wisdom and technology to the Mayas. The implication of this is that the Mayas had access to aspects of ancient knowledge, spiritualism, philosophy, and religion that are useful for coping with the modern world, whether by avoiding [[Armageddon]], embracing a mystical [[Apocalypse]], or constructing a future [[Utopia]].

Mayanism has a complex history that draws from many different sources on the fringes of mainstream [[archaeology]].  It has gained growing attention through its influence on [[popular culture]] through [[Pulp magazine|pulp fiction]], [[science fiction]], [[fantasy literature]], and more recently [[Film|cinema]], [[graphic novels]], [[fantasy]] [[role-playing games]] (especially [[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]), and [[video games]].  It has also drawn inspiration from the success of ''[[The Celestine Prophecy]]'' by [[James Redfield]], a novel that refers to the fictional discovery of a Pre-Columbian [[self-help]] manuscript in South America.

Mayanism has been promoted by specific publishing houses, most notably [[Inner Traditions - Bear &amp; Company]], which has produced a number of books on the theme of 2012 by authors such as [[José Argüelles]], [[John Major Jenkins]], [[Carl Johan Calleman]], and Barbara Hand Clow.  [[Tarcher|Jeremy P. Tarcher, Inc.]] has published works by New Age authors [[Daniel Pinchbeck]] and [[John Major Jenkins]] that have further contributed to a growing interest in Mayanism.

==History==
Mayanism can be traced to sources such as the sixteenth-century book ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'' by [[Sir Thomas More]], who developed the concept of a [[utopia]] in the New World (an idea first explored by [[Christopher Columbus]] in his 1501 [[Book of Prophecies]]). During the eighteenth century, speculations about the origins of ancient [[Maya civilization]] sought to associate Maya history with Biblical stories of [[Noah's Ark]], the [[Tower of Babel]], and the [[Ten Lost Tribes]] of Israel. This included speculation about legendary culture heroes such as [[Votan]] and [[Quetzalcoatl]].

In the early nineteenth century, [[Alexander von Humboldt]] and [[Lord Kingsborough]] contributed further to such speculation. Humboldt and Kingsborough were in turn cited by [[Godfrey Higgins]], whose ''[[Anacalypsis]]'' (1833) contributed to the emergence of [[perennial philosophy]] and claims that all religions had a common, ancient origin in a [[Golden Age]] of the distant past.

In the late nineteenth-century, [[Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg]] made significant academic contributions (including re-discovery of the [[Popol Vuh]]), but towards the end of his career became convinced that the ancient Maya culture could be traced to the lost continent of [[Atlantis]].  For example, in 1857 Brasseur identified [[Votan]] as a [[Phoenicia]]n ruler who founded [[Palenque]] and in an article published in 1872 attributed mythological Mesoamerican cataclysms to an early version of [[pole shift theory]]. Brasseur's work, some of which was illustrated by the talented but very inaccurate [[Jean-Frédéric Waldeck]], influenced other works of [[pseudoscience]] and [[pseudohistory]], such as the research of [[Désiré Charnay]], [[Augustus Le Plongeon]], [[Ignatius L. Donnelly]], and [[James Churchward]].  Le Plongeon and Donnelly in turn influenced the work of writers such as [[Madame Blavatsky]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.blavatskyarchives.com/colemansources1895.htm |title=The Sources of Madame Blavatsky's Writings|first= William Emmette |last= Coleman |publisher=Blavatskyarchives.com |accessdate=2012-06-17}} Originally published in {{cite book |title= A Modern Priestess of Isis |last= Solovyoff |first= Vsevolod Sergyeevich |year= 1895 |location= London |publisher= [[Longman]] |chapter= Appendix C |pages= 353–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; who brought misconceptions about the ancient Maya into early New Age circles.{{sfn|Washington|1993}}  These ideas became part of a belief system fostered by psychic [[Edgar Cayce]] in the early twentieth century and later popularized in the 1960s by author [[Jess Stearn]].  One example of early Mayanism is the creation of a group called the Mayan Temple by Harold D. Emerson of Brooklyn, a self-proclaimed Maya ''priest'' who edited a serial publication titled ''The Mayan, Devoted to Spiritual Enlightenment and Scientific Religion'' between 1933 and 1941.{{sfn|Thompson|1970|p=170}}  Attempts at a synthesis of religion and science, a common theme in Mayanism, are one of the contributions from [[Theosophy (Blavatskian)|Theosophy]] while Emerson would be an early example of a [[plastic shaman]] in Mayanism.

==Basic beliefs==
Since Mayanism is used to refer to a diverse collection of beliefs, it has no central doctrine.  However, a basic premise is that the ancient Maya understood aspects of the human experience and human consciousness that remain poorly understood in modern [[Western culture]].  This includes insights into [[cosmology]] and [[eschatology]] as well as lost knowledge of advanced technology and [[ecology]] that, when known, can be used to improve the human condition and create a future Utopia.  However, as a New Age belief system, Mayanism scorns academic scholarship, giving preference to knowledge gained through [[revelation]] and [[prophecy]] and to [[traditional knowledge]] (or what is imagined to be traditional knowledge).  Mayanism literature frequently features beliefs and theories that ignore and reject physical evidence, facts, or knowledge, particularly when that evidence supports the academic ''Mayanist'' theories that contradict ''Mayanism's'' beliefs.  As a result, the beliefs of Mayanism tend to be characterized by a combination of [[esotericism]] and [[syncretism]], rather than being the result of either formal controlled field research or detailed scholarly research that has been based on a broad range of primary sources.

==December 21, 2012==
{{See also|2012 phenomenon}}
The significance of this date in Mayanism stems from the ending of the current ''[[baktun]]'' cycle of the [[Maya calendar]] in 2012, which many believed would create a global "consciousness shift" and the beginning of a new age.  This has come to be known as the [[2012 phenomenon]].  Speculation about this date can be traced to the first edition of ''The Maya'' (1966) by [[Michael D. Coe]], in which he suggested the date of December 24, 2011 as one on which the Maya believed "Armageddon would overtake the degenerate peoples of the world and all creation.".{{sfn|Coe|1966}}  This date became the subject of speculation by [[Frank Waters]], who devotes two chapters to its interpretation, including discussion of an astrological chart for this date and its association with Hopi prophecies in ''Mexico Mystique: The Coming Sixth World of Consciousness'' (1975).{{sfn|Waters|1975}}  The significance of the year 2012 (but not a specific day) was mentioned briefly by [[José Argüelles]] in ''The Transformative Vision: Reflections on the Nature and History of Human Expression'' (1975){{sfn|Argüelles|1975}} and (without reference to the ancient Maya) by [[Terence McKenna]] and [[Dennis McKenna]] in ''The Invisible Landscape: Mind, Hallucinogens, and the I Ching'' (1975).{{sfn|McKenna &amp; McKenna|1975}}

Waters' book inspired further speculation in the mid-1980s, including revision of the date by the McKennas, Argüelles, and [[John Major Jenkins]] to one corresponding with the winter [[solstice]] in 2012.  Interpretations of the date became the subject of further speculation by [[José Argüelles]] in ''The Mayan Factor: Path Beyond Technology'' (1987), promoted for the 1987 [[Harmonic Convergence]]. It received further elaboration in the [[Novelty theory]] of [[Terence McKenna]].  The supposed prediction of an [[astronomical conjunction]] of the [[black hole]] at the center of the [[Milky Way]] galaxy with the winter [[solstice]] [[Sun]] on December 21, 2012, referred to by Jenkins in ''Maya Cosmogenesis 2012: The True Meaning of the Maya Calendar End-Date'' (1998){{sfn|Jenkins|1998}} and ''Galactic Alignment:The Transformation of Consciousness According to Mayan, Egyptian, and Vedic Traditions'' (2002){{sfn|Jenkins|2002}} as having been predicted by the ancient Maya and others, is a much-anticipated event in Mayanism. Although Jenkins suggests that ancient Maya knowledge of this event was based on observations of the "[[dark rift]]" in the Milky Way as seen from Earth (this ''dark rift'', it is said by some Mayan scholars, was believed by some Mayans to be one of the entrances to [[Xibalba]]), others see it as evidence of knowledge imparted via [[ancient astronaut theories|ancient contact with extraterrestrial intelligence]]. The relevance of modern "dark rift" observations to Pre-Columbian and traditional Maya beliefs is strongly debated, and academic archaeologists reject all theories regarding extraterrestrial contact, but it is clear that the promotion of Mayanism through interest in 2012 is contributing to the evolution of religious [[syncretism]] in contemporary Maya communities.  [[Psychonaut]] author [[Daniel Pinchbeck]] popularized [[New Age]] concepts about this date, linking it to beliefs about [[crop circles]], [[alien abduction]], and personal revelations based on the use of [[entheogens]] and [[mediumship]] in his 2006 book ''2012: The Return of Quetzalcoatl''.{{sfn|Pinchbeck|2006}}

[[Carl Johan Calleman]] differs in that he sees 28 October 2011 and not 21 December 2012 as the pivotal end date. Calleman does not see the date as an apocalypse but a slow transformation of consciousness with people beginning to experience a higher 'unity consciousness'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.exopolitik.org/wissen/zukunftswissenschaften/bewusstsein/641-mayakalender-ausblick-auf-den-fuenften-tag-der-neunten-unterweltMaya |title= 
Mayakalender - Ausblick auf den fünften Tag der neunten Unterwelt |trans-title=Mayan calendar - Outlook on the fifth day of the ninth underworld |language= German |date= July 23, 2011 |last= Calleman |first= Carl Johann |work= Exopolitik Deutschland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mayanism, shamanism, and "Toltecs"==
[[Shamanism]] has become a significant component of Mayanism, in part due to the scholarly interpretation of ancient Maya rulers as shamans and the popularity of [[Carlos Castaneda]], whose books described his apprenticeship to a [[Yaqui people|Yaqui]] [[Magician (paranormal)|sorcerer]]. However, Castaneda's work is seen as being fictional, inaccurate, misleading, and [[plagiarism|plagiaristic]], and there is no proof that don Juan (the sorcerer) is not a fictional character.{{sfn|de Mille|1976}}{{sfn|de Mille|1980}} Although the Yaqui are indigenous to the [[Sonoran Desert]] region of northern Mexico and southern Arizona, far from the Maya region, Mayanism often conflates the concept of [[Toltec (Castaneda)]] with the [[Toltec]] who interacted with the ancient Maya.  This stems from 19th century speculations by Brasseur and Charnay about the Toltecs as a white, [[Aryan race]] that brought advanced civilization to the Americas either through a migration from Asia across the Bering Strait (according to Charnay) or emigration from the lost continent of Atlantis (according to Brasseur).{{sfn|Evans|2004}}

==See also==
*[[David Icke]]
*[[Dreamspell]] is a calendar invented by [[José Argüelles]] that is a modern interpretation of the [[Maya calendar]].
*[[List of topics characterized as pseudoscience]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{cite web |author=Aldana, Gerardo |year=2011 |title=Behind Astronomical Patterns |url=http://www.berfrois.com/2011/06/gerardo-aldana-behind-astronomical-patterns/ |publisher=Berfrois |accessdate=2011-06-21}}
* {{cite book |author=Alexander, Dennis |year=1999 |title=Mayanism: A New Look at an Old Religion |location=Pinellas Park, FL |publisher=Sentient Temple Press |isbn=1-880534-10-X |ref={{Harvid|Alexander|1999}}}}
* {{cite book |last= Argüelles |first= José |year=1975 |title=The Transformative Vision: Reflections on the Nature and History of Human Expression |location=Boulder, CO |publisher=Shambhala |isbn=0-394-73067-4 |ref= {{Harvid|Argüelles|1975}}}}
* {{cite book |author=Barrios, Carlos |year=2009 |title=The Book of Destiny: Unlocking the Secrets of the Ancient Mayans and the Prophecy of 2012 |location=New York |publisher=HarperCollins Publishers |isbn=9780061574146 |oclc=191931974 |ref={{Harvid|Barrios|2009}} |url=https://archive.org/details/bookofdestinyunl00barr }}
* {{cite book |last=Calleman |first=Carl Johan |year=2000 |title=Solving the Greatest Mystery of Our Time: The Mayan Calendar |publisher=Garev Publishing International |isbn=978-0-9707558-0-3 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/solvinggreatestm0000call }}
* {{cite journal |last= Chiappari |first= Christopher L. |year=2002 |title=Toward a Maya Theology of Liberation: The Reformulation of a 'Traditional' Religion in the Global Context |journal=Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion |volume=41 |issue=1 |pages=47–67 |issn=0021-8294 |doi=10.1111/1468-5906.00099}}
* {{cite book |last=Coe |first=Michael D. |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |year=1966 |title=The Maya |location=New York |publisher=Praeger Publishers, Inc. |isbn=0-500-05061-9 |ref={{Harvid|Coe|1966}} |url=https://archive.org/details/breakingmayacode00coem_0 }}
* {{cite book |author=Coe, Michael D. |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |author2=[[Mark L Van Stone]] |year=2005 |title=Reading the Maya Glyphs |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |location=London |isbn=978-0-500-28553-4 |url=https://archive.org/details/readingmayaglyph0000coem }}
* {{cite web |last= Colavito |first= Jason |year= 2004 |title= Charioteer of the Gods|url=http://jcolavito.tripod.com/lostcivilizations/id26.html |accessdate=2008-01-14}} Originally published as {{cite journal |last= Colavito |first= Jason |year=2004 |title=Charioteer of the Gods |journal=Skeptic |volume=10 |issue=4}}
*{{cite book |last=de Mille |first=Richard |title=Castaneda's Journey: The Power and the Allegory |year=1976 |location=Santa Barbara, CA |publisher=Capra Press |isbn=0-88496-068-4 |ref={{Harvid|de Mille|1976}} |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/castanedasjourne0000demi }}
*{{cite book |last= de Mille |first= Richard |title=The Don Juan Papers: Further Castaneda Controversies |url= https://archive.org/details/donjuanpapersfur00demi |url-access= registration |year=1980 |location=Santa Barbara, CA |publisher=Ross-Erikson Publishers |isbn=0-534-12150-0 |ref= {{Harvid|de Mille|1980}}}}
*{{cite book |last1= Desmond |first1= Lawrence |first2= Phyllis |last2= Messenger |year= 1988 |title= A Dream of Maya: Augustus and Alice Le Plongeon in Nineteenth Century Yucatan |url= http://maya.csuhayward.edu/archaeoplanet/LgdPage/Dream/Start.htm |format= Online text reproduction |location= Albuquerque, NM |publisher= University of New Mexico Press |isbn= 0-8263-1000-1 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080531035930/http://maya.csuhayward.edu/archaeoplanet/LgdPage/Dream/Start.htm |archivedate= 2008-05-31 }}
* {{cite book |last= Evans |first=  R. Tripp |year= 2004 |title= Romancing the Maya: Mexican Antiquity in the American Imagination, 1820-1915 |location= Austin |publisher= University of Texas Press |isbn= 0-292-70247-7 |ref= {{Harvid|Evans|2004}}}}
* {{cite web |author=Giove, Joseph |year=2007 |title=January 14 Inauguration Concordance |url=http://www.commonpassion.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=72&amp;Itemid=80 |publisher=CommonPassion.org |accessdate=2008-01-14}}
* {{cite book |last=Hoopes |first= John W. |chapter=Mayanism Comes of (New) Age |editor=Joseph Gelfer |title=2012: Decoding the Counterculture Apocalypse |year=2011 |publisher=Equinox Publishing |location=London |isbn=978-1-84553-639-8 |pages=38–59 |ref= {{Harvid|Hoopes|2011}}}}
* {{cite book | last=Jenkins | first=John Major | year=1998 | title=Maya Cosmogenesis: The True Meaning of the Maya Calendar End-Date | location=Santa Fe, New Mexico | publisher=[[Bear &amp; Company]] | isbn=1-879181-48-7 | ref={{Harvid|Jenkins|1998}} | url-access=registration | url=https://archive.org/details/mayacosmogenesis0000jenk }}
* {{cite book |last= Jenkins |first= John Major | year=2002 |title=Galactic Alignment: The Transformation of Consciousness According to the Mayan, Egyptian, and Vedic Traditions | location=Rochester, VT | publisher=[[Inner Traditions]] | isbn=1-879181-84-3 |ref= {{Harvid|Jenkins|2002}}}}
* {{cite book |last= Jenkins |first= John Major | year=2009 |title=The 2012 Story: The Myths, Fallacies, and Truth Behind the Most Intriguing Date in History | location=New York | publisher=[[Jeremy P. Tarcher]]/Penguin |isbn=978-1-58542-766-6 |ref= {{Harvid|Jenkins|2009}}}}
* {{cite book |last= Johnson |first= Kenneth |year=1997 |title=Jaguar Wisdom: Mayan Calendar Magic |location=St. Paul, MN |publisher=Llwellyn Publications |isbn=1-56718-372-7 |ref= {{Harvid|Johnson|1997}}}}
* {{Cite book | last = Mace | first = Carroll Edward | contribution = Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg, 1814-1874| editor-last = Cline | editor-first = Howard F. | title = Handbook of Middle American Indians | volume = 13 | pages = 298–325 | publisher = University of Texas Press | place = Austin | year = 1973 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* {{cite book |last1 =McKenna |first1= Terence |first2= Dennis |last2= McKenna |year=1975 |title=The Invisible Landscape: Mind, Hallucinogens, and the I Ching |location=New York |publisher=Seabury Press |isbn=0-8164-9249-2 |ref= {{Harvid|McKenna &amp; McKenna|1975}}}}
* {{cite book |author=Montgomery, John |authorlink=John Montgomery (art historian) |title=How to Read Maya Hieroglyphs (Hippocrene Practical Dictionaries)|year=2004 |location=New York |publisher=Hippocrene Books |isbn=978-0-7818-1020-3}}
* {{Cite news |author=Painter, James |date=2007-09-06 |title=Task for new Guatemalan president |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7081312.stm |periodical=[[BBC News Online]] (International Edition) |accessdate=2008-01-14 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* {{cite book |last=Pinchbeck |first=Daniel |authorlink=Daniel Pinchbeck |year=2006 |title=2012: The Return of Quetzalcoatl |location=New York |publisher=Penguin Group |isbn=1-58542-483-8 |ref={{Harvid|Pinchbeck|2006}} |url=https://archive.org/details/2012returnofquet00pinc }}
* {{cite journal |author=Sitler, Robert K. |year=2006 |title=The 2012 Phenomenon: New Age Appropriation of an Ancient Mayan Calendar |journal=Nova Religio: The Journal of Alternative and Emergent Religions |volume=9 |issue=3 |pages=24–38 |issn=1541-8480 |doi=10.1525/nr.2006.9.3.024}}
* {{cite book |last= Thompson |first= J.E.S. |year=1970 |title=Maya History and Religion. |url= https://archive.org/details/mayahistoryrelig00thom |url-access= registration |location=Norman |publisher=University of Oklahoma Press |isbn=0-585-16980-2 |ref= {{Harvid|Thompson|1970}}}}
* {{Cite book |last= Van Stone |first= Mark L. |authorlink=Mark L Van Stone |title=2012: Science and Prophecy of the Ancient Maya |year=2010 |location=California |publisher=Tlacaelel Press |isbn=978-0-9826826-0-9}}
* {{Cite web|last=Van Stone |first= Mark|title=It's Not the End of the World: What the Ancient Maya Tell Us About 2012|year=2008|publisher=FAMSI|url=http://www.famsi.org/research/vanstone/2012/index.html|ref=Stone2008}}
* {{cite book |last= Washington |first= Peter |year=1993 |title=Madame Blavatsky's Baboon: A History of the Mystics, Mediums, and Misfits Who Brought Spiritualism to America |location=New York |publisher=Schocken Books |isbn=0-8052-1024-5 |ref= {{Harvid|Washington|1993}}}}
* {{cite book |last= Waters |first= Frank |year= 1963 |title= Book of the Hopi. Drawings and source material recorded by Oswald White Bear Fredericks. |location= New York |publisher= Viking Press |isbn= 978-0-14-004527-7 |ref= {{Harvid|Waters|1963}} |url= https://archive.org/details/bookofhopi00wate }}
* {{cite book |last=Waters |first= Frank |year= 1975 |title= Mexico Mystique: The Coming Sixth World of Consciousness. |location= Chicago |publisher= Sage Books |isbn= 978-0-8040-0922-5 |ref= {{Harvid|Waters|1975}}}}
{{Refend}}

{{Maya}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Maya calendars]]
[[Category:New Age]]
[[Category:Pseudohistory]]
[[Category:Pseudoarchaeology]]</text>
      <sha1>0epi2yb3cp7wqfpiiwer20fy51udg21</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
