<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetics of physical exercise</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42663845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>950506268</id>
      <parentid>949290312</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-12T12:14:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OAbot</username>
        <id>28481209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:OABOT|Open access bot]]: doi added to citation with #oabot.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="21740" xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=May 2014}}

'''Epigenetics of physical exercise''' is the study of [[epigenetic]] modifications resulting from physical exercise to the [[genome]] of cells. Epigenetic modifications are heritable alterations that are not due to changes in the sequence of [[nucleotide]]s.&lt;ref name="Handy"/&gt; Epigenetic modifications, such as [[histone]] modifications and [[DNA methylation]], alter the accessibility to DNA and change [[chromatin]] structure, thereby regulating patterns of [[gene expression]].&lt;ref name="Handy"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Handy DE, Castro R, Loscalzo J | title = Epigenetic modifications: basic mechanisms and role in cardiovascular disease | journal = Circulation | volume = 123 | issue = 19 | pages = 2145–56 | date = May 2011 | pmid = 21576679 | pmc = 3107542 | doi = 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.956839 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Methylated histones can act as binding sites for certain transcription factors due to their bromodomains and chromodomains. Methylated histones can also prevent the binding of transcription factors by hiding the transcription factor's recognition site, which is usually found on the major groove of DNA. The methyl groups bound to the cytosine residues lie in the major groove of DNA, the same region most transcription factors use to read a DNA sequence. A common epigenetic tag found in DNA is the covalent attachment of a methyl group to the C5 position of the cytosine found in CpG dinucleotide sequences.&lt;ref name="Handy"/&gt; CpG methylation is an important mechanism of [[Gene silencing|transcriptional silencing]]. [[Methylation]] of CpG islands is shown to reduce gene expression by the formation of tightly condensed [[heterochromatin]] that is transcriptionally inactive. CpG sites in a gene are most commonly found in the [[Promoter (genetics)|promoter]] regions of a gene while also being present in non promoter regions. The CpG sites in non promoter regions tend to be constitutively methylated, causing transcription machinery to ignore them as possible promoters. The CpG site near promoter regions are mostly left unmethylated until a cell decides to methylate them and repress transcription. Methylation of CpGs in promoter regions result in the transcriptional silencing of a gene. Environmental factors including physical exercise have been shown to have a beneficial influence on epigenetic modifications.

==Effects on cancer==

Physical exercise leads to epigenetic modifications that can have beneficial effects in cancer patients. The effect of physical exercise on DNA methylation patterns leads to increased expression of genes associated with tumor suppression and decreased expression of oncogenes. Cancer cells have non-normal patterns of DNA methylation including hypermethylation in promoter regions for [[tumor-suppressing gene]]s and hypomethylation in promoter regions of oncogenes.&lt;ref name="Handy"/&gt; These epigenetic mutations in cancer cells cause the cell to grow and divide uncontrollably, resulting in tumorigenesis. Physical exercise has been shown to reduce and even reverse these epigenetic mutations, increasing expression levels of tumor-suppressing genes and decreasing expression levels of oncogenes.

Hypermethylation in the promoter regions of tumor suppressor genes is thought to help cause some forms of cancer. The hypermethylation in the promoter regions of the tumor suppressing genes APC and RASSF1A are common epigenetic markers for cancer.&lt;ref name="Coyle"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Coyle YM, Xie XJ, Lewis CM, Bu D, Milchgrub S, Euhus DM | title = Role of physical activity in modulating breast cancer risk as defined by APC and RASSF1A promoter hypermethylation in nonmalignant breast tissue | journal = Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention | volume = 16 | issue = 2 | pages = 192–6 | date = February 2007 | pmid = 17301249 | doi = 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-06-0700 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; The APC gene functions to make sure cells divide properly and maintain a correct number of chromosomes after division has completed. The RASSF1A gene product interacts with the DNA repair protein XPA. Physical exercise has been shown to decrease and even reverse these promoter hypermethylation, lowering the risk of the development of cancer.&lt;ref name="Coyle"/&gt; Decreased hypermethylation patterns reveal a transcriptionally accessible promoter region, allowing for increased expression of the tumor suppressing genes.

Physical exercise increases levels of eustress, or good stress, on the body. This eustress stimulates epigenetic modifications affecting the DNA genome of cancer cells.&lt;ref name="Sanchis-Gomar"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sanchis-Gomar F, Garcia-Gimenez JL, Perez-Quilis C, Gomez-Cabrera MC, Pallardo FV, Lippi G | title = Physical exercise as an epigenetic modulator: Eustress, the "positive stress" as an effector of gene expression | journal = Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research | volume = 26 | issue = 12 | pages = 3469–72 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 22561977 | doi = 10.1519/JSC.0b013e31825bb594 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Environmental conditions, such as eustress, strongly induces expression of the tumor suppressor TP53 gene by influencing epigenetic modifications to be made to the cancer cells genome.&lt;ref name="Sanchis-Gomar"/&gt; The TP53 gene codes for the p53 protein, a protein important in the apoptotic pathway of programmed cell death. The p53 protein is important for the regulation of cell growth and apoptosis, so hypermethylation of the TP53 promoter region are common markers associated with the development of cancer. Other than methylation patterns affecting expression of TP53, [[Micro RNA|microRNAs]] and antisense RNAs control the levels of the p53 protein by regulating expression of the p53 coding TP53 gene.&lt;ref name="Sanchis-Gomar"/&gt;

===Breast cancer===

In a study on the epigenetic effects of physical exercise on breast cancer in women, blood samples from breast cancer patients were collected before and after 6 months of moderate-intensity aerobic exercise.&lt;ref name="Zeng"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zeng H, Irwin ML, Lu L, Risch H, Mayne S, Mu L, Deng Q, Scarampi L, Mitidieri M, Katsaros D, Yu H | title = Physical activity and breast cancer survival: an epigenetic link through reduced methylation of a tumor suppressor gene L3MBTL1 | journal = Breast Cancer Research and Treatment | volume = 133 | issue = 1 | pages = 127–35 | date = May 2012 | pmid = 21837478 | doi = 10.1007/s10549-011-1716-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The test group experienced 129 minutes of exercise on average per week compared to the control group’s 21.8 minutes a week. The study found 43 genes having significant changes in DNA methylation. Of the 43 genes, 3 of the genes experiencing reduced methylation levels were directly correlated with increased survival of breast cancer. The gene L3MBTL1, a known tumor suppressor, had methylation levels decreased by 1.48% in the exercise group while the limited exercise control group experienced a 2.15% increase in methylation.&lt;ref name="Zeng"/&gt; The 1.48% decrease in methylation of L3MBTL1 resulted in greater expression of the tumor suppressor while the 2.15% increase in methylation experienced by the limited exercise control group led to a decrease in expression. The findings of the study showed patients who exercised regularly had lower methylation levels and higher gene expression of L3MBTL1.&lt;ref name="Zeng"/&gt; These patients also experienced a greater than 60% reduction in risk of breast cancer death compared to patients in the limited exercise group.&lt;ref name="Zeng"/&gt;

==Effects on aging==

===DNA methylation===
Epigenetic mechanisms affected by physical exercise have also been seen to be involved in age-related processes. A major component of aging is significant loss of DNA methylation over time.&lt;ref name="Wilson"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wilson VL, Smith RA, Ma S, Cutler RG | title = Genomic 5-methyldeoxycytidine decreases with age | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 262 | issue = 21 | pages = 9948–51 | date = July 1987 | pmid = 3611071 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Methyl deoxycytidine, which is a methylated [[cytosine]] on the 5’ carbon of a cytosine, is involved in the process of [[Cellular differentiation|cell differentiation]] and maintenance. Cell differentiation involves methylation of different areas within the DNA of a cell, which can alter the transcription of genes. During cell differentiation, DNA methylation is important for establishing the identity and function of a cell because of its role in controlling gene expression. A recent study looking at genome DNA methylation of newborn infants and humans aged 100 years or older found that the older individuals had significantly decreased overall DNA methylation.&lt;ref name="Heyn"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Heyn H, Li N, Ferreira HJ, Moran S, Pisano DG, Gomez A, Diez J, Sanchez-Mut JV, Setien F, Carmona FJ, Puca AA, Sayols S, Pujana MA, Serra-Musach J, Iglesias-Platas I, Formiga F, Fernandez AF, Fraga MF, Heath SC, Valencia A, Gut IG, Wang J, Esteller M | title = Distinct DNA methylomes of newborns and centenarians | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 109 | issue = 26 | pages = 10522–7 | date = June 2012 | pmid = 22689993 | pmc = 3387108 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1120658109 | bibcode = 2012PNAS..10910522H }}&lt;/ref&gt; As one ages, the amount of DNA methylation slowly begins to decrease.

Studies have also looked at methyl deoxycytidine residues from tissues collected from rodents at various ages. These studies found that DNA methylation loss increased significantly as the rodent aged.&lt;ref name="Wilson"/&gt; Thus, aging is related to a significant loss in DNA methylation.&lt;ref name="Wilson"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Heyn"/&gt; However, this loss of DNA methylation appears to be slowed by physical exercise under rare conditions, in generel this effect is not very well studied and so far it seems like there is no connection between DNA methylation and physical activity&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang FF, Cardarelli R, Carroll J, Zhang S, Fulda KG, Gonzalez K, Vishwanatha JK, Morabia A, Santella RM | title = Physical activity and global genomic DNA methylation in a cancer-free population | journal = Epigenetics | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 293–9 | date = March 2011 | pmid = 21178401 | pmc = 3092677 | doi = 10.4161/epi.6.3.14378 }}&lt;/ref&gt;. Further studies have looked at the effects of physical exercise on DNA methylation and aging in humans. 

Another component of aging is the gradual shortening of telomeres located at the end of chromosomes. [[Telomere]]s are repetitive sequences located at the end of chromosomes whose purpose are to slow the process of shortening and cell damage which occurs after every cell division as well as stabilize the ends of DNA. Aging and age-related diseases are associated with the significant [[Telomere#Shortening|shortening]] of these sequences. The shrinking of telomeres occurs in somatic cells where telomerase, the enzyme in control of telomere lengthening, is not expressed.&lt;ref name="Henriques"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Henriques CM, Ferreira MG | title = Consequences of telomere shortening during lifespan | journal = Current Opinion in Cell Biology | volume = 24 | issue = 6 | pages = 804–8 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 23127607 | doi = 10.1016/j.ceb.2012.09.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, it has been seen that telomeres can transcribe [[non-coding RNA]], or functional RNAs that do not get translated into protein. Research has demonstrated that some of the non-coding RNAs transcribed at telomeres are involved in heterochromatin formation and stability of the telomeres.&lt;ref name="Heyn"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Shoeftner"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schoeftner S, Blasco MA | title = Chromatin regulation and non-coding RNAs at mammalian telomeres | journal = Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology | volume = 21 | issue = 2 | pages = 186–93 | date = April 2010 | pmid = 19815087 | doi = 10.1016/j.semcdb.2009.09.015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These non-coding RNAs can be positively impacted by physical exercise. Notably, a study found that mice exposed to short-term running phases had increased non-coding RNA transcription at telomeres as compared to sedentary controls.&lt;ref name="Werner"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Werner C, Hanhoun M, Widmann T, Kazakov A, Semenov A, Pöss J, Bauersachs J, Thum T, Pfreundschuh M, Müller P, Haendeler J, Böhm M, Laufs U | title = Effects of physical exercise on myocardial telomere-regulating proteins, survival pathways, and apoptosis | journal = Journal of the American College of Cardiology | volume = 52 | issue = 6 | pages = 470–82 | date = August 2008 | pmid = 18672169 | doi = 10.1016/j.jacc.2008.04.034 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This increase in non-coding RNA transcription aided telomere stability, making the exercise group's telomeres less likely to be as affected by aging over time. Through helping to increase telomere stability, physical exercise can have positive impacts on aging by helping to decreasing the shortening of telomeres.

==Effects on metabolic processes==

In addition to restructuring the muscular and skeletal system to better handle mechanical stress, physical exercise also affects gene expression with respect to metabolism. The effects are widespread and can affect anything from muscle growth to aerobic stamina to diabetes and other metabolic disorders.&lt;ref name="Ntanasis-Stathopoulos"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ntanasis-Stathopoulos J, Tzanninis JG, Philippou A, Koutsilieris M | title = Epigenetic regulation on gene expression induced by physical exercise | journal = Journal of Musculoskeletal &amp; Neuronal Interactions | volume = 13 | issue = 2 | pages = 133–46 | date = June 2013 | pmid = 23728100 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In general, even a small amount of exercise can induce hypomethylation of the whole genome within muscle cells. This means that many regulatory genes can be turned on for pathways like muscle repair and growth. The intensity of the exercise directly correlates to the amount of promoter demethylation, so more strenuous exercise activates more genes.&lt;ref name="Ntanasis-Stathopoulos"/&gt;

MicroRNAs (miRNAs) interfere with mRNA that is present and render it unusable and therefore decrease the product of that mRNA. MiRNAs regulate many physiological processes, such as inflammation, angiogenesis (the creation of blood vessels), as well as ischemia (the restriction of blood flow within the vessels) prevention. Aerobic exercise reduces the overall number of various miRNAs within the skeletal muscle that produce negative effects. Stimuli that cause the body to enter an anabolic, or constructive, phase, such as resistance training as well as the correct diet, has also shown a reduction of miRNAs. This reduction may actually play a role in the growth of the muscle cell.&lt;ref name="Ntanasis-Stathopoulos"/&gt;

Class IIa Histone deacetyltransferases ([[HDAC]]s) are highly expressed within human skeletal muscles. Exercise helps to reduce their activity, especially at promoters, which affects gene expression. In mice, this regulation of HDAC5 has been shown to increase the amount of type I fibers in muscle. Type I fibers are slow twitch, endurance fibers. This data agrees with human data that says the amount of type I fibers is positively correlated with the maximal aerobic capacity.

It also suggested that the amount of type 1 fibers is correlated with a histone acetyltransferase ([[Histone acetyltransferase|HAT]]) that is involved in [[osteoblast]] differentiation and bone formation.&lt;ref name="Ntanasis-Stathopoulos"/&gt;

===Diabetes===

Individuals with [[Diabetes mellitus type 2|type II diabetes]] have hypermethylation of several genes within the muscle, like peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma ([[PPARγ|PPAR-γ]]) and coactivator 1 alpha ([[PGC-1a|PGC-1α]]). The hypermethylation of these genes decreases the expression of both mitochondrial DNA as well as PGC-1α mRNA. Exercise is a way to prevent and treat these effects by helping to hypomethylate PPAR-γ and PGC-1α. Additionally, exercise also increases expression of glucose transporter type 4 ([[Glut4|GLUT4]]), which will also help with diabetes symptoms.&lt;ref name="Ntanasis-Stathopoulos"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ling"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ling C, Groop L | title = Epigenetics: a molecular link between environmental factors and type 2 diabetes | journal = Diabetes | volume = 58 | issue = 12 | pages = 2718–25 | date = December 2009 | pmid = 19940235 | pmc = 2780862 | doi = 10.2337/db09-1003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects on cognition==

Physical exercise causes four types of [[Epigenetics in learning and memory|epigenetic]] alterations that affect [[cognition]].  An extensive 2017 review&lt;ref name=Fernandes&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fernandes J, Arida RM, Gomez-Pinilla F | title = Physical exercise as an epigenetic modulator of brain plasticity and cognition | journal = Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews | volume = 80 | issue =  | pages = 443–456 | date = September 2017 | pmid = 28666827 | pmc = 5705447 | doi = 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.06.012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; describes effects of exercise on the brain due to (1) [[DNA methylation]], (2) [[Histone acetylation and deacetylation|histone acetylation]], (3) [[histone methylation]] and (4) [[microRNA]] expression, and the consequences of these alterations on learning and memory ([[cognition]]).

===DNA methylation===

As summarized in the 2017 review,&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt; in rats, exercise enhances the expression of the gene ''[[Brain-derived neurotrophic factor|Bdnf]]'', which has an essential role in memory formation.   [[Downregulation and upregulation|Enhanced expression]] of ''Bdnf'' occurs through demethylation of its [[CpG site#CpG island promoter|CpG island promoter]] at [[Brain-derived neurotrophic factor#expression|exon IV]].  Demethylation is implemented in part through the actions of [[thymine-DNA glycosylase]] and the [[base excision repair]] system.&lt;ref name="pmid29875631"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bayraktar G, Kreutz MR | title = The Role of Activity-Dependent DNA Demethylation in the Adult Brain and in Neurological Disorders | journal = Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience | volume = 11 | issue =  | pages = 169 | date = 2018 | pmid = 29875631 | pmc = 5975432 | doi = 10.3389/fnmol.2018.00169 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Exercise decreases [[hippocampus]] expression of the gene-repressive [[DNA methyltransferase|DNA methylating enzymes]] DNMT1, DNMT3a and DNMT3b.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt; The hippocampus has important functions in memory, spatial navigation and is part of the [[reward system]]. Exercise also attenuates the global methylation changes induced by stress.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt;

===Histone H3 acetylation===

Exercise causes [[Histone acetylation and deacetylation|acetylation]] of [[histone H3]] in the exon IV promoter region of the ''Bdnf'' gene essential for memory formation.  This acetylation contributes to upregulation of ''Bdnf'' in the brain hippocampi of rats.&lt;ref name="pmid21198979"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gomez-Pinilla F, Zhuang Y, Feng J, Ying Z, Fan G | title = Exercise impacts brain-derived neurotrophic factor plasticity by engaging mechanisms of epigenetic regulation | journal = The European Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 33 | issue = 3 | pages = 383–90 | date = February 2011 | pmid = 21198979 | pmc = 3256007 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-9568.2010.07508.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Two weeks of treadmill exercise improves memory performance in an inhibitory avoidance task.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt;

===Histone H3 methylation===

[[Histone methylation]] can cause transcription repression. Lysine can undergo mono-, di- and tri-methylation.  Di- and tri-methylation of histone H3 at lysine 9 (H3K9) is related to transcription repression.  Mice deficient in a particular histone-methyltransferase gene, [[KMT2A]] (also known as MLL1), in adult excitatory neurons show impairments in hippocampus-dependent memory tasks.&lt;ref name="pmid28082740"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kim S, Kaang BK | title = Epigenetic regulation and chromatin remodeling in learning and memory | journal = Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine | volume = 49 | issue = 1 | pages = e281 | date = January 2017 | pmid = 28082740 | pmc = 5291841 | doi = 10.1038/emm.2016.140 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Aging induces decreases in the global methylation of H3K9 in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt;  However, physical exercise counteracts the aging induced decreases in the global methylation of H3K9.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt;

===microRNA===

Eukaryotic cells can communicate directly with each other through cell–cell contact or at distance by secreting soluble factors such as hormones, growth factors, cytokines and chemokines.  Both RNA and [[microRNA]]s (miRNAs) can be functionally transferred from a donor to a recipient cell via membrane-derived vesicles called [[Exosome (vesicle)|exosomes]].  Similarly to hormones, miRNAs are released into the [[Circulatory system|circulation]] (called circulating miRNAs or c-miRNAs), to affect cells throughout the organism. The c-miRNAs are transported by exosomes, [[Lipoprotein|high-/low-density lipoproteins]], [[Apoptosis|apoptotic bodies]], and RNA-binding proteins. A bout of exercise increases c-miR-223 levels in the circulation in young healthy men, while lack of miR-223 leads to hippocampal-dependent memory deficits and neuronal cell death.&lt;ref name=Fernandes /&gt;

With further knowledge of epigenetic pathways, exercise will continue to show its benefits in all phases of life including but not limited to cancer prevention and treatment, aging, metabolism and metabolic disorders like diabetes and cognition.

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Epigenetics]]</text>
      <sha1>qksiqo43lp1fut2y0seeh6qzgtwympy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
