<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetics of anxiety and stress-related disorders</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>57388876</id>
    <revision>
      <id>950884611</id>
      <parentid>935487821</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-14T10:35:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OAbot</username>
        <id>28481209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:OABOT|Open access bot]]: hdl, doi added to citation with #oabot.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="45423" xml:space="preserve">'''Epigenetics of anxiety and stress-related disorders''' is the field studying the relationship between [[epigenetic]] modifications of genes and [[anxiety]] and [[stress-related disorders]], including mental health disorders such as [[generalized anxiety disorder]] (GAD), [[Posttraumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder]], [[Obsessive–compulsive disorder|obsessive-compulsive disorder]] (OCD), and more.

Epigenetic modifications play a role in the development and heritability of these disorders and related symptoms. For example, regulation of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis by [[glucocorticoid]]s plays a major role in stress response and is known to be epigenetically regulated.

As of 2015 most work has been done in [[animal models]] in laboratories, and little work has been done in humans; the work is not yet applicable to clinical [[psychiatry]].&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015"/&gt;

== Epigenetic writers, erasers, and readers ==
Epigenetic changes are performed by enzymes known as writers, which can add epigenetic modifications, erasers, which erase epigenetic modifications, and readers, which can recognize epigenetic modifications and cause a downstream effect. Stress-induced modifications of these writers, erasers, and readers result in important epigenetic modifications such as DNA methylation and acetylation.

=== DNA methylation ===
[[File:DNA_methylation.svg|thumb|During DNA methylation, cytosine is methylated.]]
[[DNA methylation]] is a type of epigenetic modification in which methyl groups are added to [[cytosine]]s of DNA. DNA methylation is an important regulator of [[gene expression]] and is usually associated with gene repression.

==== MeCP2 ====
Laboratory studies have found that early life stress in rodents can cause phosphorylation of methyl CpG binding protein 2 ([[MECP2|MeCP2]]), a protein that preferentially binds CpGs and is most often associated with suppression of gene expression. Stress-dependent phosphorylation of MeCP2 causes MeCP2 to dissociate from the promoter region of a gene called ''[[Arginine-vasopressin|arginine vasopressin]]'' (''avp''), causing ''avp'' to become demethylated and upregulated. This may be significant because arginine vasopressin is known to regulate mood and cognitive behavior. Additionally, arginine vasopressin upregulates [[corticotropin-releasing hormone]] (CRH), which is a hormone important for stress response. Thus, stress-induced upregulation of ''avp'' due to demethylation might alter mood, behavior, and stress responses. Demethylation of this locus can be explained by reduced binding of DNA methyl transferases (DNMT), an enzyme that adds methyl groups to DNA, to this locus.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Klengel T, Binder EB | title = Epigenetics of Stress-Related Psychiatric Disorders and Gene × Environment Interactions | journal = Neuron | volume = 86 | issue = 6 | pages = 1343–57 | date = June 2015 | pmid = 26087162 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2015.05.036 | department = review | doi-access = free }}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;

MeCP2 is known to have interactions with several other enzymes that modify chromatin (for example, HDAC-containing complexes and co-repressors) and in turn regulate activity of genes that modulate stress response either by increasing or decreasing stress tolerance. For example, epigenetic upregulation of genes that increase stress response may cause decreased stress tolerance in an organism. These interactions are dependent on the phosphorylation status of MeCP2, which as previously mentioned, can be altered by stress.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bellini_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bellini E, Pavesi G, Barbiero I, Bergo A, Chandola C, Nawaz MS, Rusconi L, Stefanelli G, Strollo M, Valente MM, Kilstrup-Nielsen C, Landsberger N | title = MeCP2 post-translational modifications: a mechanism to control its involvement in synaptic plasticity and homeostasis? | journal = Frontiers in Cellular Neuroscience | volume = 8 | issue = | pages = 236 | date = 2014 | pmid = 25165434 | pmc = 4131190 | doi = 10.3389/fncel.2014.00236 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== DNMT1 ====
DNA methyltransferase 1 (DNMT1) belongs to a family of proteins known as DNA methyltransferases, which are enzymes that add methyl groups to DNA. DNMT1 is specifically involved in maintaining DNA methylation; hence it is also known as the maintenance methylase DNMT1. DNMT1 aids in regulation of gene expression by methylating [[Promoter (genetics)|promoter]] regions of genes, causing transcriptional repression of these genes.

DNMT1 is transcriptionally repressed under stress-mimicking exposure both ''in vitro'' and ''in vivo'' using a mouse model. Accordingly, transcriptional repression of DNMT1 in response to long-term stress-mimicking exposure causes decreased DNA methylation, which is a marker of gene activation. In particular, there is decreased methylation of a gene called ''[[FKBP5|fkbp5]]'', which plays a role in stress response as a glucocorticoid-responsive gene. Thus, chronic stress may cause demethylation and hyperactivation of a stress-related gene, causing increased stress response.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Lee_2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lee RS, Tamashiro KL, Yang X, Purcell RH, Huo Y, Rongione M, Potash JB, Wand GS | title = A measure of glucocorticoid load provided by DNA methylation of Fkbp5 in mice | journal = Psychopharmacology | volume = 218 | issue = 1 | pages = 303–12 | date = November 2011 | pmid = 21509501 | pmc = 3918452 | doi = 10.1007/s00213-011-2307-3 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, ''DNMT1'' gene locus has increased methylation in individuals who were exposed to trauma and developed [[Posttraumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder]] (PTSD). Increased methylation of ''DNMT1'' did not occur in trauma-exposed individuals who did not develop PTSD. This may indicate an epigenetic phenotype that can differentiate PTSD-susceptible and PTSD-resilient individuals after exposure to trauma.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Sipahi_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sipahi L, Wildman DE, Aiello AE, Koenen KC, Galea S, Abbas A, Uddin M | title = Longitudinal epigenetic variation of DNA methyltransferase genes is associated with vulnerability to post-traumatic stress disorder | journal = Psychological Medicine | volume = 44 | issue = 15 | pages = 3165–79 | date = November 2014 | pmid = 25065861 | pmc = 4530981 | doi = 10.1017/S0033291714000968 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Transcription factors ====
[[Transcription factor]]s are proteins that bind DNA and modulate the transcription of genes into RNA such as [[Messenger RNA|mRNA]], [[Transfer RNA|tRNA]], [[Ribosomal RNA|rRNA]], and more; thus they are essential components of gene activation. Stress and trauma can affect expression of transcription factors, which in turn alter DNA methylation patterns.

For example, transcription factor nerve growth-induced protein A (NGFI-A, also called NAB1) is up-regulated in response to high maternal care in rodents, and down-regulated in response to low maternal care (a form of early life stress). Decreased NGFI-A due to low maternal care increases methylation of a [[glucocorticoid receptor]] promoter in rats. [[Glucocorticoid]] is known to play a role in downregulating stress response; therefore, downregulation of glucocorticoid receptor by methylation causes increased sensitivity to stress.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid15220929"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Weaver IC, Cervoni N, Champagne FA, D'Alessio AC, Sharma S, Seckl JR, Dymov S, Szyf M, Meaney MJ | title = Epigenetic programming by maternal behavior | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 7 | issue = 8 | pages = 847–54 | date = August 2004 | pmid = 15220929 | doi = 10.1038/nn1276 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Zhang_2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang TY, Labonté B, Wen XL, Turecki G, Meaney MJ | title = Epigenetic mechanisms for the early environmental regulation of hippocampal glucocorticoid receptor gene expression in rodents and humans | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 38 | issue = 1 | pages = 111–23 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 22968814 | pmc = 3521971 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2012.149 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Histone acetylation ===
[[File:Acetylation.png|thumb|During DNA acetylation, lysines are acetylated.]]
[[Histone acetylation and deacetylation|Histone acetylation]] is a type of epigenetic modification in which acetyl groups are added to lysine on histone tails. Histone acetylation, performed by enzymes known as [[histone acetyltransferase]]s (HATs), removes the positive charge from lysine and results in gene activation by weakening the histone's interaction with negatively-charged DNA. In contrast, histone deacetylation performed by [[histone deacetylase]]s (HDACs) results in gene deactivation.

==== HDAC ====
Transcriptional activity and expression of HDACs is altered in response to early life stress.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Levine_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Levine A, Worrell TR, Zimnisky R, Schmauss C | title = Early life stress triggers sustained changes in histone deacetylase expression and histone H4 modifications that alter responsiveness to adolescent antidepressant treatment | journal = Neurobiology of Disease | volume = 45 | issue = 1 | pages = 488–98 | date = January 2012 | pmid = 21964251 | pmc = 3225638 | doi = 10.1016/j.nbd.2011.09.005 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tesone-Coelho_2015"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tesone-Coelho C, Morel LJ, Bhatt J, Estevez L, Naudon L, Giros B, Zwiller J, Daugé V | title = Vulnerability to opiate intake in maternally deprived rats: implication of MeCP2 and of histone acetylation | journal = Addiction Biology | volume = 20 | issue = 1 | pages = 120–31 | date = January 2015 | pmid = 23980619 | doi = 10.1111/adb.12084 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt; For animals exposed to early life stress, HDAC expression tends to be lower when they are young and higher when they are older. This suggests an age-dependent effect of early life stress on HDAC expression. These HDACs may result in deacetylation and thus activation of genes that upregulate stress response and decrease stress tolerance.&lt;ref name="Klengel_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Suri_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Suri D, Bhattacharya A, Vaidya VA | title = Early stress evokes temporally distinct consequences on the hippocampal transcriptome, anxiety and cognitive behaviour | journal = The International Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 17 | issue = 2 | pages = 289–301 | date = February 2014 | pmid = 24025219 | doi = 10.1017/S1461145713001004 | department = primary | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Transgenerational epigenetic influences ==
{{See also|Transgenerational stress inheritance}}

[[Genome-wide association study|Genome-wide association studies]] have shown that psychiatric disorders are partly heritable; however, heritability cannot be fully explained by classical [[Mendelian inheritance|Mendelian genetics]]. Epigenetics has been postulated to play a role. This is because there is strong evidence of transgenerational epigenetic effects in general. For example, one study found transmission of DNA methylation patterns from fathers to offspring during spermatogenesis. More specifically to mental illnesses, several studies have shown that traits of psychiatric illnesses (such as traits of PTSD and other anxiety disorders) can be transmitted epigenetically. Parental exposure to various stimuli, both positive and negative, can cause these transgenerational epigenetic and behavioral effects.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yeshurun S, Hannan AJ | title = Transgenerational epigenetic influences of paternal environmental exposures on brain function and predisposition to psychiatric disorders | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 24 | issue = 4 | pages = 536–548 | date = March 2018 | pmid = 29520039 | doi = 10.1038/s41380-018-0039-z | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parental exposure to trauma and stress ===
Trauma and stress experienced by a parent can cause epigenetic changes to its offspring. This has been observed both in [[Population study|population]] and experimental studies.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;

==== Holocaust ====
An [[Epidemiology|epidemiological]] study investigating behavioral, physiological, and molecular changes in the children of [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]] survivors found epigenetic modifications of a glucocorticoid receptor gene, ''[[NR3C1|Nr3c1]]''. This is significant because glucocorticoid is a regulator of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis (HPA) and is known to affect stress response. These stress-related epigenetic changes were accompanied by other characteristics that indicated higher stress and anxiety in these offspring, including increased symptoms of PTSD, greater risk of anxiety, and higher levels of the stress hormone [[cortisol]].&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2001"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yehuda R, Halligan SL, Bierer LM | title = Relationship of parental trauma exposure and PTSD to PTSD, depressive and anxiety disorders in offspring | journal = Journal of Psychiatric Research | volume = 35 | issue = 5 | pages = 261–70 | date = 2001 | pmid = 11591428 | doi = 10.1016/S0022-3956(01)00032-2 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2008"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Yehuda R, Bierer LM | title = Transgenerational transmission of cortisol and PTSD risk | journal = Progress in Brain Research | volume = 167 | issue = | pages = 121–35 | date = 2008 | pmid = 18037011 | doi = 10.1016/S0079-6123(07)67009-5 | department = review | isbn = 9780444531407 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2014" /&gt;

==== Experimental evidence ====
The effect of parental exposure to stress has been tested experimentally as well. For example, male mice who were put under early life stress through poor maternal care—a scenario analogous to human childhood trauma—passed on epigenetic changes that resulted in behavioral changes in offspring. Offspring experienced altered DNA methylation of stress-response genes such as [[Cannabinoid receptor type 1|CB1]] and [[Corticotropin releasing hormone receptor 2|CRF2]] in the [[Cortex (anatomy)|cortex]], as well as epigenetic alterations in transcriptional regulation gene MeCP2. Offspring were also more sensitive to stress, which is in accordance with the altered epigenetic profile. These changes persisted for up to three generations.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Franklin_2010"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Franklin TB, Russig H, Weiss IC, Gräff J, Linder N, Michalon A, Vizi S, Mansuy IM | title = Epigenetic transmission of the impact of early stress across generations | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 68 | issue = 5 | pages = 408–15 | date = September 2010 | pmid = 20673872 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.05.036 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In another example, male mice were socially isolated as a form of stress. Offspring of these mice had increased anxiety in response to stressful conditions, increased stress hormone levels, dysregulation of the HPA axis which plays a key role in stress response, and several other characteristics that indicated increased sensitivity to stress.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Franklin_2010" /&gt;

==== Inheritance of small-noncoding RNA ====
Studies have found that early life stress induced through poor maternal care alters sperm epigenome in male mice. In particular, expression patterns of [[Non-coding RNA|small-noncoding RNAs]] (sncRNAs) are altered in the sperm, as well as in stress-related regions of the brain.&lt;ref name="Yuan_2016"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yuan TF, Li A, Sun X, Ouyang H, Campos C, Rocha NB, Arias-Carrión O, Machado S, Hou G, So KF | title = Transgenerational Inheritance of Paternal Neurobehavioral Phenotypes: Stress, Addiction, Ageing and Metabolism | journal = Molecular Neurobiology | volume = 53 | issue = 9 | pages = 6367–6376 | date = November 2016 | pmid = 26572641 | doi = 10.1007/s12035-015-9526-2 | department = review | hdl = 10400.22/7331 | hdl-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gapp_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gapp K, Jawaid A, Sarkies P, Bohacek J, Pelczar P, Prados J, Farinelli L, Miska E, Mansuy IM | title = Implication of sperm RNAs in transgenerational inheritance of the effects of early trauma in mice | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 17 | issue = 5 | pages = 667–9 | date = May 2014 | pmid = 24728267 | pmc = 4333222 | doi = 10.1038/nn.3695 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid24896534"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sharma U, Rando OJ | title = Father-son chats: inheriting stress through sperm RNA | journal = Cell Metabolism | volume = 19 | issue = 6 | pages = 894–5 | date = June 2014 | pmid = 24896534 | pmc = 4131544 | doi = 10.1016/j.cmet.2014.05.015 | department = comment }}&lt;/ref&gt; Offspring of these mice exhibited the same sncRNA expression changes in the brain, but not in the sperm. These changes were coupled with behavioral changes in the offspring that were comparable to behavior of the stressed fathers, especially in terms of stress response. Additionally, when the sncRNAs in the fathers' sperm were isolated and injected into fertilized eggs, the resulting offspring inherited the stress behavior of the father. This suggests that stress-induced modifications of sncRNAs in sperm can cause inheritance of stress phenotype independent of the father's DNA.&lt;ref name="Yuan_2016" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Gapp_2014" /&gt;

=== Parental exposure to positive stimulation ===

==== Exercise ====
Just as parental stress can alter epigenetics of offspring, parental exposure to positive environmental factors cause epigenetic modifications as well. For example, male mice that participated in voluntary physical exercise resulted in offspring that had reduced fear memory and anxiety-like behavior in response to stress. This behavioral change likely occurred due to expressions of small non-coding RNAs that were altered in sperm cells of the fathers.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Short_2017"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Short AK, Yeshurun S, Powell R, Perreau VM, Fox A, Kim JH, Pang TY, Hannan AJ | title = Exercise alters mouse sperm small noncoding RNAs and induces a transgenerational modification of male offspring conditioned fear and anxiety | journal = Translational Psychiatry | volume = 7 | issue = 5 | pages = e1114 | date = May 2017 | pmid = 28463242 | pmc = 5534950 | doi = 10.1038/tp.2017.82 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Stress effect reversal ====
Additionally, exposing fathers to enriching environments can reverse the effect of early life stress on their offspring. When early life stress is followed by environmental enrichment, anxiety-like behavior in offspring is prevented.&lt;ref name="Yeshurun_2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Gapp_2016"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gapp K, Bohacek J, Grossmann J, Brunner AM, Manuella F, Nanni P, Mansuy IM | title = Potential of Environmental Enrichment to Prevent Transgenerational Effects of Paternal Trauma | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 41 | issue = 11 | pages = 2749–58 | date = October 2016 | pmid = 27277118 | pmc = 5026744 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2016.87 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar studies have been conducted in humans and suggest that DNA methylation plays a role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mitchell C, Schneper LM, Notterman DA | title = DNA methylation, early life environment, and health outcomes | journal = Pediatric Research | volume = 79 | issue = 1–2 | pages = 212–9 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26466079 | doi = 10.1038/pr.2015.193 | department = review | pmc = 4798238 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) ==
[[Posttraumatic stress disorder|Post-traumatic stress disorder]] (PTSD) is a stress-related mental health disorder that emerges in response to traumatic or highly stressful experiences. It is believed that PTSD develops as a result of an interaction between these traumatic experiences and genetic factors. Evidence suggests epigenetics is a key element in this.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zannas AS, Provençal N, Binder EB | title = Epigenetics of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder: Current Evidence, Challenges, and Future Directions | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 78 | issue = 5 | pages = 327–35 | date = September 2015 | pmid = 25979620 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.04.003 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== DNA methylation ===
Through a number of human studies, PTSD is known to affect DNA methylation of cytosine residues in a several genes involved in stress response, neurotransmitter activity, and more.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;
{| class="wikitable"
|+Human Studies Supporting the Role of DNA Methylation in PTSD&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;
!Genetic Loci
!Finding(s)
|-
|''[[SLC4A4|SLC6A4]]''
|Following trauma exposure, low methylation levels of ''SLC6A4'' increases risk of PTSD; high methylation levels decreases risk of PTSD&lt;ref name="Koenen_2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Koenen KC, Uddin M, Chang SC, Aiello AE, Wildman DE, Goldmann E, Galea S | title = SLC6A4 methylation modifies the effect of the number of traumatic events on risk for posttraumatic stress disorder | journal = Depression and Anxiety | volume = 28 | issue = 8 | pages = 639–47 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21608084 | pmc = 3145829 | doi = 10.1002/da.20825 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''[[MAN2A1|MAN2C1]]''
|Higher ''MAN2C1'' methylation is correlated to greater risk of PTSD in individuals exposed to traumatic events&lt;ref name="Uddin_2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Uddin M, Galea S, Chang SC, Aiello AE, Wildman DE, de los Santos R, Koenen KC | title = Gene expression and methylation signatures of MAN2C1 are associated with PTSD | journal = Disease Markers | volume = 30 | issue = 2–3 | pages = 111–21 | date = 2011 | pmid = 21508515 | pmc = 3188659 | doi =  10.1155/2011/513659| department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''TPR, [[CLEC9A]], APC5, [[ANXA2]], [[TLR8]]''
|PTSD is associated with increased global methylation of these genes&lt;ref name="Smith_2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Smith AK, Conneely KN, Kilaru V, Mercer KB, Weiss TE, Bradley B, Tang Y, Gillespie CF, Cubells JF, Ressler KJ | title = Differential immune system DNA methylation and cytokine regulation in post-traumatic stress disorder | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics. Part B, Neuropsychiatric Genetics | volume = 156B | issue = 6 | pages = 700–8 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 21714072 | pmc = 3292872 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.b.31212 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''[[ADCYAP1R1]]''
|Higher methylation is associated with PTSD symptoms in individuals exposed to trauma&lt;ref name="Ressler_2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ressler KJ, Mercer KB, Bradley B, Jovanovic T, Mahan A, Kerley K, Norrholm SD, Kilaru V, Smith AK, Myers AJ, Ramirez M, Engel A, Hammack SE, Toufexis D, Braas KM, Binder EB, May V | title = Post-traumatic stress disorder is associated with PACAP and the PAC1 receptor | journal = Nature | volume = 470 | issue = 7335 | pages = 492–7 | date = February 2011 | pmid = 21350482 | pmc = 3046811 | doi = 10.1038/nature09856 | department = primary | bibcode = 2011Natur.470..492R }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''LINE-1, Alu''
|Higher methylation of these loci is observed in postdeployed veterans who developed PTSD compared to those who do not develop PTSD&lt;ref name="Rusiecki_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rusiecki JA, Chen L, Srikantan V, Zhang L, Yan L, Polin ML, Baccarelli A | title = DNA methylation in repetitive elements and post-traumatic stress disorder: a case-control study of US military service members | journal = Epigenomics | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 29–40 | date = February 2012 | pmid = 22332656 | pmc = 3809831 | doi = 10.2217/epi.11.116 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''[[SLC26A3|SLC6A3]]''
|High SLC6A3 promoter methylation, combined with a nine-repeat allele of SLC6A3, is correlated to higher PTSD risk&lt;ref name="Chang_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chang SC, Koenen KC, Galea S, Aiello AE, Soliven R, Wildman DE, Uddin M | title = Molecular variation at the SLC6A3 locus predicts lifetime risk of PTSD in the Detroit Neighborhood Health Study | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 7 | issue = 6 | pages = e39184 | date = 2012 | pmid = 22745713 | pmc = 3383758 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0039184 | department = primary | bibcode = 2012PLoSO...739184C }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''[[IGF2]], [[H19 (gene)|H19]], [[Interleukin 8|IL8]], [[Interleukin 16|IL16]], [[Interleukin 18|IL18]]''
|Higher methylation of IL18 but lower methylation of H19 and IL18 is associated with deployed veterans who developed PTSD&lt;&lt;ref name="Rusiecki_2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rusiecki JA, Byrne C, Galdzicki Z, Srikantan V, Chen L, Poulin M, Yan L, Baccarelli A | title = PTSD and DNA Methylation in Select Immune Function Gene Promoter Regions: A Repeated Measures Case-Control Study of U.S. Military Service Members | journal = Frontiers in Psychiatry | volume = 4 | issue = | pages = 56 | date = 2013 | pmid = 23805108 | pmc = 3690381 | doi = 10.3389/fpsyt.2013.00056 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''[[Glucocorticoid receptor|NR3C1]]''
|Lower methylation levels of NR3C1 1B and 1C promoters is associated with PTSD;&lt;ref name="Labonté_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Labonté B, Azoulay N, Yerko V, Turecki G, Brunet A | title = Epigenetic modulation of glucocorticoid receptors in posttraumatic stress disorder | journal = Translational Psychiatry | volume = 4 | issue = 3| pages = e368 | date = March 2014 | pmid = 24594779 | pmc = 3966043 | doi = 10.1038/tp.2014.3 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Fathers with PTSD have offspring with higher NR3C1 1F promoter methylation;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yehuda R, Daskalakis NP, Lehrner A, Desarnaud F, Bader HN, Makotkine I, Flory JD, Bierer LM, Meaney MJ | title = Influences of maternal and paternal PTSD on epigenetic regulation of the glucocorticoid receptor gene in Holocaust survivor offspring | journal = The American Journal of Psychiatry | volume = 171 | issue = 8 | pages = 872–880 | date = August 2014 | pmid = 24832930 | pmc = 4127390 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ajp.2014.13121571 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lower levels of NR3C1 1F promoter methylation is associated with PTSD in combat veterans;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2015"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yehuda R, Flory JD, Bierer LM, Henn-Haase C, Lehrner A, Desarnaud F, Makotkine I, Daskalakis NP, Marmar CR, Meaney MJ | title = Lower methylation of glucocorticoid receptor gene promoter 1F in peripheral blood of veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 77 | issue = 4 | pages = 356–64 | date = February 2015 | pmid = 24661442 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.02.006 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Higher levels of NR3C1 methylation in male (but not female) Rwandan genocide survivors is associated with decreased PTSD risk&lt;ref name="Vukojevic_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vukojevic V, Kolassa IT, Fastenrath M, Gschwind L, Spalek K, Milnik A, Heck A, Vogler C, Wilker S, Demougin P, Peter F, Atucha E, Stetak A, Roozendaal B, Elbert T, Papassotiropoulos A, de Quervain DJ | title = Epigenetic modification of the glucocorticoid receptor gene is linked to traumatic memory and post-traumatic stress disorder risk in genocide survivors | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 34 | issue = 31 | pages = 10274–84 | date = July 2014 | pmid = 25080589 | pmc = 6608273 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1526-14.2014 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

=== Hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis ===
The hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis plays a key role in stress response. Based on several findings, the HPA axis appears to be dysregulated in PTSD. A common pathway dysregulated in HPA axis involves a hormone known as glucocorticoid and its receptor, which aid in stress tolerance by downregulating stress response. Dysregulation of glucocorticoid and/or glucocorticoid receptor can disrupt stress tolerance and increase risk of stress-related disorders such as PTSD. Epigenetic modifications play a role in this dysregulation, and these modifications are likely caused by the traumatic/stressful experience that triggered PTSD.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;

==== NR3C1 ====
''Nr3c1'' is a gene that encodes a glucocorticoid receptor (GR) and contains many GR response elements. Early life stress increases methylation of the 1&lt;sub&gt;F&lt;/sub&gt; promoter in this gene (or the 1&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; promoter analog in rodents). Because of its role in stress response and its link to early life stress, this gene has been of particular interest in the context of PTSD and has been studied in PTSD of both combat veterans and civilians.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;

In studies involving combat veterans, those who developed PTSD had lowered methylation of the ''Nr3c1'' 1&lt;sub&gt;F&lt;/sub&gt; promoter compared to those who did not develop PTSD. Additionally, veterans who developed PTSD and had higher ''Nr3c1'' promoter methylation responded better to long-term psychotherapy compared to veterans with PTSD who had lower methylation. These findings were recapitulated in studies involving civilians with PTSD.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yehuda R, Daskalakis NP, Desarnaud F, Makotkine I, Lehrner AL, Koch E, Flory JD, Buxbaum JD, Meaney MJ, Bierer LM | title = Epigenetic Biomarkers as Predictors and Correlates of Symptom Improvement Following Psychotherapy in Combat Veterans with PTSD | journal = Frontiers in Psychiatry | volume = 4 | issue = | pages = 118 | date = 2013 | pmid = 24098286 | pmc = 3784793 | doi = 10.3389/fpsyt.2013.00118 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt; In civilians, PTSD is linked to lower methylation levels in the T-cells of exons 1&lt;sub&gt;B&lt;/sub&gt; and 1&lt;sub&gt;C&lt;/sub&gt; of ''Nr3c1'', as well as higher GR expression. Thus, it seems that PTSD causes lowered methylation levels of GR loci and increased GR expression.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Labonté_2014" /&gt;

Although these results of decreased methylation and hyperactivation of GR conflict with the effect of early life stress at the same loci, these results match previous findings that distinguish HPA activity in early life stress versus PTSD. For example, cortisol levels of HPA in response to early life stress is hyperactive, whereas it is hypoactive in PTSD. Thus, the timing of trauma and stress—whether early or later in life—can cause differing effects on HPA and GR.&lt;ref name="Labonté_2014" /&gt;

==== FKBP5 ====
''Fkbp5'' encodes a GR-responsive protein known as Fk506 binding protein 51 (FKBP5). FKBP5 is induced by GR activation and functions in negative feedback by binding GR and reducing GR signaling.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Zannas_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zannas AS, Binder EB | title = Gene-environment interactions at the FKBP5 locus: sensitive periods, mechanisms and pleiotropism | journal = Genes, Brain, and Behavior | volume = 13 | issue = 1 | pages = 25–37 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 24219237 | doi = 10.1111/gbb.12104 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Zhang_2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang X, Clark AF, Yorio T | title = FK506-binding protein 51 regulates nuclear transport of the glucocorticoid receptor beta and glucocorticoid responsiveness | journal = Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science | volume = 49 | issue = 3 | pages = 1037–47 | date = March 2008 | pmid = 18326728 | pmc = 2442563 | doi = 10.1167/iovs.07-1279 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Wochnik_2005"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wochnik GM, Rüegg J, Abel GA, Schmidt U, Holsboer F, Rein T | title = FK506-binding proteins 51 and 52 differentially regulate dynein interaction and nuclear translocation of the glucocorticoid receptor in mammalian cells | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 280 | issue = 6 | pages = 4609–16 | date = February 2005 | pmid = 15591061 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M407498200 | department = primary | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is particular interest in this gene because some ''FKBP5'' alleles have been correlated with increased risk of PTSD and development of PTSD symptoms—especially in PTSD caused by early life adversity. Therefore, ''FKBP5'' likely plays an important role in PTSD.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid20393453"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Xie P, Kranzler HR, Poling J, Stein MB, Anton RF, Farrer LA, Gelernter J | title = Interaction of FKBP5 with childhood adversity on risk for post-traumatic stress disorder | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 35 | issue = 8 | pages = 1684–92 | date = July 2010 | pmid = 20393453 | pmc = 2946626 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2010.37 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Binder_2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Binder EB, Bradley RG, Liu W, Epstein MP, Deveau TC, Mercer KB, Tang Y, Gillespie CF, Heim CM, Nemeroff CB, Schwartz AC, Cubells JF, Ressler KJ | title = Association of FKBP5 polymorphisms and childhood abuse with risk of posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms in adults | journal = JAMA | volume = 299 | issue = 11 | pages = 1291–305 | date = March 2008 | pmid = 18349090 | pmc = 2441757 | doi = 10.1001/jama.299.11.1291 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Boscarino_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Boscarino JA, Erlich PM, Hoffman SN, Zhang X | title = Higher FKBP5, COMT, CHRNA5, and CRHR1 allele burdens are associated with PTSD and interact with trauma exposure: implications for neuropsychiatric research and treatment | journal = Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment | volume = 8 | issue = | pages = 131–9 | date = 2012 | pmid = 22536069 | pmc = 3333786 | doi = 10.2147/NDT.S29508 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As mentioned previously, certain ''FKBP5'' alleles are correlated to increase PTSD risk, especially due to early life trauma. It is now known that epigenetic regulation of these alleles is also an important factor. For example, CpG sites in intron 7 of FKBP5 are demethylated after exposure to childhood trauma, but not adult trauma.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Klengel_2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Klengel T, Mehta D, Anacker C, Rex-Haffner M, Pruessner JC, Pariante CM, Pace TW, Mercer KB, Mayberg HS, Bradley B, Nemeroff CB, Holsboer F, Heim CM, Ressler KJ, Rein T, Binder EB | title = Allele-specific FKBP5 DNA demethylation mediates gene-childhood trauma interactions | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 16 | issue = 1 | pages = 33–41 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 23201972 | pmc = 4136922 | doi = 10.1038/nn.3275 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, methylation of FKBP5 is alters in response to PTSD treatment; thus methylation levels of FKBP5 might correspond to PTSD disease progression and recovery.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Yehuda_2014" /&gt;

==== ADCYAP1 and ADCYAP1R1 ====
Pituitary adenylate cyclase-activating polypeptide (ADCYAP1) and its receptor (ADCYAP1R1) are stress responsive genes that play a role in modulating stress, among many other functions. Additionally, high levels of ADCYAP1 in peripheral blood is correlated to PTSD diagnosis in females who have experienced trauma, thus making ADCYAP1 a gene of interest in the context of PTSD.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;

Epigenetic regulation of these loci in relation to PTSD still require further investigation, but one study has found that high methylation levels of CpG islands in ADCYAP1R1 can predict PTSD symptoms in both males and females.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ressler_2011" /&gt;

=== Immune dysregulation ===
PTSD is often linked with immune dysregulation. This is because trauma exposure can disrupt the HPA axis, thus altering peripheral immune function.

Epigenetic modifications have been observed in immune-related genes of individuals with PTSD. For example, deployed military members who developed PTSD have higher methylation in immune-related gene [[Interleukin 18|interleukin-18]] (IL-18).&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Rusiecki_2013" /&gt; This has interested scientists because high levels of IL-18 increase cardiovascular disease risk, and individuals with PTSD have elevated cardiovascular disease risk. Thus, stress-induced immune dysregulation via methylation of IL-18 may play a role in cardiovascular disease in individuals with PTSD.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Uddin_2010"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Uddin M, Aiello AE, Wildman DE, Koenen KC, Pawelec G, de Los Santos R, Goldmann E, Galea S | title = Epigenetic and immune function profiles associated with posttraumatic stress disorder | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 107 | issue = 20 | pages = 9470–5 | date = May 2010 | pmid = 20439746 | pmc = 2889041 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0910794107 | department = primary | bibcode = 2010PNAS..107.9470U }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Smith_2011" /&gt;

Additionally, an epigenome-wide study found that individuals with PTSD have altered levels of methylation in the following immune-related genes: [[Translocated promoter region|TPR]], [[CLEC9A]], [[Anaphase-promoting complex|APC5]], [[ANXA2]], [[TLR8]], [[Interleukin 4|IL-4]], and [[Interleukin 2|IL-2]]. This again shows that immune function in PTSD is disrupted, especially by epigenetic changes that are likely stress-induced.&lt;ref name="Zannas_2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Smith_2011" /&gt;

== Alcohol use disorder ==
Alcohol dependence and stress interact in many ways. For example, stress-related disorders such as anxiety and PTSD are known to increase risk of [[Alcohol Use Disorder|alcohol use disorder]] (AUD), and they are often [[Comorbidity|co-morbid]]. This may in part be due to the fact that alcohol can alleviate some symptoms of these disorders, thus promoting dependence on alcohol. Conversely, early exposure to alcohol can increase vulnerability to stress and stress-related disorders. Moreover, alcohol dependence and stress are known to follow similar neuronal pathways, and these pathways are often dysregulated by similar epigenetic modifications.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Palmisano M, Pandey SC | title = Epigenetic mechanisms of alcoholism and stress-related disorders | journal = Alcohol | volume = 60 | pages = 7–18 | date = May 2017 | pmid = 28477725|pmc=5464725 | doi = 10.1016/j.alcohol.2017.01.001 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Histone acetylation ===

==== HDAC ====
Histone acetylation is dysregulated by alcohol exposure and dependence, often through dysregulated expression and activity of HDACs, which modulate histone acetylation by removing acetyl groups from lysines of histone tails. For example, HDAC expression is upregulated in chronic alcohol use models.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017" /&gt; Monocyte-derived dendritic cells of alcohol users have increased HDAC gene expression compared to non-users.&lt;ref name="Agudelo_2016"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Agudelo M, Figueroa G, Parira T, Yndart A, Muñoz K, Atluri V, Samikkannu T, Nair MP | title = Profile of Class I Histone Deacetylases (HDAC) by Human Dendritic Cells after Alcohol Consumption and In Vitro Alcohol Treatment and Their Implication in Oxidative Stress: Role of HDAC Inhibitors Trichostatin A and Mocetinostat | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 11 | issue = 6 | pages = e0156421 | date = 2016 | pmid = 27249803 | pmc = 4889108 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0156421 | department = primary | bibcode = 2016PLoSO..1156421A }}&lt;/ref&gt; These results are also supported by ''in vivo'' rat studies, which show that HDAC expression is higher in alcohol-dependent mice that in non-dependent mice. Furthermore, knockout of HDAC2 in mice helps lower alcohol dependence behaviors.&lt;ref name="Moonat_2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moonat S, Sakharkar AJ, Zhang H, Tang L, Pandey SC | title = Aberrant histone deacetylase2-mediated histone modifications and synaptic plasticity in the amygdala predisposes to anxiety and alcoholism | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 73 | issue = 8 | pages = 763–73 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23485013 | pmc = 3718567 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.01.012 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt; The same pattern of HDAC expression is seen in alcohol withdrawal, but acute alcohol exposure has the opposite effect; ''in vivo'', HDAC expression and histone acetylation markers are decreased in the amygdala.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017" /&lt;ref name="Moonat_2013" /&gt;

Dysregulation of HDACs is significant because it can cause upregulation or downregulation of genes that have important downstream effects both in alcohol dependence and anxiety-like behaviors, and the interaction between the two. A key example is BDNF (see "BDNF" below).

==== BDNF ====
[[Brain-derived neurotrophic factor]] (BDNF) is a key protein that is dysregulated by HDAC dysregulation. BDNF is a protein that regulates the structure and function of neuronal synapses. It plays an important role in neuronal activation, synaptic plasticity, and dendritic morphology—all of which are factors that may affect cognitive function. Dysregulation of BDNF is seen both in stress-related disorders and alcoholism; thus BDNF is likely an important molecule in the interaction between stress and alcoholism.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Moonat_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moonat S, Pandey SC | title = Stress, epigenetics, and alcoholism | journal = Alcohol Research | volume = 34 | issue = 4 | pages = 495–505 | date = 2012 | pmid = 23584115 | pmc = 3860391 | department = review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, BDNF is dysregulated by acute ethanol exposure. Acute ethanol exposure causes phosphorylation of CREB, which can cause increased histone acetylation at BDNF loci. Histone acetylation upregulates BDNF, in turn upregulating a downstream BDNF target called activity-regulated cytoskeleton associated protein (Arc), which is a protein responsible for dendritic spine structure and formation. This is significant because activation of Arc can be associated with anxiolytic (anxiety-reducing) effects. Therefore, ethanol consumption can cause epigenetic changes that alleviate stress and anxiety, thereby creating a pattern of stress-induced alcohol dependence.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Moonat_2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Pandey_2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pandey SC, Ugale R, Zhang H, Tang L, Prakash A | title = Brain chromatin remodeling: a novel mechanism of alcoholism | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 28 | issue = 14 | pages = 3729–37 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 18385331 | pmc = 6671100 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5731-07.2008 | department = primary }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alcohol dependence is exacerbated by ethanol withdrawal. This is because ethanol withdrawal has the opposite effect of ethanol exposure; it causes lowered CREB phosphorylation, lowered acetylation, downregulation of BDNF, and increase in anxiety. Consequently, ethanol withdrawal reinforces desire for anxiolytic effects of ethanol exposure. Moreover, it is proposed that chronic ethanol exposure results in upregulation of HDAC activity, causing anxiety-like effects that can no longer be alleviated by acute ethanol exposure.&lt;ref name="Palmisano_2017" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Moonat_2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Moonat_2013" /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Behavioral epigenetics]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|32em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin|32em}}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Schiele MA, Domschke K | title = Epigenetics at the crossroads between genes, environment and resilience in anxiety disorders | journal = Genes, Brain, and Behavior | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = e12423 | date = March 2018 | pmid = 28873274 | doi = 10.1111/gbb.12423 | department = review | doi-access = free }}
* {{cite book | vauthors = Bartlett AA, Singh R, Hunter RG | title = Anxiety and Epigenetics | journal = Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology | volume = 978 | issue = | pages = 145–166 | date = 2017 | pmid = 28523545 | doi = 10.1007/978-3-319-53889-1_8 | department = review | isbn = 978-3-319-53888-4 }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Nieto SJ, Patriquin MA, Nielsen DA, Kosten TA | title = Don't worry; be informed about the epigenetics of anxiety | journal = Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior | volume = 146-147 | issue = | pages = 60–72 | date = 2016 | pmid = 27189589 | pmc = 4939112 | doi = 10.1016/j.pbb.2016.05.006 | department = review }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Hing B, Gardner C, Potash JB | title = Effects of negative stressors on DNA methylation in the brain: implications for mood and anxiety disorders | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics. Part B, Neuropsychiatric Genetics | volume = 165B | issue = 7 | pages = 541–54 | date = October 2014 | pmid = 25139739 | pmc = 5096645 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.b.32265 | department = review }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Hunter RG, McEwen BS | title = Stress and anxiety across the lifespan: structural plasticity and epigenetic regulation | journal = Epigenomics | volume = 5 | issue = 2 | pages = 177–94 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23566095 | doi = 10.2217/epi.13.8 | department = review }}
{{refend}}

[[Category:Epigenetics]]
[[Category:Anxiety disorders]]
[[Category:Stress]]
[[Category:Mental health]]</text>
      <sha1>68twwyebwhnh5tebfrz5gw30ymqgban</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
