<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Crosses in heraldry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33363609</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960841910</id>
      <parentid>960841908</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-05T05:55:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/CalvinHuang12|CalvinHuang12]] to version by 213.205.202.79. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3726020) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="36164" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Heraldic crosses Stroehl.png|thumb|300px|Collection of heraldic cross variants, after from [[Hugo Gerard Ströhl]]'s ''[[Heraldischer Atlas]]''.]]
A number of [[cross symbol]]s were developed for the purpose of the emerging system of [[heraldry]], which appeared in western Europe in about 1200. This tradition is partly in the use of the [[Christian cross]] an emblem from the 11th century, and increasingly during the age of the [[Crusades]]. Many cross variants were developed in the classical tradition of heraldry during the late medieval and early modern periods. Heraldic crosses are inherited in modern iconographic traditions and are used in numerous [[national flag]]s.

==History==
{{stack|[[File:Seal of Niketas, commander of the Imperial Fleet.jpg|thumb|9th-century Byzantine seal showing a [[patriarchal cross]] (seal of Niketas, commander of the Byzantine imperial fleet)]]
[[File:Bouchard3.jpg|thumb|upright|Seal of [[Bouchard de Marly]] (attested 1225), ''a cross, quarterly four [[Avalerion|alerions]]''.]]
[[File:Amadeus5.jpg|thumb|upright|Seal of [[Amadeus V, Count of Savoy]] (1249–1323), showing a knight on horseback displaying the Savoy cross on his shield, ''ailets'' (shoulder-pads) and ''caparison'' (horse covering)]]
[[File:The Segar's Roll.jpg|thumb|&lt;small&gt;A section of ''Segar's Roll'', a 17th-century copy of a late 13th-century English [[roll of arms]]. Crosses are shown on the arms of:&lt;ref&gt;see e.g. ''The Publications of the Harleian Society'', Volume 100 (1950), p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt; the legendary [[Prester John]] ([[attributed arms]] showing a full crucifix including the figure of Christ), the [[King of Jerusalem]] (the [[Jerusalem cross]]), the [[Byzantine Empire under the Palaiologos dynasty|Emperor of Constantinople]] ([[Byzantine flags and insignia|the Palaiologos dynasty emblem]] with the ''Beta''s interpreted as [[Crescent (heraldry)|crescents]]), the "[[Principality of Achaea|King of Greece]]", and King [[Edward the Confessor]] of England ([[attributed arms]] showing a cross and five martlets).&lt;/small&gt;]]}}

The [[Christian cross]] emblem ([[Latin cross]] or [[Greek cross]]) was used from the 5th century, deriving from a [[Tau Cross|T-shape]] representing the [[gibbet]] (''[[stauros]]'', ''crux'') of the [[crucifixion of Jesus]] in use from at least the 2nd century. The [[globus cruciger]] and the [[staurogram]] is used in Byzantine coins and seals during the [[Byzantine Empire under the Heraclian dynasty|Heraclian period]] (6th century). Under the [[Byzantine Empire under the Heraclian dynasty|Heraclian dynasty]] (7th century), coins also depict simply crosses [[cross potent|potent]], [[cross patty|patty]] or [[cross pommy|pommy]].

The cross was used as a [[field sign]] by the Christian troops during the [[Crusades]]. In 1188, Kings [[Henry II of England]] and [[Philip II of France]] agreed to launch the [[Third Crusade]] together, and that Henry would use a white cross and Philip a red cross. The red-on-white cross came to be used by the [[Knights Templar]], and the white-on-red one by the [[Knights Hospitaller]] (also white-on-black); the [[Teutonic Order]] used a black-on white version. Early cross or spiral-like shield decorations, not necessarily with Christian symbolism, are already found on depictions of shields of the 11th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vikingage.org/wiki/wiki/Round_Shield_Designs Round Shield Designs (vikingage.org)]: "simple cross": [[Bayeux Tapestry]], "flared cross" Arras, BM MS 559 (435), vol. 1 (c.1000-1050).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[History of heraldry|Heraldry]] emerged in western Europe at the start of the 13th century out of earlier traditions. The basic variants of the red-on-white (termed the [[St George's Cross|Cross of Saint George]]) and the white-on-red crusaders' cross were continued independently in the [[flag]]s of various states in the 13th and 14th century, including the Duchy of [[Flag of Genoa|Genoa]], the Electorate of [[Electorate of Trier|Trier]], the Bishopric of [[Bishopric of Constance|Constance]] and the Kingdoms of [[flag of England|England]] and [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], which last two had special devotions to St George.&lt;ref&gt;Red crosses seem to have been used as a distinguishing mark worn by English soldiers from the reign of [[Edward I of England|Edward I]] (1270s). Perrin (1922) concludes that the introduction of the Cross of St George as a "national emblem" is originally due to Edward I. By 1300, there was also a greater "banner of St George", but not yet in a prominent function; the king used it among several banners of saints alongside the [[Royal Banner of England|royal banner]]. 
"Among the greater banners that of St George was not as yet 
supreme; it was indeed only one of four, for when the Castle of 
Carlaverock was taken in the year 1300: ''Puis fist le roy porter amont / Sa baniere et la Seint Eymont / La Seint George et la Seint Edwart '' [...]" Perrin 1922, p. 37
"The first step towards the promotion of St George to a position of predominance seems to be due to Edward III, who in gratitude for his supposed help at the Battle of Cregy founded the Chapel of St George at Windsor in 1348." Perrin 1922, pp. 37f.
Perrin (1922), ''British Flags'', [https://archive.org/stream/britishflagsthei00perrrich#page/36/mode/2up/ p. 37]
&lt;/ref&gt; on one hand; and [[flag of Savoy|Savoy]], the [[Reichssturmfahne|war flag]] of the [[Holy Roman Empire]] and (possibly from the latter) [[flag of Switzerland|Switzerland]] and [[flag of Denmark|Denmark]] on the other.

The cross appears as heraldic charge in the oldest [[roll of arms|rolls of arms]], from about 1250. A roll of arms of the 13th century (the reign of [[Henry III of England]]) lists the coats of arms of various noblemen distinguished by crosses of different tinctures:
*''[[Roger Bigod, 4th Earl of Norfolk|Le Conte de Norffolk]], d'or a ung crois de goulez'' (viz. red on gold);
*''[[Peter II, Count of Savoy|Piers de Sauvoye]], goules ung crois d'argent'' (white on red): this is [[attributed arms|attributed]], Peter's funerary monument displays an [[eagle (heraldry)|eagle]] on his shield;
*''[[Robert de Vere, 5th Earl of Oxford|Robert de Veer]] d'argent a la crois de goulz'' (red on white).
[[Glover's Roll]] (British Museum Add MS 29796), a 16th-century copy of a roll of arms of the 1250s has depictions of various heraldic crosses, including 
the ''or a cross gules'' of the [[earl of Norfolk]], 
''gules, a cross argent'' of [[Peter II, Count of Savoy|Peter of Savoy]], 
''argent a cross gules'' of [[Robert de Vere, 5th Earl of Oxford|Robert de Veer]],
''gules a cross flory [[vair]]'' of Guillaume de Forz, Comte d'Aumale,
''gules a cross fleury argent'' of Guillaume Vescy,
''gules a cross saltire engrele'' of Fulke de Escherdestone,
''argent a cross fleury azure'' of [[John Lexington]],
''azure three crosses or'' of William de Sarren,
''or a cross gules, five scallops argent'' of Ralph Bigod,
''gules a cross fourchy argent'' of Gilbert de Vale,
''argent a cross fleury sable'' of John Lamplowe,
''or a cross saltire gules, a chief gules'' of [[Robert de Brus, 5th Lord of Annandale|Robert de Brus]],
''gules a cross saltire argent'' of [[House of Neville|Robert de Neville]], ''or a cross voided gules'' of Hamond (Robert) de Crevecoeur,
and ''azure a cross or, four lions rampant or'' of Baudouin Dakeney. In addition, the Glover Roll has ''semy of crosses crosslet'' as a tincture in several coats of arms.&lt;ref&gt;T.D. Tremlett, 'Rolls of Arms of Henri III' in ''Aspilogia'' II, Society of Antiquaries of London (1958).[http://www.heraldique-europeenne.org/Armoriaux/Glover/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

The desire to distinguish one's coat of arms from others led to a period of substantial innovation in producing variants of the basic Christian cross by the early 14th century (in England, the reign of [[Edward II of England|Edward II]]).

The great number of variants of crosses, and the deep history of such variants (going back to the 14th century or earlier) results in confusing and often contradictory terminology.&lt;ref&gt;"heraldic writers have in their ingenuity multiplied the forms. In giving a summary of the chief forms only we are met with the difficulty of many synonyms occurring, for practically the same form is often much varied by incorrect drawing, and much confusion has arisen from blunders of heraldic writers in misreading or misunderstanding the terms employed. The French terms are more varied still than the English, and the correlation of the two series can only be attempted approximately." James Parker, [http://www.heraldsnet.org/saitou/parker/Jpglossc.htm#Cross ''A Glossary of Terms Used in Heraldry'' (1894)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[heraldry of the Holy Roman Empire]], the cross is comparatively rare in the coats of arms of noble families, presumably because the plain heraldic cross was seen as an [[Reichssturmfahne|imperial symbol]] (for the same reason, the eagle was rarely used as a charge because it [[Reichsadler|represented the empire]]), but in the 14th century the plain cross is used in the seals and flags of several [[prince-bishopric]]s, including [[Electorate of Trier|Trier]], [[Bishopric of Constance|Constance]] and [[Electorate of Cologne|Cologne]].&lt;ref&gt;The 14th-century [[Zürich armorial]] has no family coats of arms with crosses, but shows plain crosses in the [[:File:Z wappenrolle 0.jpg|flags of several cities]], including Constance, Speier, Trier and Mainz.&lt;/ref&gt;

Looking back on the crusades as the foundational period of knighthood, the badge of the cross became strongly associated with the idealized Christian [[knight]] of romance, as expressed by Spenser (''[[Faerie Queene]]'' book 1, canto 1):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.readbookonline.net/readOnLine/20388/- |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-02-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304130021/http://www.readbookonline.net/readOnLine/20388/- |archivedate=2016-03-04 }} Retrieved February 27, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
:"And on his brest a bloodie crosse he bore,
:The deare remembrance of his dying Lord, 
:For whose sweete sake that glorious badge he wore,
:And dead, as living ever, his ador'd: 
:Upon his shield the like was also scor'd.

The black-on-white cross worn by the [[Teutonic Knights]] was granted by [[Pope Innocent III|Innocent III]] in 1205. The coat of arms representing the grand master (''Deutschmeisterwappen'')&lt;ref&gt;The offices of ''Hochmeister'' (grand master, head of the order) and ''Deutschmeister'' (''Magister Germaniae'') were united in 1525. The title of ''Magister Germaniae'' had been introduced in 1219 as the head of the bailiwicks in the Holy Roman Empire, from 1381 also those in Italy, raised to the rank of a prince of the Holy Roman Empire in 1494, but merged with the office of grand master under Walter von Cronberg in 1525, from which time the head of the order had the title of ''Hoch- und Deutschmeister''.
[http://www.dr-bernhard-peter.de/Heraldik/Galerien2/galerie1533.htm Bernhard Peter (2011)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150923220548/http://www.dr-bernhard-peter.de/Heraldik/Galerien2/galerie1533.htm |date=2015-09-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is shown with a golden [[cross fleury]] or [[cross potent]] superimposed on the black cross, with the [[Reichsadler|imperial eagle]] as a central inescutcheon. The golden cross fleury overlaid on the black cross becomes widely used in the 15th century. A legendary account attributes its introduction to [[Louis IX of France]], who on 20 August 1250 granted the master of the order this cross as a variation of the [[Jerusalem cross]], with the [[fleur-de-lis]] symbol attached to each arm. While this legendary account cannot be traced back further than the early modern period (Christoph Hartknoch, 1684) there is some evidence that the design does indeed date to the mid 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Helmut Nickel, "Über das Hochmeisterwappen des Deutschen Ordens im Heiligen Lande", ''Der Herold'' 4/1990, 97&amp;ndash;108 ([http://www.mgh-bibliothek.de/dokumente/b/b038670.pdf mgh-bibliothek.de]). Marie-Luise Heckmann, "Überlegungen zu einem heraldischen Repertorium an Hand der Hochmeisterwappen des Deutschen Ordens" in: Matthias Thumser, Janusz Tandecki, Dieter Heckmann (eds.) ''Edition deutschsprachiger Quellen aus dem Ostseeraum (14.-16. Jahrhundert)'', Publikationen des Deutsch-Polnischen Gesprächskreises für Quellenedition. Publikacje Niemiecko-Polskiej Grupy Dyskusyjnej do Spraw Edycij Zrodel 1, 2001, 315&amp;ndash;346 ([http://www.hs-augsburg.de/~harsch/germanica/Chronologie/14Jh/GoldeneBulle/Wappen.htm online edition]). "Die zeitgenössische Überlieferung verdeutlicht für dieses Wappen hingegen einen anderen Werdegang. Der Modelstein eines Schildmachers, der unter Hermann von Salza zwischen 1229 und 1266 auf der Starkenburg ([[Montfort Castle|Montfort]]) im Heiligen Land tätig war, und ein rekonstruiertes Deckengemälde in der Burgkapelle derselben Festung erlaubten der Forschung den Schluss, dass sich die Hochmeister schon im 13. Jahrhundert eines eigenen Wappens bedient hätten. Es zeigte ein auf das schwarze Ordenskreuz aufgelegtes goldenes Lilienkreuz mit dem bekannten Adlerschildchen. Die Wappensiegel des Elbinger Komturs von 1310 bzw. 1319, ein heute in Innsbruck aufbewahrter Vortrageschild des Hochmeisters Karl von Trier von etwa 1320 und das schlecht erhaltene Sekretsiegel desselben Hochmeisters von 1323 sind ebenfalls jeweils mit aufgelegtem goldenem Lilienkreuz ausgestattet."&lt;/ref&gt; The black cross patty was later used for military decoration and insignia by the [[Kingdom of Prussia]] and gave rise to the cross patty in the German ''[[Reichskriegsflagge]]'' and the [[Iron Cross]] and [[Pour le Mérite]] orders.

The [[Nordic cross]] is an 18th-century innovation derived from cross flags adapted as swallow-tailed (or triple-tailed) [[pennon]]s
used as [[civil ensign]]s; the first official introduction of such a flag was in a regulation of 11 June 1748 describing the Danish civil ensign (''Koffardiflaget'') for merchant ships. The Danish design was adopted for the flags of [[flag of Norway|Norway]] (civil ensign 1821) and [[flag of Sweden|Sweden]] (1906), both derived from a common ensign used during the [[Union between Sweden and Norway]] 1818&amp;ndash;1844, [[flag of Iceland|Iceland]] (1915) and [[flag of Finland|Finland]] (1917).

==Ordinary cross==
{{see|Ordinary (heraldry)}}
The blazon ''Cross'' without any addition signifies a [[Ordinary (heraldry)|heraldic ordinary]], a pale and a fess of equal widths conjoined, the width being typically one-fifth of the shield (or one third of the shield when charges are placed on the cross).&lt;ref name=Parker&gt;James Parker, [http://www.heraldsnet.org/saitou/parker/Jpglossc.htm#Cross ''A Glossary of Terms Used in Heraldry'' (1894)].&lt;/ref&gt; The four arms should be of equal length (forming a [[Greek cross]]), as far as possible within the shape of the [[heraldic shield|shield]], and they meet in the center (fesse-point) of the shield, except when it is abased (lowered) in the presence of a [[chief (heraldry)|chief]]. The plain ''cross of gules in a field argent'' is termed the [[Cross of Saint George]].&lt;ref name=Parker/&gt;

{{commonscat|Crosses by emblazonment}}
The ordinary cross may further be modify in its ''flection'' (i.e. modification of its edges as ''engrailed'' (''engreslée''), ''embattled'' (''bretessée''), ''indented'' (''denchée''), ''invected'' (''cannelée''), ''wavy'', (''ondée''), ''raguly'' (''écotée''), ''dancetty'' or ''dantelly'' (''denché'', ''émanchée''), and so on. French heraldic terminology is even more diverse, with many synonyms leading to some confusion.&lt;ref&gt;"we are met with the difficulty of many synonyms occurring, for practically the same form is often much varied by incorrect drawing, and much confusion has arisen from blunders of heraldic writers in misreading or misunderstanding the terms employed." Parker (1894).&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Blason famille fr de Savoie.svg|Gules a cross argent ([[House of Savoy|Savoy]])
File:Horizontaal gedeeld kruis.svg|Or a cross per fess gules and azure
File:Blason ville fr Dinard (Ille-et-Vilaine).svg|Vert a cross [[Ermine (heraldry)|ermine]], in each quarter a pale gules ([[Dinard]])&lt;!--De sinople à la croix d'hermine, chaque canton chargé d'un pal de gueules--&gt;
File:Sable croix engrelée d'or.svg|Sable a cross engrailed or
File:Kryzius 02 Sachmatinis.png|Or [''[[tenné]]''] a cross chequy gules and sable 
File:Blason de la famille du Peloux de Saint Romain.svg|Argent a saltire engrailed azure
File:Arms of John Michael Allen-Petrie.svg|Azure a saltire embattled parted [voided] or ([[Rouge Croix Pursuivant|John Allen-Petrie]])
File:Breedvoetig kruis met afgevlakte voeten.svg|Or a [[cross patty]] throughout sable
&lt;/gallery&gt;
The ordinary cross may also be varied in its tincture, it may be ''party'', or ''chequy, compony, counter-compony, fretty, trellised, vair maçonnée'' and so on. It may also be of two tinctures, e.g. party per fesse, per pale, or per cross (equivalent to quarterly), mostly in connection with the partition of the field (i.e. counter-charged).

{{Commonscat|Crosses quarter pierced}}
The term quarter-pierced (quarterly pierced) is used when the center of the cross has a separate tincture. Some heraldists have used quarter-voided or square-pierced for cases where the center of the cross is given the tincture of the field, or alternatively ''chequy of nine panes'' (French ''équipollée''). A [[Quadrate (heraldry)|cross quadrate]] has a square at the intersection point.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Rond doorboord kruis.svg|Argent a cross azure pierced of the field
File:Vierkant doorboord kruis.svg|Argent a cross vert quarter pierced of the field
File:BullerArms.PNG|Sable on a cross argent quarter pierced of the field four eagles displayed of the first ([[Buller baronets|Buller]]) 
File:ArmsOfBonnellofPurleigh.tif|Argent a cross gules quarterly pierced nine crosses crosslet, three, three, and three counterchanged (the first quarter ermine for distinction) (  (Mary Ann Harvey Bonnell 1841)
&lt;!--File:Colville of Ochiltree arms.svg|Argent a cross moline quarter pierced ([[Clan Colville|Colville of Ochiltree]])--&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{Anchor|Cross voided}}
The cross voided (also ''une fausse croix'') has the same tincture of the field with only a narrow border outlining the limbs. This is equivalent to superimposing one cross upon another (''croix chargée'', or ''remplie'') when the second cross is of the tincture of the field.&lt;ref name=Parker/&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Cross voided wiki.jpg|Argent a cross voided sable
File:Traliekruis.svg|Or a cross triple parted vert
File:Opstina Nova Crnja mali.png|A cross triple parted fretted in the municipal coat of arms of [[Nova Crnja]] (Serbia)
File:Hjelmeland komm.svg|A saltire triple parted fretted in the municipal coat of arms of [[Hjelmeland]] (Norway)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

A voided cross might also be blazoned as [[fimbriated]]. Fimbriated crosses are more common in [[vexillology]], e.g. the fimbriated crosses in the national flags of the [[Union Jack|United Kingdom]], of [[Flag of Norway|Norway]] and of [[flag of Iceland|Iceland]]. The German ''[[Balkenkreuz]]'', introduced originally as identification for German [[Luftstreitkräfte]] in 1918 and later used as a vehicle emblem by the [[Wehrmacht]], if used heraldically&lt;!--which it isn't, at least we don't have an example--&gt; might be blazoned as a cross double fimbriated, or as a voided cross superimposed by a second cross. The "[[Bundeswehr]] cross" is a variant of the ''Balkenkreuz'' using a cross patty.

==Named variants==
{{see|Christian cross variants}}
===Equal limbs===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Picture !! Name!! Description
|-
| [[File:Greek cross.svg|120px]] || Cross hummetty (Cross couped, alaisée, alésée) ||When the ordinary cross is couped it acquires aspects of a [[charge (heraldry)|charge]] (rather than an ordinary), i.e. a [[Greek cross]] with equal limbs. &lt;br/&gt; {{Commons_category-inline|Crosses couped in heraldry}}
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-Pattee-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | [[Cross pattée]] (patty, formée, formy)
|
A cross pattée (or formée/formy) has arms narrowing towards the centre, but with flat ends. It is usually found with curved inside edges as in the 13th c. arms of [[Baron Berkeley]] (see also [[Iron Cross]]); but sometimes encountered with straight edges (triangular arms). A cross pattée must be blazoned as throughout or fixed (''passant''), if it is intended that the four arms of the cross should reach to the edges of the shield. 
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-Potent-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | &lt;span id="cross potent"&gt;[[cross potent]]&lt;/span&gt;
|
This cross has a crossbar at the end of each of its arms. "Potent" is an old word for a crutch, and is used in heraldic terminology to describe a T shape.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Croix cercelée.svg|120px]]
| | [[Cross cercelée]] (recercely)
|
A cross recercely seems to be a cross moline parted or voided throughout—though it may be a cross moline very curly.&lt;ref&gt;Brooke-Little ''An heraldic alphabet'', p 77&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-Moline-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | [[Cross moline]] (anchory)
|
In a cross moline, the ends of the arms are bifurcated, split and curved back, also called a ''cross ancré'' or ''anchory''.
As a mark of [[cadency]] in English and Canadian heraldry, it marks an eighth son.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}
Found in the coats of arms of [[Molyneux]] and of the [[House of Broglie]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross fourchee}}[[File:Cross-Fourchee-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | Cross fourchy (fourchée)
|
One form of the heraldic cross fourchy or cross fourche ({{lang|fr|croix fourchée}} meaning "forked"). An example is the South African Postal Association (South Africa's [http://www.national.archsrch.gov.za/sm300cv/smws/sm300dl Bureau of Heraldry])
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Maltese-Cross-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | [[Maltese Cross (symbol)|Maltese cross]] 
|
With arms which narrow towards the center, and are indented at the ends, also known as the eight-pointed cross (with no curved lines). This is a gradual evolution of the eight-pointed cross moline. The sharp vertex of the modern "four-arrowhead" design is gradual, and takes place during the 15th to 16th century. The "Rhodian cross" of the early 16th century had almost, but not quite, achieved the "sharp arrowhead appearance". The modern form is known as the [[Maltese Cross]] for its use by the [[Order of Malta]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross crosslet}}[[File:Cross-Crosslet-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | Cross crosslet 
|
A cross with the ends of each arm crossed. A prominent early example is in the arms of the [[Thomas de Beauchamp, 11th Earl of Warwick|Beauchamp earls of Warwick]]. In early armory it is not always distinguished from a cross bottony. A variant is the cross crosslet double crossed,&lt;ref&gt;Terminology of Robson, Thomas, The British Herald&lt;/ref&gt; with two bars crossing each arm, as in the arms of [[Robert Willoughby, 1st Baron Willoughby de Broke]] (d.1502) sculpted on his tomb at [[Callington, Cornwall|Callington]] Church, Cornwall.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross bottony}}[[File:Cross-Bottony-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | Cross bottony (trefly)
|
A cross with the ends of the arms ''bottony'' (or ''botonny'', i.e. "furnished with knobs or buttons"), i.e. shaped like a [[trefoil]]—and so it is sometimes called a ''cross trefly''. In early armory it is not always distinguished from a cross crosslet.

It occurs counterchanged on the [[flag of Maryland]]; a saltire botonny can be seen in the coat and flag of the [http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=524&amp;ShowAll=1 Village of New Maryland], New Brunswick; and a Latin cross trefly can be seen in the coat of [http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project-pic.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=1022&amp;ProjectElementID=3517 Isidore Popowych], it also appears in the canon of the arms and flag of the [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-Flory-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | [[Cross fleury]] (flory)
|
A cross whose arms end in [[fleur-de-lys|fleurs-de-lys]] – as in the coats of arms of the [http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=80&amp;ShowAll=1 Municipalité de la Paroisse de Saint-Philémon] in Canada and the [https://www.woking.gov.uk/woking/people/crest Borough of Woking] in England. In early armory it was not consistently distinguished from the ''[[#Cross patoncé|cross patoncé]]''.  A version of the cross flory is used by the Romanian [[Order of Michael the Brave]].  Another version, the "Cross of Saint Julian" (''Cruz de San Julián'') is a special form of the cross fleury used by the Spanish [[Order of Alcántara]], [[Order of Calatrava]] and [[Order of Montesa]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{anchor|Cross patoncé}}[[File:Cross-Patonce-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | Cross patoncé 
|
A cross patoncé (or patonce) is more or less intermediate between a cross pattée and a cross flory (or fleury). The ends of its limbs are trifurcated into leaf shapes, and seems to come in two sorts: one where the limbs are the same width all along as in the coat of [http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project-pic.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=211&amp;ProjectElementID=757 Godfrey McCance Gransden]; and the other where the limbs gently widen from the centre (but do not curve) as in the coat of [http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project-pic.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=71&amp;ProjectElementID=252 John Chiu] (both of Canada). A medieval example is shown on the seal of [[William de Forz, 4th Earl of Albemarle|William de Fortibus]] (d.1260).
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross pommee}}[[File:Cross-Pommee-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | Cross pommy
|
A cross pommy ({{lang|fr|croix pommée}}) has a round knob at the end of each arm, as in the coat of [http://www.civicheraldry.co.uk/cornwall_74to09.html#penwith%20dc Penwith District Council], England.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Gammadion.svg|100px]]
| | [[gammadion|Cross gamma]] (gammate, cramponny)
|
Upright cross with truncated angled arms; essentially a variant of the [[swastika]]; uncommon, but can be found in the arms of Gordon of Hallhead.&lt;ref&gt;''Scots Public Register'' volume 31, page 20&lt;/ref&gt; Also known as a cross '''cramponny''' or '''cramponée''', a '''gammate''' or ''gammadion'' cross, or ''tetragammadion'', as it were combining four capital Greek letters [[Γ]] ([[gamma]]).
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:ArrowCross.svg|120px]]
| | [[Arrow Cross|Cross barby]]
|
In the coat of Tillie in Cornwall (cited in Parker's ''Glossary'', s.v. [http://www.heraldsnet.org/saitou/parker/Jpglossc.htm#Cross%20barby Cross barby]). The symbol is also called a "barbed cross" or an "arrow cross". An arrow cross in green was also the symbol of the [[Arrow Cross Party]] of Hungary.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross erminée.png|120px]]
| | Cross erminée
|
A cross erminée is a cross of four ermine-spots, with the heads meeting, sharing their spots. Historically borne by Hurston (Cheshire, England) c. 1490 and others&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldsnet.org/saitou/parker/Jpglossc.htm#Cross |title=A Glossary Of Terms Used In Heraldry By James Parker |publisher=Heraldsnet.org |accessdate=2013-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-avellane-1.svg|120px]]
| | [[Avellane cross]] 
|
A form of cross which resembles four hazel [[Corylus avellana|filberts]] in their husks or cases, joined together at the great end. The term comes from the Latin name for the hazel, originally {{lang|la|Nux avellana}}. It was fairly rare in English heraldry.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:OrderOfCristCross.svg|120px]]
| | [[Order of Christ Cross]] 
|
A form of cross which resembling a mix between a [[cross pattée]] or the [[cross potent]]. Also known as a "Portuguese Cross", it is associated with the [[Portuguese discoveries]]. It is fairly common in [[Portuguese heraldry]] and [[Brazilian heraldry]].
|-
|}

===Unequal limbs===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Picture !! Name!! Description
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Christian cross.svg|80px]]
| | [[Latin cross]]
| The Latin cross has an elongated lower limb. &lt;br/&gt;{{Commons category-inline|Latin crosses in heraldry}}
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Peter's Cross.svg|80px]]
| | [[Cross of Saint Peter]]
| The inverted Latin cross is known as the Cross of [[Saint Peter]]. &lt;br/&gt;{{Commons category-inline|Cross of Saint Peter in heraldry}}
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Coa Illustration Cross of St Philip.svg |120px]]
| | Cross of Saint Philip
| The sideways Latin cross is associated with [[Philip the Apostle]]. 

|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Coa Illustration Cross St. Gilbert's.svg|110px]]
| | Cross portate
| The oblique Latin cross, known as cross portate, is associated with Saint [[Gilbert of Sempringham]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Calvary cross.svg|80px]]
| | Calvary cross
|A Latin cross standing on steps (mostly three in number) is known as Calvary cross. &lt;br/&gt; {{commons category-inline|Calvary cross in heraldry}}
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross fitchy}}[[File:Croix fitchée.svg|80px]]
| | Cross fitchy 
|A cross fitchy has the lower limb pointed, as if to be driven into the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite NIE|wstitle=Fitchy|year=1905}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite Americana|wstitle=Fitché}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross pattée fitchée}}
[[File:CrossPattéeFitchée.svg|80px]]
| | Cross pattée fitchée
|
A cross pattée fitchée is a cross pattée with a sharp point added to the lower limb, as if for use in staking into the ground
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:St James Cross.svg|80px]]
| | Cross fleury fitchy ([[Cross of Saint James]])
|A special form of the cross flory fitchy is used by the [[order of Santiago]]. Also found in the Scottish arms of Mulino from Venezuela (''Scots Public Register'' volume 87, page 20) and in the coats of [http://www.ngw.nl/int/spa/t/tenerife.htm Santa Cruz de Tenerife], Spain; and [http://www.ngw.nl/int/ven/caracas.htm Caracas], Venezuela; [http://www.ngw.nl/int/afr/moz/santiago.htm Santiago de Tete], Mozambique.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|{{Anchor|Cross crosslet fitchy}}[[File:Croix recroisetée au pied fiché.svg|110px]]
| | Cross crosslet fitchy 
|
Shown here is a ''cross crosslet fitchy'', a very frequent charge in British and French armory, appearing in the arms of the [[House of Howard]], the [[Marquess of Ailsa]], the [[Earl Cathcart]], [[Clan Macpherson|Macpherson of Cluny]], [[Clan Rattray|Rattray of that Ilk]], among many others.
This is probably the most common form of the cross fitchy but others do exist, such as the ''crosses formy fitchy'' found between the antlers of the stag supporters of [http://www.civicheraldry.co.uk/thames_valley_chilterns.html#south%20bucks%20dc South Buckinghamshire District Council], England.
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Patriarchal or Archbishop Cross.svg|80px]]
| | [[Patriarchal cross]]
|The patriarchal cross or double cross was used in Byzantine seals since the early medieval period. It was adopted in the [[coat of arms of Hungary]] in the late 12th century, and also appears on the more recent [[coat of arms of Slovakia]].
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Two-bar cross.svg|70px]]
| [[Two-barred cross]]
| 
A Latin cross with an extra bar added. The lengths and placement of the bars (or "arms") vary, and most of the variations are interchangeably called either of the [[cross of Lorraine]], the [[patriarchal cross]], the [[Orthodox cross]] or the [[archiepiscopal cross]].
|-
|}

===Additional charges===
In some cases, a separate name is given to the ensemble of a heraldic cross with four additional charges in the angles.
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Picture !! Name!! Description
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Cross-Jerusalem-Potent-Heraldry.svg|120px]]
| | [[Jerusalem cross|Cross-and-crosslets]] (a cross potent between four plain crosslets); Jerusalem cross) 
|
The symbol of the Crusader [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]], which existed for almost two hundred years after the First Crusade; in the rendering at left, the large cross is shown slightly "potent" (i.e., with T-shaped ends), but that is not always the case. The four smaller crosses are said to symbolize either the four books of the Gospel or the four directions in which the Word of Christ spread from Jerusalem. Alternatively, all five crosses can symbolize the five wounds of Christ during the Passion. This symbol is used in the [[Flag of Georgia (country)|flag of Georgia]]. Also found in the coat of arms of the Papal Equestrian Order of the Holy Sepulchre of Jerusalem, Vatican City (matriculated in Scotland as "Argent; a Jerusalem cross cantoned between four crosses couped, gules"—Scots Public Register, volume 75, page 112)—to be seen at various [http://www.eohsj.net/ EOHSJ websites]; also in the Canadian coat of Robert Gerald Guest ([http://archive.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=602&amp;ShowAll=1 Canadian Public Register Volume III, page 85]).
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Serbian Cross1.svg|120px]]
| [[Tetragrammatic cross]]
|
A Greek cross with the letter [[Beta|B]] in each of its angles, which represent the imperial motto of the [[Palaiologos]] dynasty (mid-13th century, {{lang|el|βασιλεὺς βασιλέων, βασιλεύων βασιλευόντων}} - {{transl|el|Basileus Basileōn, Basileuōn Basileuontōn}} "King of Kings, Ruling Over Kings"). The [[Serbian cross]] variant with four "firesteel" shapes develops in the early modern [[Illyrian Armorials]].
|-
|}

== Flags ==
{{see|List of national flags depicting a cross}}
[[File:John Ball encouraging Wat Tyler rebels from ca 1470 MS of Froissart Chronicles in BL.jpg|thumb|left|Depiction of [[St George's Flag]] used alongside the [[Royal Standard]] by [[Wat Tyler]]'s rebels in ''[[Froissart's Chronicles]]'' (c. 1470).]]
[[File:AnthonyRoll-1 Great Harry.jpg|thumb|The [[Tudor navy]] [[carrack]] ''[[Henry Grace à Dieu]]'' (launched 1514) as depicted in the 1546 [[Anthony Roll]], with [[Pennon|streamer]]s showing [[St George's Cross]].]]
{{commons|Flags with crosses}}
Flags with crosses are recorded from the later Middle Ages, e.g. in the early 14th century the ''insignia cruxata comunis '' of the city of [[Genoa]], the red-on-white cross that would later become known as [[St George's Cross]], and the white-on-red cross of the ''[[Reichssturmfahne]]'' used as the war flag of the [[Holy Roman Emperor]] possibly from the early 13th century.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}}

Crosses on flags become more widespread in the [[Age of Sail]], as [[maritime flag]]s, and from this tradition develop into [[national flag]]s in the 18th to 19th century, the British [[Union jack|Union flag]] (as naval flag) was introduced in 1606, after the [[Union of the Crowns]]. The [[Nordic cross]] is a modern cross variant used on rectangular flags only, introduced for rectangular [[civil ensign]]s for [[Flag of Denmark|Denmark]] in 1748. This is to be distinguished from the (rare) heraldic charge of a horizontal Latin cross, known as the "Cross of Saint Philipp".

Several national flags are based on late medieval war flags, including the white-on-red crosses of the [[flag of Denmark]] and the [[flag of Switzerland]]. The elongated [[Nordic cross]] originates in the 18th century due to the rectangular shape of maritime flags.

The [[Red Cross]] flag originates in 1906 as a colour-switched version of the flag of Switzerland.

==References==
{{commonscat|Crosses in heraldry}}
{{reflist}}
*William Wood Seymour, [https://archive.org/stream/crossintraditi00seym#page/360/mode/2up "The Cross in Heraldry"], ''The Cross in Tradition, History, and Art'' (1898).

{{Christian crosses}}
{{Heraldry}}

[[Category:Crosses in heraldry| ]]
[[Category:Christian symbols]]
[[Category:Heraldic charges]]</text>
      <sha1>nvb5tfj9q1414qzg5ebmofv46oggdyz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
