<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Joseph Smith Hypocephalus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18057286</id>
    <revision>
      <id>954706348</id>
      <parentid>947142071</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-03T21:28:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith D</username>
        <id>2278355</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove comma</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="25415" xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|For a discussion of the controversy surrounding Joseph Smith's use of the hypocephalus and other papyri see [[Critical appraisal of the Book of Abraham]].}}
{{short description|A papyrus fragment, part of the original Joseph Smith Papyri}}

[[File:Facsimile 2 copy with lacunae circa 1842.jpg|thumb|right|A copy of the Hypocephalus of Sheshonq, from the [[Kirtland Egyptian Papers]]]]
[[Image:Fac2TimesandSeasons.jpg|thumb|right|Facsimile No. 2 from the Times and Seasons, with the missing sections (lacunae) filled in.]]

The '''Joseph Smith Hypocephalus''' (also known as the '''Hypocephalus of Sheshonq'''){{efn|name=fn_a}} was a papyrus fragment, part of a larger collection of papyri known as the [[Joseph Smith Papyri]], found in the Gurneh area of [[Thebes, Egypt]], around the year 1818.&lt;ref name="rhodes1997"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://home.comcast.net/~michael.rhodes/JosephSmithHypocephalus.pdf | archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20061103010005/http://home.comcast.net/~michael.rhodes/JosephSmithHypocephalus.pdf | url-status=dead | archive-date=3 November 2006 | title=The Joseph Smith Hypocephalus . . . Twenty Years Later | accessdate=15 March 2014 | author=[[Michael D. Rhodes|Rhodes, Michael D.]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The owner's name, [[Sheshonq]], is found in the hieroglyphic text on said [[hypocephalus]]. Three hypocephali in the [[British Museum]] (37909, 8445c, and 8445f) are similar to the Joseph Smith Hypocephalus both in layout and text and were also found in Thebes.&lt;ref name="rhodes1997" /&gt;

A woodcut image of the hypocephalus was initially published on March 15, 1842, in Volume III, No. 10 of the [[Latter Day Saint]] newspaper ''[[Times and Seasons]]'', two years before the death of Joseph Smith, who was the editor of the Times and Seasons. This image is included as one of several appendices to the [[Book of Abraham]], where it is called '''Facsimile No. 2'''. The Book of Abraham has been considered [[scripture]] by members of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) since 1880. The location of the original document is unknown.

== Hypocephali ==

{{further|Hypocephalus}}

Hypocephali are small disk-shaped objects, generally made of stuccoed linen, but also of papyrus, bronze, gold, wood, or clay, which were placed under the heads of the dead upon their burial. Hypocephali first appeared during the Egyptian Saite Dynasty (663–525 B.C.) and their use continued for centuries.

They were believed to protect the deceased, causing the head and body to be enveloped in light and warmth, thereby making the deceased divine. Hypocephali symbolized the Eye of Ra (later the Eye of Horus), which represented the sun, and the scenes portrayed on them relate to Egyptian ideas of resurrection and life after death, connecting them with the Osirian resurrection myth.

To the ancient Egyptians, the daily setting and rising of the sun was a symbol of death and rebirth. The hypocephalus represented all that the sun encircles — the world of the living, over which it passed during the day, was depicted in the upper half, and that of the dead, which it crossed during the night, in the lower portion.

As with other hypocephali, the Joseph Smith Hypocephalus contains the Eye of [[Shu (Egyptian deity)|Shu]], the [[Eye of Ra]], or the [[Eye of Horus]], and many other symbolic images which represent elements of ancient Egyptian religious belief. They were part of the burial materials created by Egyptians from the [[Twenty-sixth Dynasty of Egypt|Twenty-sixth Dynasty]] onward. 
 
Within the large circle are compartments containing [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|hieroglyphic text]] and figures which are extracts from Chapter CLXII of the Egyptian [[Book of the Dead]].&lt;ref&gt;The Mummy A Handbook of Egyptian Funerary Archaeology, [[E. A. Wallis Budge]], Second Edition Reprint, pgs. 476-477&lt;/ref&gt; P. J. de Horrack stated that the scenes portrayed in hypocephali relate in all their details to the resurrection and the renewed birth after death...symbolized by the course of the Sun, the living image of divine generation. The circle is divided to represent two [[celestial hemisphere]]s and the cycle of renewal.

==Lacunae and reconstructions==

As stated by LDS Egyptologist [[Michael D. Rhodes]]: "A careful examination of Facsimile No. 2 shows that there is a difference between most of the hieroglyphic signs and the signs on the right third of the figure on the outer edge as well as the outer portions of the sections numbered 12–15. These signs are [[Hieratic]], not hieroglyphic, and are inverted, or upside down, to the rest of the text. In fact, they are a fairly accurate copy of lines 2, 3, and 4 of the Joseph Smith Papyrus XI, which contains a portion of the Book of Breathings. Especially clear is the word snsn, in section 14, and part of the name of the mother of the owner of the papyrus, (tay-)uby.t, repeated twice on the outer edge. An ink drawing of the hypocephalus in the Church Historian's office shows these same areas as being blank. It is likely that these portions were destroyed on the original hypocephalus and someone (the engraver, one of Joseph Smith's associates, or Joseph himself) copied the lines from the Book of Breathings papyrus for aesthetic purposes."&lt;ref name=rhodes1997 /&gt;

==Interpretation of images (Figures No. 1-7, 22-23)==

There is still some ambiguity regarding how these Egyptian names and text may have been pronounced.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.friesian.com/egypt.htm, The Pronunciation of Ancient Egyptian&lt;/ref&gt;

The numbers labeling the figures were added to correspond to explanations of the images and text given by [[Joseph Smith]].

===Figure No. 1===

[[Image:Fac2Fig1.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figures 1, 22, 23]]

The central figure wears the undulating horns of the Ovis longipes ram, which is symbolic of [[Khnum]],&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pg. 95&lt;/ref&gt; the first creator god. Khnum was the potter who molded the souls and bodies of all living things from the clay of the earth, and gave them the breath of life.  He was described as the "ba" (spiritual force) of Re,&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pg. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ida.net/graphics/shirtail/amunre.htm|title=Amun-Re/Chnum - Fig 1 on Hypocephalus examined in light of Egyptological/Archaeological Information&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pg. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; The head of the figure is atypically offset to the right. The crouching body is a typical hieroglyphic pose for the god.&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pg. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

The characters above and to the left of the head are three ripples of water, a pennant and a single diagonal stroke:

&lt;hiero&gt;N35:N35:N35-.-R8-.-Z5&lt;/hiero&gt;

Triple ripples (mw) indicate the global mass of water. Similar to the double ripples of (nn), the "Primeval Waters" or state of being before creation. Described in An's mythological cycle as "the waters," [[Nu (mythology)|Nun]] lay inert, unending and indefinite, until Nun "rises" and "throws off" the waters to begin the act of creation.{{citation needed|date=April 2014}} Nun is a "primordial soup" from which the Self-Created god drew the materials to create its children [[Shu (Egyptian deity)|Shu]] and [[Tefnut]] (air and moisture, the Biblical "firmament"), who then created [[Geb]] (earth) and [[Nut (goddess)|Nut]] (sky).{{citation needed|date=April 2014}}  An [[ideographic]] reading of these symbols would be; The spirit of god rippling the waters.{{efn|name=fn_b}}

Left of center is the [[was scepter]], or DJAM scepter,&lt;ref&gt;The Three Facsimiles from the Book of Abraham (1980), Hugh Nibley&lt;/ref&gt; which are symbols of serenity or strength.&lt;ref&gt;An Egyptian Hieroglyphic Dictionary, E.A. Wallis Budge, pg. cxxxvi&lt;/ref&gt;

To the left, above the scepter, are characters that may be irrigated land, force or effort, and one cubit:&lt;ref&gt;Egyptian Grammar, Gardiner, 3rd Ed, 1982, pgs. 544-545&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;hiero&gt;N23-.-D40-.-D36:Z1&lt;/hiero&gt;

Joseph Smith explained figure 1 as; "Kolob, signifying the first creation, nearest to the celestial, or the residence of God. First in government, the last pertaining to the measurement of time. The measurement according to celestial time, which celestial time signifies one day to a cubit. One day in Kolob is equal to a thousand years according to the measurement of this earth, which is called by the Egyptians Jah-oh-eh."&lt;ref name=pgp&gt;Smith, Joseph; The Book of Abraham: Facsimile No. 2: Explanation - available [[s:Pearl of Great Price/Abraham#Facsimile No. 2|on Wikisource]] and [https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/pgp/abr/fac-2?lang=eng on churchofjesuschrist.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Figures No. 22 and 23===

[[Image:Fac2Fig1.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figures 1, 22, 23]]

On either side of the central, seated figure are baboons with upraised arms, wearing the lunar disk headdress, which represent the Egyptian god [[Thoth]] or Djehuty.  In Egyptian pictiographic writings Thoth was often placed opposite Re, and represented a type of  "night sun". Thoth was associated with truth and integrity, the regulation of time, record keeping and possession of secret knowledge. For example, Thoth provided [[Isis]] with the secret word formula she needed to resurrect [[Osiris]].&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pgs. 215-217.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Egyptian Ideas of the Future Life, Budge, pg. 195&lt;/ref&gt;

Adjacent to the baboons are two snakes which represent the primeval serpent, earth creator god Kematef, Sito or "Iru-to".  In the Pyramid Texts 1146 Iru-to says; "I am the scribe of the Divine Book which says what has been and effects what is yet to be."

Joseph Smith explained figures 22 and 23 as: "the medium of Kli-flos-is-es, or Hah-ko-kau-beam, the stars represented by numbers (figures) 22 and 23, receiving light from the revolutions of [[Kolob]]."&lt;ref name="pgp"/&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 2===

[[Image:Fac2Fig2.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 2]]

The standing figure has a double ram's head with undulating horns and wears the double crown, symbolic of [[Amun]], god of creation. [[Plutarch]] quoted [[Manetho]] as saying that [[Amun]] meant "that which is concealed."

On Amun's shoulders are jackal heads. In his left hand is the staff of [[Wepwawet]] and to the right is an offering stand. Amun spoke his own name and brought forth the land of Egypt from the primordial sea (nun).&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, pgs. 92-93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Budge, Egyptian Ideas of the Future Life, pg. 41 &amp; 45&lt;/ref&gt;

This figure is very similar to one in the same position on the Hypocephalus of Tashenkhons&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ancient-egypt.co.uk/ashmolean/pages/2005-mar-11%20472.htm&lt;/ref&gt; with the exception of lacking the [[ankh]] symbol, orientation of the figure and the associated text. In ancient Egypt it was believed that the gods had a secret name. Knowledge of this name gave others power over them.&lt;ref&gt;[[Understanding Hieroglyphs: A Complete Introductory Guide|Understanding Hieroglyphs]], Hilary Wilson, 1993, pg. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Michael D. Rhodes]] identified the hieroglyphs to the left as: "The name of this Mighty God."  {{Hiero|"The name of this Mighty God."&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lightplanet.com/response/BofAbraham/jshypo.htm|title=Joseph Smith Hypocephalus|first=Michael D.|last=Rhodes|website=www.lightplanet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;|&lt;hiero&gt;D21-N35:N35-R8-Z1-Q3:I9-O29:Z1:D36&lt;/hiero&gt;}}

This reading identifies/represents the name of the god without actually writing it, similar to the use of [[YHWH]] in Hebrew texts.

Joseph Smith stated that this figure; "Stands next to [[Kolob]], called by the Egyptians [[Oliblish]], which is the next grand governing creation near to the celestial or the place where God resides; holding the key of power also, pertaining to other planets; as revealed from God to Abraham, as he offered sacrifice upon an altar, which he had built unto the Lord."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 3===

[[Image:Fac2Fig3.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 3]]
[[File:TaSheritMin Scroll Vignette barque.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Vignette from the Ta-Sherit-Min scroll, where Figure No. 3 probably came from.]]

Figure 3 is located in the missing section of the Hypocephalus.  Prior to printing, the section was filled in.  The text on the rim surrounding the figure has been replaced by text from the unrelated [[Breathing Permit of Hôr]].&lt;ref name="Nibley, Hugh 2010. pg. 269"&gt;Nibley, Hugh, et al. One Eternal Round. Deseret Book, 2010. pg. 269&lt;/ref&gt;  Similarly, figure 3 is also foreign to the Hypocephalus.  As [[Hugh Nibley]] noted, "The boat in the picture is identical with another piece of Joseph Smith Papyrus, namely [[Joseph Smith Papyri#Book of Joseph Scroll or Book of the Dead for TaSheritMin|JSP IV]], which accompanies chapter 101 of the Book of the Dead.".&lt;ref name="Nibley, Hugh 2010. pg. 269"/&gt;  Despite the striking resemblance, Nibley and some other apologists feel that the boat is inspired, because boats sometimes do appear in that section on Hypocephali.  Egyptologists dispute this, arguing that just like the surrounding text, the inclusion by Joseph Smith (or his engravers) is irrelevant.&lt;ref&gt;Ritner, Robert Kriech. The Joseph Smith Egyptian Papyri: a Complete Edition ; P. JS 1-4 and the Hypocephalus of Sheshonq. The Smith Pettit Foundation, 2013. page 268&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;div&gt;A [[solar barque]] carrying the seated falcon headed god [[Ra|Re]],&lt;ref name="rhodes1997"/&gt; holding a [[was (sceptre)|was]] scepter. The solar disk is over Re's head. A divine [[Eye of Horus]] (&lt;div style="display:inline;"&gt;[[File:Eye of Ra2.svg|frameless|24px]]&lt;/div&gt;) is on both sides of Re and the solar barque.&lt;/div&gt;

Also on the barque is an offering stand.  The two characters farthest to the left may be an attempt to engrave dp.t ntr, which would translate as "Divine Ship":&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

&lt;hiero&gt;R8-P1&lt;/hiero&gt;

Alternatively, the entire row may be ideograms for a lotus flower (ssn) or grass (hn), a vaulted covering (ipt), a snake (similar to the one found at the foot of figure 23) (it 'father'?) and a sealed papyrus roll (md3t).&lt;ref&gt;[[Hieroglyphics: The Writings of Ancient Egypt]], Maria Carmela Betrò, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;hiero&gt;M9-O46-I9-Y1&lt;/hiero&gt;

In the religious tradition of ancient Heliopolis, Ra emerged from the petals of a lotus blossom which re-enfolded him each night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shira.net/symbols.htm|title=Symbols From The Middle East&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lotus was also a symbol of rebirth associated with Osiris. The [[Book of the Dead]] contains spells for "transforming oneself into a lotus", fulfilling the promise of resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egyptianmyths.net/lotus.htm|title=Ancient Egypt: the Mythology - Lotus|website=www.egyptianmyths.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Pyramid Texts]] the snake Iru-to was the scribe of the Divine Book which said what has been and effects what is yet to be.

Joseph Smith's interpretation: "Is made to represent God, sitting upon his throne, clothed with power and authority; with a crown of eternal light upon his head; representing also the grand Key-words of the [[Melchizedek Priesthood|Holy Priesthood]], as revealed to Adam in the Garden of Eden, as also to Seth, Noah, Melchizedek, Abraham, and all to whom the Priesthood was revealed."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 4===

[[Image:Fac2Fig4.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 4]]

A falcon, representing [[Horus]], 'lord of the sky',&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt, pg. 200&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Seker|Sokar]]&lt;ref name=rhodes1997 /&gt; sitting on a mummy case, with outstreatched wings, sitting upon a papyrus boat. This image is similar to the one in the same panel from the hypocephalus of Tashenkhons,&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient-egypt.co.uk/ashmolean/pages/2005-mar-11%20472.htm|title=Two Hypocephali&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the exception of the rudder and text. The Coffin Texts state; "He takes the ship of 1000 cubits from end to end and he sails it to the stairway of fire."

Joseph Smith's interpretation: "Answers to the Hebrew word [[Firmament#Translation|Raukeeyang]], signifying expanse, or the firmament of the heavens; also a numerical figure, in Egyptian signifying one thousand; answering to the measuring of the time of Oliblish, which is equal with Kolob in its revolution and in its measuring of time."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 5===

[[Image:Fac2Fig5.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 5]]

A cow, representing Hathor, who was the goddess of the sky, home of the great falcon. Behind is a standing female figure with the [[Eye of Horus]] depicted on her head and holding out a papyrus stem in her left hand.  This image is similar to the one in the same panel from the hypocephalus of Tashenkhons.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

Joseph Smith's interpretation: "Is called in Egyptian Enish-go-on-dosh; this is one of the governing planets also, and is said by the Egyptians to be the Sun, and to borrow its light from Kolob through the medium of Kae-e-vanrash, which is the grand Key, or, in other words, the governing power, which governs fifteen other fixed planets or stars, as also Floeese or the Moon, the Earth and the Sun in their annual revolutions. This planet receives its power through the medium of Kli-flos-is-es, or Hah-ko-kau-beam, the stars represented by numbers 22 and 23, receiving light from the revolutions of Kolob."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 6===

[[Image:Fac2Fig6.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 6]]

Four standing mummiform figures, representing the four sons of [[Horus]] (left to right); [[Imsety]], [[Hapy]], [[Duamutef]]  and Qebesenuef, with the heads of a human, baboon, jackal, and falcon, who were associated with the south, north, east and west. They were the patron gods of the liver, lungs, stomach and intestines of the deceased and were protected by [[Isis]], [[Nephthys]], [[Neith]] and [[Serket]].&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, Richard H. Wilkinson, 2003, pg. 88&lt;/ref&gt; The figures behind them are typically a lotus stem (h3), lion and ram.

Joseph Smith's interpretation: "Represents this earth in its four quarters."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

===Figure No. 7===

[[Image:Fac2Fig7.jpg|thumb|right|Detail of Figure No. 7]]

A seated figure with the tail of a falcon, symbolic of the supreme celestial deity,&lt;ref&gt;The Thames and Hudson Dictionary of Egypt, Toby Wilkinson , 2005, pg. 79&lt;/ref&gt; with a human head and a pharonic beard. This figure has been identified with [[Min (god)|Min]], a predynastic god who was usually depicted as a mummy wrapped ithyphallic man with his legs bound together, wearing a twin plumed crown with long streamers and with his arm raised to the square,&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, pg. 115-116&lt;/ref&gt; a gesture identified as the Sign of Preservation.&lt;ref&gt;Secret Sign Languages by J.S.M. Ward, M.A., Land's End Press, 1969, pgs. 13-14&lt;/ref&gt; Behind his head is an inverted V. A right angle projects to the right of the shoulder.  To the left is a figure with a bird's head, presenting the [[Eye of Horus|Eye of Ra]].  In the hypocephalus of Tashenkhons,&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; the figure on the left is Nehebu-Kau, whose name meant "he who harnesses the spirits" and the inverted V is a [[flail]], symbolic of provenance.&lt;ref&gt;The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Egypt, pgs. 224-225&lt;/ref&gt;

Joseph Smith's interpretation:"Represents God sitting upon his throne, revealing through the heavens the grand Key-words of the Priesthood; as, also, the sign of the Holy Ghost unto Abraham, in the form of a dove."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

{{clear}}

==Text to the left (Figures No. 8-11)==

{| border="1"
|-
!Figure No. 11
![[Image:Fac2Fig11.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 11]]
!"O god, sleeping in the time"
|-
!Figure No. 10
![[Image:Fac2Fig10.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 10]]
!"of the beginning. Great God, Lord of Heaven and earth,"
|-
!Figure No. 9
![[Image:Fac2Fig9.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 9]]
!"and below the earth and of the waters" (Damaged in the original.)
|-
!Figure No. 8
![[Image:Fac2Fig8.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 8]]
!"Grant that the Ba of Osiris Sheshonq live."
|-
|}

[[Theodule Deveria]] gave the following translation: "O great God in Sekhem; O great God, Lord of heaven, earth and hell. ... Osiris S'es'enq."&lt;ref name=deveria&gt;Quoted here: https://books.google.com/books?id=UEgOAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA515&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Michael D. Rhodes]] gives the following translation: "O God of the Sleeping Ones from the time of the creation.  O Mighty God, Lord of heaven and earth, of the hereafter, and of his great waters, may the soul of the Osiris Shishaq be granted life."&lt;ref name="rhodes1997" /&gt;

Robert K. Ritner gives the following translation: "O noble god from the beginning of time, great god, lord of heaven, earth, underworld, waters &lt;nowiki&gt;[and mountains,]&lt;/nowiki&gt; cause the ''ba''-spirit of the Osiris Sheshonq to live." (brackets and italics in original)&lt;ref name="ritnerxmission"&gt;Quoted and attributed here: http://user.xmission.com/~research/mormonpdf/hypocephalus3.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Joseph Smith said of figure 8 in particular, "Contains writings that cannot be revealed unto the world; but is to be had in the Holy Temple of God."&lt;ref name=pgp /&gt;

==Text to the right (Figures No. 12-15)==

{| border="1"
!Figure No. 12
![[Image:Fac2Fig12.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 12]]
&lt;!--!rowspan="4"| ... --&gt;
|-
!Figure No. 13
![[Image:Fac2Fig13.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 13]]
|-
!Figure No. 14
![[Image:Fac2Fig14.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 14]]
|-
!Figure No. 15
![[Image:Fac2Fig15.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 15]]
|}

The right portion of these characters are [[hieratic]] and appear to have been copied from Joseph Smith Papyrus XI.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

Included is sn-sn:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

&lt;hiero&gt;N35:O34-N35:O34&lt;/hiero&gt;

Val Sederholm&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.blogger.com/profile/11853353050355842605|title=Blogger: User Profile:  I began to reflect|website=www.blogger.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; has identified that the surviving traces of the original content parallel other hypocephali, and suggested the reading ''j nTr pfy 'A, 'nx m TAw, jw m mw: 'q r' jw [=r] sDm md.t=f. [Mj n] Wsjr'', explaining that "the officiator, calling upon that special, particular, transcendent god, who lives by breathing, who negotiates the waters, pleads from the depths: May Re descend to hear Osiris' words! Come to Shoshenq, who is dead!"&lt;ref name="sederholmright"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://valsederholm.blogspot.co.uk/2013/03/reading-erased-right-panels-on.html | title=Restoring the Right Panels on LDS Book of Abraham Facsimile 2 (New Translations) | accessdate=21 September 2016 | author=Sederholm, Val}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Text at the bottom (Figures No. 16-17)==
{| border="1"
![[Image:Fac2Fig17.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 17]]
|-
![[Image:Fac2Fig16.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 16]]
|-
!Figure No. 17: (h3t)tomb. (thy)desecration. (nn) strong negative.
|-
!Figure No. 16: "is not to be disturbed along with its Lord in the Duat forever."
|}

[[Michael D. Rhodes]] gives the following translation: "May this tomb never be desecrated, and may this soul and its lord never be desecrated in the hereafter."&lt;ref name="rhodes1997" /&gt;

Robert K. Ritner gives the following translation: "Back, injury, back! There is none who attacks you. This ''ba''-spirit and his lord will not be attacked in the underworld forever."&lt;ref name="ritnerxmission" /&gt;

==Text around the rim (Figure No. 18)==

One third of the rim contains characters taken from another papyrus. [[Michael D. Rhodes]] provided a possible reading of the text in its original state:

"I am the Provider in the Sun Temple in Heliopolis. [I am] most exalted and very glorious. [I am] a virile bull without equal. [I am] that Mighty God in the Sun Temple in Heliopolis. &lt;May the Osiris Shishaq live forever&gt; with that Mighty God in Heliopolis."&lt;ref name=rhodes1997 /&gt;

==Text to upper left (Figures No. 19-21, numbered 19,21-22 in Times and Seasons)==

{| border="1"
|-
![[Image:Fac2Fig22.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 21]]
![[Image:Fac2Fig21.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 20]]
![[Image:Fac2Fig19.jpg|left|Detail of Figure No. 19]]
|-
!"Behold thou art ever"
!"as this god of thine"
!"in(of) Busiris"
|}

[[Michael D. Rhodes|Rhodes]] gives the following translation: "You shall ever be as that God, the Busirian."&lt;ref name="rhodes1997"/&gt;

== Notes ==

{{notelist|refs=

{{efn|Sometimes given in translations as Shishaq,{{refn|name=rhodes1997}} Shoshenq,{{refn|name=sederholmright}} S'es'enq.{{refn|name=deveria}} |name=fn_a}}

{{efn|Compare with [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 1:2; And the spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters.|name=fn_b}}

}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
*{{Commons-inline|Book of Abraham Facsimile Number 2}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Pearl of Great Price (Mormonism)]]
[[Category:1842 documents]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Times and Seasons]]
[[Category:Book of the Dead]]
[[Category:Egyptian papyri containing images]]
[[Category:Book of Abraham]]</text>
      <sha1>grb1idk7lqqtsfv78vytyr739qoewox</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
