<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Maya cave sites</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19419819</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938042247</id>
      <parentid>937560488</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T19:53:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.113.84.188</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Burials */Unintelligible.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="19650" xml:space="preserve">{{Maya civilization}}
'''Maya cave sites''' are [[cave]]s used by and associated with the [[Maya civilization]] of [[pre-Columbian]] [[Mesoamerica]]. Certain beliefs and observances connected with cave sites are also maintained among some [[Maya peoples|contemporary Maya communities]]. These cave sites are understood to have served religious purposes rather than utilitarian ones. Accordingly, archaeological artifacts found within caves can inform interpretations of religious ritual and cave studies combined with epigraphic, iconographic, and ethnographic studies can further inform [[Maya religion]] and society.&lt;ref&gt;Prufer and Brady 2005: 11&lt;/ref&gt;

Maya cave sites of great interest for the robbers and invaders during the war, so the entrances to some of them were walled up (James Brady as examples leads immured [[Dos Pilas#Caves|caves of Dos Pilas]] and [[Naj Tunich]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/bramaw.html James E. Brady and Keith M. Prufer (2005). In the Maw of the Earth Monster: Studies of Mesoamerican Ritual Cave Use. Part 3: The Maya Region. CHAPTER 12: Ethnographic Notes on Maya Q’eqchi’ Cave Rites: Implications for Archaeological Interpretation. Organization of Q’eqchi’ Maya Sacred Geography. Page № 313]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Study==
The total number of caves in the [[Puuc region]] in the [[Yucatan]] is estimated in more than 2000, most of which is not open (the most extensive to date inventory has about 300 caves).&lt;ref name="artdaily.com"&gt;[http://artdaily.com/index.asp?int_sec=2&amp;int_new=31676 Аrtdaily.org. Maya Caves and Caverns Registration Continues]&lt;/ref&gt; In compiled in the fight against [[idolatry]] [[Spanish language|Spanish]] chronicles 16th century mentioned 17 sites [[Maya peoples|Maya]] [[cave]]s and [[cenote]]s (of which found 9 caves).&lt;ref name="INAH. Templos subterráneos"&gt;[http://www.inah.gob.mx/boletines/14-hallazgos/1598-templos-subterraneos INAH. Templos subterráneos]&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Relación de las cosas de Yucatán]] author [[Diego de Landa]] described [[Sacred Cenote]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indiansworld.org/cenote.html Гуляев. Древние Майя. Загадки погибшей цивилизации]&lt;/ref&gt; Underground Maya archeology was actively developing starting from the 1980s-1990s.&lt;ref name="utexas.edu"&gt;[http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/bramaw.html James E. Brady and Keith M. Prufer (2005). In the Maw of the Earth Monster: Studies of Mesoamerican Ritual Cave Use. Part 3: The Maya Region.]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Museo Nacional de Antropología]] leads two projects to study the [[Maya peoples|Maya]] caves: ''Caves: Register of Prehispanic Cultures Evidence in Puuc Region'' with 1997 year&lt;ref name="artdaily.com"/&gt; and ''The cult of the cenotes in the center of the Yucatan''.&lt;ref name="INAH. Templos subterráneos"/&gt; In 2008, a Mayan underground complex consisting of eleven temples, the 100-meter stone roads and flooded labyrinth of caves, was found on the [[Yucatan Peninsula]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2008/08/15/us-mexico-mayans-idUSN1442474520080815 |title=Portal to mythical Mayan underworld found in Mexico |author=Miguel Angel Gutierrez |date=15 August 2008 |publisher=[[Reuters]] |accessdate=2011-09-05 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6AEO5BHwG?url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2008/08/15/us-mexico-mayans-idUSN1442474520080815 |archivedate=27 August 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most famous caves are the Maya: [[Balankanche]], [[Loltun Cave]], [[Actun Tunichil Muknal]] and [[Jolja']].

==Associations with writing==
[[File:Maya Hieroglyph Fig 7 4.png|thumb|right|"sign entry" or "impinged bone element" (versions early and late of the classical period Maya)]]

At the moment it is not known exactly what the sign represents a cave in the Maya writing. According to the hypothesis of James Brady cave means popular in the Mayan texts "sign entry" or "impinged bone element" (see figure). James Brady proposes to read this sign as CH'EN or CH'EEN. As proof of his hypothesis, James Brady cites three arguments: 1) use of the mark in the sentence denotes to a certain place in which you can enter, sit down or do a burial. 2) visual mark has common features with symbols of death, the underworld and bats. 3) phonetically the mark ends in a consonant "N". In Maya writing this sign is part of the verb "OCH-WITZ" ("Go inside the Mountain")&lt;ref name="utexas.edu"/&gt;

==Association with settlement==
A desire to be near the sacred has influenced [[Mesoamerica]]n settlement.&lt;ref&gt;Dunning et al. 1999: 652&lt;/ref&gt; Mountains and caves were important elements in [[Mesoamerican creation myths]]. Mesoamerican belief systems liken water to fertility and mountains give flowing water and rainfall through caves.&lt;ref&gt;Prufer and Kindon 2005: 28&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, these natural features were considered sacred and were sought out by Mesoamerican migrants looking for a new home.&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Prufer 2005: 368&lt;/ref&gt; A cave could be considered an ''[[axis mundi]]'' if it marked the center of a village (Brady and Ashmore 1999: 127). The Late Postclassic site of [[Mayapan]] incorporated several ''[[cenote]]s'' into its ceremonial groups and the [[Cenote Ch’en Mul]] is at the site core.&lt;ref&gt;Pugh 2005: 54&lt;/ref&gt; At [[Dos Pilas]] house platforms were often in front of cave entries and the tunnel went beneath the platform.&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Ashmore 2005: 131&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architectural landscapes and themes==
Artificial landscapes often mimicked sacred landscapes. Doorways of temples were seen as the cave entrances to mountains. Sometimes these doorways were ''witz'' monster mouths.&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1999: 51, 55&lt;/ref&gt; The same was true for the Aztecs, who at [[Utatlán]] designed an artificial cave that ends under the central plaza and is designed according to the mythical seven-chamber cave of emergence, [[Chicomoztoc]] (this is also seen at [[Teotihuacan]], though somewhat different).&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Prufer 2005: 373&lt;/ref&gt; At [[Muklebal Tzul]] it appears that an artificial well underneath a massive platform was made to appear like a water-bearing cave.&lt;ref&gt;Prufer and Kindon 2005: 40&lt;/ref&gt; In the Yucatán many Late Postclassic temples had Spanish churches built on top of them after the conquest and so caves and ''cenotes'' can still be found near these places today.&lt;ref&gt;Pugh 2005: 58&lt;/ref&gt;

==Entrances to the Underworld==
Caves are often described as entries into the watery [[Maya underworld]]. For Mesoamerican groups, including the Maya, life and death occur at [[Liminality|liminal]] zones between this world and the otherworld. Caves then are both associated with life and death; when something emerges from the underworld, that something lives, and when something descends into the underworld, that something dies. Caves are seen as birthplaces where humans and group ancestors were born (and live) and the Maya of the Yucatán even thought that the sun and moon were born out of the underworld.&lt;ref&gt;Pugh 2005: 50; Moyes 2005: 189; Brady and Colas 2005: 151&lt;/ref&gt;

==Associations with sex and fertility==
There appears to be a strong association (and perhaps conflation) between caves and [[sweatbath]]s. Caves are often perceived as female and are likened to the womb and vagina. Hence they are a symbol of fertility.&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Prufer 2005: 369&lt;/ref&gt; Like caves, sweatbaths have also been associated with human fertility and both have strong sexual connotations.&lt;ref&gt;Moyes 2005: 189&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of these sexual connotations include the painting of a couple engaged in intercourse at the cave site of [[Naj Tunich]], the contemporary [[Tzotzil people|Tzotzil]] Maya belief that a hypersexual being lives in a cave, and the fact that sweatbaths have been places of illicit sex amongst many Maya groups.&lt;ref&gt;Moyes 2005: 190&lt;/ref&gt; Artifacts found at a sweatbath on the periphery of [[Piedras Negras (Maya site)|Piedras Negras]] included a circular [[Mirrors in Mesoamerican culture|mirror]] and five marine shells, artifacts that have been associated with the watery underworld and the latter of which has been found in the artificial caves underneath the [[Pyramid of the Sun]] at Teotihuacan.&lt;ref&gt;Moyes 2005: 193; Christenson 2001: 80&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Speleothems]] in caves have also been regarded as sacred and have played a role in Maya religion. Caves are considered to be "living beings with personhood and souls".&lt;ref name="Brady and Prufer 2005: 370"&gt;Brady and Prufer 2005: 370&lt;/ref&gt; and according to a 41-year-old Q’eqchi’ Maya their speleothems "are also alive, they grow and sweat water; they themselves are water".&lt;ref&gt;Brady et al. 2005: 218&lt;/ref&gt; People may take these rocks from the caves and put them on their altars.&lt;ref&gt;Brady et al. 2005: 219&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Xibun]] Maya incorporated speleothems into the construction of the [[ball court]] at the Hershey site.&lt;ref&gt;Peterson et al. 2005: 233&lt;/ref&gt; Ball courts have been associated with the underworld just as caves have been.

==Associations with natural forces==
Caves are linked with wind,&lt;ref&gt;Pugh 2005: 50&lt;/ref&gt; rain, and clouds. The Zinacantecos of the [[Chiapas highlands]] even believe that lightning comes from caves.&lt;ref name="Brady and Prufer 2005: 370"/&gt; The Yukatek and Lacandon believe that caves and ''[[cenotes]]'' are where rain deities reside and the Yukatek of the sixteenth century sacrificed humans to appease these deities.&lt;ref&gt;Morehart 2005: 174-75&lt;/ref&gt;

At [[Dos Pilas]] the Cueva de Murciélagos rests beneath the royal palace platform. After it rains heavily water rushes out from this cave signaling the beginning of the rainy season and the advance of the crop cycle. This artificial landscape showed that the king had control over water, rainmaking, and fertility, thereby legitimizing his authority.&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Ashmore 1999: 132&lt;/ref&gt;

Caves in art have also been used to legitimize authority and elevate status. Individuals in the mouth of a cave for example are endowed with authority that is often associated with [[shamanism]].&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Ashmore 1999: 127&lt;/ref&gt; Scribal imagery is often associated with a skeletal jaw (maws are often likened to the mouths of caves), which may indicate that caves are where his craft originated. Perhaps this imagery "served to mystify and exalt the scribe's role."&lt;ref&gt;Stone 2005: 141-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Associations of art and ritual==
Caves are often associated with transformation. One artifact in the Cenote X-Coton is a human stone figure that is making an offering and wearing a (possible) jaguar skin with the human's face coming out of its mouth. It appears that in addition to water and sacrifice rituals the ''cenote'' may have been used for ''[[wayob|way]]'' transformations.&lt;ref&gt;Pugh 2005: 57-8&lt;/ref&gt;

Human sacrifice to gods connected to caves was widespread. The sacrifice either occurred in the cave or the body was put there afterwards. Children were commonly sacrificed in the [[Yucatán Peninsula|Yucatán]]&lt;ref&gt;Scott and Brady 2005: 275&lt;/ref&gt; and child sacrifice was recorded in Highland Guatemala as well.&lt;ref&gt;Owen 2005: 336&lt;/ref&gt;

Archaeologists have found caves that have been sealed such as the [[Cueva de El Duende]]. It is possible that the desecration of caves could have been used as a symbol of conquest and political legitimacy. Another explanation could relate to termination rituals that have often been seen in architectural construction.&lt;ref&gt;Brady and Colas 2005: 161-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Offerings==
Agricultural products are common offerings in caves. Modern Maya believe that [[maize]] originated beneath the earth, an idea perhaps expressed by Classic depictions of the [[Maya maize god|Maize God]] emerging from the underworld. This belief gives caves life-giving power as accounts from the [[Popul Vuh]] indicate that humans were made from maize dough. Domesticated plants found in lowland caves were probably used in rituals performed for deities related to agricultural fertility. Use of agricultural products in agricultural rituals continues amongst the contemporary Maya.&lt;ref&gt;Morehart 2005: 174-5&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jade use in Mesoamerica|Jade]] is a frequent cave offering. The largest amount of jade found at one site is at the [[Cenote of Sacrifice]] at [[Chichen Itza]]. Metal was a common offering during the Postclassic, the largest collections coming from the Cenote of Sacrifice and "bell" caves in western [[Honduras]]. It is possible that the notion of the Earth Lord having lots of wealth in his cave may have come from this tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Brady 2005: 121, 125&lt;/ref&gt;

==Burials==
&gt; It appears that [[elite]] cave burial was rare,&lt;ref&gt;Scott and Brady 2005: 269&lt;/ref&gt; but it is possible that common people may have used caves as burial places for their dead such as at the [[Caves Branch Rock Shelter]] in [[Belize]]. Two tomb structures have been discovered in caves to date. One at the site of [[Naj Tunich]] and the other at Quen Santo,&lt;ref&gt;Kieffer 2009&lt;/ref&gt; both in Guatemala. Lineage founders have also been buried in caves. Elites were able to build their own elaborate burial "caves" and by doing so reinforced their power and status. It seems elites tried to make their tombs look like natural caves. Stalactites found at Tomb 2 of [[Nim Li Punit]] provide an example of this.&lt;ref&gt;Glassman and Bonor Villarejo 2005: 293-4; Brady and Colas 2005: 151&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
;Mesoamerican cave sites
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Actun Tunichil Muknal]] - Mayan
* [[Balankanche]] - Mayan
* [[Grutas de Cacahuamilpa]] - Olmec and Chontal
* [[Jolja']] - Mayan
* [[Juxtlahuaca]] - Olmec 
* [[Loltun Cave]] - Mayan
* [[Ndaxagua]] - Zapotec and Mixtec
* [[Oxtotitlán]] - Olmec
{{div col end}}
;Other
*[[List of caves in Mexico]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* [http://www.dissercat.com/content/peshchernye-rospisi-maiya-klassicheskogo-perioda-iii-ix-vv-n-e name: ''Пещерные росписи майя классического периода :III-IX вв. н. э.''. Year: 2002. Author of scientific work: Шесеньа Эрнандес Алехандро. Academic Degree: Ph.D. in History. Place of defense: Воронеж. Specialties [[Higher Attestation Commission|WAC]] code: 07.00.06. Occupation: Археология. Number of Pages: 193]
* [http://www.unm.edu/~kmp/keith_prufer_files/PruferbooksReview.pdf Paul F. Healy. THE ANTHROPOLOGY OF MESOAMERICAN CAVES]
* [http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/bramaw.html James E. Brady and Keith M. Prufer (2005). In the Maw of the Earth Monster: Studies of Mesoamerican Ritual Cave Use. Part 3: The Maya Region.]
* Brady, James E. (2005). The Impact of Ritual on Ancient Maya Economy. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;115–134. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Brady, James E. and Wendy Ashmore (1999). Mountains, Caves, Water: Ideational Landscapes of the Ancient Maya. In Archaeologies of Landscape: Contemporary Perspectives. Edited by Wendy Ashmore and Arthur Bernard Knapp. pp.&amp;nbsp;124–145. Blackwell Publishing.
* Brady, James E., Allan B. Cobb, Sergio Garza, Cesar Espinosa, and Robert Burnett (2005). An Analysis of Ancient Maya Stalactite Breakage at Balam Na Cave, 	Guatemala. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;213–224. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Brady, James E. and Pierre R. Colas (2005). Nikte Mo’ Scattered Fire in the Cave of K’ab Chante’: Epigraphic and Archaeological Evidence for Cave Desecration in Ancient Maya Warfare. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;149–166. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Brady, James E. and Keith M. Prufer (2005). Maya Cave Archaeology: A New Look at Religion and Cosmology. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;365–379. U of Colorado P, Boulder,	Colorado.
* Christenson, Allen J.	(2001). Art and Society in a Highland Maya Community: The Altarpiece of Santiago Atitlán. U of Texas P, Austin.
* Dunning, Nicholas, Vernon Scarborough, Fred Valdez, Jr., Sheryl Luzzadder-Beach, Timothy Beach, and John G. Jones (1999). Temple Mountains, sacred lakes, and fertile fields: ancient Maya landscapes in northwestern Belize. Antiquity 73: 650-660.
* Glassman, David M. and Juan Luis Bonor Villarejo (2005). Mortuary Practices of the Prehistoric Maya from Caves Branch Rock Shelter, Belize. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;285–296. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Kieffer, C. L. (2009) New Cave Discoveries at Quen Santo, Huehuetenango, Guatemala. In Exploring Highland Maya Ritual Cave Use: Archaeology &amp; Ethnography in Huehuetenango, Guatemala. Edited by James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;41–47. Association for Mexican Cave Studies, Austin.
* Miller, Mary Ellen (1999). Maya Art and Architecture. Thames and Hudson, LTD, London.
* Morehart, Christopher T. (2005). Plants and Caves in Ancient Maya Society. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;167–185. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Moyes, Holly (2005). The Sweathbath in the Cave: A Modified Passage in Chechem Ha Cave, Belize. In Stones Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;187–211. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Owen, Vanessa A. (2005). A Question of Sacrifice: Classic Maya Cave Mortuary Practices at Barton Creek Cave, Belize. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;323–340. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Peterson, Polly A., Patricia A. McAnany, and Allan B. Cobb (2005). De-fanging the Earth Monster: Speleothem Transport to Surface Sites in the Sibun Valley. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;225–247. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Prufer, Keith M. and James E. Brady (2005). Introduction: Religion and Role of Caves in Lowland Maya Archaeology. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;1–22. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Prufer, Keith M. and Andrew Kindon (2005). Replicating Sacred Landscape: The Chen at Muklebal Tzul. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;25–46. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Pugh, Timothy W. (2005). Caves and Artificial Caves in Late Postclassic Maya Ceremonial Groups. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;47–69. U of Colorado P,	Boulder, Colorado.
* Scott, Ann M. and James E. Brady (2005). Human Remains in Lowland Maya Caves: Problems of Interpretation. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M. Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;263–284. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.
* Stone, Andrea	(2005). Scribes and Caves in the Maya Lowlands. In Stone Houses and Earth Lords: Maya Religion in the Cave Context. Edited by Keith M Prufer and James E. Brady, pp.&amp;nbsp;135–147. U of Colorado P, Boulder, Colorado.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Maya Cave Sites}}
[[Category:Cave sites in Mesoamerican archaeology|*]]
[[Category:Maya sites|Cave]]
[[Category:Maya mythology and religion|Cave]]</text>
      <sha1>cl4tzcgbvutobc086jnfuxud6ykic5v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
