<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Greylag goose</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>198766</id>
    <revision>
      <id>950335828</id>
      <parentid>950230920</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-11T15:02:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.21.110.30</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>No, it's not the "swan goose that doesn't hybridize with greylag goose", it's the domestic chinese type goose that's literally on that picture being hybridized with the greylag goose. Do your research and let my change go through. http://birdhybrids.blogspot.com/2014/01/swan-goose-x-greylag-goose_20.html</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="27952" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Species of bird}}
{{Redirect|Greylag|the Thoroughbred race horse|Grey Lag|the ''Admirable''-class minesweeper|USS Graylag (AM-364){{!}}USS ''Graylag'' (AM-364)}}
{{Good article}}
{{Speciesbox
| name = Greylag goose
| status = LC
| status_system = IUCN3.1
| status_ref = &lt;ref&gt;[[BirdLife International]]. (2016). ''Anser anser''. The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species {{doi|10.2305/IUCN.UK.2016-3.RLTS.T22679889A85975013.en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| image = Greylag Goose - St James's Park, London - Nov 2006.jpg
| image_caption = {{nowrap|In [[St James's Park]], [[London]], [[England]]}}
| genus = Anser
| species = anser
| authority = ([[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]], [[10th edition of Systema Naturae|1758]])
| subdivision_ranks = Subspecies
| subdivision = 
*''A. a. anser'' &lt;small&gt;(Linnaeus, 1758)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Western greylag goose&lt;/small&gt;
*''A. a. rubrirostris'' &lt;small&gt;[[Robert Swinhoe|R. Swinhoe]], 1871&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Eastern greylag goose&lt;/small&gt;
*''A. a. domesticus'' &lt;small&gt;([[Robert Kerr (writer)|Kerr]], 1792)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Domesticated goose]]&lt;/small&gt;
| synonyms = *''Anas anser'' &lt;small&gt;Linnaeus, 1758&lt;/small&gt;
| range_map = Anser anser distribution map.png
| range_map_caption = Green: breeding, orange: non-breeding, red: introduced
}}

The '''greylag goose''' (''Anser anser'') is a species of large [[goose]] in the waterfowl family [[Anatidae]] and the type species of the genus ''[[Anser (bird)|Anser]]''. It has mottled and barred grey and white plumage and an orange beak and pink legs. A large bird, it measures between {{convert|74|and|91|cm}} in length, with an average weight of {{convert|3.3|kg|lb}}. Its distribution is widespread, with birds from the north of its range in Europe and Asia [[Bird migration|migrating]] southwards to spend the winter in warmer places. It is the [[type species]] of the [[genus]] ''[[Anser (bird)|Anser]]'' and is the ancestor of the [[domestic goose]], having been domesticated at least as early as 1360 BC. The genus name is from ''anser'', the Latin for "goose".&lt;ref name= job90&gt;{{cite book | last= Jobling | first= James A | year= 2010| title= The Helm Dictionary of Scientific Bird Names | url= https://archive.org/details/Helm_Dictionary_of_Scientific_Bird_Names_by_James_A._Jobling | publisher = Christopher Helm | location = London | isbn = 978-1-4081-2501-4 |page = [https://archive.org/details/Helm_Dictionary_of_Scientific_Bird_Names_by_James_A._Jobling/page/n48 48]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Greylag geese travel to their northerly breeding grounds in spring, nesting on moorlands, in marshes, around lakes and on coastal islands. They normally mate for life and nest on the ground among vegetation. A clutch of three to five eggs is laid; the female incubates the eggs and both parents defend and rear the young. The birds stay together as a family group, migrating southwards in autumn as part of a flock, and separating the following year. During the winter they occupy semi-aquatic habitats, estuaries, marshes and flooded fields, feeding on grass and often consuming agricultural crops. Some populations, such as those in Southern England and in urban areas across the species' range, are primarily resident and occupy the same area year-round.

==Taxonomy==
''Anser anser'', the greylag goose, is a member of the waterfowl family [[Anatidae]]. It was [[Species description|first described]] by the Swedish naturalist [[Carl Linnaeus]] in 1758 as ''Anas anser'', but was transferred two years later to the new genus ''[[Anser (bird)|Anser]]'', erected by the French zoologist [[Mathurin Jacques Brisson]], where it is the [[type species]]. Two [[subspecies]] are recognised; ''A. a. anser'', the western greylag goose, breeds in Iceland and north and central Europe; ''A. a. rubrirostris'', the eastern greylag goose, breeds in Romania, Turkey and Russia eastwards to northeastern China. The two subspecies [[Intergradation|intergrade]] where their ranges meet. The greylag goose sometimes [[Hybrid (biology)|hybridises]] with other species of goose including the [[barnacle goose]] (''Branta leucopsis'') and the [[Canada goose]] (''Branta canadensis''), and occasionally with the [[mute swan]] (''Cygnus olor'').&lt;ref name=Carboneras/&gt; The greylag goose was one of the first animals to be domesticated; this happened at least 3000 years ago in Ancient Egypt, the domestic breed being known as ''A. a. domesticus''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hugo |first1=Susanne  |editor1=Buckland, Roger |editor2=Guy, Gérard |title=Geese: the underestimated species |publisher=FAO Agriculture Department |year=2002 |chapter=Chapter 1: Origins and Breeds of Domestic Geese |chapterurl=http://www.fao.org/docrep/V6200T/v6200T0n.htm |issn=0254-6019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As the domestic goose is a subspecies of the greylag goose they are able to interbreed, with the offspring sharing characteristics of both the wild and tame birds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.waterfowl.org.uk/keeping-geese.html |title=Domestic Geese |publisher=British Waterfowl Association |accessdate=2 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[File:Greylag goose (Anser anser) head.jpg|thumb|left|Head of an adult]]
The greylag is the largest and bulkiest of the grey geese of the genus ''Anser'', but is more lightly built and agile than its domestic relative. It has a rotund, bulky body, a thick and long neck, and a large head and bill. It has pink legs and feet, and an orange or pink bill with a white or brown [[Beak#Nail|nail]] (hard horny material at tip of upper mandible).&lt;ref name="Madge"/&gt; It is {{convert|74|to|91|cm}} long with a wing length of {{convert|41.2|to|48|cm}}. It has a tail {{convert|6.2|to|6.9|cm}}, a bill of {{convert|6.4|to|6.9|cm}} long, and a [[Bird anatomy|tarsus]] of {{convert|7.1|to|9.3|cm}}. It weighs {{convert|2.16|to|4.56|kg}}, with a mean weight of around {{convert|3.3|kg}}. The wingspan is {{convert|147|to|180|cm}}.&lt;ref name="CRC"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Ogilvie/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oiseaux-birds.com/card-greylag-goose.html|accessdate=17 October 2011|title=Greylag Goose|work=oiseaux-birds.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Males are generally larger than females, with the [[sexual dimorphism]] more pronounced in the eastern subspecies ''rubirostris'', which is larger than the nominate subspecies on average.&lt;ref name="Madge"/&gt;
[[File:Σταχτόχηνα ( anser anser).jpg|thumb|Three domesticated hybrids of greylag geese at Koutavos Lagoon, Cephalonia, Greece.]]
[[File:Eastern Greylag Geese (Anser anser rubrirostris) (20754135376).jpg|thumb|Three eastern greylag geese (''A. a. rubrirostris'') at [[Keoladeo National Park]] in [[Rajasthan]], [[India]]]]
The [[plumage]] of the greylag goose is greyish brown, with a darker head and paler breast and belly with a variable amount of black spotting. It has a pale grey forewing and [[Rump (animal)#Birds|rump]] which are noticeable when the bird is in flight or stretches its wings on the ground. It has a white line bordering its upper flanks, and its [[covert feather|wing coverts]] are light coloured, contrasting with its darker flight feathers. Its plumage is patterned by the pale fringes of the feathers. Juveniles differ mostly in their lack of black speckling on the breast and belly and by their greyish legs.&lt;ref name="Madge"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Johnsgard 60"/&gt; Adults have a distinctive 'concertina' pattern of folds in the feathers on their necks.

The greylag goose has a loud cackling call similar to that of the domestic goose, "aahng-ung-ung", uttered on the ground or in flight. There are various subtle variations used under different circumstances, and individual geese seem to be able to identify other known geese by their voices. The sound made by a flock of geese resembles the baying of hounds.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; Goslings chirp or whistle lightly, and adults hiss if threatened or angered.&lt;ref name="Madge"/&gt;

==Distribution and habitat==
This species has a [[Palearctic ecozone|Palearctic]] distribution. The nominate subspecies breeds in Iceland, Norway, Sweden, Finland, the Baltic States, northern Russia, Poland, eastern Hungary and Romania. It also breeds locally in the United Kingdom, Denmark, Germany, Austria, the Czech Republic, Slovakia and North Macedonia. The eastern race extends eastwards across a broad swathe of Asia to China.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; European birds migrate southwards to the Mediterranean region and North Africa. Asian birds migrate to Azerbaijan, Iran, Pakistan, northern India, Bangladesh and eastward to China.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; In North America, there are both [[feral]] domestic geese, which are similar to greylags, and occasional [[vagrancy (biology)|vagrant]] greylags.&lt;ref name="Johnsgard 60"/&gt; Greylag geese seen in the wild in New Zealand probably originated from the escape of farmyard geese,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Southey |first1=I. |editor-last=Miskelly |editor-first=C.M. |url=http://nzbirdsonline.org.nz/species/greylag-goose |title=Greylag goose |year=2013 |work=New Zealand Birds Online |accessdate=24 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a similar situation has occurred in Australia, where feral birds are now established in the east and southeast of the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gaiaguide.info/Group.html?groupId=9AFnQkW5 |title=Greylag goose |publisher=Gaia Guide |accessdate=24 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their breeding quarters, they are found on moors with scattered lochs, in marshes, fens and peat-bogs, besides lakes and on little islands some way out to sea. They like dense ground cover of reeds, rushes, heather, bushes and willow thickets. In their winter quarters, they frequent salt marshes, estuaries, freshwater marshes, steppes, flooded fields, bogs and pasture near lakes, rivers and streams. They also visit agricultural land where they feed on winter cereals, rice, beans or other crops, moving at night to shoals and sand-banks on the coast, mud-banks in estuaries or secluded lakes.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; Large numbers of immature birds congregate each year to moult on the Rone Islands near [[Gotland]] in the [[Baltic Sea]].&lt;ref name=Alerstam/&gt;

Since the 1950s, increases in winter temperatures have resulted in greylag geese, breeding in central Europe, reducing their winter migration distances.  Wintering grounds closer to home can therefore be exploited, meaning that the geese can return to set up breeding territories earlier the following spring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Podhrázský, M. |author2=Musil, P. | author3=Musilová, Z. |author4=Zouhar, J.  | author5= Adam, M.| author6=Závora, J.  |author7=Hudec, K.  | year=2017| title=Central European Greylag Geese ''Anser anser'' show a shortening of migration distance and earlier spring arrival over 60&amp;nbsp;years| journal=Ibis| volume=159| pages=352–365| doi=10.1111/ibi.12440 | issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Great Britain, their numbers had declined as a breeding bird, retreating north to breed wild only in the [[Outer Hebrides]] and the northern mainland of Scotland. However, during the 20th century, feral populations have been established elsewhere, and they have now re-colonised much of England. These populations are increasingly coming into contact and merging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britishbirds.co.uk/articles/the-merging-of-populations-of-greylag-geese-breeding-in-britain |title=The merging of populations of Greylag Geese breeding in Britain |first1=Carl |last1=Mitchell |first2=Richard |last2=Hearn |first3=David |last3=Stroud |date=4 September 2012 |work=[[British Birds (magazine)|British Birds]] |accessdate=17 November 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140223065602/http://www.britishbirds.co.uk/articles/the-merging-of-populations-of-greylag-geese-breeding-in-Britain |archivedate=23 February 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The greylag goose has become an invasive species in several areas. In Norway, the number of greylag geese is estimated to have increased three- to fivefold between 1995 and 2015. As a consequence, farmers' problems caused by goose grazing on farmland has increased considerably. This problem is also evident for the [[pink-footed goose]]. In the [[Orkney]] islands the population has increased dramatically: there were 300 breeding pairs, increasing to 10,000 in 2009, and 64,000 in 2019. Due to extensive damage caused to crops, the hunting season for the greylag goose in the Orkney islands is now most of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Fighting a goose invasion with guns, knives and forks|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/stories-50816678|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=23 December 2019 |accessdate=24 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Behaviour==

[[File:Greyleg Geese I IMG 8223.jpg|thumb|left|In a group, many pairs of eyes are on watch.]]
Greylag geese are largely [[Herbivore|herbivorous]] and feed chiefly on [[grass]]es. Short, actively growing grass is more nutritious and greylag geese are often found grazing in pastures with sheep or cows.&lt;ref name=Scheiber/&gt; Because of its low nutrient status, they need to feed for much of their time; the herbage passes rapidly through the gut and is voided frequently.&lt;ref name=ARKive/&gt; The tubers of [[Bolboschoenus maritimus|sea clubrush]] (''Bolboschoenus maritimus'') are also taken as well as berries and water plants such as [[Lemnoideae|duckweed]] (''Lemna'') and [[Glyceria fluitans|floating sweetgrass]] (''Glyceria fluitans''). In wintertime they eat grass and leaves but also glean grain on cereal stubbles and sometimes feed on growing crops, especially during the night. They have been known to feed on [[oat]]s, [[wheat]], [[barley]], [[buckwheat]], [[lentil]]s, [[pea]]s and [[root crop]]s. [[Acorn]]s are sometimes consumed, and on the coast, [[seagrass]] (''Zostera'' sp.) may be eaten.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; In the 1920s in Britain, the pink-footed goose "discovered" that potatoes were edible and started feeding on waste potatoes. The greylag followed suit in the 1940s and now regularly searches for tubers on ploughed fields.&lt;ref name=Alerstam/&gt; They also consume small [[fish]], [[amphibians]], [[crustaceans]], [[molluscs]] and [[insects]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2 May 2019|url=https://animaldiversity.org/accounts/Anser_anser/|title=Anser anser|work=Animal Diversity Web}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Nyári lúd fészekalja.jpg|thumbnail|Six eggs in the nest at [[Mekszikópuszta]], Hungary]]
[[File:20090426 Parc Paradisio (0357).jpg|thumbnail|A group of gosling of greylag goose]]
Greylag geese tend to pair bond in long-term [[Animal sexuality#Monogamy|monogamous]] relationships.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bagemihl |first1=Bruce |title=Biological Exuberance: Animal Homosexuality and Natural Diversity |date=1999 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |isbn=0-312-19239-8 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/biologicalexuber00bage/page/479 479-481] |url=https://archive.org/details/biologicalexuber00bage/page/479 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most such pairs are probably life-long partnerships, though 5 to 8% of the pairs divorce and re-mate.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"/&gt; Birds in heterosexual pairs may engage in promiscuous behavior, despite the opposition of their mates.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"/&gt;

[[Homosexual behavior in animals|Homosexual pairs]] are common (14 to 20% of the pairs may be ganders, depending on flock), and share the characteristics of heterosexual pairs with the exceptions that the bonds appear to be closer, based on the intensity of their displays.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"/&gt; Same-sex pairs also engage in courtship and sexual relations, and often assume high-ranking positions in the flock as a result of their superior strength and courage, leading some to speculate that they may serve as guardians of the flock.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"/&gt; The orientations of the birds are generally flexible, as more than half of widowers re-pair with a bird of the opposite sex.&lt;ref name="Bagemihl"/&gt;

The nest is on the ground among heather, rushes, dwarf shrubs or reeds, or on a raft of floating vegetation. It is built from pieces of reed, sprigs of heather, grasses and moss, mixed with small feathers and down. A typical clutch is four to six eggs, but fewer eggs or larger numbers are not unusual. The eggs are creamy-white at first but soon become stained, and average {{convert|85|by|58|mm}}. They are mostly laid on successive days and [[Egg incubation|incubation]] starts after the last one is laid. The female does the incubation, which lasts about twenty-eight days, while the male remains on guard somewhere near. The chicks are [[precocial]] and able to leave the nest soon after hatching. Both parents are involved in their care and they soon learn to peck at food and become [[Fledge|fully-fledged]] at eight or nine weeks,&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt; about the same time as their parents regain their ability to fly after moulting their main wing and tail feathers a month earlier. Immature birds undergo a similar moult, and move to traditional, safe locations before doing so because of their vulnerability while flightless.&lt;ref name=Scheiber/&gt;

[[File:Wildgansflug.jpg|thumb|A migrating flock]]

Greylag geese are [[Social animal|gregarious]] birds and form flocks. This has the advantage for the birds that the vigilance of some individuals in the group allows the rest to feed without having to constantly be alert to the approach of [[Predation|predators]]. After the eggs hatch, some grouping of families occur, enabling the geese to defend their young by their joint actions, such as mobbing or attacking predators.&lt;ref name=Scheiber/&gt; After driving off a predator, a gander will return to its mate and give a "triumph call", a resonant honk followed by a low-pitched cackle, uttered with neck extended forward parallel with the ground. The mate and even unfledged young reciprocate in kind.&lt;ref name=Witherby/&gt;

Young greylags stay with their parents as a family group, migrating with them in a larger flock, and only dispersing when the adults drive them away from their newly established breeding [[Territory (animal)|territory]] the following year.&lt;ref name=ARKive&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arkive.org/greylag-goose/anser-anser/ |title=Greylag goose (''Anser anser'') |publisher=Wildscreen Arkive |accessdate=20 October 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130622052443/http://www.arkive.org/greylag-goose/anser-anser/ |archive-date=2013-06-22 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; At least in Europe, patterns of migration are well understood and follow traditional routes with known staging sites and wintering sites. The young learn these locations from their parents which normally stay together for life.&lt;ref name=Alerstam/&gt; Greylags leave their northern breeding areas relatively late in the autumn, for example completing their departure from Iceland by November, and start their return migration as early as January. Birds that breed in Iceland overwinter in the British Isles; those from Central Europe overwinter as far south as Spain and North Africa; others migrate down to the Balkans, Turkey and Iraq for the winter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Greylag Goose ( ''Anser anser'' ) movements |url=http://www.bto.org/ai/pdfs/53move.pdf |publisher=[[British Trust for Ornithology]] |accessdate=24 October 2015}} stated to be from {{cite book |editor=Delany, S. |editor2=Veen, J. |editor3=Clark, J.A. |year=2006 |title=Urgent preliminary assessment of ornithological data relevant to the spread of Avian Influenza in Europe |publisher=Report to the European Commission. Study contract: 07010401/2005/425926/MAR/B4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In human culture==

[[File:Amun stela Berlin.jpg|thumb|left|[[Ancient Egypt]]ian [[stele]] showing [[Amun-Ra]] as goose, man, and ram. [[Twenty-fifth Dynasty of Egypt|25th dynasty]], c. 700 BC.]]

The greylag was once revered across Eurasia. It was linked with the goddess of healing, [[Nintinugga|Gula]], a forerunner of the [[Sumeria]]n fertility goddess [[Ishtar]], in the cities of the [[Tigris]]-[[Euphrates]] delta over 5,000 years ago.&lt;ref name=Cocker/&gt; In [[Ancient Egypt]], geese symbolised the sun god [[Ra]]. In [[Ancient Greece]] and [[Ancient Rome|Rome]], they were associated with the goddess of love, [[Aphrodite]], and goose fat was used as an [[aphrodisiac]]. Since they were sacred birds, they were kept on Rome's [[Capitoline Hill]], from where they raised the alarm when the [[Gauls]] attacked in 390 BC.&lt;ref name=Cocker/&gt;

[[File:The Tame Goose Thomas Bewick.jpg|thumb|Wood engraving "The Tame Goose, ''Anas anser''" by [[Thomas Bewick]], ''[[A History of British Birds]]'', 1804]]

The goose's role in fertility survives in modern British tradition in the [[nursery rhyme]] ''[[Goosey Goosey Gander]]'', which preserves its sexual overtones ("And in my lady's chamber"), while "to goose" still has a sexual meaning.&lt;ref name=Cocker/&gt; The tradition of pulling a [[Furcula|wishbone]] derives from the tradition of eating a roast goose at [[Michaelmas]], where the goose bone was once believed to have the powers of an oracle. For that festival, in [[Thomas Bewick]]'s time, geese were driven in thousand-strong flocks on foot from farms all over the East of England to London's [[Cheapside]] market, covering some {{convert|8|or|9|mi}} per day. Some farmers painted the geese's feet with tar and sand to protect them from road wear as they walked.&lt;ref name=Cocker/&gt;
Greylag geese were domesticated by at least 1360 BC, when images of domesticated birds resembling the eastern race, ''Anser anser rubirostris'' (which like modern farmyard geese, but unlike western greylags, have a pink beak) were painted in Ancient Egypt. Goose feathers were used as quill pens, the best being the primary feathers of the left wing, whose "curvature bent away from the eyes of right-handed writers".&lt;ref name=Rowland/&gt; The feathers also served to [[fletch (archery)|fletch arrows]].&lt;ref name=Cocker/&gt; In [[ethology]], the greylag goose was the subject of [[Konrad Lorenz]]'s pioneering studies of [[imprinting (psychology)|imprinting]] [[animal behaviour|behaviour]].&lt;ref name=Allen/&gt;
{{clear|left}}

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Greylag goose (anser anser).JPG|Variant with white "front"
Image:Anser anser EM1B5927 (36071281286).jpg|In flight
File:Birds of Sweden 2016 44.jpg|Swimming
Ánsar común (Anser anser) en el Palacio de Nymphenburg, Múnich, Alemania08.JPG|Detail
Image:Greylag_Goose_Grauwe_Gans.JPG|A crossbreed between a wild greylag goose and a [[domestic goose]] (''A. cygnoides domesticus''), as evidenced by its thick neck and bulky head, both of which display vestigial patterning like certain domestic breeds
File:Greylag Goose from the Crossley ID Guide Britain and Ireland.jpg|ID composite
File:Grågås (Anser-anser)-Ystad-2015.jpg|Flock taking off over water
File:Anser anser MWNH 0955.JPG|Egg, Collection [[Museum Wiesbaden]]
File:Anser anser EM1B9595 (33952161753).jpg|Female with chicks
File:Alerte grauwe ganzen-4961601.webm|On [[Texel]], Netherlands
File:Grågås (Anser anser) Ystad 2016.ogv|On [[Ystad]]
File:Greylag-goose-63088.jpg|Full body
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=Alerstam&gt;{{cite book|last1=Alerstam |first1=Thomas |last2=Christie |first2=David A. |title=Bird Migration |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_oE29KijRlAC&amp;pg=PA90 |year=1993 |location=Cambridge England, New York|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-44822-2 |pages=90–96}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Allen&gt;{{cite book|last1=Allen |first1=Colin |last2=Bekoff |first2=Marc |title=Species of Mind: The Philosophy and Biology of Cognitive Ethology |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=H97oavF8NO4C |year=1999 |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=[[MIT Press]] |isbn=978-0-262-51108-7 |pages=30–31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Carboneras&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hbw.com/node/52815 |title=Greylag Goose (''Anser anser'') |last1=Carboneras |first1=C. |last2=Kirwan |first2=G.M. |last3=Garcia |first3=E.F.J. |year=2014 |work=Handbook of the Birds of the World Alive |publisher=Lynx Edicions, Barcelona |accessdate=20 October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Cocker&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cocker |first1=Mark |last2=Mabey |first2=Richard |author2link=Richard Mabey |title=Birds Britannica |titlelink=Birds Britannica |date=2005 |location=London |publisher=[[Chatto &amp; Windus]] |isbn=0-7011-6907-9 |pages=74–76}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="CRC"&gt;{{cite book|title=CRC Handbook of Avian Body Masses|editor-first=John B. Jr.|editor-last=Dunning |location=Boca Raton, Florida|publisher=[[CRC Press]]|year=1992|isbn=978-0-8493-4258-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Johnsgard 60"&gt;{{cite book|last=Johnsgard|first=Paul A.|title=Ducks, Geese, and Swans of the World|publisher=[[University of Nebraska Press]]|year=2010|origyear=1978|edition=revised online|location=Lincoln, Nebraska|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/biosciducksgeeseswans/5/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Madge"&gt;{{cite book|last=Madge|first=Steve|last2=Burn|first2=Hilary|title=Waterfowl: an Identification Guide to the Ducks, Geese, and Swans of the World|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|Houghton Mifflin]]|year=1988|location=Boston|isbn=0-395-46727-6|pages=[https://archive.org/details/waterfowl00stev/page/140 140–141]|url=https://archive.org/details/waterfowl00stev/page/140}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Ogilvie&gt;{{cite book|last=Ogilvie|first=Malcolm A.|last2=Young|first2=Steve |title=Wildfowl of the World |location=London|publisher=[[New Holland Publishers]] |year=2004|isbn=978-1-84330-328-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Rowland&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rowland |first1=Beryl |title=Birds with Human Souls: a Guide to Bird Symbolism |date=1978 |publisher=[[University of Tennessee Press]] |page=[https://archive.org/details/birdswithhumanso0000rowl/page/69 69] |isbn=0870492152 |url=https://archive.org/details/birdswithhumanso0000rowl/page/69 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Scheiber&gt;{{cite book|last1=Scheiber |first1=Isabella B.R. |last2=Weiß |first2=Brigitte M.|last3=Hemetsberger |first3=Josef  |last4=Kotrschal |first4=Kurt |title=The Social Life of Greylag Geese|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fTgoAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA9 |year=2013 |location=New York |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-82270-1 |pages=9–10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Witherby&gt;{{cite book |title=Handbook of British Birds, Volume 3: Hawks to Ducks |editor-last=Witherby |editor-first=H. F.  |authorlink=Harry Forbes Witherby|year=1943|location=London |publisher=H. F. and G. Witherby Ltd. |pages=149–186 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Lorenz|first=Konrad Z.|authorlink=Konrad Lorenz|last2=Martys|first2=Michael|last3=Tipler|first3=Angelika|translator=Robert D. Martin|title=Here Am I—Where Are You? The Behavior of the Greylag Goose|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|location=Orlando, Florida|year=1991|isbn=0-15-140056-3|url=https://archive.org/details/hereamiwherearey00lore}}
*{{cite journal|journal=Folia Biol.|location=Krakow|year=2007|volume=55|pages=35–40|url=http://www.isez.pan.krakow.pl/journals/folia/pdf/55%281-2%29/05.pdf|format=[[Portable Document Format|PDF]]|issue=1–2|title=Description of the ''Anser anser'' Goose Karyotype|first=Ewa|last=Wójcik|first2=Elżbieta|last2=Smalec}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Anser anser|Greylag Goose}}
{{Wikispecies|Anser anser}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20170712075411/http://aulaenred.ibercaja.es/wp-content/uploads/63_GreylagGooseAanser.pdf Ageing and sexing (PDF) by Javier Blasco-Zumeta &amp; Gerd-Michael Heinze]
*[http://www.rspb.org.uk/birds/guide/g/greylaggoose/index.asp Greylag Goose at RSPB A to Z of UK Birds]
*{{InternetBirdCollection|greylag-goose-anser-anser|Greylag Goose}}
*[http://www.nature-pictures.org/foto/58/ Greylag Goose pictures] Wildlife Greylag Goose photos- adult with nestlings and voice at nature-pictures.org
*{{VIREO|graylag+goose|Graylag Goose}}
*{{IUCN_Map|22679889|Anser anser}}

{{Taxonbar |from=Q25882}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:goose, greylag}}
[[Category:Anser (bird)|greylag goose]]
[[Category:Geese|greylag goose]]
[[Category:Birds of Eurasia]]
[[Category:Birds described in 1758|greylag goose]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Taxa named by Carl Linnaeus|greylag goose]]</text>
      <sha1>pd0fagzdzmviq31xfzwa6n58octdpgc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
