<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Twenty-One Balloons</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1644687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943976154</id>
      <parentid>943976018</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-04T23:23:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:2C7:980:2E60:20F5:3421:915C:E7F8</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9513" xml:space="preserve">{{infobox book|&lt;!-- See [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Novels]] or [[a:WikiProject Books]] --&gt;
| name = The Twenty-One Balloons
| title_orig = 
| translator = 
| image = 21BalloonsCover.jpeg
| caption = First edition
| author = William
| illustrator = William DE bulis
| cover_artist = 
| country = United States
| language = English
| series = 
| genre = [[Children's literature|Children's novel]]
| publisher = [[The Viking Press]]
| release_date = 1947
| english_release_date = 
| media_type = Print ([[hardcover]] and [[paperback]])
| pages = 181
| isbn = 0-14-032097-0
| oclc = 17885994
| preceded_by = 
| followed_by = 
}}

'''''The Twenty-One Balloons''''' is a [[novel]] by [[William Pène du Bois]], published in 1947 by the Viking Press and awarded the [[Newbery Medal]] for excellence in [[United States|American]] [[children's literature]] in 1948. The story is about a retired schoolteacher whose ill-fated balloon trip leads him to discover an island full of great wealth and fantastic inventions. The events and ideas are based both on scientific fact and imagination, and the descriptions are accompanied by illustrations by du Bois.

==Plot summary==

The introduction compares two types of journeys: one that aims to reach a place within the shortest time, and another that begins without regard to speed and without a destination in mind. Balloon travel is said to be ideal for the second kind.

The main story begins with the rescue of Professor William Waterman Sherman, who is picked up by a steamship while floating among a strange wreck of twenty deflated [[gas balloon]]s in the [[North Atlantic]]. Sherman, a recently retired schoolteacher, was last seen three weeks earlier leaving [[San Francisco]] on a giant balloon, determined to spend a year drifting alone, because he wants to relax. The world waits breathlessly to find out how Sherman could have circumnavigated the globe in record time and landed in the ocean with twenty balloons rather than the one with which he began his journey. After several days' rest and a hero's welcome, the professor recounts his journey before a captivated audience.

Sherman's flight over the [[Pacific Ocean]] was uneventful until an unfortunate accident involving a seagull puncturing his balloon forced him to crash land on the volcanic island of [[Krakatoa]]. He discovers from Mr.F that the island is populated by twenty families sharing the wealth of a secret [[diamond mine]] - by far the richest in the world - which they operate as a [[cartel]]. Each year, the families sail to the outside world with a small amount of diamonds, to purchase supplies for the hidden and sophisticated civilization they have built on the island (they explain that introducing too many diamonds into the market at once would drive down their value to "a shipload of broken glass"). Each family has been assigned one of the first twenty letters of the alphabet, and lives in its own whimsical and elaborate house that also serves as a restaurant. The Krakatoa society follows a calendar with twenty-day months. On "A" Day of each month, everyone eats in Mr. and Mrs. A's [[Cuisine of the United States|American]] restaurant; on "B" Day, in Mr. and Mrs. B's [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Meat chop|chop]] house; on "C" Day, in Mr. and Mrs. C's [[Chinese cuisine|Chinese]] restaurant; on "D" Day, in Mr. and Mrs. D's [[Dutch cuisine|Dutch]] restaurant, and so forth. Sherman's first friend on the island, Mr. F, runs a [[French cuisine|French]] restaurant containing a replica of the [[Hall of Mirrors]]. The houses are full of incredible items, such as Mr. M's [[Morocco|Moroccan]] house, which has a living room with mobile furniture that operate like [[bumper cars]]. The children of the island invented their own form of amusement that combines elements from [[merry-go-round]]s and balloon travel.

When the volcano on Krakatoa [[1883 eruption of Krakatoa|erupts]], the families and Sherman escape on a platform held aloft by twenty balloons. As the platform drifts westward around the world, the families parachute off to India and Belgium to start their new lives. Sherman remains on the platform and finally descends onto the waters of the Atlantic Ocean, where he is rescued. The professor concludes his speech by telling the audience he intends to build an improved balloon for a year of life in the air, financed by the diamond cufflinks he obtained in Krakatoa.

The novel describes Krakatoa as an island in the Pacific Ocean, but the [[Sunda Strait]] that contains the island is considered an arm of the [[Indian Ocean]].

==Comparison to ''The Diamond as Big as the Ritz''==

The story is preceded by a note from du Bois,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Twenty-One Balloons|url=https://archive.org/details/twentyoneballoon00dubo|url-access=registration|first=William|last=Pène du Bois|publisher=The Viking Press|year=1947}} Page headed ''Author's Note'' preceding the table of contents&lt;/ref&gt; informing that just before publication his publisher noted a "strong resemblance" between the book and ''[[The Diamond as Big as the Ritz]]'', a novella written by [[F. Scott Fitzgerald]] in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Diamond as Big as the Ritz|url=http://www.sc.edu/fitzgerald/diamond/index.html|publisher=The Board of Trustees of the University of South Carolina|date=1998-01-22|accessdate=2006-07-15|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/19990302051221/http://www.sc.edu/fitzgerald/diamond/index.html|archivedate=1999-03-02}}: first appeared in the magazine "The Smart Set", 1922. [http://www.sc.edu/fitzgerald/diamond/diamond.html Full text online] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050901022550/http://sc.edu/fitzgerald/diamond/diamond.html |date=2005-09-01 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title="The Diamond as Big as the Ritz" and Other stories |publisher=Courier Dover Publications |year=1998 |origyear=1920, 1922 |isbn=0-486-29991-0 |first=F. Scott |last=Fitzgerald}}, copyright page attributes a story as having been published in {{cite book |title=Tales of the Jazz Age |url=https://archive.org/details/talesofjazzage00fitz |publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons |location=New York |year=1922}}&lt;/ref&gt; Du Bois acknowledges it is "not only quite similar in general plot, but was also altogether a collection of very similar ideas." He says it was the first time he had heard of Fitzgerald's story, and "the fact that F. Scott Fitzgerald and I apparently would spend our billion in like ways right down to being dumped from bed into a bathtub is, quite frankly, beyond my explanation."

The two stories share the common concept of a giant diamond mine and the resulting need to protect the secret of its existence. However, they differ significantly in tone and plot details. Fitzgerald's story does not involve balloons, nor a Utopian society on Krakatoa, nor fantastic mechanical inventions like those described in du Bois's story. Fitzgerald's story also takes a darker tone, with the mad owner of the mine having constructed a hollow in the earth to imprison the unfortunates who had discovered the mine. The story's protagonist has a [[sexual encounter]] with the daughter of the mine owner, and discovers that he faces execution.

The stories also differ in their intentions and audiences. ''The Twenty-One Balloons'' is a children's story, with only a mild, playful interest in social commentary. By contrast, "The Diamond as Big as the Ritz" is a [[parable]] for adults; it articulates large social themes that preoccupied Fitzgerald throughout his career as a mature writer, and which found their way into his major novels, notably ''[[The Great Gatsby]]''.

==The two stories in popular culture==
In the TV show ''[[Mad Men]]'', season four, episode five ("[[The Chrysanthemum and the Sword (Mad Men)|The Chrysanthemum and the Sword]]"), the du Bois novel is being read by a child, [[List of Mad Men characters#Sally Draper|Sally Draper]]; in season two, episode three ("[[Mad Men (season 2)#Episodes|The Benefactor]]"), her mother, [[Betty Draper]], reads out of the Fitzgerald collection containing his story (''[[Babylon Revisited and Other Stories]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{url
| 1 = http://www.nypl.org/blog/2012/01/19/mad-men-mystery-solved
| 2 = A "Mad Men" Mystery Solved &amp;ndash; The New York Public Library
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*{{isfdb title|id=172191|title=The Twenty-One Balloons}}

*The motion picture and digital rights to ''The Twenty-One Balloons'' are owned by Big View Pictures Inc.{{Primary source inline|date=March 2018|reason=Isolated, one-project site that hasn't been updated since 2004, according to the Internet Archive. The only non-primary sources available seem to have no further information, indicating sourcing from either Wikipedia or original site.}}  The flash story board for the film project can be viewed online http://bigviewpictures.com



{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|aw}}
{{succession box|title=[[Newbery Medal|Newbery Medal recipient]]|before=''[[Miss Hickory]]''|after=''[[King of the Wind]]''|years=[[1948 in literature|1948]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Twenty-One Balloons, The}}
[[Category:Newbery Medal-winning works]]
[[Category:1947 American novels]]
[[Category:American children's novels]]
[[Category:Balloons (aircraft)]]
[[Category:Children's fantasy novels]]
[[Category:Fiction set in 1883]]
[[Category:Krakatoa]]
[[Category:Novels set in Indonesia]]
[[Category:Novels set in San Francisco]]
[[Category:Viking Press books]]
[[Category:1947 children's books]]</text>
      <sha1>8n3nmtf2pxov1o76eaojxkqj7xkzvny</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
