<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetics of depression</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46690704</id>
    <revision>
      <id>951587955</id>
      <parentid>941396256</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-17T21:44:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OAbot</username>
        <id>28481209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:OABOT|Open access bot]]: doi added to citation with #oabot.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="35480" xml:space="preserve">{{MEDREF|date=September 2018}}

[[Major depressive disorder]] is heavily influenced by environmental and genetic factors. These factors include [[Epigenetics|epigenetic]] modification of the genome in which there is a persistent change in [[gene expression]] without a change in the actual DNA sequence.  Genetic and environmental factors can influence the genome throughout a life; however, an individual is most susceptible during childhood.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Heim C, Binder EB | title = Current research trends in early life stress and depression: review of human studies on sensitive periods, gene-environment interactions, and epigenetics | journal = Experimental Neurology | volume = 233 | issue = 1 | pages = 102–11 | date = January 2012 | pmid = 22101006 | doi = 10.1016/j.expneurol.2011.10.032 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Early life stresses that could lead to major depressive disorder include periodic maternal separation, child abuse, divorce, and loss.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Toyokawa S, Uddin M, Koenen KC, Galea S | title = How does the social environment 'get into the mind'? Epigenetics at the intersection of social and psychiatric epidemiology | journal = Social Science &amp; Medicine | volume = 74 | issue = 1 | pages = 67–74 | date = January 2012 | pmid = 22119520 | doi = 10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.09.036 | pmc = 3246041 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vialou V, Feng J, Robison AJ, Nestler EJ | title = Epigenetic mechanisms of depression and antidepressant action | journal = Annual Review of Pharmacology and Toxicology | volume = 53 | pages = 59–87 | date = 2013 | pmid = 23020296 | pmc = 3711377 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-pharmtox-010611-134540 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These factors can result in epigenetic marks that can alter gene expression and impact the development of key brain regions such as the hippocampus.&lt;ref name="Sun" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;Epigenetic factors, such as methylation, could serve as predictors for the effectiveness of certain antidepressant treatments.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Currently, antidepressants can be used to stabilize moods and decrease global DNA methylation levels, but they could also be used to determine the risk of depression caused by epigenetic changes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Menke A, Binder EB | title = Epigenetic alterations in depression and antidepressant treatment | journal = Dialogues in Clinical Neuroscience | volume = 16 | issue = 3 | pages = 395–404 | date = September 2014 | pmid = 25364288 | pmc = 4214180 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Identifying gene with altered expression could result in new antidepressant treatments.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

==Epigenetic alterations in depression==
===Histone deacetylases===
[[Histone deacetylase|Histone deacetylases]] (HDACs) are a class of enzymes that [[Histone acetylation and deacetylation|remove acetyl groups from histones]]. Different HDACs play different roles in response to depression, and these effects often vary in different parts of the body. In the [[nucleus accumbens]] (NaC), it is generally found that H3K14 acetylation decreases after chronic stress (used to produce a depression-like state in rodent model systems). However, after a while, this acetylation begins to increase again, and is correlated with a decrease in the activity and production of [[Histone deacetylase 2|HDAC2]].&lt;ref name="Covington"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Covington HE, Maze I, LaPlant QC, Vialou VF, Ohnishi YN, Berton O, Fass DM, Renthal W, Rush AJ, Wu EY, Ghose S, Krishnan V, Russo SJ, Tamminga C, Haggarty SJ, Nestler EJ | display-authors = 6 | title = Antidepressant actions of histone deacetylase inhibitors | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 29 | issue = 37 | pages = 11451–60 | date = September 2009 | pmid = 19759294 | pmc = 2775805 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1758-09.2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adding HDAC2i (an [[Histone deacetylase inhibitor|HDAC2 inhibitor]]) leads to an improvement of the symptoms of depression in animal model systems.&lt;ref name=Sun&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sun H, Kennedy PJ, Nestler EJ | title = Epigenetics of the depressed brain: role of histone acetylation and methylation | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 38 | issue = 1 | pages = 124–37 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 22692567 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2012.73 | doi-access = free | pmc = 3521990 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, mice with a [[Mutation#By effect on function|dominant negative]] HDAC2 mutation, which suppresses HDAC2 enzymatic activity, generally show less depressive behavior than mice who do not have this dominant negative mutation.&lt;ref name="Uchida"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Uchida S, Hara K, Kobayashi A, Otsuki K, Yamagata H, Hobara T, Suzuki T, Miyata N, Watanabe Y | title = Epigenetic status of Gdnf in the ventral striatum determines susceptibility and adaptation to daily stressful events | journal = Neuron | volume = 69 | issue = 2 | pages = 359–72 | date = January 2011 | pmid = 21262472 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2010.12.023 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Histone deacetylase 5|HDAC5]] shows the opposite trend in the NaC. A lack of HDAC5 leads to an increase in depressive behaviors. This is thought to be due to the fact that HDAC2 targets have antidepressant properties, while targets of HDAC5 have depressant properties.&lt;ref name="Sun"/&gt;

In the [[hippocampus]], there is a correlation between decreased [[acetylation]] and depressive behavior in response to stress. For example, H3K14 and H4K12 acetylation was found to be decreased, as well as general acetylation across [[Histone H2B|histones H2B]] and [[Histone H3|H3]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Covington HE, Vialou VF, LaPlant Q, Ohnishi YN, Nestler EJ | title = Hippocampal-dependent antidepressant-like activity of histone deacetylase inhibition | journal = Neuroscience Letters | volume = 493 | issue = 3 | pages = 122–6 | date = April 2011 | pmid = 21335060 | pmc = 3074929 | doi = 10.1016/j.neulet.2011.02.022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hollis F, Duclot F, Gunjan A, Kabbaj M | title = Individual differences in the effect of social defeat on anhedonia and histone acetylation in the rat hippocampus | journal = Hormones and Behavior | volume = 59 | issue = 3 | pages = 331–7 | date = March 2011 | pmid = 20851702 | pmc = 3037445 | doi = 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2010.09.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tsankova_2004"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tsankova NM, Kumar A, Nestler EJ | title = Histone modifications at gene promoter regions in rat hippocampus after acute and chronic electroconvulsive seizures | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 24 | issue = 24 | pages = 5603–10 | date = June 2004 | pmid = 15201333 | pmc = 6729334 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0589-04.2004 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another study found that [[HDAC3]] was decreased in individuals resilient to depression. In the hippocampus, increased HDAC5 was found with increased depressive behavior (unlike in the nucleus accumbens).&lt;ref name="Sun" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Tsankova_2004" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ferland CL, Schrader LA | title = Regulation of histone acetylation in the hippocampus of chronically stressed rats: a potential role of sirtuins | journal = Neuroscience | volume = 174 | pages = 104–14 | date = February 2011 | pmid = 21056634 | pmc = 3020273 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.10.077 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Histone methyltransferases===

Like HDACs, [[histone methyltransferases]] (HMTs) alter histones, but these enzymes are involved in the transfer of [[methyl groups]] to the histone's [[arginine]] and [[lysine]] residues. Chronic stress has been found to decrease the levels of a number of HMTs, such as [[EHMT2|G9a]], in the NAc of susceptible mice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Covington HE, Maze I, Sun H, Bomze HM, DeMaio KD, Wu EY, Dietz DM, Lobo MK, Ghose S, Mouzon E, Neve RL, Tamminga CA, Nestler EJ | display-authors = 6 | title = A role for repressive histone methylation in cocaine-induced vulnerability to stress | journal = Neuron | volume = 71 | issue = 4 | pages = 656–70 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21867882 | pmc = 3163060 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2011.06.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, in resilient mice, these HMTs have increased activity. H3K9 and H3K27 have less methylation when depressive behavior is seen. The hippocampus also experiences a number of histone methylation changes: H3K27-trimethylation is hypomethylated in response to stress, while H3K9-trimethylation and H3K4-trimethylation are hypermethylated in response to short term stress. However, H3K9-trimethylation and H3K4-trimethylation can also be hypomethylated in response to chronic, long term stress. In general, stress leading to depression is correlated with a decrease in methylation and a decrease in the activity of HMTs.{{Cn|date=January 2018}}

===Brain-derived neurotrophic factor===

[[Brain-derived neurotrophic factor]] (BDNF) is a neurotrophic [[growth factor]] that plays an important role in memory, learning, and higher thinking. It has been found that BDNF [[Blood plasma|plasma]] levels and hippocampal volume are decreased in individuals suffering from depression.&lt;ref name="Covington" /&gt; The expression of BDNF can be affected by different epigenetic modifications, and BDNF [[Promoter (genetics)|promoters]] can be individually regulated by different epigenetic alterations. [[MECP2|MeCP2]] can act as a [[repressor]] and has been shown to regulate BDNF when activated. [[Depolarization]] of neurons causing an increase in calcium leads to the [[phosphorylation]] of MeCP2, which results in a decrease in the binding of MeCP2 to BDNF promoter IV.&lt;ref name="Karpova"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Karpova NN | title = Role of BDNF epigenetics in activity-dependent neuronal plasticity | journal = Neuropharmacology | volume = 76 Pt C | pages = 709–18 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 23587647 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuropharm.2013.04.002 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because MeCP2 can no longer bind to the BDNF promoter and repress transcription, BDNF levels increase and neuronal development improves. When there is direct methylation of the BDNF promoter, transcription of BDNF is repressed. Stressful situations have been shown to cause increased methylation of BDNF promoter IV, which causes an increase in MeCP2 binding, and as a result reduction in the activity of BDNF in the hippocampus and depressive behavior. BDNF maintains the survival of neurons in the hippocampus, and decreased levels can cause hippocampal [[atrophy]]. Also, there was found to be increased methylation of BDNF region IV CpGs in the [[Wernicke area]] of the brain in suicidal individuals.&lt;ref name="Karpova" /&gt; The interaction of BDNF and MeCP2 is complex, and there are instances where MeCP2 can cause an increase in BDNF levels instead of repressing. Previous studies have found that in MeCP2 knockout mice, the release and trafficking of BDNF within the neurons are significantly decreased in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name="Xu"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Xu X, Kozikowski AP, Pozzo-Miller L | title = A selective histone deacetylase-6 inhibitor improves BDNF trafficking in hippocampal neurons from Mecp2 knockout mice: implications for Rett syndrome | journal = Frontiers in Cellular Neuroscience | volume = 8 | pages = 68 | pmid = 24639629 | pmc = 3945638 | doi = 10.3389/fncel.2014.00068 | year = 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another epigenetic modification of BDNF promoters is the neuron-restrictive silencing factor ([[RE1-silencing transcription factor|REST or NRSF]]) which epigenetically regulates the BDNF promoter I and is repressed by MeCP2. Like MeCP2, REST has also been found to inhibit BDNF transcription.

===Hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis===

[[File:HPA Axis Diagram (Brian M Sweis 2012).png|thumb|HPA axis diagram|300x300px]]

In the [[hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis]] (HPA Axis), [[corticotropin-releasing factor]] (CRF) is secreted by the hypothalamus in response to stress and other normal body processes. CRH then acts on the [[anterior pituitary]] and causes it to secrete [[adrenocorticotropic hormone]] (ACTH). ACTH acts on the [[adrenal cortex]] to secrete [[cortisol]], which acts as a [[Negative feedback#Biology and chemistry|negative feedback]] indicator of the pathway. When an individual is exposed to stressful situations, the HPA axis activates the [[sympathetic nervous system]] and also increases the production of CRF, ACTH, and cortisol, which in turn increases [[Blood sugar level|blood glucose levels]] and suppresses the immune system. Increased expression of CRF has been found in the [[cerebrospinal fluid]] in depressed monkeys and rats, as well as individuals with depression. Increased CRF levels have also been seen in the hypothalamus of depressed individuals.&lt;ref name="Depression"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Binder EB, Nemeroff CB | title = The CRF system, stress, depression and anxiety-insights from human genetic studies | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 15 | issue = 6 | pages = 574–88 | year = 2010 | pmid = 20010888 | pmc = 3666571 | doi = 10.1038/mp.2009.141 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was found that pregnant mice in early gestation stage who were exposed to chronic stress produced offspring with a decreased methylation of the CRF promoter in the hypothalamus area.&lt;ref name="Murgatroyd"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Epigenetics of early child development| pmc=3102328 | pmid=21647402 | doi=10.3389/fpsyt.2011.00016| volume=2| journal=Front Psychiatry| pages=16| vauthors=Murgatroyd C, Spengler D| year=2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This decreased methylation would cause increased expression of CRF and thus, increased activity of the HPA axis. The higher levels of the HPA axis in response to chronic stress can also cause damage to the hippocampus region of the brain. Increased cortisol levels can lead to a decrease in hippocampal volume which is commonly seen in depressed individuals.

===Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor===

[[Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor|Glial cell-derived neurotrophic factor]] (GDNF) is a protein that aids in the survival and differentiation of [[dopaminergic]] neurons. By looking at expression levels in the nucleus accumbens, it is seen that GDNF expression is decreased in strains of mice susceptible to depression.&lt;ref name="Sun" /&gt; It has also been shown that increased GDNF expression in the [[ventral tegmental area]] is present in mice that are not susceptible to [[Social defeat#In human|social defeat stress]] by promoting the survival of neurons.&lt;ref name="Krishnan"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Krishnan V, Han MH, Graham DL, Berton O, Renthal W, Russo SJ, Laplant Q, Graham A, Lutter M, Lagace DC, Ghose S, Reister R, Tannous P, Green TA, Neve RL, Chakravarty S, Kumar A, Eisch AJ, Self DW, Lee FS, Tamminga CA, Cooper DC, Gershenfeld HK, Nestler EJ | display-authors = 6 | title = Molecular adaptations underlying susceptibility and resistance to social defeat in brain reward regions | journal = Cell | volume = 131 | issue = 2 | pages = 391–404 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17956738 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2007.09.018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lin LF, Doherty DH, Lile JD, Bektesh S, Collins F | title = GDNF: a glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor for midbrain dopaminergic neurons | journal = Science | volume = 260 | issue = 5111 | pages = 1130–2 | date = May 1993 | pmid = 8493557 | doi = 10.1126/science.8493557 | bibcode = 1993Sci...260.1130L }}&lt;/ref&gt; The ventral tegmenal area and nucleus accumbens network of the [[Mesolimbic pathway|mesolimbic]] dopamine system is thought to be involved in the resistance and susceptibility to chronic stress (which leads to depressed behavior). Thus it is seen that GDNF, by protecting neurons of the mesolimbic pathway, helps to protect against depressive behavior.&lt;ref name="LaPlant_2010" /&gt; After chronic stress, there are a number of changes that result in the reduction of GDNF levels in the nucleus accumbens. This decrease is associated with decreased H3 acetylation and decreased H3K4-trimethylation, as well as an increased amount of DNA methylation at particular [[CpG site|CpG]] sites on the GDNF promoter.&lt;ref name="LaPlant_2010" /&gt; This DNA methylation is associated with histone deacetylase 2 and [[methyl CpG binding protein 2]] (MeCP2) recruitment to the GDNF promoter.&lt;ref name = "LaPlant_2010"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = LaPlant Q, Vialou V, Covington HE, Dumitriu D, Feng J, Warren BL, Maze I, Dietz DM, Watts EL, Iñiguez SD, Koo JW, Mouzon E, Renthal W, Hollis F, Wang H, Noonan MA, Ren Y, Eisch AJ, Bolaños CA, Kabbaj M, Xiao G, Neve RL, Hurd YL, Oosting RS, Fan G, Morrison JH, Nestler EJ | display-authors = 6 | title = Dnmt3a regulates emotional behavior and spine plasticity in the nucleus accumbens | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 13 | issue = 9 | pages = 1137–43 | date = September 2010 | pmid = 20729844 | pmc = 2928863 | doi = 10.1038/nn.2619 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Increased HDAC activity results in a reduction of GDNF expression, since HDAC causes the decreased acetylation at H3. Alternatively, knocking out HDACs (via HDAC [[RNA interference|interference]]) results in normalization of GDNF levels, and as a result, decreased depression like behavior, even in susceptible strains of mice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miller CA | title = Stressed and depressed? Check your GDNF for epigenetic repression | journal = Neuron | volume = 69 | issue = 2 | pages = 188–90 | date = January 2011 | pmid = 21262458 | pmc = 3785080 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2011.01.006 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cyclic amp response element-binding protein|Cyclic-AMP response element-binding protein]] (CREB), which is thought to be involved in GDNF regulation, associates with the aforementioned MeCP2, and complexes to methylated CpG sites on the GDNF promoter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chahrour M, Jung SY, Shaw C, Zhou X, Wong ST, Qin J, Zoghbi HY | title = MeCP2, a key contributor to neurological disease, activates and represses transcription | journal = Science | volume = 320 | issue = 5880 | pages = 1224–9 | date = May 2008 | pmid = 18511691 | pmc = 2443785 | doi = 10.1126/science.1153252 | bibcode = 2008Sci...320.1224C }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cen X, Nitta A, Ohya S, Zhao Y, Ozawa N, Mouri A, Ibi D, Wang L, Suzuki M, Saito K, Ito Y, Kawagoe T, Noda Y, Ito Y, Furukawa S, Nabeshima T | display-authors = 6 | title = An analog of a dipeptide-like structure of FK506 increases glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor expression through cAMP response element-binding protein activated by heat shock protein 90/Akt signaling pathway | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 26 | issue = 12 | pages = 3335–44 | date = March 2006 | pmid = 16554484 | pmc = 6674092 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5010-05.2006 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; This recruitment of CREB plays a role in the repression of GDNF in the nucleus accumbens. As further evidence that DNA methylation plays a role in depressive behavior, delivery of [[DNA methyltransferase inhibitor|DNA methyltransferase inhibitors]] results in a reversal of depression-like behaviors.
 
It is seen that DNA methylation of the GDNF [[promoter region]] results in the recruitment of MeCP2 and HDACs, resulting in an epigenetic alteration of the histone marks. This correlates to an increase in depression-like behavior.

===Glucocorticoid receptor===

[[Glucocorticoid receptors]] (GR) are receptors to which cortisol (and other [[glucocorticoid]]s) bind. The bound receptor is involved in the regulation of gene transcription.&lt;ref name="Sun" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Weaver"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Weaver IC, Cervoni N, Champagne FA, D'Alessio AC, Sharma S, Seckl JR, Dymov S, Szyf M, Meaney MJ | title = Epigenetic programming by maternal behavior | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 7 | issue = 8 | pages = 847–54 | date = August 2004 | pmid = 15220929 | doi = 10.1038/nn1276 | url = https://www.reed.edu/biology/professors/srenn/pages/teaching/2008_syllabus/2008_readings/5_Weaver_etal_2004.pdf | via =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The GR gene promoter region has a sequence that allows for binding by the transcription factor [[EGR1|nerve growth factor induced protein A]] (NGFI-A), which is involved in [[neuronal plasticity]]. In rats, it has been shown that individuals less susceptible to depressive behavior have increased binding of NGFI-A to the promoter region of the GR gene, specifically in the hippocampus. As a result, there is an increased amount of hippocampal GR expression, both in transcription of its [[mRNA]] and overall protein level.

This is associated with an increase in acetylation of H3K9 in the GR promoter region. Methylation of [[CpG islands]] in the promoter region of GR leads to a decrease in the ability of NGFI-A to bind to the GR promoter region. It has also been experimentally shown that methylation of CpG sites in the [[Enhancer (genetics)|enhancer region]] bound by NGFI-A is detrimental to the ability of NGFI-A to bind to the promoter region.&lt;ref name="Weaver 2"&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Transcription Factor Nerve Growth Factor-Inducible Protein A Mediates Epigenetic Programming: Altering Epigenetic Marks by Immediate-Early Genes| pmid=17301183 | doi=10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4164-06.2007 | volume=27| issue=7| pmc=2951014| journal=J Neurosci| pages=1756–68| vauthors=Weaver IC, D'Alessio AC, Brown SE, Hellstrom IC, Dymov S, Sharma S, Szyf M, Meaney MJ| year=2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the methylation of the promoter region results in a decrease in recruitment of the [[CREB-binding protein]], which has [[histone acetyltransferase]] ability. This results in less acetylation of the histones, which has been shown to be a modification that takes place within individuals less susceptible to depression.&lt;ref name="Weaver 2" /&gt;

Due to environmental factors, there is a decrease in methylation of the promoter region of the GR gene, which then allows for increased binding of the NGFI-A protein, and as a result, an increase in the expression of the GR gene. This results in decreased depressive behavior.

==Treatment==
{{Organize section|date=February 2018}}

===Antidepressants===

Through computational methodology, epigenetics has been found to play a critical role in mood disorder susceptibility and development, and has also been shown to mediate treatment response to SSRI medications. SSRI medications including fluoxetine, paroxetine, and escitalopram reduce gene expression and enzymatic activity related to methylation and acetylation pathways in numerous brain regions implicated in patients with major depression.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"&gt;{{cite book|title=Fluoxetine: Pharmacology, Mechanism of Action and Potential side effects|last=Pina|first=Graziano |year=2015|isbn=978-1-63482-077-6|pages=125–167|name-list-format=vanc}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pharmacogenetic research has focused on epigenetic factors related to BDNF, which has been a biomarker for neuropsychiatric diseases. BDNF has been shown to be sensitive to the prolonged effects of stress (a common risk factor of depressive phenotypes), with epigenetic modifications (primarily histone methylation) at BDNF promoters and splice variants. Such variation in gene splicing and repressed hippocampal BDNF expression is associated with major depressive disorder while increased expression in this region is associated with successful antidepressant treatment.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167" /&gt;  Patients suffering from major depression and bipolar disorder show increased methylation at BDNF promoters and reduced BDNF mRNA levels in the brain and in blood monocytes while SSRI treatment in patients with depression results in decreased histone methylation and increased BDNF levels.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167" /&gt;

In addition to the BDNF gene, micro RNAs (miRNAs) play a role in mood disorders, and transcript levels are suggested in SSRI treatment efficacy. Post-mortem work in patients with major depressive disorder, as well as other psychiatric diseases, show that miRNAs play a critical role in regulating brain structure via synaptic plasticity and neurogenesis.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; Increased hippocampal neural development plays a role in the efficacy of antidepressant treatment, while reductions in such development is related to neuropsychiatric disorders.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; In particular, the miRNA MIR-16 plays a critical role in regulating these processes in individuals with mood disorders. Increased hippocampal MIR-16 inhibits proteins which promote neurogenesis including the serotonin transporter (SERT), which is the target of SSRI therapeutics.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; MIR-16 downregulates SERT expression in humans, which decreases the number of serotonin transporters.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; Inhibition of MIR-16 therefore promotes SERT production and serves as a target for SSRI therapeutics.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; SSRI medications increase neurogenesis in the hippocampus by reductions in MIR-16, thereby restoring hippocampal neuronal activity following treatment in patients suffering from neuropsychiatric disorders.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; In patients with major depressive disorder, treatment with SSRI medications results in differential expression of 30 miRNAs, half of which play a role in modulating neuronal structure and/or are implicated in psychiatric disorders.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt;

Understanding epigenetic profiles of patients suffering from neuropsychiatric disorders in key brain regions has led to more knowledge of patient outcome following SSRI treatment. Genome wide association studies seek to assess individual polymorphisms in genes which are implicated in depressive phenotypes, and aid in the efficacy of pharmacogenetic studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fabbri C, Minarini A, Niitsu T, Serretti A | title = Understanding the pharmacogenetics of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors | journal = Expert Opinion on Drug Metabolism &amp; Toxicology | volume = 10 | issue = 8 | pages = 1093–118 | date = August 2014 | pmid = 24930681 | doi = 10.1517/17425255.2014.928693 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Single-nucleotide polymorphisms of the 5-HT(2A) gene correlated with paroxetine discontinuation due to side effects in a group of elderly patients with major depression, but not mirtazapine (a non-SSRI antidepressant) discontinuation. In addition, hypomethylation of the SERT promoter was correlated with poor patient outcomes and treatment success following 6 weeks of escitalopram treatment.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt; Such work addressing methylation patterns in the periphery has been shown to be comparable to methylation patterns in brain tissue, and provides information allowing for tailored pharmacogenetic approaches.&lt;ref name="Pina 2015 125–167"/&gt;

====BDNF as a serotonin modulator====

Decreased brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) is known to be associated with depression. Research suggests that increasing BDNF can reverse some symptoms of depression. For instance, increased BDNF signaling can reverse the reduced hippocampal brain signaling observed in animal models of depression. BDNF is involved in depression through its effects on serotonin. BDNF has been shown to promote the development, function, and expression of serotonergic neurons.&lt;ref name="Martinowich"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Martinowich K, Lu B | title = Interaction between BDNF and serotonin: role in mood disorders | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 33 | issue = 1 | pages = 73–83 | year = 2008 | pmid = 17882234 | doi = 10.1038/sj.npp.1301571 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because more active serotonin results in more positive moods, antidepressants work to increase serotonin levels. Tricyclic antidepressants generally work by blocking [[serotonin transporter]]s in order to keep serotonin in the synaptic cleft where it is still active. Noradrenergic and specific serotonergic antidepressants antagonize serotonin receptors. Noradrenergic and specific serotonergic antidepressants ([[Noradrenergic and specific serotonergic antidepressant|NaSSAs]])  such as [[Mirtazapine|miratzapine]] and [[tricyclic antidepressant]]s such as [[Imipramine|imapramine]] both increased BDNF in the cerebral cortices and hippocampi of rats.&lt;ref name="Rogo"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rogóz Z, Skuza G, Legutko B | title = Repeated treatment with mirtazepine induces brain-derived neurotrophic factor gene expression in rats | journal = Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology | volume = 56 | issue = 4 | pages = 661–71 | date = December 2005 | pmid = 16391422 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because BDNF mRNA levels increase with long-term miratzapine use, increasing BDNF gene expression may be necessary for improvements in depressive behaviors. This also increases the potential for neuronal plasticity.&lt;ref name="Zobel"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zobel A, Maier W | title = Pharmacogenetics of antidepressive treatment | journal = European Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience | volume = 260 | issue = 5 | pages = 407–17 | date = August 2010 | pmid = 20047055 | doi = 10.1007/s00406-009-0091-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Generally, these antidepressants increase peripheral BDNF levels by reducing methylation at BDNF promoters that are known to modulate serotonin.&lt;ref name="Menke"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Menke A, Binder EB | title = Epigenetic alterations in depression and antidepressant treatment | journal = Dialogues in Clinical Neuroscience | volume = 16 | issue = 3 | pages = 395–404 | date = September 2014 | pmid = 25364288 | pmc = 4214180 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As BDNF expression is increased when [[H3K27me3]] is decreased with antidepressant treatment, BDNF increases its effect on serotonin modulation.&lt;ref name="Duclot"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Duclot F, Kabbaj M | title = Epigenetic mechanisms underlying the role of brain-derived neurotrophic factor in depression and response to antidepressants | journal = The Journal of Experimental Biology | volume = 218 | issue = Pt 1 | pages = 21–31 | year = 2015 | pmid = 25568448 | pmc = 4286703 | doi = 10.1242/jeb.107086 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It modulates serotonin by downregulating the [[G protein–coupled receptor|G protein-coupled receptor]], [[5-HT2A receptor|5-HT2A]] receptor protein levels in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name="Trajkovska"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Trajkovska V, Santini MA, Marcussen AB, Thomsen MS, Hansen HH, Mikkelsen JD, Arneberg L, Kokaia M, Knudsen GM, Aznar S | title = BDNF downregulates 5-HT(2A) receptor protein levels in hippocampal cultures | journal = Neurochemistry International | volume = 55 | issue = 7 | pages = 697–702 | date = December 2009 | pmid = 19563850 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuint.2009.06.013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This increased BDNF increases the inhibition of presynaptic serotonin uptake, which results in fewer symptoms of depression.

====Effects of antidepressants on glucocorticoid receptors====

Increased NGFI-A binding, and the resulting increase in glucocorticoid receptor (GR) expression, leads to a decrease in depression-like behavior. Antidepressants can work to increase GR levels in affected patients, suppressing depressive symptoms. [[Electroconvulsive therapy|Electric shock therapy]], is often used to treat patients suffering from depression. It is found that this form of treatment results in an increase in NGFI-A expression levels.&lt;ref name="Morinbu"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Morinobu S, Strausbaugh H, Terwilliger R, Duman RS | title = Regulation of c-Fos and NGF1-A by antidepressant treatments | journal = Synapse | volume = 25 | issue = 4 | pages = 313–20 | year = 1997 | pmid = 9097389 | doi = 10.1002/(SICI)1098-2396(199704)25:4&lt;313::AID-SYN1&gt;3.0.CO;2-D }}&lt;/ref&gt; Electric shock therapy [[Depolarization|depolarizes]] a number of neurons throughout the brain, resulting in the increased activity of a number of intracellular pathways. This includes the cAMP pathway&lt;ref name="Morinbu" /&gt; which, through downstream effects, results in expression of NGFI-A. Antidepressant drugs, such as [[Tranylcypromine]] and [[Imipramine]] were found to have a similar effect; treatment with these drugs led to increases in NGFI-A expression and subsequent GR expression.&lt;ref name="Morinbu" /&gt; These two drugs are thought to alter synaptic levels of 5-HT, which then alters the activity level of the cAMP pathway. It is also known that increased glucocorticoid receptor expression has been shown to modulate the HPA pathway by increasing negative feedback.&lt;ref name="Morinbu" /&gt; This increase in expression results from decreased methylation, increased acetylation and binding of HGFI-A transcription factor.&lt;ref name="Weaver" /&gt; This promotes a more moderate HPA response than seen in those with depression which then decreases levels of hormones associated with stress.&lt;ref name="Weaver 2" /&gt; Another antidepressant, [[Desipramine]] was found to increase GR density and GR mRNA expression in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name="Frechilla"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Frechilla D, Otano A, Del Río J | title = Effect of chronic antidepressant treatment on transcription factor binding activity in rat hippocampus and frontal cortex | journal = Progress in Neuro-psychopharmacology &amp; Biological Psychiatry | volume = 22 | issue = 5 | pages = 787–802 | year = 1998 | pmid = 9723120 | doi = 10.1016/S0278-5846(98)00040-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is thought that this is happening due to an interaction between the response element of GR and the acetyltransferase, CREB Binding Protein. Therefore, this antidepressant, by increasing acetylation, works to lessen the HPA response, and as a result, decrease depressive symptoms.

====HDAC inhibitors as antidepressants====

HDAC inhibitors have been show to cause antidepressant-like effects in animals. Research shows that antidepressants make epigenetic changes to gene transcription thus altering signaling. These gene expression changes are seen in the BDNF, CRF, GDNF, and GR genes (see above sections). Histone modifications are consistently reported to alter chromatin structure during depression by the removal of acetyl groups, and to reverse this, HDAC inhibitors work by countering the removal of acetyl groups on histones. HDAC inhibitors can decrease gene transcription in the hippocampus and prefrontal cortex that is increased as a characteristic of depression. In animal studies of depression, short-term administration of HDAC inhibitors reduced the fear response in mice, and chronic administration produced antidepressant-like effects. This suggests that long-term treatment of HDAC inhibitors help in the treatment of depression. Some studies show that administration of HDAC inhibitors like [[Vorinostat]] and [[Romidepsin]], hematologic cancer drugs, can augment the effect of other antidepressants. These HDAC inhibitors may become antidepressants in the future, but clinical trials must further assess their efficacy in humans.&lt;ref name="pmid25818247"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fuchikami M, Yamamoto S, Morinobu S, Okada S, Yamawaki Y, Yamawaki S | title = The potential use of histone deacetylase inhibitors in the treatment of depression | journal = Progress in Neuro-psychopharmacology &amp; Biological Psychiatry | volume = 64 | issue = | pages = 320–4 | year = 2016 | pmid = 25818247 | doi = 10.1016/j.pnpbp.2015.03.010 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Epigenetics|Depression]]
[[Category:Major depressive disorder]]
[[Category:Neuroscience of depression]]</text>
      <sha1>t50xwnuh3ftv4sscxquzk6fpq8rc9p8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
