<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Much Ado About Nothing (1993 film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1615355</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959094674</id>
      <parentid>958854905</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-27T03:44:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ser Amantio di Nicolao</username>
        <id>753665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */recategorize</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="19658" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Much Ado About Nothing
| image          = Much ado about nothing movie poster.jpg
| director       = [[Kenneth Branagh]]
| producer       = Kenneth Branagh&lt;br /&gt;[[Stephen Evans (film producer)|Stephen Evans]]&lt;br /&gt;[[David Parfitt]]
| screenplay     = Kenneth Branagh
| based_on       = {{Based on|''[[Much Ado About Nothing]]''|[[William Shakespeare]]}}
| starring       = {{plainlist|
* Kenneth Branagh
* [[Michael Keaton]]
* [[Robert Sean Leonard]]
* [[Keanu Reeves]]
* [[Emma Thompson]]
* [[Denzel Washington]]}}
| music          = [[Patrick Doyle]]
| cinematography = Roger Lanser
| editing        = Andrew Marcus
| studio         = [[BBC Films]]&lt;br /&gt;American Playhouse Theatrical Films&lt;br /&gt;Renaissance Films
| distributor    = [[The Samuel Goldwyn Company]]
| released       = {{Film date|1993|5|7|United States|1993|8|27|United Kingdom}}
| runtime        = 110 minutes&lt;ref name="mojo"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=muchadoaboutnothing.htm |title=Much Ado About Nothing (1993) |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=May 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country        = United Kingdom&lt;br /&gt;United States
| language       = English
| budget         = $11 million&lt;ref name="mojo"/&gt;
| gross          = $36 million
}}

'''''Much Ado About Nothing''''' is a 1993 [[Cinema of the United Kingdom|British]]/[[Cinema of the United States|American]] [[romantic comedy]] film based on [[William Shakespeare]]'s [[Much Ado About Nothing|play of the same name]]. It was [[Film adaptation|adapted for the screen]] and [[Film director|directed]] by [[Kenneth Branagh]], who also stars in the film. The film also stars [[Emma Thompson]], [[Robert Sean Leonard]], [[Denzel Washington]], [[Michael Keaton]], [[Keanu Reeves]], and [[Kate Beckinsale]] in her film debut.

The film was released on May 7, 1993, reaching 200 U.S. screens at its widest release. It earned $22 million at the [[United States|U.S.]] box office and $36 million total worldwide, which, despite failing to reach the mark set by [[Franco Zeffirelli]]'s ''[[Romeo and Juliet (1968 film)|Romeo and Juliet]]'', made it one of the most financially successful Shakespeare films ever released. It was also entered into the [[1993 Cannes Film Festival]].&lt;ref name="festival-cannes.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.festival-cannes.com/en/archives/ficheFilm/id/2566/year/1993.html |title=Festival de Cannes: Much Ado About Nothing |accessdate=2009-08-22|work=festival-cannes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plot==
&lt;!--NOTE: PER WP:FILMPLOT, PLOT SUMMARIES FOR FEATURE-LENGTH FILMS SHOULD BE BETWEEN 400 AND 700 WORDS. The current word count is 638.--&gt;
Having just crushed an uprising by his half-brother, Don John, Don Pedro of Aragon and his noblemen visit their friend Leonato in [[Messina]]. Accompanying Don Pedro is the witty Benedick, former lover of Leonato's equally sharp-tongued niece, Beatrice. Also present are Benedick's friend Claudio, a young count; and Don John who, despite his rebellion, has apparently reconciled with his brother. Claudio has been thinking of Leonato's beautiful daughter Hero since before he went to war, and returns to find her as attractive as ever. Don Pedro, learning of his friend's feelings, decides to act on his behalf and arranges the match at a party. An unrepentant Don John attempts to foil it, but unsuccessfully – the match is made. Needing something to pass the time until the wedding, Don Pedro decides to arrange a similar fate for Beatrice and Benedick, whose animosity for each other is clear.

Don Pedro, Leonato, and Claudio stage a conversation containing a false account of how much Beatrice loves Benedick, all the while knowing Benedick to be hiding within earshot. Hero and her [[gentlewoman]] Ursula play the same trick upon Beatrice. Each of them believes the story they hear about the other. In the midst of all of this good-natured scheming, Don John has been searching for ways to stop the marriage between Claudio and Hero. The night before the wedding, Don John's servant Borachio arranges a steamy liaison with Hero's gentlewoman Margaret at Hero's chamber window. Don John shows Don Pedro and Claudio this, and they believe that they are seeing Hero in the act of infidelity.

Against the revelry of the evening, the upright but incompetent constable [[Dogberry]] appoints a watch to keep the peace. The three hapless watchmen happen to hear Borachio bragging to his colleague Conrade about how he and Don John had succeeded in stopping the wedding. The watchmen apprehend Borachio and Conrade, and, in the morning, Dogberry attempts to have Leonato [[Interrogation|interrogate]] the prisoners. However, a hurried Leonato is unable to decipher what the bumbling Dogberry is trying to tell him. Amidst the confusion, Don John quietly flees.

At the wedding, Claudio publicly disgraces his would-be bride and storms away, along with most of the guests, except for Ursula, the Friar, Leonato, Beatrice, Antonio, and Benedick. They all agree to the Friar's plan to publish the tale that Hero, upon the grief of Claudio's accusations, suddenly died. Beatrice and Benedick linger a moment and eventually confess their love to one another. In the wake of this declaration, Beatrice asks Benedick to do the one thing that will satisfy her outrage with what has just happened – kill Claudio. With a heavy heart, he agrees to challenge his friend. Meanwhile, Borachio and Conrade are interrogated by Dogberry and his men. Despite Dogberry's incompetence, the truth of Don John's sinister machinations is revealed.

Moments after Benedick's challenge to Claudio, Leonato is made aware of what really happened. Leonato continues to pretend to Claudio that Hero is dead. Claudio entreats Leonato to impose whatever vengeance he sees fit for Claudio's part in Hero's disgrace and death. Leonato forgives Claudio on the condition that he publicly declare his wrongdoing and then marry Hero's cousin - Antonio's daughter - the next morning. Claudio agrees, and carries out the former by reciting an epitaph at Hero's tomb that night.

When the bride is brought forth the next day, she is revealed to be none other than Hero herself. She and Claudio profess their true, undying love for each other, as do Beatrice and Benedick, who agree to marry. Benedick renounces his challenge against Claudio and embraces him. Moments later, Don John is marched in, having been captured before he could escape. Those gathered begin to dance, with the two happy couples at the middle. Don Pedro remains behind, still single, but happy for his friends.

==Cast==
* [[Kenneth Branagh]] as Benedick, a nobleman in the court of Don Pedro. He is fairly arrogant but shows himself to have a good heart during the "wedding" scene, as he is the only man from Don Pedro's entourage who implicitly believes Hero. His vanity and brash persona make his interactions with Beatrice argumentative, but at the end of the film, Beatrice and Benedick agree to marry.
* [[Emma Thompson]] as Beatrice, Leonato's niece, and Hero's cousin and chamber-mate. She is a strong-willed woman who charms and impresses all who know her with her [[wit]] and intelligence. She confesses her love for Benedick and agrees to marry him.
* [[Robert Sean Leonard]] as Count Claudio, the best friend of Don Pedro and Benedick, and fiancé to Hero, with whom he has been in love since before the men went to war against Don John. He does not believe Hero when she protests her innocence, and humiliates her by publicly casting her off during their wedding ceremony.  When Borachio finally confesses and Hero's innocence becomes clear, Claudio is devastated over his part in her "death" (as Hero's father leads him to believe).  He agrees to marry Hero's cousin at Leonato's request, and is reunited with his love when it is revealed that "sweet Hero" is still alive and now his bride in truth.
* [[Kate Beckinsale]] as Hero, the naïve, kind-hearted only child of Governor Leonato, who is in love with Claudio. She is falsely accused of being unfaithful to Claudio on the night before her wedding. At the end of the film, Don John's plot against her and Claudio is revealed and they are happily married as was planned in the beginning.
* [[Denzel Washington]] as Don Pedro, Prince of Aragon; remarkable for being one of the few "marriageable" men in the piece who does not get married by the end of the play, though he does play matchmaker for others. In the second act, when he and Beatrice are alone, he quietly asks her, "will you have me, lady?", revealing his true feelings for her.  Beatrice gently rebuffs his proposal, and the two remain friends. He believes, with Claudio, in Hero's alleged infidelity, but is likewise earnestly sorry when he learns the truth.
* [[Keanu Reeves]] as Don John, Don Pedro's evil half-brother. After leading a failed rebellion against Don Pedro, he conspires with his men Borachio and Conrade to stop Hero and Claudio's wedding by ruining Hero's honor. When his plot is found out, he attempts to escape but is captured and imprisoned.
* [[Richard Briers]] as Leonato, Governor of Messina and the father of Hero. He loves his daughter immensely but upon hearing the false news that she was being unfaithful to Claudio, he wishes she had never been born if that would mean that he would be spared the pain of her disgrace. He eventually listens to the Friar's counsel and becomes party to the pretence that Hero has died in order to test Claudio's remorse over his humiliation of Hero, before finally reuniting the two young lovers in the last act.
* [[Michael Keaton]] as Dogberry, the local constable. He is not as clever as he thinks he is and has a bad habit for [[malapropism]]s. He solves crimes and misdeeds accidentally. He and his men accidentally catch Borachio boasting about his involvement with separating Claudio and Hero. His men arrest Borachio and his conspiring friends. He ultimately saves the day by forcing Borachio to confess his part in Don John's plot to Leonato.
* [[Gerard Horan]] as Borachio, Don John's [[Alcoholism|drunken]] henchman. He assists Don John in sabotaging Claudio's and Hero's wedding by making Hero appear unfaithful and initially succeeds, but is caught boasting about his crime by Dogberry's men and forced to confess.
* [[Imelda Staunton]] as Margaret, Hero's waiting gentlewoman who is tricked by Borachio, and mistaken for Hero by Don Pedro and Claudio.
* [[Brian Blessed]] as Antonio, the brother of Leonato. He is very friendly, but is incensed by the accusations leveled against Hero.
* [[Ben Elton]] as Verges, the local headborough and Dogberry's partner. 
* [[Jimmy Yuill]] as Friar Francis, the priest at Claudio and Hero's wedding who fervently defends Hero from the accusations made against her. 
* Richard Clifford as Conrade, a henchman of Don John.
* [[Phyllida Law]] as Ursula, Hero's other waiting gentlewoman.
* [[Patrick Doyle]] as Balthazar, Don Pedro's musician.

==Production==
''Much Ado About Nothing'' was filmed entirely at Villa Vignamaggio, [[Greve in Chianti]] in [[Metropolitan City of Florence|Florence]], [[Tuscany]], [[Italy]].

===Soundtrack===
&lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Albums --&gt;
{{Infobox album
| name       = Much Ado About Nothing
| type       = [[Film score]]
| artist     = [[Patrick Doyle]]
| cover      =
| alt        =
| released   = 4 May 1993
| recorded   = 1993
| venue      =
| studio     =
| genre      = [[Soundtrack]]
| length     = 59:02
| label      = Epic Soundtrax
| producer   =
| prev_title =
| prev_year  =
| next_title =
| next_year  =
}}
{{Album ratings
| rev1 = [[Filmtracks.com|Filmtracks]]
| rev1Score = {{Rating|4|5}} [http://www.filmtracks.com/titles/much_ado.html link]
}}

The music to ''Much Ado About Nothing'' was composed by frequent [[Kenneth Branagh]] collaborator [[Patrick Doyle]], who makes a brief [[cameo appearance|cameo]] in the film as Balthazar singing ''Sigh No More Ladies'' and ''Pardon, Goddess of the Night''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/film/1/Patrick-Doyle.html Patrick Doyle Biography (1953-)] at Filmreference.com. Retrieved 2011-04-14.&lt;/ref&gt;  The soundtrack was released May 4, 1993 through [[Epic Soundtrax]] and features twenty-four tracks of score at a running time just under an hour.&lt;ref&gt;Clemmensen, Christian. [http://www.filmtracks.com/titles/much_ado.html ''Much Ado About Nothing''] soundtrack review at [[Filmtracks.com]]. Retrieved 2011-04-14.&lt;/ref&gt;

# "The Picnic" (2:57)
# "Overture" (4:20)
# "The Sweetest Lady" (2:05)
# "The Conspirators" (2:39)
# "The Masked Ball" (1:55)
# "The Prince Woos Hero" (1:18)
# "A Star Danced" (2:43)
# "Rich She Shall Be" (1:42)
# "Sigh No More Ladies" (1:58)
# "The Gulling of Benedick" (3:12)
# "It Must Be Requited" (1:58)
# "The Gulling of Beatrice" (1:41)
# "Contempt Farewell" (1:32)
# "The Lady is Disloyal" (2:14)
# "Hero's Wedding" (0:47)
# "Take Her Back Again" (3:10)
# "Die to Live" (4:43)
# "You Have Killed a Sweet Lady" (3:03)
# "Choose Your Revenge" (1:48)
# "Pardon, Goddess of the Night" (4:32)
# "Did I Not Tell You" (1:40)
# "Hero Revealed" (1:26)
# "Benedick the Married Man" (2:06)
# "Strike Up Pipers" (2:41)

==Reception==
''Much Ado About Nothing'' received general acclaim from critics. The film currently holds a 90% "Certified Fresh" rating on [[Rotten Tomatoes]], a website that [[aggregate data|aggregates]] professional critiques, from 48 reviews with the consensus "Kenneth Branagh's love for the material is contagious in this exuberant adaptation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/1045992-much_ado_about_nothing/ |title=Much Ado About Nothing (1993) |accessdate=5 April 2012 |work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roger Ebert]] of the ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'' gave it three out of four stars, calling it "cheerful from beginning to end".&lt;ref name="Roger Ebert" &gt;{{cite web |last=Ebert |first=Roger |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Much Ado About Nothing |work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]] |publisher= |date=21 May 1993 |url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19930521/REVIEWS/305210302/1023 |accessdate=5 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Vincent Canby]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' also wrote the film a positive review, praising Branagh's direction and calling it "ravishing entertainment".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Canby |first=Vincent |title=Much Ado About Nothing (1993) Review/Film; 'A House Party of Beatrice, Benedick and Friends' |work=[[The New York Times]] |publisher= |date=7 May 1993 |url=https://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9F0CE7DD133DF934A35756C0A965958260 |accessdate=5 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Desson Thomson]] of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' praised Branagh's cuts to the text as giving "wonderful import to this silliness from long ago" and stated that "Kenneth Branagh has, once again, blown away the forbidding academic dust and found a funny retro-essence for the '90s."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Thomson |first=Desson |authorlink= |title=Much Ado About Nothing |work=[[The Washington Post]] |publisher= |date=21 May 1993 |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/movies/videos/muchadoaboutnothingpg13howe_a0afbc.htm |doi = |accessdate=5 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Online critic [[James Berardinelli]] gave the film a glowing four-star review, calling it a "gem of a movie", especially praising the accessibility of the humor, the performances, and Branagh's lively direction, of which he wrote, "This film cements Branagh's status as a great director of Shakespeare, and perhaps of film in general, as well."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Berardinelli |first=James |title=Much Ado About Nothing |work=ReelViews |publisher= |date= |url=http://preview.reelviews.net/movies/m/much_ado.html |accessdate=5 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, [[Peter Travers]] of ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' wrote the film a negative review, praising some moments as "invigorating fun", but ultimately calling it "overripe".&lt;ref name="Peter Travers" &gt;{{cite web |last=Travers |first=Peter |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Much Ado About Nothing |work=[[Rolling Stone]] |publisher= |date=7 May 1993 |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/movies/reviews/much-ado-about-nothing-19930507 |accessdate=5 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Most of the negative criticisms focused on particular casting choices, notably [[Keanu Reeves]] as Don John, and [[Michael Keaton]] as [[Dogberry]].&lt;ref name="Roger Ebert" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Peter Travers" /&gt;  For his performance in the film, Reeves was nominated for a [[Golden Raspberry Award]] for [[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Supporting Actor|Worst Supporting Actor]], where he lost to [[Woody Harrelson]] for ''[[Indecent Proposal]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.razzies.com/forum/topic343_page2.html|title=Nominees &amp; Winners|last=Wilson|first=John|authorlink=John J. B. Wilson|date=4 December 2005|work=Fourteenth Annual RAZZIE® Awards (for 1993)|publisher=Golden Raspberry Award Foundation|accessdate=9 July 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130709032209/http://www.razzies.com/forum/topic343_page2.html|archive-date=9 July 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Much Ado About Nothing'' was ranked #11 on [[Rotten Tomatoes]] list of Greatest Shakespeare Movies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/guides/greatest_shakespeare_movies/1045992-much_ado_about_nothing/ |title=Greatest Shakespeare Movies |accessdate=5 April 2012 |work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accolades===
{| class="wikitable plainrowheaders" style="font-size: 95%;"
|-
! scope="col" |Award
! scope="col" |Category
! scope="col" |Recipients and nominees
! scope="col" |Result
|-
| [[British Academy Film Awards]]
| [[BAFTA Award for Best Costume Design|Best Costume Design]]
| Phyllis Dalton
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Cannes Film Festival]]
| [[Palme d'Or]]
| [[Kenneth Branagh]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Evening Standard British Film Awards]]
| Best Actress
| [[Emma Thompson]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Golden Globe Awards]]
| [[Golden Globe Award for Best Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy|Best Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy]]
| [[Kenneth Branagh]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan=2 | [[Independent Spirit Awards]]
| [[Independent Spirit Award for Best Film|Best Film]]
| [[Kenneth Branagh]], Stephen Evans, [[David Parfitt]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Independent Spirit Award for Best Female Lead|Best Female Lead]]
| [[Emma Thompson]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[London Film Critics' Circle]]
| British Producer of the Year
| [[Kenneth Branagh]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Golden Raspberry Award]]
| [[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Supporting Actor|Worst Supporting Actor]]
| [[Keanu Reeves]]
| {{nom}}
|-
|}

The film is recognized by [[American Film Institute]] in these lists:
* 2005: [[AFI's 100 Years of Film Scores]] – Nominated&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afi.com/Docs/100Years/scores250.pdf |title= AFI's 100 Years of Film Scores Nominees |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2016-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* {{IMDb title|0107616|Much Ado About Nothing}}

{{Kenneth Branagh}}
{{Much Ado About Nothing}}

[[Category:1993 films]]
[[Category:1990s romantic comedy films]]
[[Category:British films]]
[[Category:British romantic comedy films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Kenneth Branagh]]
[[Category:Films set in Sicily]]
[[Category:Films shot in Tuscany]]
[[Category:British independent films]]
[[Category:Films based on Much Ado About Nothing]]
[[Category:BBC Films films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American independent films]]
[[Category:American romantic comedy films]]
[[Category:Films scored by Patrick Doyle]]
[[Category:Films produced by David Parfitt]]
[[Category:The Samuel Goldwyn Company films]]
[[Category:1993 comedy films]]</text>
      <sha1>lhvk8oitl4659mz5iobt0vj3d0gyu2l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
