<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Solar power in Israel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20856116</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961434915</id>
      <parentid>961394479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-08T13:01:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KH-1</username>
        <id>21857263</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/Patrapooja|Patrapooja]] ([[User talk:Patrapooja|talk]]) to last version by DannyS712</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="35603" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Photovoltaic arrays at the Israeli National Solar Energy Center.jpg|thumb|Photovoltaic arrays at the Israel National Solar Energy Center]]
[[File:Zin Valley in the Negev Desert of Israel.jpg|thumb|The [[Negev Desert]] is home to the Israeli solar research industry, in particular the [[National Solar Energy Center]] and the [[Arava Valley]], the sunniest region of Israel]]

The use of '''[[Solar energy|solar energy]]''' began '''in [[Israel]]''' in the 1950s with the development by [[Levi Yissar]]  of a solar water heater to address the energy shortages that plagued the new country.&lt;ref name=Bach&gt;Petrotyranny by John C. Bacher, [[David Suzuki]], published by Dundurn Press Ltd., 2000;  Page 70 [https://books.google.com/books?id=P7LPZk8NuBgC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;lpg=PA70&amp;dq=Levi+Yissar&amp;source=web&amp;ots=gvKMZgYqNZ&amp;sig=DKXQT9_oPFwvQrUI8IqB1dBYRWQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ct=result#PPA70,M1]&lt;/ref&gt; By 1967 around 5% of water of  [[household]]s was solar heated and 50,000 solar heaters had been sold.&lt;ref name=Bach/&gt; 
With the [[1973 oil crisis|1970s oil crisis]], [[Harry Zvi Tabor]] developed the prototype of the solar water heater now used in over 90% of Israeli homes.&lt;ref name=BW&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/globalbiz/content/mar2008/gb20080326_485582.htm?chan=globalbiz_europe+index+page_companies At the Zenith of Solar Energy], Neal Sandler, ''[[BusinessWeek]]'', March 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; There are over 1.3 million solar water heaters installed as a result of mandatory solar water heating regulations.

Israeli engineers have been at the cutting edge of solar energy technology&lt;ref name=NPR&gt;[https://www.npr.org/templates/transcript/transcript.php?storyId=15503716 Israel Pushes Solar Energy Technology], Linda Gradstein, ''[[National Public Radio]]'', October 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and its solar companies work on projects around the world.&lt;ref name=CBC&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/reportsfromabroad/parry/20070815.html Looking to the sun], Tom Parry, [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]], August 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 
However, even though Israeli engineers have been involved in both photovoltaic and concentrated solar power, the earliest Israeli companies which have become market leaders in their respective fields have all been involved in concentrated solar power. 
Some notable examples of this are BrightSource, Solel and Brenmiller Energy which all deal with utility scale projects. Additionally, Herzliya based [[SolarEdge]] has become a market leader in inverters for non-utility scale [[Photovoltaics|photovoltaic]] solar power.

In 2009, Israel found natural gas reserves within their exclusive economic zone which may reduce urgency of solar development. Solar technology in Israel has advanced to the point where it is almost cost-competitive with [[fossil fuels]].&lt;ref name=BW/&gt; The high annual incidence of [[sunshine]] in the [[Negev Desert]] has spurred an internationally renowned solar research and development industry.&lt;ref name=JVL&gt;[https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Environment/Solar.html Solar Energy in Israel], [[David Faiman]] for the Jewish Virtual Library.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 2008, a [[feed-in tariff]] scheme was approved which has led to many residential and commercial solar energy power station projects.

Israel's objective is to produce 10% of the country's energy from renewable sources by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/weekend/anglo-file/born-again-ziontist-revolutionizing-solar-energy-field-1.388639 Born-again Ziontist revolutionizing solar energy field, Haaretz]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History and development ==
In 1949, [[prime minister]] [[David Ben-Gurion]] offered Harry Zvi Tabor a job on the 'physics and engineering desk' of the Research Council of Israel, which he accepted. He created an Israeli national laboratory and created standards amongst the different measurements in use in the country, primarily [[Imperial units|British]], [[Ancient Arabic weights and measures|Ottoman]] and [[Metric system|metric]].&lt;ref name=Bright&gt;[http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1222017430932 Bright ideas], Ehud Zion Waldoks, ''[[Jerusalem Post]]'', October 1, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Earth&gt;[http://www.eoearth.org/article/Tabor,_Harry_Zvi Harry Zvi Tabor], Cleveland Cutler, [[Encyclopedia of the Earth]], 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Once the laboratory was established, he focused on [[solar energy]] for [[research and development]].

Solar energy was particularly attractive because of the abundance and strength in Israel of the sun's rays and Israel's [[geographic latitude]] location is on the [[30th parallel north]], where the annual incident [[solar irradiance]] is 2000 [[kWh]] per m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=JVL/&gt; Second, Israel lacks oil, and the [[Arab–Israeli conflict|conflicts with its neighbors]] made the procurement of a stable source of energy a national priority. In particular, it is argued that the best defense against missile attack felling the national power grid would be to build a [[Distributed generation|distributed power network]], which would mean solar fields of 25&amp;ndash;50 megawatts across Israel.&lt;ref name=Abr&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1033081.html The solar vote], Yosef I. Abramowitz and David Lehreer, ''[[Haaretz]]'', November 2, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early in the 1950s, Tabor began to examine why solar installations were inefficient. He eventually devised ‘selective black surfaces’, which his team at the National Physical Laboratory modified using [[nickel]] and [[chromium|chrome]] methods to blacken metals. These surfaces, which became known as [[Tabor surfaces]], are particularly effective at trapping heat for use in [[solar water heater]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Infrared Technology Fundamentals, by Monroe Schlessinger, Irving J. Spiro; CRC Press, 1995, {{ISBN|0-8247-9259-9}}; reference is at page 68 [https://books.google.com/books?id=QPBQ5w4X8RkC&amp;pg=PA68&amp;lpg=PA68&amp;dq=%22Tabor+Surfaces%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dC1vDRmCJW&amp;sig=SfYdCJ-EkxpK6q3TgC5iXFGmTOk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result]&lt;/ref&gt;

Tabor and French immigrant Lucien Bronicki developed a small solar power unit, the [[Organic Rankine cycle]] [[turbine]], for developing countries with problematic power grids.&lt;ref name=Earth/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grossman&gt;[http://www2.technion.ac.il/~ises/papers/IsraelSectionISESfinal.pdf Israeli Section of the International Solar Energy Society] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090111053453/http://www2.technion.ac.il/~ises/papers/IsraelSectionISESfinal.pdf |date=2009-01-11 }}, edited by Gershon Grossman, Faculty of Mechanical Energy, [[Technion]], [[Haifa]]; Final draft.&lt;/ref&gt;  It was designed to neutralize the maintenance issues of [[reciprocating engine]]s so it had only one moving part, the [[rotor (electric)|rotor]].  A 3 kWe prototype was exhibited at the 1961 [[United Nations]] Conference on New Sources of Energy in [[Rome]], but it failed to find commercial success.&lt;ref name=Grossman/&gt;

{| class=wikitable style="text-align:right"
|+Photovoltaics Cumulative Capacity ([[Watt#Megawatt|MW]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iea-pvps.org/ International Energy Agency Photovoltaic Power System Programme]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!2004!!2005!!2006!!2007!!2008!!2009!!2010!!2011!!2012!!2013!!2014!!2015!!2016!!2017!!2018!!2019(forecast)
|-
|0.9||1.0||1.3||1.8||3.0||24.5||69.9||190||237||481||731||780&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iea-pvps.org/index.php?id=6&amp;eID=dam_frontend_push&amp;docID=3108&lt;/ref&gt;||905.6&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iea-pvps.org/index.php?id=6&amp;eID=dam_frontend_push&amp;docID=3951&lt;/ref&gt;||1005&lt;ref&gt;http://iea-pvps.org/index.php?id=6&amp;eID=dam_frontend_push&amp;docID=4412&lt;/ref&gt;||1450&lt;ref&gt;https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/business/.premium-israel-poised-for-energy-revolution-as-solar-prices-fall-1.7187095&lt;/ref&gt;||2670&lt;ref&gt;https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/business/.premium-israel-poised-for-energy-revolution-as-solar-prices-fall-1.7187095&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Dead Sea Solar pond===
In 1965, Lucien Bronicki established [[Ormat Industries]] to commercialize the [[Organic Rankine cycle]] [[turbine]] concept. In the 1970s and 1980s Ormat built and operated one of the world's first power stations to produce electricity from solar energy; the plant was located at [[Ein Bokek]] near the southern part of the [[Dead Sea]] in Israel.&lt;ref name=solar &gt;{{Citation
 | title = Israel's 150-KW Solar Pond
 | url = http://www.motherearthnews.com/Modern-Homesteading/1980-05-01/Israels-150-KW-Solar-Pond.aspx
 | publisher = Mother Earth News May/June 1980 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The plant utilised a technology known as the [[solar pond]], a large-scale solar thermal energy collector with integral heat storage for supplying thermal energy.  It was the largest operating solar pond ever built for electricity generation and operated up until 1988. It had an area of 210,000 m² and gave an electrical output of 5 MW.&lt;ref&gt;Carl Nielson, Aliakbar Akbarzedeh, John Andrews, Humberto R Becerra L and Peter Golding, 'The History of Solar Pond Science &amp; Technology', Proceedings of the International Solar Energy Society, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Solar water heaters ===
{{main article|Solar water heater}}
[[Image:Solarboiler.jpg|thumb|250px|Solar water heater on a rooftop in [[Jerusalem]]]]
During the period of [[austerity in Israel]] in the 1950s, there was a fuel shortage, and the government forbade heating water between 10 a.m. and 6 p.m. As the situation worsened, engineer Levi Yissar proposed that instead of the construction of more electrical generation plants, homes should switch to solar water heaters. He built a prototype in his home, and in 1953 he started NerYah Company, Israel's first commercial manufacturer of solar water heaters.&lt;ref name=Bach/&gt; By 1967 around one in twenty [[household]]s heated its water with the sun and 50,000 solar heaters had been sold.&lt;ref name=Bach/&gt; However, cheap oil from Iran and from oil fields captured in the [[Six-Day War]] made Israeli electricity cheaper and the demand for solar heaters dropped.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.californiasolarcenter.org/history_solarthermal.html]&lt;/ref&gt; After the energy crisis in the 1970s, in 1980 the Israeli [[Knesset]] passed a law requiring the installation of solar water heaters in all new homes (except high towers with insufficient roof area). As a result, Israel is now the world leader in the use of solar energy ''[[per capita]]'' (3% of the primary national energy consumption).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.neaman.org.il/neaman/publications/publication_item.asp?fid=590&amp;parent_fid=490&amp;iid=3639 The Samuel Neaman Institute for Advanced Studies in Science and Technology &amp;mdash; Publications &amp;mdash; Solar energy for the production of heat Summary and recommendations of the 4th assembly of the energy forum at SNI] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071106034326/http://www.neaman.org.il/neaman/publications/publication_item.asp?fid=590&amp;parent_fid=490&amp;iid=3639 |date=2007-11-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of the early 1990s, all new residential buildings were required by the government to install solar water-heating systems, and Israel's National Infrastructure Ministry estimates that solar panels for water-heating satisfy 4% of the country's total energy demand.&lt;ref name=BW/&gt; Israel and Cyprus are the per-capita leaders in the use of solar hot water systems with over 90% of homes using them.&lt;ref name="Environment California SWH"&gt;{{cite web| author=Del Chiaro, Bernadette| author2=Telleen-Lawton, Timothy| title=Solar Water Heating (How California Can Reduce Its Dependence on Natural Gas)| publisher=Environment California Research and Policy Center| url=http://www.environmentcalifornia.org/uploads/at/56/at563bKwmfrtJI6fKl9U_w/Solar-Water-Heating.pdf| accessdate=2007-09-29| format=PDF| url-status=dead| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927082332/http://www.environmentcalifornia.org/uploads/at/56/at563bKwmfrtJI6fKl9U_w/Solar-Water-Heating.pdf| archivedate=2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry of National Infrastructures estimates solar water heating saves Israel {{convert|2|Moilbbl|m3}} of oil a year.&lt;ref name=Grossman/&gt;

== Feed-in tariff ==
On June 2, 2008 the Israeli Public Utility Authority approved a [[feed-in tariff]] for solar plants. The tariff is limited to a total installation of 50&amp;nbsp;MW during 7 years, whichever is reached first, with a maximum of 15 kWp installation for [[residential]] and a maximum of 50kWp for [[Commerce|commercial]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eng.shirasol.co.il/Approved-Feed-in-tariff-in-Israel.htm Approved &amp;mdash; Feed-in tariff in Israel] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090603195611/http://eng.shirasol.co.il/Approved-Feed-in-tariff-in-Israel.htm |date=2009-06-03 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; The National Infrastructures Ministry announced on December 2009 on expanding the [[feed-in tariff]] scheme to include medium-sized solar-power stations ranging from 50 kilowatts to 5 megawatts, though only one project was approved by June 2010.

== Educational and research facilities ==

=== The Grand Technion Energy Program (GTEP) ===

Multidisciplinary scientists at [[Technion – Israel Institute of Technology|Technion]] - Israel Institute of Technology are pooling resources at [http://gtep.technion.ac.il/ GTEP] to advance the science behind solar power.

'''Nano science and solar energy'''

With its strong basis in nanotechnology and science, [[Grand Technion Energy Program|GTEP]] is pioneering the field of nano-energy. 
*Efrat Lifshitz discovered that nano-sized materials consisting of nanocrystal quantum dots can absorb sunlight not only in the visible range, as materials currently used in solar panels do, but also in the infrared and UV ranges. This makes them ideal in photovoltaic cells used to turn sunlight into electricity, promising much more efficient solar power.
*Nir Tessler leads a group on organic photovoltaic material.
*Gitti Frey specializes in organic electronics - plastic electronics that are functional electronically and optically. They emit light and can transmit electrical signals, or absorb light and generate energy such as electricity. Frey introduces whole new properties in this field, creating effective and useful self-organizing structures on the nano-scale. Frey is working on a solar cell to convert sunlight into electrical energy. She predicts this research will lead to solar-power systems which are cheaper, unbreakable, flexible, more aesthetic and versatile.

=== National Solar Energy Center ===
{{main article|Ben-Gurion National Solar Energy Center}}
[[File:Solar dish at Ben-Gurion National Solar Energy Center in Israel.jpg|thumb|The world's largest solar energy dish is located at Ben Gurion National Solar Energy Center]]
The National Solar Energy Center was founded in 1987 by the Ministry of National Infrastructures, and is part of [[Ben-Gurion University of the Negev]].&lt;ref name=BFNSEC&gt;[http://cmsprod.bgu.ac.il/Eng/Units/bidr/Departments/EnvironmentalResearch/solarcenter Ben Gurion National Solar Energy Center] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110813063458/http://cmsprod.bgu.ac.il/Eng/Units/bidr/Departments/EnvironmentalResearch/solarcenter |date=2011-08-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishjournal.com/geekheeb/item/bright_idea_for_solar_energy_20081121/]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, [[David Faiman]], the Center's director, announced that the Center had entered into a project with [[Zenith Solar]] to create a home solar energy system that uses a 10-square meter reflector dish.&lt;ref name=Reuters&gt;[https://www.reuters.com/article/latestCrisis/idUSL16893018 Reflective mirrors seen raising solar potential], Ari Rabinovitch, [[Reuters]], August 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  In testing, the concentrated solar technology proved to be up to five times more efficient than standard flat [[photovoltaic]] [[silicon]] panels, which would make it almost as cheap as oil and natural gas.  A prototype ready for commercialization achieved a concentration of solar energy that was more than 1,000 times greater than that from standard flat panels.&lt;ref name=BW/&gt;  According to Faiman, who led the Israeli team that developed the technology, 10% of Israel’s population (1,000 [[megawatts]]) could live on the energy from 12 square kilometres of land.&lt;ref name=Green&gt;[http://greenprophet.com/2007/12/16/7/the-light-of-a-thousand-suns/ Zenith Solar’s Light of a Thousand Suns], ''Green Prophet'', December 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Jacob Blaustein Institutes for Desert Research ===
The [[Jacob Blaustein Institutes for Desert Research]] facility was founded by Amos Richmond, and its faculty is part of the [[Ben-Gurion University of the Negev]].  It has a solar energy research program that has assisted in the development of [[Passive solar|passive heating]], involving the mitigation of extremes of heat and cold in the desert through efficient storage from day to nighttime. One research project is an inhabited [[adobe]] house with rational [[window|fenestration]]. [[Prism (optics)|Prism]]s that transmit heat during the day are installed in the room and can be rotated to allow the heat to discharge at night.

There is a double-skin [[greenhouse]] that uses [[copper sulfate]] solution as a heat screen during the day. The liquid is pumped between the two skins, protects the interior from [[ultraviolet]] rays, and collects heat. At night the liquid is recirculated, returning the heat to the greenhouse.

=== Weizmann Institute Solar Research Facilities Unit ===
In addition to a solar reactor,&lt;ref&gt;The Climate of Israel by Y. Goldreich, [https://books.google.com/books?id=7FsnT8Jx_O4C&amp;pg=RA5-PA225&amp;lpg=RA5-PA225&amp;dq=Israel+Solar+Weizmann&amp;source=web&amp;ots=pFKV3N6Rp4&amp;sig=nSfrGdFMrl6EzFa-lNsFRXINDxk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ct=result], Published by Springer, 2003, {{ISBN|0-306-47445-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; the solar research facilities of the [[Weizmann Institute of Science]] are among the most advanced laboratories in the world for concentrated solar energy research.&lt;ref name=Weiz&gt;[http://www.weizmann.ac.il/acadaff/Scientific_Activities/current/Solar_Research_Facilities.html Jacob Karni and Michael Epstein, Weizmann Institute, July 2002.]&lt;/ref&gt;  They have tested solar technology in the production of hydrogen fuel, which has been successfully trialled on a large scale.&lt;ref name=hydro&gt;[http://www.weizmann-usa.org/site/News2?id=6606&amp;page=NewsArticle Solar Energy Project at the Weizmann Institute Promises to Advance the Use of Hydrogen Fuel] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303174600/http://www.weizmann-usa.org/site/News2?id=6606&amp;page=NewsArticle |date=2016-03-03 }}, American Committee for the Weizmann Institute, August 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  Tareq Abu-Hamed, an Israeli scientist at the [[University of Minnesota]], with colleagues Jacob Karni and Michael Epstein, head of the Solar Facility at Weizmann, were the developers of a new method to produce [[hydrogen fuel]] more cheaply, efficiently and safely while solving storage and transportation issues.&lt;ref name=jpost&gt;[http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1157913666855 Forget gas! Fill your tanks with water, Weizmann researcher says]{{dead link|date=May 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}, Nicky Blackburn, ''[[Jerusalem Post]]'', September 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other innovations include harnessing sunlight for space communications and meteorological information; controlling [[Light-dependent reaction|light-dependent]] chemical reactions; and developing [[photodynamic therapy|photodynamic cancer therapy]].&lt;ref name=wander&gt;[http://wis-wander.weizmann.ac.il/site/en/weizman.asp?pi=696&amp;doc_id=3855&amp;Interface=true The Crystal Connection: Solar Lasers in Space]{{dead link|date=May 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Solar power stations ==

=== The Negev ===
[[File:Solar troughs in the Negev desert of Israel.jpg|thumb|250px|Solar troughs in the Negev]]
{{Main|Negev}}
The Negev Desert and the surrounding area, including the [[Arava Valley]], are the sunniest parts of Israel and little of this land is [[arable land|arable]], which is why it has become the center of the Israeli solar industry.&lt;ref name=Kib&gt;[https://www.jpost.com/health-and-sci-tech/science-and-environment/head-of-kibbutz-movement-we-will-not-be-discriminated-against-by-the-government Head of Kibbutz Movement: We will not be discriminated against by the government] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110713124653/http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1205420713036&amp;pagename=JPost%2FJPArticle%2FPrinter |date=2011-07-13 }}, Ehud Zion Waldoks, ''[[Jerusalem Post]]'', March 10, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  David Faiman thinks the energy needs of Israel's future could be met by building solar energy plants in the Negev.  As director of Ben-Gurion National Solar Energy Center, he operates one of the largest solar dishes in the world.&lt;ref name=Register&gt;[https://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/01/25/faiman_negev_solar_plan/ Giant solar plants in Negev could power Israel's future], John Lettice, ''[[The Register]]'', January 25, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2016, the 50 MW  Zmorot Solar Park came online. The plant uses  207,000-panel solar park and took 18 months to construct.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/Business-and-Innovation/Environment/French-PM-Valls-inaugurates-Israels-latestand-largestsolar-field-454678 French PM Valls inaugurates Israel's latest—and largest—solar field], ''Jeruslaem Post'', 05.23.2016&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Rotem Industrial Complex outside of [[Dimona, Israel]], more than 1,600 solar mirrors focus the sun's rays on a tower to heat a water boiler to create steam. BrightSource Industries (Israel), Ltd., uses the solar array to test new technology for the three new solar plants to be built in California for [[Pacific Gas and Electric Company]] and [[Southern California Edison]].&lt;ref name=Dimona&gt;[http://www.nbcnews.com/id/25124614 Calif. solar power test begins — in Israeli desert], [[Associated Press]], June 12, 2008; accessed December 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CA&gt;[https://www.reuters.com/article/environmentNews/idUSL1110252820080611 Israel site for California solar power test], Ari Rabinovitch, [[Reuters]], June 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://www.voanews.com/english/archive/2008-05/2008-05-08-voa17.cfm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-10-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090826073530/http://www.voanews.com/english/archive/2008-05/2008-05-08-voa17.cfm |archivedate=2009-08-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Farming and kibbutzim ====
[[File:Dud3.png|thumb|250px|Solar panels installed on residential housing in Israel]]
Israel's first solar power station opened in August 2008.&lt;ref name=Moshe/&gt; Moshe Tenne built the 50 KW plant on his [[Negev]] farm for [[Israeli new sheqel|NIS]] 1.3 million, and he expects to earn NIS 220,000 a year from selling excess electricity to the national [[power grid]].&lt;ref name=Moshe&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1015898.html Israel's first solar power station up and running in Negev], Avi Bar-Eli, [[Haaretz]], September 18, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the National Infrastructures Ministry announced it would expand its [[feed-in tariff]] scheme to include medium-sized solar-power stations ranging from 50 kilowatts to 5 megawatts, [[Sunday Solar Energy]] announced that it would invest $133 million in photovoltaic solar arrays for installation on [[kibbutzim]].&lt;ref name=Sunday&gt;[http://www.cleantech.com/news/3715/sunday-solar-powers-kibbutzim Sunday Solar powers Israeli kibbutzim] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081224192937/http://www.cleantech.com/news/3715/sunday-solar-powers-kibbutzim |date=2008-12-24 }}, Cleantech.com news, October 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  In December 2008, the Sunday company announced that [[Kibbutz Reim]] in the western Negev would be the first community in the world to rely entirely on solar energy.&lt;ref name=Ynet&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3641794,00.html The first solar kibbutz], Amir Ben-David, [[Ynet]], December 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Reim installation, costing NIS 60-100 million, would generate at least 2.5 megawatts during peak consumption.  Excess energy would be sold to the [[Israel Electric Company]].  The investment is expected to pay for itself in 10 years, and the costs and revenues will be divided evenly between the kibbutz and Sunday.&lt;ref name=Ynet/&gt;

===Arava Power Company===
[[File:Ketura3.jpg|thumb|250px|Ketura solar field, 2012]]
{{Main|Arava Power Company}}

[[Ketura Sun]] is [[Israel| Israel’s]] first commercial solar field. Built in early 2011 by the Arava Power Company on [[Ketura, Israel|Kibbutz Ketura]], Ketura Sun covers twenty acres and is expected to produce green energy amounting to 4.95 megawatts. The field consists of 18,500 [[Photovoltaics|photovoltaic]] panels made by [[Suntech Power|Suntech]], which will produce about 9 gigawatt-hours of electricity per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.aravapower.com/Technical%20Figures |title= Ketura Sun Technical Figures |accessdate= 26 June 2011 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120309003501/http://www.aravapower.com/Technical%20Figures |archivedate= 9 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the next twenty years, the field will spare the production of some 125,000 metric tons of carbon dioxide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.aravapower.com/Environmental%20Figures|archive-url= https://archive.today/20120722132945/http://www.aravapower.com/Environmental%20Figures|url-status= dead|archive-date= 22 July 2012|title= Ketura Sun Environmental Figures|accessdate= 26 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The field was inaugurated on June 15, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.aravapower.com/
|title= Arava Power Company|accessdate=June 27, 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110707154923/http://www.aravapower.com/| archivedate= July 7, 2011 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 22, 2012 Arava Power Company announced that it had reached financial close on an additional 58.5 MW for 8 projects to be built in the Arava and the Negev valued at 780 million NIS or approximately $204 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last = Roca| first = Marc| title = Arava Closes Funding For $204 Million Israeli Solar Plants| newspaper = Bloomberg| date = May 22, 2012| url = https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-05-22/arava-closes-funding-for-204-million-israeli-solar-plants-1-.html| accessdate = June 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; APC President and Co-Founder [[Yosef Abramowitz]] stated, "Our work is not yet done. Israel needs to adopt the European Union goal of 20 percent renewables by 2020 and this major milestone by Arava Power is proof positive that it can be reached. Furthermore, an injustice must be corrected by creating a special quota of solar fields for Bedouin land owners, who are locked out of the current solar program."&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last = Rabinovitch| first = Ari| title = Israel's Arava power to build eight solar fields| newspaper = Reuters| date = May 22, 2012| url = https://www.reuters.com/article/2012/05/22/israel-arava-solar-idUSL5E8GM0IV20120522 | accessdate = June 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, the Arava Power Company has signed multiple agreements with [[Bedouin]] families in the [[Negev]] desert to build solar fields on approximately 92 acres of land, with a production capability of up to 20 megawatts. APC has been lobbying the Israeli government to create separate solar caps for Bedouins.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last = Rinat| first = Zafrir| title = Solar panels prove a money-spinner for Bedouin in the Negev| newspaper = Haaretz| date = January 4, 2011| url = http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/news/solar-panels-prove-a-money-spinner-for-bedouin-in-the-negev-1.353394| accessdate =June 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 7, 2012, Arava Power announced that it had received a license for the Tarabin Solar Field, the first solar field for the Bedouin community. Financing for the $30 million Tarabin installation is to be provided by [[Overseas Private Investment Corporation|OPIC]] – the Overseas Private Investment Corporation of the United States Government.  Arava Power President Yosef Abramowitz sees solar power for the Bedouin as a positive example for Native Americans, First Nations, Aboriginals and others with historic land claims.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last = Udasin| first=Sharon| title= Regulator approves first Beduin solar license| newspaper = The Jerusalem Post| date = February 8, 2012| url = http://www.jpost.com/Sci-Tech/Article.aspx?id=256928| accessdate =February 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Carmey Avdat Winery ===
Sunday Solar Energy was commissioned to build a solar installation for the Carmey Avdat winery in the Negev Desert. The 50&amp;nbsp;kW peak installation covers the 200-square meter roof of the winery and provides 65 percent of its annual energy needs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenprophet.com/2009/08/19/11396/sunday-energy-solar-israel/Every Day is Like Sunday Solar Energy], October 19, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Brigthsource Tower Ashalim.jpg|thumb|Ashalim Power Station, on completion the tallest solar power tower in the world.]]

=== Kibbutz Samar ===
The Aora's [[Solar "Flower" Tower]] is the world's first solar hybrid power plant, comprising 30 heliostat solar reflectors. The plant switches to natural gas-powered turbines after dark so that it can continue producing power 24 hours a day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://popsci.com.au/scitech/article/2009-06/sunsphere-new-solar-hybrid-power-plant First Hybrid Solar/Natural Gas Power Station Goes Online in Israel] Popular Science Australia&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ramat Hovav solar field ===

The ''[[Ramat Hovav]] solar field'' is 37.5&amp;nbsp;[[Megawatt|MW]] project near Ramat Hovav, operational since December 2014. The [[photovoltaic power plant]] is owned by [[Energix Renewable Energies Ltd]]  It was built by the [[Belectric]] over a rehabilitated evaporation pond. The facility uses [[Cadmium telluride photovoltaics|CdTe photovoltaic modules]] based on [[thin-film solar cell|thin-film technology]], manufactured by U.S. company [[First Solar]], making it the country's largest PV power plant so far and one of the largest of its kind in the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.tashtiot.co.il/2014/12/23/%D7%90%D7%A0%D7%A8%D7%92%D7%99%D7%94-%D7%A1%D7%95%D7%9C%D7%90%D7%A8%D7%99%D7%AA-520/ | title=Ramat Hovav solar field began to supply power to the grid (in Hebrew)| date=24 December 2014 | accessdate=28 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ashalim ===
The [[Ashalim power station]] is a [[solar energy|solar]] [[power station]] in the [[Negev]] [[desert]] near the [[kibbutz]] of [[Ashalim]], (south of the district city of [[Be'er Sheva]]) in [[Israel]]. It has the tallest solar power tower in the world.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

== Finance and business ==
===Technology providers===
[[File:Solel testing site at the National Solar Energy Center in Israel.jpg|thumb|A [[Solel]] testing site in the [[Negev]]]]
*[http://www.kedmasolar.com/ Kedma Solar] is dedicated to bringing affordable renewable energy to Israelis through the use of solar [[Microgrids|mircrogrids]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kedmasolar.com/#!about-kedma/cee5|title=Kedma Solar {{!}} Israel {{!}} Solar Power at No Cost|website=Kedma Solar {{!}} Israel {{!}} Solar Power at No Cost|access-date=2016-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[SolarEdge]] is a provider of [[power optimizer]], [[solar inverter]] and monitoring solutions for [[photovoltaic arrays]]. These products aim to increase energy output through module-level [[MPPT|Maximum Power Point Tracking]] (MPPT).&lt;ref name="frost"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.frost.com/prod/servlet/press-release.pag?docid=179551655 |title=Frost &amp; Sullivan Picks SolarEdge for Hot Investment Opportunity Award in European Solar Photovoltaic Market |publisher=Frost &amp; Sullivan |date=2009-09-10 |accessdate=2009-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Established in 2006, the company has offices in the [[United States]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pv-tech.org/news/solaredge_names_former_sma_america_president_john_berdner_as_north_america_ SolarEdge names former SMA America president John Berdner as North America GM]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Germany]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.newenergyworldnetwork.com/renewable-energy-news/by-technology/solar/germany-to-house-solaredge%E2%80%99s-new-solar-sales-office.html |title=Germany to house SolarEdge's new solar sales office |access-date=2018-01-09 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110429060714/http://www.newenergyworldnetwork.com/renewable-energy-news/by-technology/solar/germany-to-house-solaredge%E2%80%99s-new-solar-sales-office.html |archive-date=2011-04-29 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Italy]], [[Japan]], and [[Israel]].
*[http://www.solaris-synergy.com/ Solaris Synergy] developed a solution, which has been proven in operating water surface installations in Israel and is ready for commercial deployment worldwide.
*[[Solel]] has nine fields of solar collectors in the [[Solar power plants in the Mojave Desert|Mojave Desert of California]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/bin/en.jsp?enDispWho=Articles^l1721&amp;enPage=BlankPage&amp;enDisplay=view&amp;enDispWhat=object&amp;enVersion=0&amp;enZone=Technology dead link]&lt;/ref&gt; It recently signed a contract to build the [[Mojave Solar Park]], which will be the world's largest solar generating plant.&lt;ref name=CBC/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/technology/content/feb2006/tc20060214_533101.htm Israeli Solar Startup Shines]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[https://www.soltell.com/ Soltell] an advanced solution for operation and management of distributed solar photovoltaic facilities via the use of AI technology.
*[[Zenith Solar]] pioneered "concentrated solar power", claiming it to be up to five times more efficient than standard PV technology, making it almost as cost as traditional [[fossil fuels]].&lt;ref name=BW/&gt; In December 2013, Zenith Solar was acquired by [[Suncore Photovoltaics]] Technology Company Limited, a Chinese-US joint venture that specializes in [[Concentrated photovoltaics|CPV]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.barlaw.co.il/content/chinas-suncore-represented-barnea-co-acquired-assets-israels-zenith-solar-0 China's Suncore represented by Barnea &amp; Co. acquired the assets of Israel's Zenith Solar] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131224120348/http://www.barlaw.co.il/content/chinas-suncore-represented-barnea-co-acquired-assets-israels-zenith-solar-0 |date=December 24, 2013 }}, Barnea &amp; Co&lt;/ref&gt;

===Holdings and Finance===
*[[Arava Power Company]] was founded in 2006 on Ketura in the Arava Valley. On June 5, 2011, APC inaugurated Israel’s first medium sized solar field, Ketura Sun at 5 MW.
*[[Israel Cleantech Ventures]] is a venture capital fund that invests in the Israeli [[clean technology]] sector.

==See also==
{{Portal|Energy|Israel}}
*[[List of photovoltaic power stations]]
*[[List of solar thermal power stations]]
*[[List of power stations in Israel]]
*[[Photovoltaic power station]]
*[[Renewable energy commercialization]]
*[[Energy in Israel]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Solar energy in Israel}}
*[http://greenprophet.com/2008/08/31/2179/quick-guide-to-israeli-solar-energy-companies/ Quick Guide to Israeli Solar Energy Companies on Green Prophet]
*[https://archive.today/20130628014830/http://www.solarwaterheatersmalta.com/about-chromagen-alternative-technologies-ltd-malta/ Chromagen dominates the Israeli market in which 85% of the households rely on thermal solar systems for hot water]
*[https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=15503716 Israel Pushes Solar Energy Technology], [[National Public Radio]]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081121110916/http://www.iea-pvps.org/ar/ar07/07ar_Israel.pdf 2007 IEA Annual Report for Israel]
*[http://www.weizmann.ac.il/weizsites/solarenergy/ Center for Energy Research]
{{Energy in Israel}}
{{Solar power by country}}

[[Category:Solar power in Israel| ]]</text>
      <sha1>ggxj3uhds7wyu4s0lxl8b46dd8j7ly7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
