<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Set (deity)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>59236</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961005465</id>
      <parentid>960906808</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-06T03:47:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor2020</username>
        <id>6046894</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/129.205.167.219|129.205.167.219]] ([[User talk:129.205.167.219|talk]]) to last version by Bender235</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="25376" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Egyptian god of the desert, storms, violence, and foreigners}}
{{about|the Egyptian deity|other uses|Set (disambiguation)|the third son of Adam and Eve|Seth|other uses|Seth (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox deity
| type = Egyptian
| name = Set
| image = Set.svg
| alt =
| caption =
| hiro =
| cult_center = [[Naqada|Ombos]]
| symbol = [[Was-sceptre]], [[Set animal]]
| parents = [[Geb]], [[Nut (goddess)|Nut]]
| siblings = [[Osiris]], [[Isis]], [[Nephthys]], [[Horus the Elder]]
| consort = [[Nephthys]], [[Anat]], [[Astarte]]
| offspring = [[Anubis]]
}} 
{{Hiero|Set|&lt;hiero&gt;sw-W-t:X-E20-A40&lt;/hiero&gt;&lt;br /&gt;or&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hiero&gt;s-t:S&lt;/hiero&gt;&lt;br /&gt;or&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hiero&gt;z:t:X&lt;/hiero&gt;| translittération = Swtḫ|align=right|era=Egypt}}
{{Ancient Egyptian religion}}

'''Set''' {{IPAc-en|s|ɛ|t}} or '''Seth''' {{IPAc-en|s|ɛ|θ}} (Egyptian: ''stẖ;''{{efn|Also transliterated '''Sheth''', '''Setesh''',  '''Sutekh''', '''Setan''', '''Seth Merksamer''', '''Seteh''', '''Setekh''', or '''Suty'''. Probably '''Seteh''' is the lection of a god adored by the Hittites, the "Kheta", afterwards assimilated to the local Afro-Asiatic Seth. Sutekh appears, in fact, as a god of Hittites in the treaty declarations between the Hittite kings and Ramses II after the battle of Qadesh. (see Archibald H. Sayce, "The Hittites: The Story of a Forgotten Empire"; also E. A. Wallis Budge, "A History of Egypt from the End of the Neolithic Period to the Death of Cleopatra VII B.C. 30".)}}) is a [[deity|god]] of deserts, storms, envy, disorder, violence, and foreigners in [[ancient Egyptian religion]].&lt;ref name="Ancient Egypt p. 269"&gt;Oxford Encyclopedia of Ancient Egypt, vol. 3, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ancient Greek]], the god's name is given as ''Sēth'' (Σήθ). Set had a positive role where he accompanies [[Ra]] on his [[Solar deity#Solar barge and sun chariot|solar boat]] to repel [[Apep]], the serpent of Chaos.&lt;ref name="Ancient Egypt p. 269"/&gt; Set had a vital role as a reconciled combatant.&lt;ref name="Ancient Egypt p. 269"/&gt; He was lord of the red (desert) land, where he was the balance to [[Horus]]' role as lord of the black (soil) land.&lt;ref name="Ancient Egypt p. 269"/&gt;

In the [[Osiris myth]], the most important [[Egyptian mythology|Egyptian myth]], Set is portrayed as the [[usurper]] who killed and mutilated his own brother [[Osiris]]. Osiris's wife [[Isis]] reassembled his corpse and resurrected her dead husband long enough to conceive his son and heir [[Horus]]. Horus sought revenge upon Set and the myths describe their conflicts.

In ancient Egyptian astronomy, Set was commonly associated with the planet [[Mercury (planet)|Mercury]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Parker |first1=R. A |title=Ancient Egyptian Astronomy |journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series A, Mathematical and Physical Sciences |date=1974 |volume=276 |issue=1257 |pages=51–65 |jstor=74274 |doi=10.1098/rsta.1974.0009 |bibcode=1974RSPTA.276...51P }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Family ==
[[File:Nephthis and Seth-E 3374-IMG 8007-gradient.jpg|thumb|275px|Set and Nephthys, 1279-1213 BC, stone, [[Louvre]]]]
Set is the son of [[Geb]], the Earth, and [[Nut (goddess)|Nut]], the Sky; his siblings are [[Osiris]], [[Isis]], and [[Nephthys]]. He married Nephthys and fathered [[Anubis]] and in some accounts he had relationships with the foreign goddesses Anat and Astarte.&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Encyclopedia of Ancient Egypt, vol. 3, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin==
The meaning of the name ''Set'' is unknown but it is thought to have been originally pronounced *''sūtiẖ'' [ˈsuw.tixʲ] based on spellings of his name in [[Egyptian hieroglyphs]] as ''stẖ'' and ''swtẖ''.{{sfn|te Velde |1967 |pp=1–7}} The [[Late Egyptian language|Late Egyptian]] spelling ''stš'' reflects the palatalization of ''ẖ'' while the eventual loss of the final consonant is recorded in spellings like ''swtj.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://aaew2.bbaw.de/tla/servlet/GetWcnDetails?wn=600254|title=Thesaurus Linguae Aegyptiae |website=aaew2.bbaw.de|access-date=2017-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Coptic language|Coptic]] form of the name, {{Coptic|ⲥⲏⲧ}} ''Sēt,'' is the basis for the English vocalization.{{sfn|te Velde |1967 |pp=1–7}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://corpling.uis.georgetown.edu/coptic-dictionary/entry.cgi?entry=2733&amp;super=1095|title=Coptic Dictionary Online|website=corpling.uis.georgetown.edu|access-date=2017-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Set animal==
{{main|Set animal}}
In [[art of ancient Egypt|art]], Set is usually depicted as an enigmatic creature referred to by [[Egyptologists]] as the ''[[Set animal]]'', a beast resembling no known creature, although it could be seen as a composite of an [[aardvark]], a [[donkey]], a [[jackal]], or a [[fennec fox]]. The animal has a curved [[snout]], long rectangular ears, a thin forked tail and [[Canidae|canine]] body, with sprouted fur tufts in an inverted arrow shape; sometimes, Set is depicted as a human with the distinctive head. Some early Egyptologists proposed that it was a stylised representation of the [[giraffe]], owing to the large flat-topped "horns" which correspond to a giraffe's [[ossicone]]s. The Egyptians themselves, however, made a distinction between the giraffe and the Set animal. During the Late Period, Set is depicted as a donkey or as having a donkey's head.{{sfn|te Velde |1967 |pp=13–15}}

The earliest representations of what might be the Set animal comes from a tomb dating to the [[Amratian culture]] ("Naqada I") of [[prehistoric Egypt]] (3790 BC–3500 BC), though this identification is uncertain. If these are ruled out, then the earliest Set animal appears on a [[ceremonial mace]]head of [[Scorpion II]], a ruler of the [[Naqada III]] phase. The head and the forked tail of the Set animal are clearly present.{{sfn|te Velde |1967 |pp=7–12}}

==Conflict of Horus and Set==
A major element of Set's mythology was his conflict with his brother or nephew, [[Horus]], for the throne of Egypt. The contest between them is often violent but is also described as a legal judgment before the [[Ennead]], an assembled group of Egyptian deities, to decide who should [[royal succession|inherit]] the kingship. The judge in this trial may be Geb, who, as the father of Osiris and Set, held the throne before they did, or it may be the creator gods Ra or Atum, the originators of kingship.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Griffiths|1960|pp=58–59}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other deities also take important roles: Thoth frequently acts as a conciliator in the dispute&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Griffiths|1960|p=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; or as an assistant to the divine judge, and in "Contendings", Isis uses her cunning and magical power to aid her son.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Assmann|2001|pp=135, 139–140}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rivalry of Horus and Set is portrayed in two contrasting ways. Both perspectives appear as early as the ''Pyramid Texts'', the earliest source of the myth. In some spells from these texts, Horus is the son of Osiris and nephew of Set, and the murder of Osiris is the major impetus for the conflict. The other tradition depicts Horus and Set as brothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Griffiths|1960|pp=12–16}}&lt;/ref&gt; This incongruity persists in many of the subsequent sources, where the two gods may be called brothers or uncle and nephew at different points in the same text.&lt;ref name="Assmann 134"&gt;{{harvnb|Assmann|2001|pp=134–135}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Edfu47.JPG|thumb|right|Horus spears Set, who appears in the form of a hippopotamus, as Isis looks on]]
The divine struggle involves many episodes. "Contendings" describes the two gods appealing to various other deities to arbitrate the dispute and competing in different types of contests, such as racing in boats or fighting each other in the form of hippopotami, to determine a victor. In this account, Horus repeatedly defeats Set and is supported by most of the other deities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lichtheim|2006b|pp=214–223}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet the dispute drags on for eighty years, largely because the judge, the creator god, favors Set.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hart|2005|p=73}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late ritual texts, the conflict is characterized as a great battle involving the two deities' assembled followers.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pinch|2004|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; The strife in the divine realm extends beyond the two combatants. At one point Isis attempts to harpoon Set as he is locked in combat with her son, but she strikes Horus instead, who then cuts off her head in a fit of rage.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lichtheim|2006b|pp=218–219}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thoth replaces Isis's head with that of a cow; the story gives a [[origin myth|mythical origin]] for the cow-horn headdress that Isis commonly wears.&lt;ref&gt;Griffiths, J. Gwyn, "Osiris", in {{harvnb|Redford|2001|loc=vol. II|pp=188–190}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a key episode in the conflict, Set sexually abuses Horus. Set's violation is partly meant to degrade his rival, but it also involves homosexual desire, in keeping with one of Set's major characteristics, his forceful, potent, and indiscriminate sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1967|pp=55–56, 65}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the earliest account of this episode, in a fragmentary Middle Kingdom papyrus, the sexual encounter begins when Set asks to have sex with Horus, who agrees on the condition that Set will give Horus some of his strength.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Griffiths|1960|p=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; The encounter puts Horus in danger, because in Egyptian tradition semen is a potent and dangerous substance, akin to poison. According to some texts, Set's semen enters Horus's body and makes him ill, but in "Contendings", Horus thwarts Set by catching Set's semen in his hands. Isis retaliates by putting Horus's semen on lettuce-leaves that Set eats. Set's defeat becomes apparent when this semen appears on his forehead as a golden disk. He has been impregnated with his rival's seed and as a result "gives birth" to the disk. In "Contendings", Thoth takes the disk and places it on his own head; in earlier accounts, it is Thoth who is produced by this anomalous birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1967|pp=38–39, 43–44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another important episode concerns mutilations that the combatants inflict upon each other: Horus injures or steals Set's testicles and Set damages or tears out one, or occasionally both, of Horus's eyes. Sometimes the eye is torn into pieces.&lt;ref name="Pinch 82"&gt;{{harvnb|Pinch|2004|pp=82–83, 91}}&lt;/ref&gt; Set's mutilation signifies a loss of virility and strength.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1967|pp=42–43}}&lt;/ref&gt; The removal of Horus's eye is even more important, for this stolen [[Eye of Horus]] represents a wide variety of concepts in Egyptian religion. One of Horus's major roles is as a sky deity, and for this reason his right eye was said to be the sun and his left eye the moon. The theft or destruction of the Eye of Horus is therefore equated with the darkening of the moon in the course of its cycle of phases, or during [[lunar eclipse|eclipses]]. Horus may take back his lost Eye, or other deities, including Isis, Thoth, and Hathor, may retrieve or heal it for him.&lt;ref name="Pinch 82"/&gt; The Egyptologist [[Herman te Velde]] argues that the tradition about the lost testicles is a late variation on Set's loss of semen to Horus, and that the moon-like disk that emerges from Set's head after his impregnation is the Eye of Horus. If so, the episodes of mutilation and sexual abuse would form a single story, in which Set assaults Horus and loses semen to him, Horus retaliates and impregnates Set, and Set comes into possession of Horus's Eye when it appears on Set's head. Because Thoth is a moon deity in addition to his other functions, it would make sense, according to te Velde, for Thoth to emerge in the form of the Eye and step in to mediate between the feuding deities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1967|pp=43–46, 58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In any case, the restoration of the Eye of Horus to wholeness represents the return of the moon to full brightness,&lt;ref&gt;Kaper, Olaf E., "Myths: Lunar Cycle", in {{harvnb|Redford|2001|loc=vol. II|pp=480–482}}&lt;/ref&gt; the return of the kingship to Horus,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Griffiths|1960|p=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many other aspects of ''[[maat]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pinch|2004|p=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes the restoration of Horus's eye is accompanied by the restoration of Set's testicles, so that both gods are made whole near the conclusion of their feud.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1967|pp=56–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protector of Ra==
[[File:Set speared Apep.jpg|thumb|Set [[spear]]s [[Apep]].]]
Set was depicted standing on the prow of [[Ra]]'s [[Atet|barge]] defeating the dark [[serpent (symbolism)|serpent]] [[Apep]]. In some [[Late Period of Egypt|Late Period]] representations, such as in the [[Twenty-seventh dynasty of Egypt|Persian Period]] [[Temple of Hibis]] at [[Kharga Oasis|Khargah]], Set was represented in this role with a [[falcon]]'s head, taking on the guise of [[Horus]]. In the ''[[Amduat]]'', Set is described as having a key role in overcoming [[Apep]].

==Set in the Second Intermediate and Ramesside Periods==
[[File:SethAndHorusAdoringRamsses crop.jpg|thumb|Set and [[Horus]] adore Ramesses in the small temple at [[Abu Simbel]].]]
During the [[Second Intermediate Period of Egypt|Second Intermediate Period]] (1650–1550&amp;nbsp;BCE), a group of Near Eastern peoples, known as the ''[[Hyksos]]'' (literally, "''rulers of foreign lands''") gained control of Lower Egypt, and ruled the [[Nile Delta]], from [[Avaris]]. They chose Set, originally Upper Egypt's chief god, the god of foreigners and the god they found most similar to their own chief god, [[Hadad]], as their patron. Set then became worshiped as the chief god once again. The Hyksos King [[Apepi (pharaoh)|Apophis]] is recorded as worshiping Set [[Monolatrism|exclusively]], as described in the following passage:
{{quote|text=[He] chose for his Lord the god Seth. He did not worship any other deity in the whole land except Seth.|author=''Papyrus Sallier&amp;nbsp;1 (Apophis and Sekenenre)''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Papyrus Sallier&amp;nbsp;1 (Apophis and Sekenenre) |at=1.2–3 |editor-last=Gardiner |year=1932}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Jan Assmann]] argues that because the ancient Egyptians could never conceive of a "lonely" god lacking personality, Seth the desert god, who was worshiped on his own, represented a manifestation of evil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Of God and Gods: Egypt, Israel, and the rise of monotheism |first=Jan |last=Assmann |pages=47–48 |publisher=University of Wisconsin Press |date=2008 |isbn=978-0-299-22550-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When, c.&amp;nbsp;1522&amp;nbsp;BCE, [[Ahmose I]] overthrew the Hyksos and expelled them, Egyptians' attitudes towards Asiatic foreigners became [[xenophobia|xenophobic]], and royal propaganda discredited the period of Hyksos rule. The Set cult at Avaris flourished, nevertheless, and the Egyptian garrison of Ahmose stationed there became part of the priesthood of Set.

The founder of the [[Nineteenth dynasty of Egypt|Nineteenth Dynasty]], [[Ramesses I]] came from a military family from Avaris with strong ties to the priesthood of Set. Several of the Ramesside kings were named after the god, most notably [[Seti I|Seti&amp;nbsp;I]] (literally, "''man of Set''") and [[Setnakht]] (literally, "''Set is strong''"). In addition, one of the garrisons of [[Ramesses II|Ramesses&amp;nbsp;II]] held Set as its patron deity, and Ramesses&amp;nbsp;II erected the so-called "''Four Hundred Years' Stele''" at [[Pi-Ramesses]], commemorating the 400th anniversary of the Set cult in the Nile delta.

Set also became associated with foreign gods during the [[New Kingdom]], particularly in the delta. Set was also identified by the Egyptians with the [[Hittite mythology|Hittite]] deity [[Teshub]], who, like Set, was a storm god.

==Demonization of Set==
[[File:Relief Herihor Seth obliterated.jpg|thumb|140px|Set on a late New Kingdom relief from Karnak: his figure was erased during his demonization.]]
According to Herman te Velde, the demonization of Set took place after Egypt's conquest by several foreign nations in the [[Third Intermediate Period|Third Intermediate]] and [[Late Period of Ancient Egypt|Late Periods]]. Set, who had traditionally been the god of foreigners, thus also became associated with foreign oppressors, including the [[Assyrian Empire|Assyrian]] and [[Persian Empire|Persian]] empires.{{sfn|te Velde |1967 |pp=138–140}} It was during this time that Set was particularly vilified, and his defeat by Horus widely celebrated.

Set's negative aspects were emphasized during this period. Set was the killer of Osiris, having hacked Osiris' body into pieces and dispersed it so that he could not be [[resurrection|resurrected]]. The Greeks would later associate Set with [[Typhon]], a monstrous and evil force of raging nature. Both were sons of deities representing the Earth ([[Gaia (mythology)|Gaia]] and Geb) who attacked the principal deities (Osiris for Set, [[Zeus]] for Typhon).

Nevertheless, throughout this period, in some outlying regions of Egypt, Set was still regarded as the heroic chief deity.

==Temples==
Set was worshipped at the [[Egyptian temple|temples]] of [[Ombos]] (Nubt near Naqada) and Ombos (Nubt near [[Kom Ombo]]), at Oxyrhynchus in upper Egypt, and also in part of the [[Fayyum]] area.

More specifically, Set was worshipped in the relatively large metropolitan (yet provincial) locale of [[Sepermeru]], especially during the Ramesside Period.&lt;ref&gt;cf. Sauneron, Priests of Ancient Egypt, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; There, Seth was honored with an important temple called the "House of Seth, Lord of Sepermeru". One of the epithets of this town was "gateway to the desert", which fits well with Set's role as a deity of the frontier regions of ancient Egypt. At Sepermeru, Set's temple enclosure included a small secondary shrine called "The House of Seth, Powerful-Is-His-Mighty-Arm", and Ramesses II himself built (or modified) a second land-owning temple for Nephthys, called "The House of Nephthys of Ramesses-Meriamun".{{sfn|Katary|1989|p=216}}

The two temples of Seth and Nephthys in Sepermeru were under separate administration, each with its own holdings and prophets.{{sfn|Katary|1989|p=220}} Moreover, another moderately sized temple of Seth is noted for the nearby town of Pi-Wayna.{{sfn|Katary|1989|p=216}} The close association of Seth temples with temples of Nephthys in key outskirt-towns of this ''milieu'' is also reflected in the likelihood that there existed another "House of Seth" and another "House of Nephthys" in the town of Su, at the entrance to the Fayyum.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner, Papyrus Wilbour Commentary, S28, pp. 127–128&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Papyrus Bologna]] preserves a most irritable complaint lodged by one Pra'em-hab, Prophet of the "House of Seth" in the now-lost town of Punodjem ("The Sweet Place"). In the text of Papyrus Bologna, the harried Pra'em-hab laments undue taxation for his own temple (The House of Seth) and goes on to lament that he is also saddled with responsibility for: "the ship, and I am likewise also responsible for the House of Nephthys, along with the remaining heap of district temples".&lt;ref&gt;Papyrus Bologna 1094, 5,8–7, 1&lt;/ref&gt;

Nothing is known about the particular theologies of the closely connected Set and Nephthys temples in these districts—for example, the religious tone of temples of Nephthys located in such proximity to those of Seth, especially given the seemingly contrary Osirian loyalties of Seth's consort-goddess. When, by the [[Twentieth Dynasty]], the "demonization" of Seth was ostensibly inaugurated, Seth was either eradicated or increasingly pushed to the outskirts, Nephthys flourished as part of the usual Osirian pantheon throughout Egypt, even obtaining a Late Period status as tutelary goddess of her own Nome (UU Nome VII, "Hwt-Sekhem"/Diospolis Parva) and as the chief goddess of the Mansion of the Sistrum in that district.&lt;ref&gt;Sauneron, Beitrage Bf. 6, 46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Le temple d'El-Qal'a. Relevés des scènes et des textes. I' Sanctuaire central. Sanctuaire nord. Salle des offrandes 1 à 112 |first1=L.|last1=Pantalacci  |first2=C.|last2=Traunecker |publisher=Institut Français d'Archéologie Orientale |location=Cairo |date=1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=P.|last=Wilson |title=A Ptolemaic Lexicon: A Lexicographical Study of the Texts in the Temple of Edfu |series=OLA 78 |location=Leuven |date=1997 |isbn=978-90-6831-933-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=P.|last=Collombert |title=Hout-sekhem et le septième nome de Haute Égypte II: Les stèles tardives (Pl. I–VII) |journal=Revue d'Égyptologie |volume=48 |date=1997 |pages=15–70 |doi=10.2143/RE.48.0.2003683}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seth's cult persisted even into the latter days of ancient Egyptian religion, in outlying but important places like Kharga, Dakhlah, Deir el-Hagar, Mut, and Kellis. In these places, Seth was considered "Lord of the Oasis/Town" and Nephthys was likewise venerated as "Mistress of the Oasis" at Seth's side, in his temples{{sfn|Kaper|1997b|pp=234–237}} (esp. the dedication of a Nephthys-cult statue). Meanwhile, Nephthys was also venerated as "Mistress" in the Osirian temples of these districts as part of the specifically Osirian college.{{sfn|Kaper|1997b|pp=234–237}} It would appear that the ancient Egyptians in these locales had little problem with the paradoxical dualities inherent in venerating Seth and Nephthys as juxtaposed against Osiris, Isis, and Nephthys.

==In modern religion==
{{main|Kemetism|Temple of Set|Sethian Liberation Movement}}

==In popular culture==
{{main|Ancient Egyptian deities in popular culture#Set}}

==Notes==
{{noteslist}}

==References==
===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Sources===
* {{cite book|last=Allen |first=James P. |year=2004 |chapter=Theology, Theodicy, Philosophy: Egypt |editor=Sarah Iles Johnston |title=Religions of the Ancient World: A Guide |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |isbn=978-0-674-01517-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bickel |first=Susanne |year=2004 |chapter=Myths and Sacred Narratives: Egypt |editor=Sarah Iles Johnston |title=Religions of the Ancient World: A Guide |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=Harvard University Press |isbn= 978-0-674-01517-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Cohn |first= Norman |date= 1995 |title=Cosmos, Chaos and the World to Come: The Ancient Roots of Apocalyptic Faith |location= New Haven |publisher= [[Yale University Press]] |isbn=978-0-300-09088-8 |ref=harv}} (1999 paperback reprint)
* {{cite book |last=Ions |first=Veronica |date=1982 |title=Egyptian Mythology |location=New York |publisher=Peter Bedrick Books |isbn=978-0-87226-249-2 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/egyptianmytholog00vero_0 }}
* {{cite thesis|last=Kaper |first=Olaf Ernst |date=1997a |title=Temples and Gods in Roman Dakhlah: Studies in the Indigenous Cults of an Egyptian Oasis |type=doctoral dissertation |location=Groningen |publisher=[[Rijksuniversiteit Groningen]], Faculteit der Letteren |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Kaper |first=Olaf Ernst |date=1997b |chapter=The Statue of Penbast: On the Cult of Seth in the Dakhlah Oasis |url=http://print.google.com/print?id=dv_2slpteq4C |title=Egyptological Memoirs, Essays on ancient Egypt in Honour of Herman Te Velde |editor=Jacobus van Dijk |series=Egyptological Memoirs 1 |location=Groningen |publisher=Styx Publications |pages=231–241 |isbn=978-90-5693-014-1 |ref=harv }}{{dead link|date=March 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* {{cite book|last=Katary |first=Sally L. D. |title=Land Tenure in the Rammesside Period |year=1989 |publisher=Kegan Paul International |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Lesko |first=Leonard H. |chapter=Seth |title=The Encyclopedia of Religion |others=[Edited 1987 by Mircea Eliade] |edition=2nd |year=2005 |editor=Lindsay Jones |location=Farmington Hills, Michigan |publisher=Thomson-Gale |isbn=978-0-02-865733-2 |ref=harv |chapter-url-access=registration |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofre0000unse_v8f2 }}
* {{cite journal|last=Osing |first=Jürgen |year=1985 |title=Seth in Dachla und Charga |journal=Mitteilungen des Deutschen Archäologischen Instituts, Abteilung Kairo |volume=41 |pages=229–233 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Quirke |first=Stephen G. J. |year=1992 |title=Ancient Egyptian Religion |location=New York |publisher= Dover Publications |isbn=978-0-486-27427-0 |ref=harv}} (1993 reprint)
* {{cite book|last=Stoyanov |first=Yuri |year=2000 |title=The Other God: Dualist Religions from Antiquity to the Cathar Heresy |location=New Haven |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0-300-08253-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=te Velde |first=Herman |year=1967 |title=Seth, God of Confusion: A Study of His Role in Egyptian Mythology and Religion |edition=2nd |series=Probleme der Ägyptologie 6 |location=Leiden |publisher=[[Brill Publishers|E. J. Brill]] |isbn=978-90-04-05402-8 |translator-first=G. E.|translator-last=van Baaren-Pape |ref=harv}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Seth}}
* [http://alain.guilleux.free.fr/khargha_hibis/khargha_temple_hibis.html Le temple d'Hibis, oasis de Khargha]: ''Hibis Temple representations of Sutekh as Horus''
{{Ancient Egyptian religion footer}}
{{Ancient Egypt topics}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Set (Mythology)}}
[[Category:Earth gods]]
[[Category:Egyptian gods]]
[[Category:Liminal gods]]
[[Category:LGBT themes in mythology]]
[[Category:Mercurian deities]]
[[Category:Sky and weather gods]]
[[Category:War gods]]</text>
      <sha1>fle7x1dv735istchsxa0zwu018ny0pw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
