<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>United States v. Microsoft Corp.</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20770</id>
    <revision>
      <id>951435679</id>
      <parentid>949066711</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-17T04:26:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemonDays64 Bot</username>
        <id>37890503</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>HTTPS security. [[User talk:DemonDays64|Tell me]] if there's an issue with my edit. (via [[WP:JWB]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="38284" xml:space="preserve">{{about|the 2001 antitrust lawsuit|other cases with similar names|United States v. Microsoft Corp. (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|Antitrust lawsuit in 2001}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2015}}
{{Infobox COA case
  |Litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp.
  |Court=[[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit]]
  |ArgueDate=February 26–27,
  |ArgueYear= 2001
  |DecideDate=June 28,
  |DecideYear=2001
  |FullName=United States v. Microsoft Corporation 
  |Citations=253 [[F.3d]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F3/253/34/576095/ 34]
  |Prior=''United States v. Microsoft Corp.'', 87 [[F. Supp. 2d]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp2/87/30/2307082/ 30] ([[D.D.C.]] 2000); 97 [[F. Supp. 2d]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp2/97/59/2339529/ 59] (D.D.C. 2000), ''direct appeal denied, pet. cert. denied'', {{ussc|530|1301|2000|el=no}}.
  |Subsequent=''Microsoft Corp. v. United States'', {{ussc|534|952|2001|el=no}} (''pet. cert. denied''); 224 [[F. Supp. 2d]] [https://www.leagle.com/decision/2002300224fsupp2d761291 76] (D.D.C. 2002); 231 [[F. Supp. 2d]] [https://www.leagle.com/decision/2002375231fsupp2d1441362 144] (D.D.C. 2002) (on remand), ''aff'd in part and rev'd in part'', 373 [[F.3d]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F3/373/1199/474311/ 1199] (D.C. Cir. 2004)
  |Holding=The finding of the District Court that Microsoft violated the Antitrust Act is confirmed, the order of that court is reversed, and remanded for the drafting of a subsequent order.
  |Judges=[[Harry T. Edwards]], CJ; [[Stephen F. Williams]], [[Douglas H. Ginsburg]], [[David B. Sentelle]], [[A. Raymond Randolph]], [[Judith W. Rogers]], and [[David S. Tatel]], JJ.
  |PerCuriam=yes
  |Majority=
  |JoinMajority=
  |Concurrence=
  |JoinConcurrence=
  |Dissent=
  |JoinDissent=
  |LawsApplied={{usc|15|2}}
}}
'''''United States v. Microsoft Corporation''''', 253 F.3d 34 (D.C. Cir. 2001),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol=253 |reporter=F.3d |opinion=34 |pinpoint=|court=[[D.C. Cir.]] |date=2001 |url=https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F3/253/34/576095/ |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a noted American [[antitrust law]] case in which the U.S. government accused [[Microsoft]] of illegally maintaining its [[monopoly]] position in the PC market primarily through the legal and technical restrictions it put on the abilities of PC manufacturers ([[original equipment manufacturer|OEMs]]) and users to uninstall [[Internet Explorer]] and use other programs such as [[Netscape Navigator|Netscape]] and [[Java (software platform)|Java]]. At trial, the district court ruled that Microsoft's actions constituted unlawful monopolization under Section 2 of the [[Sherman Antitrust Act of 1890]], and the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit|U.S. Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit]] affirmed most of the district court's judgments.

The plaintiffs alleged that Microsoft had abused monopoly power on Intel-based personal computers in its handling of [[operating system]] and [[web browser]] integration. The issue central to the case was whether Microsoft was allowed to bundle its flagship [[Internet Explorer]] (IE) web browser software with its [[Windows]] operating system. Bundling them is alleged to have been responsible for Microsoft's victory in the [[browser wars]] as every Windows user had a copy of IE. It was further alleged that this restricted the market for competing web browsers (such as [[Netscape Navigator]] or [[Opera (web browser)|Opera]]), since it typically took a while to download or purchase such software at a store. Underlying these disputes were questions over whether Microsoft had manipulated its [[application programming interface]]s to favor IE over third-party web browsers, Microsoft's conduct in forming restrictive licensing agreements with [[original equipment manufacturer]]s (OEMs), and Microsoft's intent in its course of conduct.

Microsoft stated that the merging of Windows and IE was the result of [[innovation]] and competition, that the two were now the same product and inextricably linked, and that consumers were receiving the benefits of IE free. Opponents countered that IE was still a separate product which did not need to be tied to Windows, since a separate version of IE was available for [[Classic Mac OS|Mac OS]]. They also asserted that IE was not really free because its development and marketing costs may have inflated the price of Windows.

The case was tried before Judge [[Thomas Penfield Jackson]] in the [[United States District Court for the District of Columbia]]. The DOJ was initially represented by [[David Boies]]. Compared to the European Decision against Microsoft, the DOJ case is focused less on interoperability and more on predatory strategies and market barriers to entry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://leconcurrentialiste.com/2014/02/10/the-microsoft-case-by-the-numbers-comparison-between-u-s-and-e-u/|title=The Microsoft case by the numbers: comparison between U.S. and E.U.|work=Le Concurrentialiste|accessdate=February 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
By 1984 Microsoft was one of the most successful software companies, with $55&amp;nbsp;million in 1983 sales. ''[[InfoWorld]]'' wrote:&lt;ref name="caruso19840402"&gt;{{cite news | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kC4EAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA80&amp;pg=PA80#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | title=Company Strategies Boomerang | work=InfoWorld | date=1984-04-02 | accessdate=10 February 2015 | author=Caruso, Denise | pages=80–83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|[Microsoft] is widely recognized as the most influential company in the microcomputer-software industry. Claiming more than a million installed [[MS-DOS]] machines, founder and chairman [[Bill Gates]] has decided to certify Microsoft's jump on the rest of the industry by dominating [[List of Microsoft software|applications, operating systems]], [[Microsoft hardware|peripherals]] and, most recently, [[Microsoft Press|book publishing]]. Some insiders say Microsoft is attempting to be the IBM of the software industry.

Although Gates says that he isn't trying to dominate the industry with sheer numbers, his strategy for dominance involves Microsoft's new [[Windows]] operating system ... "Our strategies and energies as a company are totally committed to Windows, in the same way that we're committed to operating-system kernels like MS-DOS and [[Xenix]]," says Gates. "We're also saying that only applications that take advantage of Windows will be competitive in the long run."

Gates claimed that Microsoft's entrance into the application market with such products as [[Multiplan]], [[Microsoft Word|Word]] and the new [[Microsoft Chart|Chart]] product was not a big-time operation.}}

The [[Federal Trade Commission]] began an inquiry in 1992 over whether Microsoft was abusing its monopoly on the PC operating system market. The commissioners deadlocked with a 2–2 vote in 1993 and closed the investigation, but the Department of Justice led by Janet Reno opened its own investigation on August 21 of that year, resulting in a settlement on July 15, 1994 in which Microsoft consented not to tie other Microsoft products to the sale of Windows but remained free to integrate additional features into the operating system. In the years that followed, Microsoft insisted that Internet Explorer (which, in addition to OEM versions of Windows 95, appeared in the [[Microsoft Plus!|Plus! Pack]] sold separately&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/internet-explorer/products/history|title=Download Web Browser - Internet Explorer|publisher=Microsoft|work=windows.microsoft.com|accessdate=February 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Facts&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol= |reporter= |opinion=98-CV-1232, 98-CV-1233 |pinpoint= |court=[[D.D.C.]] |date=Nov. 5, 1999 |url=https://www.justice.gov/atr/us-v-microsoft-courts-findings-fact |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;) was not a ''product'' but a ''feature'' which it was allowed to add to Windows, although the DOJ did not agree with this definition.

In its 2008 Annual Report, Microsoft stated:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/789019/000119312508162768/d10k.htm#tx31450_3|title=Microsoft Corporation Form 10-K Annual Report for fiscal year ending June 30, 2008 (pg. 14)|accessdate=June 18, 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190614024422if_/https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/789019/000119312508162768/d10k.htm#tx31450_3|archive-date=2019-06-12|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|Lawsuits brought by the U.S. Department of Justice, 18 states, and the District of Columbia in two separate actions were resolved through a [[Consent Decree]] that took effect in 2001 and a Final Judgment entered in 2002. These proceedings imposed various constraints on our Windows operating system businesses. These constraints include limits on certain contracting practices, mandated disclosure of certain software program interfaces and protocols, and rights for computer manufacturers to limit the visibility of certain Windows features in new PCs. We believe we are in full compliance with these rules. However, if we fail to comply with them, additional restrictions could be imposed on us that would adversely affect our business.}}

==Trial==
[[File:US v. Microsoft Bill Gates Color.png|thumb|right|Bill Gates during his deposition.]]
The suit began on May 18, 1998, with the U.S. Department of Justice and the Attorneys General of twenty U.S. states (and the District of Columbia) suing Microsoft for illegally thwarting competition in order to protect and extend its software monopoly. In October 1998, the U.S. Department of Justice also sued Microsoft for violating a 1994 consent decree by forcing computer makers to include its Internet browser as a part of the installation of Windows software. While the DOJ was represented by David Boies, the States were separately represented by New York Attorneys General Alan Kusinitz, Gail Cleary and Steve Houck.

Bill Gates was called "evasive and nonresponsive" by a source present at his videotaped deposition.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20120524145641/http://news.com.com/2100-1023-214993.html Gates Deposition Called Evasive&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He argued over the definitions of words such as "compete", "concerned", "ask", and "we"; certain portions of the proceeding would later provoke laughter from the judge, when an excerpted version was shown in court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/TECH/computing/9811/17/judgelaugh.ms.idg/index.html |work=CNN |title=Gates deposition makes judge laugh in court |date=November 16, 1998 |accessdate=May 27, 2010 |archivedate=September 2, 1999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/19990902200311/http://www.infoworld.com/cgi-bin/displayStory.pl?981116.ecdeposition.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Businessweek]]'' reported that "early rounds of his [[Deposition (law)|deposition]] show him offering obfuscatory answers and saying 'I don't recall' so many times that even the presiding judge had to chuckle. Many of the technology chief's denials and pleas of ignorance have been directly refuted by prosecutors with snippets of email Gates both sent and received."&lt;ref name=neuborne&gt;{{cite news|last=Neuborne|first=Ellen|title=Microsoft's Teflon Bill|url=http://www.businessweek.com/1998/48/b3606125.htm|accessdate=March 19, 2013|newspaper=Businessweek|date=November 30, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Intel]] Vice-President [[Steven McGeady]], called as a witness, quoted [[Paul Maritz]], a senior Microsoft vice president, as having stated an intention to "[[Embrace, extend and extinguish|extinguish]]" and "smother" rival [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] and to "cut off Netscape's air supply" by giving away a clone of Netscape's flagship product for free.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Microsoft Attacks Credibility of Intel Exec | first=Rajiv | last=Chandrasekaran | url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/business/longterm/microsoft/stories/1998/microsoft111398.htm | work=The Washington Post | page=B1 | date=November 13, 1998 | accessdate=May 27, 2010 | archivedate=February 5, 2012 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120205182337/http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/business/longterm/microsoft/stories/1998/microsoft111398.htm | url-status=live | df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of videotapes were submitted as evidence by Microsoft during the trial, including one that demonstrated that removing Internet Explorer from Microsoft Windows caused slowdowns and malfunctions in Windows. In the videotaped demonstration of what then-Microsoft vice president [[Jim Allchin]] stated to be a seamless segment filmed on one PC, the plaintiff noticed that some icons mysteriously disappear and reappear on the PC's [[Desktop environment|desktop]], suggesting that the effects might have been falsified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Buggy Video and More, Microsoft Is Going Backward|url=http://www.businessweek.com/microsoft/updates/up90203a.htm | work=Business Week | date=February 3, 1999 | accessdate=December 12, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allchin admitted that the blame for the tape problems lay with some of his staff. "They ended up filming it—grabbing the wrong screen shot", he said of the incident. Later, Allchin re-ran the demonstration and provided a new videotape, but in so doing Microsoft dropped the claim that Windows is slowed down when Internet Explorer is removed. Mark Murray, a Microsoft spokesperson, berated the government attorneys for "nitpicking on issues like video production".&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = McCullagh | first = Declan | title = Feds Accuse MS of Falsification | newspaper = Wired | date = February 2, 1999 | url = https://www.wired.com/news/politics/0,1283,17689,00.html | accessdate = November 14, 2009 | archivedate = January 15, 2011 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110115024801/http://www.wired.com/politics/law/news/1999/02/17689 | url-status = live | df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft submitted a second inaccurate videotape into evidence later the same month as the first. The issue in question was how easy or hard it was for [[AOL|America Online]] users to download and install Netscape Navigator onto a Windows PC. Microsoft's videotape showed the process as being quick and easy, resulting in the Netscape icon appearing on the user's desktop. The government produced its own videotape of the same process, revealing that Microsoft's videotape had conveniently removed a long and complex part of the procedure and that the Netscape icon was not placed on the desktop, requiring a user to search for it. Brad Chase, a Microsoft vice president, verified the government's tape and conceded that Microsoft's own tape was falsified.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.wired.com/news/politics/0,1283,17938,00.html Compaq: It Was All a Big Mix-Up] by [[Declan McCullagh]] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wlkViMOh?url=http://www.wired.com/politics/law/news/1999/02/17938&lt;/ref&gt;

When the judge ordered Microsoft to offer a version of Windows which did not include Internet Explorer, Microsoft responded that the company would offer manufacturers a choice: one version of Windows that was obsolete, or another that did not work properly. The judge asked, "It seemed absolutely clear to you that I entered an order that required that you distribute a product that would not work?" David Cole, a Microsoft vice president, replied, "In plain English, yes. We followed that order. It wasn't my place to consider the consequences of that."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |access-date=November 19, 2018 |url=http://www.richardnoble.com/microsoft-trial.htm |title=Retracing the Missteps in Microsoft's Defense at Its Antitrust Trial |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010503053902/http://www.richardnoble.com:80/microsoft-trial.htm |archive-date=May 3, 2001 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gates and his successor as CEO [[Steve Ballmer]] were so worried about the outcome of the case that they discussed leaving Microsoft "if they really screw the company that badly, really just split it up in a totally irrational way", Gates recalled.&lt;ref name="leibovich20001231"&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/2000/12/31/alter-egos/91b267b0-858c-4d4e-a4bd-48f22e015f70/ |title=Alter Egos |last=Leibovich |first=Mark |date=2000-12-31 |work=Washington Post |access-date=2019-06-24 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161225224631/https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/2000/12/31/alter-egos/91b267b0-858c-4d4e-a4bd-48f22e015f70/ |archive-date=2016-12-25 |language=en-US |issn=0190-8286 | url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft vigorously defended itself in the public arena, arguing that its attempts to "innovate" were under attack by rival companies jealous of its success, and that government litigation was merely their pawn (see [[public choice theory]]). A full-page ad run in ''[[The Washington Post]]'' and ''[[The New York Times]]'' on June 2, 1999, by [[The Independent Institute]] delivered "An Open Letter to President Clinton From 240 Economists On Antitrust Protectionism." It said, in part, "Consumers did not ask for these antitrust actions – rival business firms did. Consumers of high technology have enjoyed falling prices, expanding outputs, and a breathtaking array of new products and innovations. ... Increasingly, however, some firms have sought to handicap their rivals by turning to government for protection. Many of these cases are based on speculation about some vaguely specified consumer harm in some unspecified future, and many of the proposed interventions will weaken successful U.S. firms and impede their competitiveness abroad."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.org/issues/article.asp?id=483 Open Letter on Antitrust Protectionism from "The Independent Institute"] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1298665666970537)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Judgment ===
Judge [[Thomas Penfield Jackson]] issued his findings of fact on November 5, 1999, which stated that Microsoft's dominance of the [[x86]]-based personal computer [[operating system]]s market constituted a monopoly, and that Microsoft had taken actions to crush threats to that monopoly, including [[Apple Inc.|Apple]], [[Java (software platform)|Java]], [[Netscape]], [[Lotus Software]], [[RealNetworks]], [[Linux]], and others.&lt;ref name=Facts/&gt; Judgment was split in two parts. On April 3, 2000, he issued his ''conclusions of law'', according to which Microsoft had committed [[monopolization]], attempted monopolization, and [[tying (commerce)|tying]] in violation of Sections 1 and 2 of the [[Sherman Antitrust Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol=87 |reporter=F. Supp. 2d |opinion=30 |pinpoint= |court=[[D.D.C.]] |date=2000 |url=https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp2/87/30/2307082/ |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft immediately appealed the decision.&lt;ref name="timeline"&gt;{{cite web|title=''U.S. v. Microsoft'': Timeline|url=https://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/news/2002/11/35212|work=Wired |publisher=Condé Nast|date=November 4, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
On June 7, 2000, the court ordered a breakup of Microsoft as its remedy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol=97 |reporter=F. Supp. 2d |opinion=59 |pinpoint= |court=[[D.D.C.]] |date=2000 |url=https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp2/97/59/2339529/ |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to that judgment, Microsoft would have to be broken into two separate units, one to produce the operating system, and one to produce other software components.&lt;ref name="timeline" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ingram|first=Mike|title=U.S. Judge Orders Break-up of Microsoft| url=http://www.wsws.org/articles/2000/jun2000/micr-j09.shtml|work=World Socialist Web Site|publisher=International Committee of the Fourth International|date=June 9, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appeal==
After a notice of appeal was filed in the intermediate appellate court, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit|D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals]], the district (trial) court certified appeal directly to the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] under 15&amp;nbsp;[[United States Code|U.S.C.]]&amp;nbsp;§29(b),&lt;ref name="253 F.3d at 48"&gt;''United States v. Microsoft Corp.'', [https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=17987618389090921096#p48 253 F.3d 34, 48] (D.C. Cir. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt; which gives the Supreme Court jurisdiction to hear direct appeals from the district court in certain antitrust cases initiated by the federal government if "the district judge who adjudicated the case enters an order stating that immediate consideration of the appeal by the Supreme Court is of general public importance in the administration of justice."&lt;ref&gt;{{USCSub|15|29|b}}&lt;/ref&gt; The states also filed a [[Certiorari before judgment|petition for certiorari before judgment]] in the Supreme Court, which requested that the Supreme Court hear their appeals from the district court's decision without proceeding first through the district court of appeals.&lt;ref name="253 F.3d at 48"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Russell |first1=Kevin |title=Overview of Supreme Court’s cert. before judgment practice |url=http://www.scotusblog.com/2011/02/overview-of-supreme-court%E2%80%99s-cert-before-judgment-practice/ |website=[[SCOTUSblog]] |accessdate=15 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Supreme Court declined to hear the federal government's appeal, remanding the case to the district court of appeals, and also denied the states' petition for certiorari before judgment.&lt;ref name="253 F.3d at 48"/&gt;

The D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals overturned Judge Jackson's rulings against Microsoft. This was partly because the [[appellate court]] had adopted a "drastically altered scope of liability" under which the remedies could be taken, and also partly due to the [[News embargo|embargoed]] interviews Judge Jackson had given to the news media while he was still hearing the case, in violation of the [[Code of Conduct]] for US Judges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscourts.gov/guide/vol2/ch1.html#3 Judiciary Policies And Procedures: Codes Of Conduct&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Judge Jackson did not attend the D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals hearing, in which the appeals court judges accused him of unethical conduct and determined he should have recused himself from the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.wired.com/politics/law/news/2001/02/42071 | work=Wired | title=Microsoft Judge Ripped in Court | date=February 28, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Judge Jackson's response to this was that Microsoft's conduct itself was the cause of any "perceived bias"; Microsoft executives had, according to him, "proved, time and time again, to be inaccurate, misleading, evasive, and transparently false. ... Microsoft is a company with an institutional disdain for both the truth and for rules of law that lesser entities must respect. It is also a company whose senior management is not averse to offering specious testimony to support spurious defenses to claims of its wrongdoing."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windowsitpro.com/Article/ArticleID/20269/20269.html Pricing at Issue As U.S. Finishes Microsoft Case ] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wljiJcnF?url=http://www.windowsitpro.com/article/news2/judge-jackson-exits-microsoft-discrimination-case.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; However, the appeals court did not overturn the findings of fact. Although the D.C. Circuit found that it was possible to examine high-tech industries with traditional antitrust analysis, the court announced a new and permissive liability rule that repudiated the Supreme Court's dominant rule of per se illegality for tie-ins, due to the court's concern for the dynamic effects that a per se rule would have on innovation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bluebook journal | first=J. Gregory | last=Sidak | first2=David J. | last2=Teece | title=Dynamic Competition in Antitrust Law | volume=5 | journal=J. Competition L. &amp; Econ. | page=581 | pin=621–22 | url=https://www.criterioneconomics.com/docs/dynamic-comp1.pdf | year=2009}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The D.C. Circuit remanded the case for consideration of a proper remedy under a more limited scope of liability. Judge [[Colleen Kollar-Kotelly]] was chosen to hear the case.

The DOJ announced on September 6, 2001 that it was no longer seeking to break up Microsoft and would instead seek a lesser antitrust penalty. Microsoft decided to draft a settlement proposal allowing PC manufacturers to adopt non-Microsoft software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilke|first=John R.|title=Microsoft Drafts Settlement Proposal, Hoping to Resolve Antitrust Lawsuit|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB1000076767888491506|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal|date=September 10, 2001|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010919223203/http://public.wsj.com/sn/y/SB1000076767888491506.html |archivedate=September 19, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Settlement==
On November 2, 2001, the DOJ reached an agreement with Microsoft to settle the case. The proposed settlement required Microsoft to share its [[Application Programming Interface|application programming interfaces]] with third-party companies and appoint a panel of three people who would have full access to Microsoft's systems, records, and source code for five years in order to ensure compliance.&lt;Ref Name="MSCourtSettlement"&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol= |reporter= |opinion=98-CV-1232 |pinpoint= |court=[[D.D.C.]] |date=Nov. 12, 2002 |url=https://www.justice.gov/atr/case-document/file/503541/download |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the DOJ did not require Microsoft to change any of its code nor prevent Microsoft from tying other software with Windows in the future. On August 5, 2002, Microsoft announced that it would make some concessions towards the proposed final settlement ahead of the judge's verdict. On November 1, 2002, Judge Kollar-Kotelly released a judgment accepting most of the proposed DOJ settlement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=United States v. Microsoft Corp. |vol=231 |reporter=F. Supp. 2d |opinion=144 |pinpoint= |court=[[D.D.C.]] |date=2002 |url=https://www.leagle.com/decision/2002375231fsupp2d1441362 |accessdate=2018-06-10 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nine states (California, Connecticut, Iowa, Florida, Kansas, Minnesota, Utah, Virginia and Massachusetts) and the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]] (which had been pursuing the case together with the DOJ) did not agree with the settlement, arguing that it did not go far enough to curb Microsoft's anti-competitive business practices.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}} On June 30, 2004, the U.S. appeals court unanimously approved the settlement with the Justice Department, rejecting objections that the sanctions were inadequate.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}

The dissenting states regarded the settlement as merely a slap on the wrist. Industry pundit [[Robert X. Cringely]] believed a breakup was not possible, and that "now the only way Microsoft can die is by suicide."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/cringely/pulpit/pulpit20040408.html I, Cringely . The Pulpit . The Once and Future King: Now the Only Way Microsoft Can Die is by Suicide | PBS] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wllczABm?url=http://www.pbs.org/cringely/pulpit/2004/pulpit_20040408_000808.html&lt;/ref&gt; Andrew Chin, an antitrust law professor at the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] who assisted Judge Jackson in drafting the findings of fact, wrote that the settlement gave Microsoft "a special antitrust immunity to license Windows and other 'platform software' under contractual terms that destroy freedom of competition."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unclaw.com/chin/scholarship/nando.pdf A case of insecure browsing] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wlmVlRTG)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unclaw.com/chin/scholarship/decodingmicrosoft.pdf DECODING MICROSOFT: A FIRST PRINCIPLES APPROACH] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wlmSZmAI)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unclaw.com/chin/scholarship/microsoft.htm The Microsoft Case&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1298667420478138)&lt;/ref&gt;

Law professor [[Eben Moglen]] noted that the way Microsoft was required to disclose its APIs and protocols was useful only for “interoperating with a Windows Operating System Product”, not for implementing support of those APIs and protocols in any competing operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url = http://moglen.law.columbia.edu/publications/lu-18.pdf |title = Free Software Matters: Shaking Up The Microsoft Settlement |author = [[Eben Moglen]] |format = PDF |date = January 28, 2002 |accessdate = February 7, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Microsoft's obligations under the settlement, as originally drafted, expired on November 12, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/f201200/201205a.htm Microsoft Consent Decree Compliance Advisory – August 1, 2003 : U.S. v. Microsoft&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] (Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wllczAC3?url=http://www.justice.gov/atr/cases/f201200/201205a.htm&lt;/ref&gt; However, Microsoft later "agreed to consent to a two-year extension of part of the Final Judgments" dealing with [[communications protocol]] licensing, and that if the plaintiffs later wished to extend those aspects of the settlement even as far as 2012, it would not object. The plaintiffs made clear that the extension was intended to serve only to give the relevant part of the settlement "the opportunity to succeed for the period of time it was intended to cover", rather than being due to any "pattern of willful and systematic violations".&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.seattlepi.nwsource.com/microsoft/library/jsr20060512.pdf ATR-SV-DIV401;MDE;15906;7&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;](Archive at https://www.webcitation.org/5wllczACC?url=http://blog.seattlepi.com/microsoft/files/library/jsr20060512.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Economist [[Milton Friedman]] believed that the antitrust case against Microsoft set a dangerous precedent that foreshadowed increasing government regulation of what was formerly an industry that was relatively free of government intrusion and that future technological progress in the industry will be impeded as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cato.org/pubs/policy_report/v21n2/friedman.html |title=The Business Community's Suicidal Impulse | last=Friedman | first=Milton | publisher=[[Cato Institute]] | work=Policy Forum |date=March–April 1999 |accessdate= February 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the January 2007 edition of the ''Journal of Business &amp; Economic Research'', Jenkins and Bing argue that, contrary to Friedman's concerns, the settlement actually had little effect on Microsoft's behavior. The fines, restrictions, and monitoring imposed were not enough to prevent it from "abusing its monopolistic power and too little to prevent it from dominating the software and operating system industry." They conclude that, remaining dominant and monopolistic after the trial, it had continued to stifle competitors and innovative technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bluebook journal | first=Gregory T. | last=Jenkins | first2=Robert W. | last2=Bing | title=Microsoft’s Monopoly: Anti-Competitive Behavior, Predatory Tactics, And The Failure Of Governmental Will | volume=5 | journal=J. Bus. &amp; Econ. Research | page=222 | url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/264845425_Microsoft%27s_Monopoly_Anti-Competitive_Behavior_Predatory_Tactics_And_The_Failure_Of_Governmental_Will | year=2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jean-Louis Gassée]], CEO of [[Be Inc.]], claimed Microsoft was not really making any money from Internet Explorer, and its incorporation with the operating system was due to consumer expectation to have a browser packaged with the operating system. For example, [[BeOS]] comes packaged with its web browser, [[NetPositive]]. Instead, he argued, Microsoft's true anticompetitive clout was in the rebates it offered to [[OEM]]s preventing other operating systems from getting a foothold in the market.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1298667420478086 Jean-Louis Gassée on why PC manufacturers don't sell non MS products&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] (Archive link)&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Slist tying}}
*''[[Antitrust (film)|Antitrust]]'', a 2001 film about "NURV", a large software company that presents a fictionalized Microsoft
*[[Browser wars]]
*[[Criticism of Microsoft]]
*[[European Union Microsoft competition case]]
*[[Microsoft litigation]]
*[[Removal of Internet Explorer]]
*[[US antitrust law]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* {{cite book | first1 = Phillip E. | last1 = Areeda | first2 = Herbert | last2 = Hovenkamp | title = Antitrust Law: An Analysis of Antitrust Principles and Their Application | edition = 4th | year = 2015 | location = New York | publisher = Wolters Kluwer | isbn = 978-0-7355-6428-2 | ref = harv }}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
===Articles===
* Andrew Chin, [http://www.unclaw.com/chin/scholarship/microsoft.htm Decoding Microsoft: A First Principles Approach], 40 Wake Forest Law Review 1 (2005)
* Kenneth Elzinga, David Evans, and Albert Nichols, United States v. Microsoft: Remedy or Malady? 9 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 633 (2001)
* John Lopatka and William Page, Antitrust on Internet Time: Microsoft and the Law and Economics of Exclusion, 7 Supreme Court Economic Review 157–231 (1999)
* John Lopatka and William Page, The Dubious Search For Integration in the Microsoft Trial, 31 Conn. L. Rev. 1251 (1999)
* John Lopatka and William Page, Who Suffered Antitrust Injury in the Microsoft Case?, 69 George Washington Law Review 829-59 (2001)
* Alan Meese, Monopoly Bundling In Cyberspace: How Many Products Does Microsoft Sell ? 44 Antitrust Bulletin 65 (1999)
* Alan Meese, Don't Disintegrate Microsoft (Yet), 9 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 761 (2001)
* Steven Salop and R. Craig Romaine, Preserving Monopoly: Economic Analysis, Legal Standards, and the Microsoft Case, 7 Geo. Mas. L. Rev. 617 (1999)
* Howard A. Shelanski and [[J. Gregory Sidak]], Antitrust Divestiture in Network Industries, 68 University of Chicago Law Review 1 (2001)

===Books===
* {{cite book |author-last=Abramson |author-first=Bruce |title=Digital Phoenix; Why the Information Economy Collapsed and How it Will Rise Again |year=2005 |publisher=[[MIT Press]] |isbn=978-0-262-51196-4}}
* {{cite book |title=The Microsoft Antitrust Cases - Competition Policy for the Twenty-first Century |author-first1=Andrew I. |author-last1=Gavil |author-first2=Harry |author-last2=First |publisher=[[MIT Press]] |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA |date=2014-12-09 |isbn=978-0-262-02776-2}}
* {{cite book |author-last1=Liebowitz |author-first1=S. J. |author-last2=Margolis |author-first2=Stephen |title=Winners, losers &amp; Microsoft: competition and antitrust in high technology |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-2C5AAAAIAAJ |access-date=2010-11-29 |date=2001-03-01 |publisher=[[Independent Institute]] |isbn=978-0-945999-84-3 |archive-date=March 20, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150320043358/http://books.google.com/books?id=-2C5AAAAIAAJ |url-status=live |df=mdy-all }}
* {{cite book |author-last1=Page |author-first1=William H. |author-first2=John E. |author-last2=Lopatka |title=The Microsoft Case: Antitrust, High Technology, and Consumer Welfare |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=2009 |isbn= 978-0-226-64464-6}}
* {{cite book |author-first=Alan |author-last=Reynolds |title=The Microsoft Antitrust Appeal |publisher=Hudson Institute |date=2001}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/f200400/200457.htm Final Judgment in ''U.S. v. Microsoft''] (injunction including final settlement terms approved by the court) (note that the copy posted on the district court's web site is actually an earlier version that the court declined to approve).
* [http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/ms_index.htm The United States DOJ's website on U.S. v. Microsoft]
* [https://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/legal_newsroomarchive.mspx?case=Government%20Anti-Trust%20Case Microsoft's Antitrust Case, Microsoft News Center]
* [https://www.wired.com/news/antitrust/0,1551,35212,00.html Wired news timeline of the Microsoft antitrust case]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20020808104706/http://zdnet.com.com/2100-1104-917931.html ZDnet story on 4th anniversary of Microsoft antitrust case]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20021012081934/http://zdnet.com.com/2100-1104-948381.html ZDnet story on proposed concessions]
* [http://www.netlitigation.com/netlitigation/antitrust.htm Antitrust &amp; the Internet: Microsoft case archive]
* [http://www.unclaw.com/chin/scholarship/microsoft.htm "A Case of Insecure Browsing" by Andrew Chin. ''Raleigh News &amp; Observer'', September 30, 2004]
* [http://www.groklaw.net/staticpages/index.php?page=GatesDepo Bill Gates deposition video at Microsoft on August 27, 1998] (Windows Media, Ogg Theora and Ogg Vorbis formats)
* [http://www.capitalismcenter.org/Advocacy/Antitrust/Microsoft/ The Center for the Advancement of Capitalism]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/19980110230150/http://upside.com/texis/mvm/story?id=349ef3fa0 Nader 0, Microsoft 0 at Upside Magazine of December 31, 1997]
* [https://archive.org/stream/10Kahle000190#page/n77/mode/2up An Interview with Marc Andreessen about Microsoft antitrust litigation and browser wars] &lt;!-- Here's a citation for when this source is incorporated into the article someday. &lt;ref name="Upside March 1998"&gt;{{cite magazine | magazine=[[Upside (magazine)|Upside]] | date=March 1998 | url=https://archive.org/stream/10Kahle000190 | accessdate=February 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|76}} --&gt;
*{{cite web |title=How Microsoft Internet Explorer Almost Became The Default Web Browser |date=September 6, 2019 |work=[[CNBC]] |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e33Go6gbL7s |via=[[YouTube]] }}

{{Microsoft}}
{{Internet Explorer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:United States V. Microsoft}}
[[Category:United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit cases]]
[[Category:United States computer case law]]
[[Category:Microsoft criticisms and controversies]]
[[Category:United States antitrust case law]]
[[Category:Microsoft litigation]]
[[Category:2001 in United States case law]]</text>
      <sha1>2ylpaiiyyw1541ny127t49dee0crgfl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
