<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Gene expression</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>159266</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961132671</id>
      <parentid>960345352</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-06T19:45:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add: s2cid. Removed URL that duplicated unique identifier. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | Activated by Amigao | [[Category:Molecular biology]] | via #UCB_Category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="68858" xml:space="preserve">{{about||vocabulary|Glossary of gene expression terms|a non-technical introduction to the topic|Introduction to genetics}}
{{short description|Conversion of a gene's sequence into a mature gene product or products}}
[[File:Extended Central Dogma with Enzymes.jpg|alt=extended central dogma|thumb|The extended Central Dogma of molecular Biology includes all the cellular processes involved in the flow of genetic information|298x298px]]
'''Gene expression''' is the process by which information from a [[gene]] is used in the synthesis of a functional [[gene product]]. These products are often [[protein]]s, but in non-protein-coding genes such as [[Transfer RNA|transfer RNA (tRNA)]] or [[Small nuclear RNA|small nuclear RNA (snRNA)]] genes, the product is a functional [[RNA]]. Gene expression  is summarized in the Central Dogma first formulated by [[Francis Crick]]  in 1958,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Crick FH | title = On protein synthesis | journal = Symposia of the Society for Experimental Biology | volume = 12 | pages = 138–63 | date = 1958 | pmid = 13580867 }}&lt;/ref&gt; further developed in his 1970 article,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Crick F | title = Central dogma of molecular biology | journal = Nature | volume = 227 | issue = 5258 | pages = 561–3 | date = August 1970 | pmid = 4913914 | doi = 10.1038/227561a0 | bibcode = 1970Natur.227..561C }}&lt;/ref&gt; and expanded by the subsequent discoveries of [[reverse transcription]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors =  | title = Central dogma reversed | journal = Nature | volume = 226 | issue = 5252 | pages = 1198–9 | date = June 1970 | pmid = 5422595 | doi = 10.1038/2261198a0 | bibcode = 1970Natur.226.1198. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Temin HM, Mizutani S | title = RNA-dependent DNA polymerase in virions of Rous sarcoma virus | journal = Nature | volume = 226 | issue = 5252 | pages = 1211–3 | date = June 1970 | pmid = 4316301 | doi = 10.1038/2261211a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baltimore D | title = RNA-dependent DNA polymerase in virions of RNA tumour viruses | journal = Nature | volume = 226 | issue = 5252 | pages = 1209–11 | date = June 1970 | pmid = 4316300 | doi = 10.1038/2261209a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[RNA replication]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Iyer LM, Koonin EV, Aravind L | title = Evolutionary connection between the catalytic subunits of DNA-dependent RNA polymerases and eukaryotic RNA-dependent RNA polymerases and the origin of RNA polymerases | journal = BMC Structural Biology | volume = 3 | pages = 1 | date = January 2003 | pmid = 12553882 | pmc = 151600 | doi = 10.1186/1472-6807-3-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The process of gene expression is used by all known life—[[eukaryotes]] (including [[multicellular organisms]]), [[prokaryotes]] ([[bacteria]] and [[archaea]]), and utilized by [[virus]]es—to generate the [[macromolecule|macromolecular]] machinery for life.

In [[genetics]], gene expression is the most fundamental level at which the [[genotype]] gives rise to the [[phenotype]], ''i.e.'' observable trait. The genetic information stored in [[DNA]]  represents the genotype, whereas the phenotype results from the "interpretation" of that information. Such phenotypes are often expressed by the synthesis of proteins that control the organism's structure and development, or that act as [[enzyme]]s catalyzing specific metabolic pathways.

All steps in the gene expression process may be modulated (regulated), including the [[Transcription (biology)|transcription]], [[RNA splicing]], [[Translation (biology)|translation]], and [[post-translational modification]] of a protein. [[Gene regulation|Regulation of gene expression]] gives control over the timing, location, and amount of a given gene product (protein or ncRNA) present in a cell and can have a profound effect on the cellular structure and function. Regulation of gene expression is the basis for [[cellular differentiation]], [[Developmental biology|development]], [[morphogenesis]] and the versatility and [[adaptability]] of any [[organism]]. Gene regulation may therefore serve as a substrate for evolutionary change.

==Mechanism==

===Transcription===
[[File:simple transcription elongation1.svg|thumb|400px|alt=RNA polymerase moving along a stretch of DNA, leaving behind newly synthetized strand of RNA.|The process of transcription is carried out by RNA polymerase (RNAP), which uses DNA (black) as a template and produces RNA (blue).]]
{{main|Transcription (biology)}} 
The production of a RNA copy from a DNA strand is called [[Transcription (biology)|transcription]], and is performed by [[RNA polymerase]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s, which add one ribo[[nucleotide]] at a time to a growing RNA strand as per the [[Complementarity (molecular biology)|complementarity]] law of the nucleotide bases. This RNA is [[Complementarity (molecular biology)|complementary]] to the template 3' → 5' DNA strand,&lt;ref name="Brueckner2009"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Brueckner F, Armache KJ, Cheung A, Damsma GE, Kettenberger H, Lehmann E, Sydow J, Cramer P|date=February 2009|title=Structure-function studies of the RNA polymerase II elongation complex|journal=Acta Crystallographica D|volume=65|issue=Pt 2|pages=112–20|doi=10.1107/S0907444908039875|pmc=2631633|pmid=19171965}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the exception that [[thymine]]s (T)  are replaced with [[uracil]]s (U) in the RNA.

In prokaryotes, transcription is carried out by a single type of RNA polymerase, which needs to bind a DNA sequence called a [[Pribnow box]] with the help of the [[sigma factor]] protein (σ factor) to start transcription. In eukaryotes, transcription is performed in the nucleus by three types of RNA polymerases, each of which needs a special DNA sequence called the [[Promoter (biology)|promoter]] and a set of DNA-binding proteins—[[transcription factors]]—to initiate the process (see regulation of transcription below). [[RNA polymerase I]] is responsible for transcription of ribosomal RNA (rRNA) genes. [[RNA polymerase II]] (Pol II) transcribes all protein-coding genes but also some non-coding RNAs (''e.g.'', snRNAs, snoRNAs or long non-coding RNAs). [[RNA polymerase III]] transcribes 5S rRNA, transfer RNA (tRNA) genes, and some small non-coding RNAs (''e.g.'', [[7SK RNA|7SK]]). Transcription ends when the polymerase encounters a sequence called the [[Terminator (genetics)|terminator]].

===mRNA processing===
{{main|Post-transcriptional modification}}

While transcription of prokaryotic protein-coding genes creates [[MRNA|messenger RNA]] (mRNA) that is ready for translation into protein, transcription of eukaryotic genes leaves a [[primary transcript]] of RNA ([[Precursor mRNA|pre-RNA]]), which first has to undergo a series of modifications to become a mature RNA. Types and steps involved in the maturation processes vary between coding and non-coding preRNAs; ''i.e.'' even though preRNA molecules for both mRNA and [[Transfer RNA|tRNA]] undergo splicing, the steps and machinery involved are different.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Krebs, Jocelyn E.|title=Lewin's genes XII|others=Goldstein, Elliott S.,, Kilpatrick, Stephen T.|isbn=978-1-284-10449-3|location=Burlington, MA|oclc=965781334|date=2017-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The processing of non-coding RNA is described below (non-coring RNA maturation).

The processing of premRNA  include 5' ''capping'', which is set of enzymatic reactions that add [[7-methylguanosine]] (m&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;G) to the 5' end of pre-mRNA and thus protect the RNA from degradation by [[exonucleases]]. The m&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;G cap is then bound by [[cap binding complex]] heterodimer (CBC20/CBC80), which aids in mRNA export to cytoplasm and also protect the RNA from decapping.

Another modification is 3' ''cleavage and polyadenylation''. They occur if polyadenylation signal sequence (5'- AAUAAA-3') is present in pre-mRNA, which is usually between protein-coding sequence and terminator. The pre-mRNA is first cleaved and then a series of ~200 adenines (A) are added to form poly(A) tail, which protects the RNA from degradation. The poly(A) tail is bound by multiple [[poly(A)-binding protein|poly(A)-binding proteins (PABPs)]] necessary for mRNA export and translation re-initiation. In the inverse process of deadenylation, poly(A) tails are shortened by the [[CCR4-Not]] 3′-5′ exonuclease, which often leads to full transcript decay.

[[Image:Pre-mRNA.svg|right|thumbnail|404x404px|alt=Pre-mRNA is spliced to form of mature mRNA.|Illustration of exons and introns in pre-mRNA and the formation of mature mRNA by splicing. The UTRs (in green) are non-coding parts of exons at the ends of the mRNA.]]
A very important modification of eukaryotic pre-mRNA is ''[[RNA splicing]]''. The majority of eukaryotic pre-mRNAs consist of alternating segments called [[exons]] and [[introns]]. During the process of splicing, an RNA-protein catalytical complex known as [[spliceosome]] catalyzes two transesterification reactions, which remove an intron and release it in form of lariat structure, and then splice neighbouring exons together. In certain cases, some introns or exons can be either removed or retained in mature mRNA. This so-called [[alternative splicing]] creates series of different transcripts originating from a single gene. Because these transcripts can be potentially translated into different proteins, splicing extends the complexity of eukaryotic gene expression and the size of a species [[proteome]].

Extensive RNA processing may be an [[evolution|evolutionary advantage]] made possible by the nucleus of eukaryotes. In prokaryotes, transcription and translation happen together, whilst in eukaryotes, the [[nuclear membrane]] separates the two processes, giving time for RNA processing to occur.

===Non-coding RNA maturation===
{{main|TRNA#tRNA biogenesis|l1=tRNA maturation|RRNA#Prokaryotes vs. Eukaryotes|l2=rRNA maturation|MicroRNA#Biogenesis|l3=miRNA maturation}}
In most organisms [[ncRNA|non-coding genes (ncRNA)]] are transcribed as precursors that undergo further processing.  In the case of ribosomal RNAs (rRNA), they are often transcribed as a pre-rRNA that contains one or more rRNAs. The pre-rRNA is cleaved and modified (2′-O-methylation and [[pseudouridine]] formation) at specific sites by approximately 150 different small nucleolus-restricted RNA species, called snoRNAs. SnoRNAs associate with proteins, forming snoRNPs. While snoRNA part basepair with the target RNA and thus position the modification at a precise site, the protein part performs the catalytical reaction. In eukaryotes, in particular a snoRNP called RNase, MRP cleaves the 45S pre-rRNA into the 28S, 5.8S, and 18S rRNAs. The rRNA and RNA processing factors form large aggregates called the [[nucleolus]].&lt;ref name="Sirri2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sirri V, Urcuqui-Inchima S, Roussel P, Hernandez-Verdun D | title = Nucleolus: the fascinating nuclear body | journal = Histochemistry and Cell Biology | volume = 129 | issue = 1 | pages = 13–31 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 18046571 | pmc = 2137947 | doi = 10.1007/s00418-007-0359-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the case of transfer RNA (tRNA), for example, the 5' sequence is removed by [[RNase P]],&lt;ref name="pmid9759486"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Frank DN, Pace NR | title = Ribonuclease P: unity and diversity in a tRNA processing ribozyme | journal = Annual Review of Biochemistry | volume = 67 | issue =  | pages = 153–80 | year = 1998 | pmid = 9759486 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.biochem.67.1.153 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas the 3' end is removed by the [[Ribonuclease Z|tRNase Z]] enzyme&lt;ref name="pmid17305600"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ceballos M, Vioque A | title = tRNase Z | journal = Protein and Peptide Letters | volume = 14 | issue = 2 | pages = 137–45 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17305600 | doi = 10.2174/092986607779816050 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the non-templated 3' CCA tail is added by a [[nucleotidyl transferase]].&lt;ref name="pmid15498478"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Weiner AM | title = tRNA maturation: RNA polymerization without a nucleic acid template | journal = Current Biology | volume = 14 | issue = 20 | pages = R883–5 | date = October 2004 | pmid = 15498478 | doi = 10.1016/j.cub.2004.09.069 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of [[miRNA|micro RNA (miRNA)]], miRNAs are first transcribed as primary transcripts or pri-miRNA with a cap and poly-A tail and processed to short, 70-nucleotide stem-loop structures known as pre-miRNA in the cell nucleus by the enzymes [[Drosha]] and [[Pasha (protein)|Pasha]]. After being exported, it is then processed to mature miRNAs in the cytoplasm by interaction with the endonuclease [[Dicer]], which also initiates the formation of the [[RNA-induced silencing complex|RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC)]], composed of the [[Argonaute]] protein.

Even snRNAs and snoRNAs themselves undergo series of modification before they become part of functional RNP complex. This is done either in the nucleoplasm or in the specialized compartments called [[cajal body|Cajal bodies]]. Their bases are methylated or pseudouridinilated by a group of [[Small Cajal body-specific RNA|small Cajal body-specific RNAs (scaRNAs)]], which are structurally similar to snoRNAs.

===RNA export===
{{main|Nuclear transport}}
In eukaryotes most mature RNA must be exported to the cytoplasm from the [[cell nucleus|nucleus]]. While some RNAs function in the nucleus, many RNAs are transported through the [[nuclear pore]]s and into the [[cytosol]] &lt;ref name="K2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Köhler A, Hurt E | title = Exporting RNA from the nucleus to the cytoplasm | journal = Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology | volume = 8 | issue = 10 | pages = 761–73 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17786152 | doi = 10.1038/nrm2255 }}&lt;/ref&gt; . Export of RNAs requires association with specific proteins known as exportins. Specific exportin molecules are responsible for the export of a given RNA type. mRNA transport also requires the correct association with [[Exon junction complex|Exon Junction Complex]] (EJC), which ensures that correct processing of the mRNA is completed before export. In some cases RNAs are additionally transported to a specific part of the cytoplasm, such as a [[synapse]]; they are then towed by [[motor protein]]s that bind through linker proteins to specific sequences (called "zipcodes") on the RNA.&lt;ref name="Jambhekar2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jambhekar A, Derisi JL | title = Cis-acting determinants of asymmetric, cytoplasmic RNA transport | journal = RNA | volume = 13 | issue = 5 | pages = 625–42 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17449729 | pmc = 1852811 | doi = 10.1261/rna.262607 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Translation===
{{main|Translation (genetics)}}
For some RNA (non-coding RNA) the mature RNA is the final gene product.&lt;ref name="Amaral2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Amaral PP, Dinger ME, Mercer TR, Mattick JS | title = The eukaryotic genome as an RNA machine | journal = Science | volume = 319 | issue = 5871 | pages = 1787–9 | date = March 2008 | pmid = 18369136 | doi = 10.1126/science.1155472 | bibcode = 2008Sci...319.1787A }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of messenger RNA (mRNA) the RNA is an information carrier coding for the synthesis of one or more proteins. mRNA carrying a single protein sequence (common in eukaryotes) is [[monocistronic]] whilst mRNA carrying multiple protein sequences (common in prokaryotes) is known as [[polycistronic]].[[File:Ribosome mRNA translation en.svg|300px|thumb|right|alt=Ribosome translating messenger RNA to chain of amino acids (protein).|During the translation, tRNA charged with amino acid enters the ribosome and aligns with the correct mRNA triplet. Ribosome then adds amino acid to growing protein chain.]]Every mRNA consists of three parts: a 5' untranslated region (5'UTR), a protein-coding region or open reading frame (ORF), and a 3' untranslated region (3'UTR). The coding region carries information for protein synthesis encoded by the [[genetic code]] to form triplets. Each triplet of nucleotides of the [[coding region]] is called a [[codon]] and corresponds to a binding site complementary to an anticodon triplet in transfer RNA. Transfer RNAs with the same anticodon sequence always carry an identical type of [[amino acid]]. Amino acids are then chained together by the [[ribosome]] according to the order of triplets in the coding region. The ribosome helps transfer RNA to bind to messenger RNA and takes the amino acid from each transfer RNA and makes a structure-less protein out of it.&lt;ref name="Hansen2003"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hansen TM, Baranov PV, Ivanov IP, Gesteland RF, Atkins JF | title = Maintenance of the correct open reading frame by the ribosome | journal = EMBO Reports | volume = 4 | issue = 5 | pages = 499–504 | date = May 2003 | pmid = 12717454 | pmc = 1319180 | doi = 10.1038/sj.embor.embor825 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Berk2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Berk V, Cate JH | title = Insights into protein biosynthesis from structures of bacterial ribosomes | journal = Current Opinion in Structural Biology | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = 302–9 | date = June 2007 | pmid = 17574829 | doi = 10.1016/j.sbi.2007.05.009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Each mRNA molecule is translated into many protein molecules, on average ~2800 in mammals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schwanhäusser B, Busse D, Li N, Dittmar G, Schuchhardt J, Wolf J, Chen W, Selbach M | title = Global quantification of mammalian gene expression control | journal = Nature | volume = 473 | issue = 7347 | pages = 337–42 | date = May 2011 | pmid = 21593866 | doi = 10.1038/nature10098 | bibcode = 2011Natur.473..337S | url = http://edoc.mdc-berlin.de/11664/1/11664oa.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schwanhaeusser2011"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schwanhäusser B, Busse D, Li N, Dittmar G, Schuchhardt J, Wolf J, Chen W, Selbach M | title = Corrigendum: Global quantification of mammalian gene expression control | journal = Nature | volume = 495 | issue = 7439 | pages = 126–7 | date = March 2013 | pmid = 23407496 | doi = 10.1038/nature11848 | bibcode = 2013Natur.495..126S | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In prokaryotes translation generally occurs at the point of transcription (co-transcriptionally), often using a messenger RNA that is still in the process of being created. In eukaryotes translation can occur in a variety of regions of the cell depending on where the protein being written is supposed to be. Major locations are the [[cytoplasm]] for soluble cytoplasmic proteins and the membrane of the [[endoplasmic reticulum]] for proteins that are for export from the cell or insertion into a cell [[lipid bilayer|membrane]]. Proteins that are supposed to be expressed at the endoplasmic reticulum are recognised part-way through the translation process. This is governed by the [[signal recognition particle]]—a protein that binds to the ribosome and directs it to the endoplasmic reticulum when it finds a [[signal peptide]] on the growing (nascent) amino acid chain.&lt;ref name="Hegde2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hegde RS, Kang SW | title = The concept of translocational regulation | journal = The Journal of Cell Biology | volume = 182 | issue = 2 | pages = 225–32 | date = July 2008 | pmid = 18644895 | pmc = 2483521 | doi = 10.1083/jcb.200804157 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Folding===
{{main|Protein folding}}
[[Image:Protein folding.png|thumb|right|300px|alt=Process of protein folding.|Protein before (left) and after (right) folding]]

Each [[protein]] exists as an unfolded polypeptide or random coil when translated from a sequence of [[mRNA]] into a linear chain of [[amino acid]]s. This polypeptide lacks any developed three-dimensional structure (the left hand side of the neighboring figure). The [[Peptide|polypeptide]] then folds into its characteristic and functional [[protein structure|three-dimensional structure]] from a [[random coil]].&lt;ref name=Alberts&gt;{{cite book | last1 =Alberts| first1 =Bruce| first2 = Alexander | last2 = Johnson | first3 = Julian | last3 = Lewis | first4 = Martin | last4 = Raff | first5 = Keith | last5 = Roberts | first6 = Peter | last6 = Walters | name-list-format = vanc  | title =Molecular Biology of the Cell; Fourth Edition | publisher =Garland Science| year =2002 | location =New York and London | chapter =The Shape and Structure of Proteins |chapter-url = https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK26830/ | isbn =978-0-8153-3218-3 | authorlink =Bruce Alberts}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amino acids interact with each other to produce a well-defined three-dimensional structure, the folded protein (the right hand side of the figure) known as the [[native state]]. The resulting three-dimensional structure is determined by the amino acid sequence ([[Anfinsen's dogma]]).&lt;ref name="Anfinsen"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Anfinsen CB | title = The formation and stabilization of protein structure | journal = The Biochemical Journal | volume = 128 | issue = 4 | pages = 737–49 | date = July 1972 | pmid = 4565129 | pmc = 1173893 | doi = 10.1042/bj1280737 | authorlink = Christian B. Anfinsen }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The correct three-dimensional structure is essential to function, although some parts of functional proteins [[Intrinsically unstructured proteins|may remain unfolded]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jeremy M. Berg, John L. Tymoczko, [[Lubert Stryer]]; Web content by Neil D. Clarke|title=Biochemistry|publisher=W. H. Freeman|location=San Francisco |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-7167-4684-3 |chapter=3. Protein Structure and Function |chapterurl=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Search&amp;db=books&amp;doptcmdl=GenBookHL&amp;term=stryer%5Bbook%5D+AND+215168%5Buid%5D&amp;rid=stryer.chapter.280}}&lt;/ref&gt; Failure to fold into the intended shape usually produces inactive proteins with different properties including toxic [[prion]]s. Several [[neurodegenerative]] and other [[disease]]s are believed to result from the accumulation of ''misfolded'' proteins.&lt;ref name="Selkoe:03"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Selkoe DJ | title = Folding proteins in fatal ways | journal = Nature | volume = 426 | issue = 6968 | pages = 900–4 | date = December 2003 | pmid = 14685251 | doi = 10.1038/nature02264 | bibcode = 2003Natur.426..900S }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Protein allergy|allergies]] are caused by the folding of the proteins, for the immune system does not produce antibodies for certain protein structures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Alberts | first1 = Bruce | first2 =  Dennis | last2 = Bray | first3 = Karen | last3 = Hopkin | first4 = Alexander | last4 = Johnson | first5 = Julian | last5 = Lewis | first6 = Martin | last6 = Raff | first7 = Keith | last7 = Roberts | first8 = Peter | last8 = Walter | name-list-format = vanc | chapter = Protein Structure and Function | title = Essential Cell Biology | edition = 3rd | location = New York | publisher = Garland Science, Taylor and Francis Group, LLC | year = 2010 | pages = 120–170 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Enzymes called [[Chaperone (protein)|chaperone]]s assist the newly formed protein to attain ([[protein folding|fold]] into) the 3-dimensional structure it needs to function.&lt;ref name="Hebert2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hebert DN, Molinari M | title = In and out of the ER: protein folding, quality control, degradation, and related human diseases | journal = Physiological Reviews | volume = 87 | issue = 4 | pages = 1377–408 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17928587 | doi = 10.1152/physrev.00050.2006 | url = https://works.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1021&amp;context=daniel_hebert }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, RNA chaperones help RNAs attain their functional shapes.&lt;ref name="Russell2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Russell R | title = RNA misfolding and the action of chaperones | journal = Frontiers in Bioscience | volume = 13 | issue = 13 | pages = 1–20 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 17981525 | pmc = 2610265 | doi = 10.2741/2557 | url = http://www.bioscience.org/2008/v13/af/2557/fulltext.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; Assisting protein folding is one of the main roles of the endoplasmic reticulum in eukaryotes.

===Translocation ===
Secretory proteins of eukaryotes or prokaryotes must be translocated to enter the secretory pathway. Newly synthesized proteins are directed to the eukaryotic Sec61 or prokaryotic SecYEG translocation channel by [[signal peptide]]s. The efficiency of protein secretion in eukaryotes is very dependent on the [[signal peptide]] which has been used.&lt;ref name="pmid23124363"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kober L, Zehe C, Bode J | title = Optimized signal peptides for the development of high expressing CHO cell lines | journal = Biotechnology and Bioengineering | volume = 110 | issue = 4 | pages = 1164–73 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23124363 | doi = 10.1002/bit.24776 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protein transport===
Many proteins are destined for other parts of the cell than the cytosol and a wide range of signalling sequences or [[Signal peptide|(signal peptides)]] are used to direct proteins to where they are supposed to be. In prokaryotes this is normally a simple process due to limited compartmentalisation of the cell. However, in eukaryotes there is a great variety of different targeting processes to ensure the protein arrives at the correct organelle.

Not all proteins remain within the cell and many are exported, for example, [[digestive enzymes]], [[hormone]]s and [[extracellular matrix]] proteins. In eukaryotes the export pathway is well developed and the main mechanism for the export of these proteins is translocation to the endoplasmic reticulum, followed by transport via the [[Golgi apparatus]].&lt;ref name="Moreau2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moreau P, Brandizzi F, Hanton S, Chatre L, Melser S, Hawes C, Satiat-Jeunemaitre B | title = The plant ER-Golgi interface: a highly structured and dynamic membrane complex | journal = Journal of Experimental Botany | volume = 58 | issue = 1 | pages = 49–64 | year = 2007 | pmid = 16990376 | doi = 10.1093/jxb/erl135 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Prudovsky2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Prudovsky I, Tarantini F, Landriscina M, Neivandt D, Soldi R, Kirov A, Small D, Kathir KM, Rajalingam D, Kumar TK | title = Secretion without Golgi | journal = Journal of Cellular Biochemistry | volume = 103 | issue = 5 | pages = 1327–43 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 17786931 | pmc = 2613191 | doi = 10.1002/jcb.21513 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regulation of gene expression==
{{main|Regulation of gene expression}}
[[File:Tortie-flame.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A cat with patches of orange and black fur. |The patchy colours of a [[tortoiseshell cat]] are the result of different levels of expression of [[pigmentation]] genes in different areas of the [[skin]].]]

Regulation of gene expression refers to the control of the amount and timing of appearance of the functional product of a gene. Control of expression is vital to allow a cell to produce the gene products it needs when it needs them; in turn, this gives cells the flexibility to adapt to a variable environment, external signals, damage to the cell, and other stimuli.  More generally, gene regulation gives the cell control over all structure and function, and is the basis for [[cellular differentiation]], [[morphogenesis]] and the versatility and adaptability of any organism.

Numerous terms are used to describe types of genes depending on how they are regulated; these include:
* A '''constitutive gene'''&lt;!--Bolded per MOS:BOLD because the phrase redirects here--&gt; is a gene that is transcribed continually as opposed to a facultative gene, which is only transcribed when needed.
* A ''[[housekeeping gene]]'' is a gene that is required to maintain basic cellular function and so is typically expressed in all cell types of an organism. Examples include [[actin]], [[GAPDH]] and [[ubiquitin]].  Some housekeeping genes are transcribed at a relatively constant rate and these genes can be used as a reference point in experiments to measure the expression rates of other genes.
* A '''facultative gene'''&lt;!--Bolded per MOS:BOLD because the phrase redirects here--&gt; is a gene only transcribed when needed as opposed to a constitutive gene.
* An '''inducible gene'''&lt;!--Bolded per MOS:BOLD because the phrase redirects here--&gt; is a gene whose expression is either responsive to environmental change or dependent on the position in the cell cycle.

Any step of gene expression may be modulated, from the DNA-RNA transcription step to [[post-translational modification]] of a protein. The stability of the final gene product, whether it is RNA or protein, also contributes to the expression level of the gene—an unstable product results in a low expression level. In general gene expression is regulated through changes&lt;ref name="pmid15277516"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zaidi SK, Young DW, Choi JY, Pratap J, Javed A, Montecino M, Stein JL, Lian JB, van Wijnen AJ, Stein GS | title = Intranuclear trafficking: organization and assembly of regulatory machinery for combinatorial biological control | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 279 | issue = 42 | pages = 43363–6 | date = October 2004 | pmid = 15277516 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.R400020200 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; in the number and type of interactions between molecules&lt;ref name="pmid19154003"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mattick JS, Amaral PP, Dinger ME, Mercer TR, Mehler MF | title = RNA regulation of epigenetic processes | journal = BioEssays | volume = 31 | issue = 1 | pages = 51–9 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 19154003 | doi = 10.1002/bies.080099 }}&lt;/ref&gt; that collectively influence transcription of DNA&lt;ref name="pmid19274664"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Martinez NJ, Walhout AJ | title = The interplay between transcription factors and microRNAs in genome-scale regulatory networks | journal = BioEssays | volume = 31 | issue = 4 | pages = 435–45 | date = April 2009 | pmid = 19274664 | pmc = 3118512 | doi = 10.1002/bies.200800212 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and translation of RNA.&lt;ref name="pmid18348251"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tomilin NV | title = Regulation of mammalian gene expression by retroelements and non-coding tandem repeats | journal = BioEssays | volume = 30 | issue = 4 | pages = 338–48 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 18348251 | doi = 10.1002/bies.20741 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some simple examples of where gene expression is important are:
* Control of [[insulin]] expression so it gives a signal for [[blood glucose regulation]].
* [[X-inactivation|X chromosome inactivation]] in female [[mammals]] to prevent an "overdose" of the genes it contains.
* [[Cyclin]] expression levels control progression through the eukaryotic [[cell cycle]].

===Transcriptional regulation===
{{main|Transcriptional regulation}}
[[File:Regulation of Lactose Metabolism in Prokaryotes.svg|thumb|When lactose is present in a prokaryote, it acts as an inducer and inactivates the repressor so that the genes for lactose metabolism can be transcribed.]]
Regulation of transcription can be broken down into three main routes of influence; genetic (direct interaction of a control factor with the gene), modulation interaction of a control factor with the transcription machinery and epigenetic (non-sequence changes in DNA structure that influence transcription).

[[File:Lambda repressor 1LMB.png|thumb|185px|right|alt=Ribbon diagram of the lambda repressor dimer bound to DNA.|The [[Lambda phage#Repressor|lambda repressor]] transcription factor (green) binds as a dimer to [[Nucleic acid double helix|major groove]] of DNA target (red and blue) and disables initiation of transcription. From {{PDB|1LMB}}.]]

Direct interaction with DNA is the simplest and the most direct method by which a protein changes transcription levels. Genes often have several protein binding sites around the coding region with the specific function of regulating transcription. There are many classes of regulatory DNA binding sites known as [[enhancer (genetics)|enhancer]]s, [[insulator (genetics)|insulator]]s and [[silencer (genetics)|silencer]]s. The mechanisms for regulating transcription are very varied, from blocking key binding sites on the DNA for [[RNA polymerase]] to acting as an [[activator (genetics)|activator]] and promoting transcription by assisting RNA polymerase binding.

The activity of transcription factors is further modulated by intracellular signals causing protein post-translational modification including [[phosphorylation|phosphorylated]], [[acetylation|acetylated]], or [[glycosylation|glycosylated]]. These changes influence a transcription factor's ability to bind, directly or indirectly, to promoter DNA, to recruit RNA polymerase, or to favor elongation of a newly synthesized RNA molecule.

The nuclear membrane in eukaryotes allows further regulation of transcription factors by the duration of their presence in the nucleus, which is regulated by reversible changes in their structure and by binding of other proteins.&lt;ref name="pmid18937349"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Veitia RA | title = One thousand and one ways of making functionally similar transcriptional enhancers | journal = BioEssays | volume = 30 | issue = 11–12 | pages = 1052–7 | date = November 2008 | pmid = 18937349 | doi = 10.1002/bies.20849 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Environmental stimuli or endocrine signals&lt;ref name="pmid19182219"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nguyen T, Nioi P, Pickett CB | title = The Nrf2-antioxidant response element signaling pathway and its activation by oxidative stress | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 284 | issue = 20 | pages = 13291–5 | date = May 2009 | pmid = 19182219 | pmc = 2679427 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.R900010200 }}&lt;/ref&gt; may cause modification of regulatory proteins&lt;ref name="pmid18937370"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Paul S | title = Dysfunction of the ubiquitin-proteasome system in multiple disease conditions: therapeutic approaches | journal = BioEssays | volume = 30 | issue = 11–12 | pages = 1172–84 | date = November 2008 | pmid = 18937370 | doi = 10.1002/bies.20852 }}&lt;/ref&gt; eliciting cascades of intracellular signals,&lt;ref name="pmid19319914"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Los M, Maddika S, Erb B, Schulze-Osthoff K | title = Switching Akt: from survival signaling to deadly response | journal = BioEssays | volume = 31 | issue = 5 | pages = 492–5 | date = May 2009 | pmid = 19319914 | pmc = 2954189 | doi = 10.1002/bies.200900005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which result in regulation of gene expression.

More recently it has become apparent that there is a significant influence of non-DNA-sequence specific effects on transcription. These effects are referred to as [[Epigenetics|epigenetic]] and involve the higher order structure of DNA, non-sequence specific DNA binding proteins and chemical modification of DNA. In general epigenetic effects alter the accessibility of DNA to proteins and so modulate transcription.

[[File:Nucleosome 1KX5 2.png|thumb|left|alt=A cartoon representation of the nucleosome structure.|In eukaryotes, DNA is organized in form of [[nucleosomes]]. Note how the DNA (blue and green) is tightly wrapped around the protein core made of [[histone]] [[octamer]] (ribbon coils), restricting access to the DNA. From {{PDB|1KX5}}.]]

[[DNA methylation]] is a widespread mechanism for epigenetic influence on gene expression and is seen in [[bacteria]] and [[eukaryotes]] and has roles in heritable transcription silencing and transcription regulation. In eukaryotes the structure of [[chromatin]], controlled by the [[histone code]], regulates access to DNA with significant impacts on the expression of genes in [[euchromatin]] and [[heterochromatin]] areas.

===Transcriptional regulation in cancer===
{{main|Regulation of transcription in cancer}}

The majority of gene [[Promoter (genetics)#CpG islands in promoters|promoters]] contain a [[CpG site#CpG islands|CpG island]] with numerous [[CpG site]]s.&lt;ref name="pmid16432200"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Saxonov S, Berg P, Brutlag DL | title = A genome-wide analysis of CpG dinucleotides in the human genome distinguishes two distinct classes of promoters | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 103 | issue = 5 | pages = 1412–7 | date = January 2006 | pmid = 16432200 | pmc = 1345710 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0510310103 | bibcode = 2006PNAS..103.1412S }}&lt;/ref&gt;  When many of a gene's promoter CpG sites are [[DNA methylation|methylated]] the gene becomes silenced.&lt;ref name=Bird&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bird A | title = DNA methylation patterns and epigenetic memory | journal = Genes &amp; Development | volume = 16 | issue = 1 | pages = 6–21 | date = January 2002 | pmid = 11782440 | doi = 10.1101/gad.947102 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Colorectal cancers typically have 3 to 6 [[Somatic evolution in cancer#Glossary|driver]] mutations and 33 to 66 [[Genetic hitchhiking|hitchhiker]] or passenger mutations.&lt;ref name="pmid23539594"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vogelstein B, Papadopoulos N, Velculescu VE, Zhou S, Diaz LA, Kinzler KW | title = Cancer genome landscapes | journal = Science | volume = 339 | issue = 6127 | pages = 1546–58 | date = March 2013 | pmid = 23539594 | pmc = 3749880 | doi = 10.1126/science.1235122 | bibcode = 2013Sci...339.1546V }}&lt;/ref&gt;   However, transcriptional silencing may be of more importance than mutation in causing progression to cancer.  For example, in colorectal cancers about 600 to 800 genes are transcriptionally silenced by CpG island methylation (see [[regulation of transcription in cancer]]).  Transcriptional repression in cancer can also occur by other [[Cancer epigenetics|epigenetic]] mechanisms, such as altered expression of [[MicroRNA#DNA repair and cancer|microRNAs]].&lt;ref name="pmid24616890"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tessitore A, Cicciarelli G, Del Vecchio F, Gaggiano A, Verzella D, Fischietti M, Vecchiotti D, Capece D, Zazzeroni F, Alesse E | title = MicroRNAs in the DNA Damage/Repair Network and Cancer | journal = International Journal of Genomics | volume = 2014 | issue =  | pages = 1–10 | year = 2014 | pmid = 24616890 | pmc = 3926391 | doi = 10.1155/2014/820248 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In breast cancer, transcriptional repression of [[BRCA1]] may occur more frequently by over-expressed microRNA-182 than by hypermethylation of the BRCA1 promoter (see [[BRCA1#Low expression of BRCA1 in breast and ovarian cancers|Low expression of BRCA1 in breast and ovarian cancers]]).

===Post-transcriptional regulation===
{{main|Post-transcriptional regulation}}
In eukaryotes, where export of RNA is required before translation is possible, nuclear export is thought to provide additional control over gene expression. All transport in and out of the nucleus is via the [[nuclear pore]] and transport is controlled by a wide range of [[importin]] and [[exportin]] proteins.

Expression of a gene coding for a protein is only possible if the messenger RNA carrying the code survives long enough to be translated. In a typical cell, an RNA molecule is only stable if specifically protected from degradation. RNA degradation has particular importance in regulation of expression in eukaryotic cells where mRNA has to travel significant distances before being translated. In eukaryotes, RNA is stabilised by certain post-transcriptional modifications, particularly the [[5' cap]] and [[polyadenylation|poly-adenylated tail]].

Intentional degradation of mRNA is used not just as a defence mechanism from foreign RNA (normally from viruses) but also as a route of mRNA ''destabilisation''. If an mRNA molecule has a complementary sequence to a [[small interfering RNA]] then it is targeted for destruction via the RNA interference pathway.

===Three prime untranslated regions and microRNAs===
{{main|Three prime untranslated region}}
{{main|MicroRNA}}
[[Three prime untranslated region]]s (3'UTRs) of [[messenger RNA]]s (mRNAs) often contain regulatory sequences that post-transcriptionally influence gene expression. Such 3'-UTRs often contain both binding sites for [[microRNA]]s (miRNAs) as well as for regulatory proteins. By binding to specific sites within the 3'-UTR, miRNAs can decrease gene expression of various mRNAs by either inhibiting translation or directly causing degradation of the transcript. The 3'-UTR also may have silencer regions that bind repressor proteins that inhibit the expression of a mRNA.

The 3'-UTR often contains [[Three prime untranslated region#MicroRNA response elements|microRNA response elements (MREs)]]. MREs are sequences to which miRNAs bind.  These are prevalent motifs within 3'-UTRs. Among all regulatory motifs within the 3'-UTRs (e.g. including silencer regions), MREs make up about half of the motifs.

As of 2014, the [[miRBase]] web site,&lt;ref&gt;miRBase.org&lt;/ref&gt; an archive of [[microRNA|miRNA]] [[Sequence (biology)|sequences]] and annotations, listed 28,645 entries in 233 biologic species.  Of these, 1,881 miRNAs were in annotated human miRNA loci.  miRNAs were predicted to have an average of about four hundred target [[messenger RNA|mRNAs]] (affecting expression of several hundred genes).&lt;ref name=Friedman&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Friedman RC, Farh KK, Burge CB, Bartel DP | title = Most mammalian mRNAs are conserved targets of microRNAs | journal = Genome Research | volume = 19 | issue = 1 | pages = 92–105 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 18955434 | pmc = 2612969 | doi = 10.1101/gr.082701.108 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Friedman et al.&lt;ref name=Friedman /&gt; estimate that &gt;45,000 miRNA target sites within human mRNA 3'UTRs are conserved above background levels, and &gt;60% of human protein-coding genes have been under selective pressure to maintain pairing to miRNAs.

Direct experiments show that a single miRNA can reduce the stability of hundreds of unique mRNAs.&lt;ref name="pmid15685193"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lim LP, Lau NC, Garrett-Engele P, Grimson A, Schelter JM, Castle J, Bartel DP, Linsley PS, Johnson JM | title = Microarray analysis shows that some microRNAs downregulate large numbers of target mRNAs | journal = Nature | volume = 433 | issue = 7027 | pages = 769–73 | date = February 2005 | pmid = 15685193 | doi = 10.1038/nature03315 | bibcode = 2005Natur.433..769L }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other experiments show that a single miRNA may repress the production of hundreds of proteins, but that this repression often is relatively mild (less than 2-fold).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Selbach M, Schwanhäusser B, Thierfelder N, Fang Z, Khanin R, Rajewsky N | title = Widespread changes in protein synthesis induced by microRNAs | journal = Nature | volume = 455 | issue = 7209 | pages = 58–63 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 18668040 | doi = 10.1038/nature07228 | bibcode = 2008Natur.455...58S }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baek D, Villén J, Shin C, Camargo FD, Gygi SP, Bartel DP | title = The impact of microRNAs on protein output | journal = Nature | volume = 455 | issue = 7209 | pages = 64–71 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 18668037 | pmc = 2745094 | doi = 10.1038/nature07242 | bibcode = 2008Natur.455...64B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The effects of miRNA dysregulation of gene expression seem to be important in cancer.&lt;ref name="pmid21931505"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Palmero EI, de Campos SG, Campos M, de Souza NC, Guerreiro ID, Carvalho AL, Marques MM | title = Mechanisms and role of microRNA deregulation in cancer onset and progression | journal = Genetics and Molecular Biology | volume = 34 | issue = 3 | pages = 363–70 | date = July 2011 | pmid = 21931505 | pmc = 3168173 | doi = 10.1590/S1415-47572011000300001 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in gastrointestinal cancers, nine miRNAs have been identified as [[Epigenetics|epigenetically]] altered and effective in down regulating DNA repair enzymes.&lt;ref name="pmid25987950"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bernstein C, Bernstein H | title = Epigenetic reduction of DNA repair in progression to gastrointestinal cancer | journal = World Journal of Gastrointestinal Oncology | volume = 7 | issue = 5 | pages = 30–46 | date = May 2015 | pmid = 25987950 | pmc = 4434036 | doi = 10.4251/wjgo.v7.i5.30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The effects of miRNA dysregulation of gene expression also seem to be important in neuropsychiatric disorders, such as schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, major depression, Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer's disease and autism spectrum disorders.&lt;ref name="pmid22539927"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mellios N, Sur M | title = The Emerging Role of microRNAs in Schizophrenia and Autism Spectrum Disorders | journal = Frontiers in Psychiatry | volume = 3 | issue =  | pages = 39 | year = 2012 | pmid = 22539927 | pmc = 3336189 | doi = 10.3389/fpsyt.2012.00039 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid25636176"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Geaghan M, Cairns MJ | title = MicroRNA and Posttranscriptional Dysregulation in Psychiatry | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 78 | issue = 4 | pages = 231–9 | date = August 2015 | pmid = 25636176 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.12.009 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Translational regulation===
[[File:Neomycin B C.svg|thumb|right|alt=A chemical structure of neomycin molecule.|[[Neomycin]] is an example of a small molecule that reduces expression of all protein genes inevitably leading to cell death; it thus acts as an [[antibiotic]].]]

{{Main|Translation (genetics)}}
Direct regulation of translation is less prevalent than control of transcription or mRNA stability but is occasionally used. Inhibition of protein translation is a major target for [[toxin]]s and [[antibiotic]]s, so they can kill a cell by overriding its normal gene expression control. [[Protein synthesis inhibitor]]s include the antibiotic [[neomycin]] and the toxin [[ricin]].

===Post-translational modifications===
{{Main|Post-translational modification}}
Post-translational modifications (PTMs) are [[covalent]] modifications to proteins. Like RNA splicing, they help to significantly diversify the proteome. These modifications are usually catalyzed by enzymes. Additionally, processes like covalent additions to amino acid side chain residues can often be reversed by other enzymes. However, some, like the [[proteolysis|proteolytic cleavage]] of the protein backbone, are irreversible.&lt;ref name="WalshGarneau-Tsodikova2005"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Walsh CT, Garneau-Tsodikova S, Gatto GJ | s2cid = 32157563 | title = Protein posttranslational modifications: the chemistry of proteome diversifications | journal = Angewandte Chemie | volume = 44 | issue = 45 | pages = 7342–72 | date = December 2005 | pmid = 16267872 | doi = 10.1002/anie.200501023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

PTMs play many important roles in the cell.&lt;ref name="KhouryBaliban2011"&gt;{{cite journal|authorlink3=Christodoulos Floudas | vauthors = Khoury GA, Baliban RC, Floudas CA | title = Proteome-wide post-translational modification statistics: frequency analysis and curation of the swiss-prot database | journal = Scientific Reports | volume = 1 | pages = 90 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 22034591 | pmc = 3201773 | doi = 10.1038/srep00090 | number = 90 | bibcode = 2011NatSR...1E..90K }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, phosphorylation is primarily involved in activating and deactivating proteins and in signaling pathways.&lt;ref name="MannJensen2003"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mann M, Jensen ON | title = Proteomic analysis of post-translational modifications | journal = Nature Biotechnology | volume = 21 | issue = 3 | pages = 255–61 | date = March 2003 | pmid = 12610572 | doi = 10.1038/nbt0303-255 }}&lt;/ref&gt; PTMs are involved in transcriptional regulation: an important function of acetylation and methylation is histone tail modification, which alters how accessible DNA is for transcription.&lt;ref name="WalshGarneau-Tsodikova2005"/&gt; They can also be seen in the immune system, where glycosylation plays a key role.&lt;ref name="SeoLee2004"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Seo J, Lee KJ | title = Post-translational modifications and their biological functions: proteomic analysis and systematic approaches | journal = Journal of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology | volume = 37 | issue = 1 | pages = 35–44 | date = January 2004 | pmid = 14761301 | doi = 10.5483/bmbrep.2004.37.1.035 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; One type of PTM can initiate another type of PTM, as can be seen in how [[ubiquitination]] tags proteins for degradation through proteolysis.&lt;ref name="WalshGarneau-Tsodikova2005"/&gt; Proteolysis, other than being involved in breaking down proteins, is also important in activating and deactivating them, and in regulating biological processes such as DNA transcription and cell death.&lt;ref name="RogersOverall2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rogers LD, Overall CM | title = Proteolytic post-translational modification of proteins: proteomic tools and methodology | journal = Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics | volume = 12 | issue = 12 | pages = 3532–42 | date = December 2013 | pmid = 23887885 | pmc = 3861706 | doi = 10.1074/mcp.M113.031310 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Measurement==
Measuring gene expression is an important part of many [[life science]]s, as the ability to quantify the level at which a particular gene is expressed within a cell, tissue or organism can provide a lot of valuable information. For example, measuring gene expression can:
*Identify viral infection of a cell ([[viral protein]] expression).
*Determine an individual's susceptibility to [[cancer]] ([[oncogene]] expression).
*Find if a bacterium is resistant to [[penicillin]] ([[beta-lactamase]] expression).
Similarly, the analysis of the location of protein expression is a powerful tool, and this can be done on an organismal or cellular scale. Investigation of localization is particularly important for the study of [[Developmental biology|development]] in multicellular organisms and as an indicator of protein function in single cells. Ideally, measurement of expression is done by detecting the final gene product (for many genes, this is the protein); however, it is often easier to detect one of the precursors, typically [[mRNA]] and to infer gene-expression levels from these measurements.

===mRNA quantification===
{{unreferenced section|date=February 2020}}
Levels of mRNA can be quantitatively measured by [[northern blotting]], which provides size and sequence information about the mRNA molecules. A sample of RNA is separated on an [[agarose gel]] and hybridized to a radioactively labeled RNA probe that is complementary to the target sequence. The radiolabeled RNA is then detected by an [[autoradiograph]]. Because the use of radioactive reagents makes the procedure time consuming and potentially dangerous, alternative labeling and detection methods, such as digoxigenin and biotin chemistries, have been developed. Perceived disadvantages of Northern blotting are that large quantities of RNA are required and that quantification may not be completely accurate, as it involves measuring band strength in an image of a gel. On the other hand, the additional mRNA size information from the Northern blot allows the discrimination of alternately spliced transcripts.

Another approach for measuring mRNA abundance is RT-qPCR. In this technique, [[reverse transcription]] is followed by [[quantitative PCR]]. Reverse transcription first generates a DNA template from the mRNA; this single-stranded template is called [[Complementary DNA|cDNA]]. The cDNA template is then amplified in the quantitative step, during which the [[fluorescence]] emitted by labeled [[hybridization probe]]s or [[Intercalation (biochemistry)|intercalating dyes]] changes as the [[Polymerase chain reaction|DNA amplification]] process progresses. With a carefully constructed standard curve, qPCR can produce an absolute measurement of the number of copies of original mRNA, typically in units of copies per nanolitre of homogenized tissue or copies per cell. qPCR is very sensitive (detection of a single mRNA molecule is theoretically possible), but can be expensive depending on the type of reporter used; fluorescently labeled oligonucleotide probes are more expensive than non-specific intercalating fluorescent dyes.

For [[expression profiling]], or high-throughput analysis of many genes within a sample, [[quantitative PCR]] may be performed for hundreds of genes simultaneously in the case of low-density arrays. A second approach is the [[DNA microarrays|hybridization microarray]]. A single array or "chip" may contain probes to determine transcript levels for every known gene in the genome of one or more organisms. Alternatively, "tag based" technologies like [[Serial analysis of gene expression]] (SAGE) and [[RNA-Seq]], which can provide a relative measure of the cellular [[concentration]] of different mRNAs, can be used. An advantage of tag-based methods is the "open architecture", allowing for the exact measurement of any transcript, with a known or unknown sequence. Next-generation sequencing (NGS) such as [[RNA-Seq]] is another approach, producing vast quantities of sequence data that can be matched to a reference genome. Although NGS is comparatively time-consuming, expensive, and resource-intensive, it can identify [[single-nucleotide polymorphisms]], splice-variants, and novel genes, and can also be used to profile expression in organisms for which little or no sequence information is available.

===RNA profiles in Wikipedia ===
[[File:PBB GE SLC2A4 206603 at fs.png|thumb|right|300px|alt=An RNA Expression diagram.|The RNA expression profile of the GLUT4 Transporter (one of the main glucose transporters found in the human body)]]

Profiles like these are found for almost all proteins listed in Wikipedia. They are generated by organizations such as the [[Genomics Institute of the Novartis Research Foundation]] and the [[European Bioinformatics Institute]]. Additional information can be found by searching their databases (for an example of the GLUT4 transporter pictured here, see citation).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GLUT4 RNA Expression Profile|url=http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/genes/ENSG00000181856}}&lt;/ref&gt; These profiles indicate the level of DNA expression (and hence RNA produced) of a certain protein in a certain tissue, and are color-coded accordingly in the images located in the Protein Box on the right side of each Wikipedia page.

===Protein quantification===
For genes encoding proteins, the expression level can be directly assessed by a number of methods with some clear analogies to the techniques for mRNA quantification.

The most commonly used{{Citation needed|date=February 2016}} method is to perform a [[Western blot]] against the protein of interest—this gives information on the size of the protein in addition to its identity. A sample (often cellular [[lysate]]) is separated on a [[polyacrylamide gel]], transferred to a membrane and then probed with an [[antibody]] to the protein of interest. The antibody can either be conjugated to a [[fluorophore]] or to [[horseradish peroxidase]] for imaging and/or quantification. The gel-based nature of this assay makes quantification less accurate, but it has the advantage of being able to identify later modifications to the protein, for example proteolysis or ubiquitination, from changes in size.

===mRNA-protein correlation===
Quantification of protein and mRNA permits a correlation of the two levels. The question of how well protein levels correlate with their corresponding transcript levels is highly debated and depends on multiple factors. Regulation on each step of gene expression can impact the correlation, as shown for regulation of translation&lt;ref name="Schwanhaeusser2011"/&gt; or protein stability.&lt;ref name="Geiger2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Burkhart JM, Vaudel M, Gambaryan S, Radau S, Walter U, Martens L, Geiger J, Sickmann A, Zahedi RP | title = The first comprehensive and quantitative analysis of human platelet protein composition allows the comparative analysis of structural and functional pathways. | journal = Blood | volume = 120 | issue = 15 | pages = e73–82 | date = October 2011 | pmid = 22869793| doi = 10.1182/blood-2012-04-416594 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Post-translational factors, such as protein transport in highly polar cells,&lt;ref name="Moritz2019"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moritz CP, Mühlhaus T, Tenzer S, Schulenborg T, Friauf E | title = Poor transcript-protein correlation in the brain: negatively correlating gene products reveal neuronal polarity as a potential cause. | journal = Journal of Neurochemistry | volume = 149 | issue = 5 | pages = 582–604 | date = June 2019 | pmid = 30664243| doi = 10.1111/jnc.14664 | url = https://hal-univ-lyon1.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02098886/file/Moritz-et-al_X-Omics_final.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; can influence the measured mRNA-protein correlation as well.

===Localisation===
{{Main|In situ hybridization|Immunofluorescence}}
[[File:Hunchback in situ.jpg|thumb|alt=Visualization of hunchback mRNA in Drosophila embryo.|In situ-hybridization of [[Drosophila]] [[embryo]]s at different developmental stages for the mRNA responsible for the expression of [[Drosophila embryogenesis#Maternal effect genes|hunchback]]. High intensity of blue color marks places with high hunchback mRNA quantity.]]

Analysis of expression is not limited to quantification; localisation can also be determined. mRNA can be detected with a suitably labelled complementary mRNA strand and protein can be detected via labelled antibodies. The probed sample is then observed by microscopy to identify where the mRNA or protein is.

[[File:GFP structure.png|thumb|left|200px|alt=A ribbon diagram of green fluorescent protein resembling barrel structure.|The three-dimensional structure of [[green fluorescent protein]]. The residues in the centre of the "barrel" are responsible for production of green light after exposing to higher energetic blue light. From {{PDB|1EMA}}.]]

By replacing the gene with a new version fused to a [[green fluorescent protein]] (or similar) marker, expression may be directly quantified in live cells. This is done by imaging using a [[fluorescence microscope]]. It is very difficult to clone a GFP-fused protein into its native location in the genome without affecting expression levels so this method often cannot be used to measure endogenous gene expression. It is, however, widely used to measure the expression of a gene artificially introduced into the cell, for example via an [[expression vector]]. It is important to note that by fusing a target protein to a fluorescent reporter the protein's behavior, including its cellular localization and expression level, can be significantly changed.

The [[enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay]] works by using antibodies immobilised on a [[microtiter plate]] to capture proteins of interest from samples added to the well. Using a detection antibody conjugated to an enzyme or fluorophore the quantity of bound protein can be accurately measured by [[fluorometric]] or [[Colorimetry (chemical method)|colourimetric]] detection. The detection process is very similar to that of a Western blot, but by avoiding the gel steps more accurate quantification can be achieved.

==Expression system==
[[Image:Tet-ON inducible transgene expression cells.svg|thumbnail|500px|Tet-ON inducible shRNA system]]
{{main|Protein production (biotechnology)}}

An expression system is a system specifically designed for the production of a gene product of choice. This is normally a protein although may also be RNA, such as [[tRNA]] or a [[ribozyme]]. An expression system consists of a gene, normally encoded by [[DNA]], and the [[molecular machinery]] required to [[Transcription (genetics)|transcribe]] the DNA into [[mRNA]] and [[translate]] the mRNA into [[protein]] using the reagents provided. In the broadest sense this includes every living cell but the term is more normally used to refer to expression as a laboratory tool. An expression system is therefore often artificial in some manner. Expression systems are, however, a fundamentally natural process. Viruses are an excellent example where they replicate by using the host cell as an expression system for the viral proteins and genome.

===Inducible expression===
[[Doxycycline]] is also used in "Tet-on" and "Tet-off" [[tetracycline controlled transcriptional activation]] to regulate [[transgene]] expression in organisms and [[cell culture]]s.

===In nature===
In addition to these biological tools, certain naturally observed configurations of DNA (genes, promoters, enhancers, repressors) and the associated machinery itself are referred to as an expression system. This term is normally used in the case where a gene or set of genes is switched on under well defined conditions, for example, the simple repressor switch expression system in [[Lambda phage]] and the [[lac operator]] system in bacteria. Several natural expression systems are directly used or modified and used for artificial expression systems such as the [[Tetracycline controlled transcriptional activation|Tet-on and Tet-off]] expression system.

==Gene networks==
{{main|Gene regulatory network}}
Genes have sometimes been regarded as nodes in a network, with inputs being proteins such as [[transcription factor]]s, and outputs being the level of gene expression. The node itself performs a function, and the operation of these functions have been interpreted as performing a kind of [[information processing]] within cells and determines cellular behavior.

Gene networks can also be constructed without formulating an explicit causal model. This is often the case when assembling networks from large expression data sets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Banf M, Rhee SY | title = Computational inference of gene regulatory networks: Approaches, limitations and opportunities | journal =  Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Gene Regulatory Mechanisms| volume = 1860 | issue = 1 | pages = 41–52 | date = January 2017 | pmid = 27641093 | doi = 10.1016/j.bbagrm.2016.09.003 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Covariation and correlation of expression is computed across a large sample of cases and measurements (often [[transcriptome]] or [[proteome]] data). The source of variation can be either experimental or natural (observational). There are several ways to construct gene expression networks, but one common approach is to compute a matrix of all pair-wise correlations of expression across conditions, time points, or individuals and convert the matrix (after thresholding at some cut-off value) into a graphical representation in which nodes represent genes, transcripts, or proteins and edges connecting these nodes represent the strength of association (see [http://www.genenetwork.org]).&lt;ref name="pmid 15114364"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chesler EJ, Lu L, Wang J, Williams RW, Manly KF | title = WebQTL: rapid exploratory analysis of gene expression and genetic networks for brain and behavior | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 7 | issue = 5 | pages = 485–6 | date = May 2004 | pmid = 15114364 | doi = 10.1038/nn0504-485 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Techniques and tools==

The following experimental techniques are used to measure gene expression and are listed in roughly chronological order, starting with the older, more established technologies. They are divided into two groups based on their degree of [[multiplex (assay)|multiplexity]].

* Low-to-mid-plex techniques:
** [[Reporter gene]]
** [[Northern blot]]
** [[Western blot]]&lt;ref name="Song2009"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Song Y, Wang W, Qu X, Sun S | title = Effects of hypoxia inducible factor-1alpha (HIF-1alpha) on the growth &amp; adhesion in tongue squamous cell carcinoma cells | journal = The Indian Journal of Medical Research | volume = 129 | issue = 2 | pages = 154–63 | date = February 2009 | pmid = 19293442 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Fluorescent in situ hybridization]]
** [[Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction|Reverse transcription PCR]]
* Higher-plex techniques:
** [[Serial analysis of gene expression|SAGE]]&lt;ref name="Hanriot2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hanriot L, Keime C, Gay N, Faure C, Dossat C, Wincker P, Scoté-Blachon C, Peyron C, Gandrillon O | title = A combination of LongSAGE with Solexa sequencing is well suited to explore the depth and the complexity of transcriptome | journal = BMC Genomics | volume = 9 | pages = 418 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 18796152 | pmc = 2562395 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2164-9-418 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[DNA microarray]]&lt;ref name="Wheelan2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wheelan SJ, Martínez Murillo F, Boeke JD | title = The incredible shrinking world of DNA microarrays | journal = Molecular BioSystems | volume = 4 | issue = 7 | pages = 726–32 | date = July 2008 | pmid = 18563246 | pmc = 2535915 | doi = 10.1039/b706237k }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Tiling array]]&lt;ref name="Miyakoshi2009"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miyakoshi M, Nishida H, Shintani M, Yamane H, Nojiri H | title = High-resolution mapping of plasmid transcriptomes in different host bacteria | journal = BMC Genomics | volume = 10 | pages = 12 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 19134166 | pmc = 2642839 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2164-10-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[RNA-Seq]]&lt;ref name="Denoeud2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Denoeud F, Aury JM, Da Silva C, Noel B, Rogier O, Delledonne M, Morgante M, Valle G, Wincker P, Scarpelli C, Jaillon O, Artiguenave F | title = Annotating genomes with massive-scale RNA sequencing | journal = Genome Biology | volume = 9 | issue = 12 | pages = R175 | year = 2008 | pmid = 19087247 | pmc = 2646279 | doi = 10.1186/gb-2008-9-12-r175 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gene expression databases ==

* [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/ Gene expression omnibus] (GEO) at [[National Center for Biotechnology Information|NCBI]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Clough E, Barrett T | title = Statistical Genomics | chapter = The Gene Expression Omnibus Database | series = Methods in Molecular Biology | volume = 1418 | pages = 93–110 | date = 2016 | pmid = 27008011 | pmc = 4944384 | doi = 10.1007/978-1-4939-3578-9_5 | isbn = 978-1-4939-3576-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/home Expression Atlas] at the [[European Bioinformatics Institute|EBI]]
* Mouse [http://www.informatics.jax.org/expression.shtml Gene Expression Database] at the [[Jackson Laboratory]]
* [[CollecTF]]: a database of experimentally validated transcription factor-binding sites in Bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kiliç S, White ER, Sagitova DM, Cornish JP, Erill I | title = CollecTF: a database of experimentally validated transcription factor-binding sites in Bacteria | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 42 | issue = Database issue | pages = D156–60 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 24234444 | pmc = 3965012 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkt1123 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* COLOMBOS: collection of bacterial expression compendia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moretto M, Sonego P, Dierckxsens N, Brilli M, Bianco L, Ledezma-Tejeida D, Gama-Castro S, Galardini M, Romualdi C, Laukens K, Collado-Vides J, Meysman P, Engelen K | display-authors = 6 | title = COLOMBOS v3.0: leveraging gene expression compendia for cross-species analyses | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 44 | issue = D1 | pages = D620–3 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26586805 | pmc = 4702885 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkv1251 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://m3d.mssm.edu Many Microbe Microarrays Database]: microbial Affymetrix data&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Faith JJ, Driscoll ME, Fusaro VA, Cosgrove EJ, Hayete B, Juhn FS, Schneider SJ, Gardner TS | display-authors = 6 | title = Many Microbe Microarrays Database: uniformly normalized Affymetrix compendia with structured experimental metadata | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 36 | issue = Database issue | pages = D866–70 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 17932051 | pmc = 2238822 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkm815 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Columns-list|
*[[AlloMap molecular expression testing]]
*[[Bookmarking]]
*[[Expressed sequence tag]]
*[[Expression Atlas]]
*[[Expression profiling]]
*[[Gene structure]]
*[[Genetic engineering]]
*[[Genetically modified organism]]
*[[List of biological databases]]
*[[List of human genes]]
*[[Oscillating gene]]
*[[Paramutation]]
*[[Protein production]]
*[[Protein purification]]
*[[Ribonomics]]
*[[Ridge (biology)|Ridge]]
*[[Sequence profiling tool]]
*[[Transcriptional bursting]]
*[[Transcriptional noise]]
*[[Transcript of unknown function]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|32em}}

== External links ==
&lt;!-- Please do not add external links here that are not referenced in the text above or help in describing the encyclopedic article 'Gene expression'. Please discuss new additions in the 'discussion' tab or explain clearly in edit notes why this external resource help build the content of this article. This is an article ABOUT gene expression, not a resource of all things related. Thanks! --&gt;
* [http://plantregmap.cbi.pku.edu.cn/ Plant Transcription Factor Database and Plant Transcriptional Regulation Data and Analysis Platform]

{{Gene expression}}
{{Portal bar|Biology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gene Expression}}
[[Category:Molecular biology]]
[[Category:Gene expression| ]]</text>
      <sha1>fsw5z69onrmt4oef5l943thslbcrkkb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
