<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sacbe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1881844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>913607783</id>
      <parentid>900455061</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-02T02:56:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pauli133</username>
        <id>146032</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>cleanup</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="10145" xml:space="preserve">[[image:Sacbe Dzibilchaltun.jpg|right|thumb|Sacbe at Dzibilchaltun in the Yucatán]]
[[image:Kabah Arch 2002.12.29 27.jpg|thumb|right|Arch at the end of the sacbé, Kabah, Yucatán]]

A '''sacbe''', plural '''sacbeob''' ([[Yucatec Maya]]: singular ''sakbej'', plural ''sakbejo'ob''), or "white way", is a raised paved [[road]] built by the [[Maya civilization]] of [[pre-Columbian]] [[Mesoamerica]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharer 2001, 70&lt;/ref&gt; Most connect temples, plazas, and groups of structures within ceremonial centers or cities, but some longer roads between cities are also known. The term "sacbe" is [[Yucatec Maya language|Yucatec Maya]] for "white road"; white perhaps because there is evidence that they were originally coated with limestone [[stucco]] or plaster, which was over a stone and rubble fill.&lt;ref name="Roys and Shook 1966, 43"&gt;Roys and Shook 1966, 43&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The word "Beh" operates as the [[Root (linguistics)|root term]] for "Sacbe" it is a Mayan term for "road, pathway, or trail." Beh is spelled alternately as Be, bej, bey, be, bih, as well as "beel" in the possessive.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Keller |first=Angela |date=2009 |chapter=A Road by any other Name: Trails, Paths, and Roads in Maya Language and Thought |title=Landscapes of Movement: Trails, Paths, and Roads in Anthropological Perspective |editor1=James E. Snead |editor2=Clark L. Erickson |editor3=J. Andrew Darling |pages=133–157 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology |location=Pennsylvania |isbn=978-1-934536-13-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has many distinctions from English concepts of roads, pathways, or trails. Beh's metaphoric meanings are just as important if not more important than its literal meaning of "road." Ethnographers working the lowlands have noted that it means "more than the road you see with your eyes." The term Beh refers to "the road of life".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

In the Colonial times "Sacbe" was translated to calzada which is Spanish for "main road/Highway." The literal translation of Sacbe is "white road." This is used to refer to Mayan large constructed roads covered in a white (Sac) surfacing.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== Sacbeob today ==
Many sacbeob can be seen by modern visitors to Maya sites; a prominent one is at [[Chichen Itza]], running from the main group around [[El Castillo, Chichen Itza|El Castillo]] to the [[Sacred Cenote]]. Few of the longer roads still exist in their entirety. A well known sacbe connects [[Uxmal]] with [[Kabah (Maya site)|Kabah]], which is marked by [[corbel arch]]es at either end. The 62-mile-long (100&amp;nbsp;km) road connecting the ancient cities of [[Coba]] and [[Yaxuna]] was for decades the longest known to archaeologists{{Citation needed|date=December 2017}}. The remains of an even longer route have recently{{When|date=December 2012}} received the attention of archaeologists. This long sacbe apparently ran from the site of Ti'ho (modern [[Mérida, Yucatán]]), through such sites as [[Ake]] and [[Izamal]], to the [[Caribbean Sea]] near modern [[Puerto Morelos]], a total distance of some 300&amp;nbsp;km{{Citation needed|date=December 2017}}. In modern times, some of the ancient sacbeob have been used as bases or incorporated into modern highways and railway lines{{Citation needed|date=December 2017}}.

== Historical use ==
All sacbeob apparently had ritual or religious significance for pilgrimages.&lt;ref&gt;Villa 1934, 207&lt;/ref&gt; Travel writer and early [[Mayanist]] [[John Lloyd Stephens]] reported that some local [[Maya people]] in [[Yucatán (state)|Yucatán]] still said a short ritual [[prayer]] when crossing a sacbe in the early 1840s, even though they had been overgrown with jungle for centuries at the time.{{Citation needed|date=December 2017}} He is said to have been pleased to have discovered evidence of large, well-constructed sacbeob, reports of which he had previously believed to be exaggerations on the part of the Spanish [[conquistador]]es.&lt;ref name="Koch 2013, 217"&gt;Koch 2013, 217&lt;/ref&gt;

Sacbeob had a number of practical uses in addition to any religious significance they may have had. Longer sacbeob could be used for trade and communication. The Maya did not have a [[Pack animal|beast of burden]] suitable for carrying goods over long distances, so it is likely that the sacbeob would have been regularly walked by traders, though the Maya are also known to have used water routes.&lt;ref&gt;Northrup et al. 2004, 612&lt;/ref&gt; There is a wealth of evidence of mounds, often interpreted as remains of huts or way stations for travelers, along large sacbeob.&lt;ref&gt;Coe and Coe 1939, 377&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Koch 2013, 217"/&gt; Looking at the large sacbe connecting [[Kabah (Maya site)|Kabah]] to [[Uxmal]], natives told [[John Lloyd Stephens]] that ancient Mayan couriers used the sacbeob to deliver messages between large cities.&lt;ref name="Koch 2013, 217"/&gt; At [[Ake]] in the [[Yucatán (state)|Yucatán]], several sacbeob lead directly to [[cenote]]s, which serve both as important religious sites and sources of clean water.&lt;ref name="Roys and Shook 1966, 43"/&gt;

At [[Coba]], there are more than 50 sacbeob still visible today. Some researchers believe that some of the sacbeob were used to divide the population of about 55,000 people into at least four [[barrio]]s or neighborhoods.&lt;ref name="Folan 1978, 73"&gt;Folan 1978, 73&lt;/ref&gt; Many smaller sacbeob fall in places around sources of water or other high-traffic areas like ceremonial or administrative centers.&lt;ref name="Folan 1978, 73"/&gt; Two much larger sacbeob connect Coba to the smaller sites of Yaxuna, almost 100&amp;nbsp;km to the west, and Ixil, about 20&amp;nbsp;km to the southwest.&lt;ref name="Folan 1978, 73"/&gt; Since Coba is the only major Classic Period site in a 5,000 square kilometer area around it, Yaxuna and Ixil are believed to be outposts or subsidiaries of Coba, which would have been the capital of the state in which they all resided.&lt;ref&gt;Folan 1978, 73-74&lt;/ref&gt;

Some sacbeob that have been studied in the northwest Yucatan seem to have been constructed at times of conflict, rapid population growth and migration, and they have been interpreted by some as "permanent markers attesting to the relationships between dominant centers and satellite settlements," effectively a way of signifying and maintaining political boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;Kurjack and Andrews 1976, 322-324&lt;/ref&gt;

While the sacbeob in the Yucatán are the best known, they are documented elsewhere in the Maya area. A number of sacbeob have been found around [[El Mirador]] and [[Tikal]] in the northern [[Petén Basin]] and around [[Copán|Copan]] in the southern [[Guatemalan Highlands]], as well as at other sites.&lt;ref&gt;Wahl et al. 2007, 213&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sharer 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cosmic and ceremonial reference ==
Within the Maya, movement holds a ceremonial and spiritual power. In [[Maya medicine|Maya Healing]], some forms of illness are diagnosed through concepts of the movement of various forces through the body and the world. Rituals include curing the sick, [[Maya pilgrimage|pilgrimage]], procession, and dedication involve movement as a generative source of power, capable of change and influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Morton|first=Shawn G.|date=2012|title=Ritual Procession and the Creation of Civitas Among the Ancient Maya: A Case Study from Naachtun, Guatemala|jstor=23267573|journal=Canadian Journal of Archaeology|volume=36|issue=1|pages=141–165|doi=10.2307/23267573}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The present day and colonial Maya term for the [[Milky Way]] is also "sacbe." The fulfillment of one's destiny is considered the fulfillment of their "road." Seeing that movement, roads, and the cosmos are important to Mayan mythos, the conflation of Sacbe with the celestial Milky Way suggests a ceremonial importance of the Sacbe.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Coe, William R., and Michael D. Coe. "Some New Discoveries at Coba (1949)." In The Carnegie Maya III: Carnegie Institution of Washington Notes on Middle American Archaeology and Ethnology, 1940-1957, edited by Weeks John M., 377-81. University Press of Colorado, 2011. 
* Folan, William J. "Coba, Quintana Roo, Mexico: An Analysis of a Prehispanic and Contemporary Source of Sascab." American Antiquity 43, no. 1 (1978): 79-85. doi:10.2307/279634. 
* Keller, Angela H. 2009 A Road by any other Name: Trails, Paths, and Roads in Maya Language and Thought. In Landscapes of Movement: Trails, Paths, and Roads in Anthropological Perspective. J. E. Snead, C. L. Erickson, and J. A. Darling, eds. Pp.&amp;nbsp;133–157. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology. 
* Koch, P.O. 2013. ''John Lloyd Stephens and Frederick Catherwood: Pioneers of Mayan Archaeology''. McFarland, Incorporated, Publishers. 
* Kurjack, Edward B., and E. Wyllys Andrews. "Early Boundary Maintenance in Northwest Yucatan, Mexico." American Antiquity 41, no. 3 (1976): 318-25. doi:10.2307/279520.
* Northrup, Cynthia Clark, Bentley, Jerry H., and Eckes, Jr, Alfred E.. 2004. ''Encyclopedia of World Trade: From Ancient Times to the Present''. Florence: Taylor and Francis. 
* Roys, Lawrence, and Edwin M. Shook. "Preliminary Report on the Ruins of Ake, Yucatan." ''Memoirs of the Society for American Archaeology'', no. 20 (1966): Ii-54. 
* Sharer, Robert (2001). ''Encyclopedia of Prehistory''. Springer, Boston, MA. pp.&amp;nbsp;69–81. [[Digital object identifier|doi]]:10.1007/978-1-4615-0525-9_5.pdf. {{ISBN|9781468471328}}.
* Villa R., Alfonso. ''The Yaxuna-Cobá Causeway. Contributions to American Archaeolog''y 2(9) (1934) :187-208. Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution of Washington.
* Wahl, David; Schreiner, Thomas; Byrne, Roger; Hansen, Richard (2007). "A Paleoecological Record from a Late Classic Maya Reservoir in the North Petén". ''Latin American Antiquity''. '''18''' (2): 212–222. [[Digital object identifier|doi]]:10.2307/25063105.

== External links ==
* [http://www.mesoweb.com/publications/CAA/09_text.html Causeways of Yucatan]
* [http://academic.reed.edu/uxmal/contents.html Reed college web site with Kabah and Labná sacbes]

[[Category:Maya architecture]]
[[Category:Ancient roads and tracks]]</text>
      <sha1>6qkth4jt2vcqvocu2x75ov5jr3c66sb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
