<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Egypt (Roman province)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>496519</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961127539</id>
      <parentid>961037236</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-06T19:10:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add: s2cid. Removed URL that duplicated unique identifier. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | Activated by AManWithNoPlan | All pages linked from [[User:AManWithNoPlan/sandbox2]] | via #UCB_webform_linked</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="39176" xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=April 2016}}
{{Infobox Former Subdivision
|native_name  = {{native name|la|Provincia Aegypti}}&lt;br/&gt;{{lang|grc|Ἐπαρχία Αἰγύπτου}}&lt;br/&gt;{{native name|grc|Eparchía Aigýptou}}
|conventional_long_name = Roman province of Egypt
|common_name  = Egypt
|subdivision  = [[Roman province|Province]]
|nation       = the [[Roman Empire]]
|era          = [[Classical antiquity|Classic antiquity]]
|capital      = [[Alexandria]] 
|title_leader = Praefectus Augustalis
|image_map    = Roman Empire - Aegyptus (125 AD).svg
|image_map_caption = Province of Aegyptus in AD 125.
|year_start   = 30 BC
|event_start  = Conquest of [[Ptolemaic Kingdom]]
|event1       = Formation of the [[Diocese of Egypt|Diocese]]
|date_event1  = 390
|year_end     = 641
|event_end    = [[Muslim conquest of Egypt|Muslim conquest]]
|life_span = 30 BC–619 AD;&lt;br /&gt;629 AD–641 AD
|today        = [[Egypt]]
|p1           = Ptolemaic Kingdom
|flag_p1      = Ptolemaic-Empire 200bc.jpg
|s1           = Sasanian Egypt
|flag_s1      = Derafsh Kaviani flag of the late Sassanid Empire.svg
|s2           = Rashidun Caliphate
|flag_s2      = Mohammad adil-Rashidun-empire-at-its-peak-close.PNG
}}

The '''Roman province of Egypt''' ({{Lang-la|Aegyptus}}, {{IPA-la|ae̯ˈɡʏptʊs|pron}}; {{Lang-grc-koi|Αἴγυπτος|translit=Aígyptos}}, {{IPA-el|ɛ́ːɡyptos|pron}}) was established in 30 BC after Octavian (the future [[Roman emperor]] [[Augustus]]) defeated his rival [[Mark Antony]], deposed Pharaoh [[Cleopatra]], and annexed the [[Ptolemaic Kingdom]] to the [[Roman Empire]]. The [[Roman province|province]] encompassed most of modern-day [[Egypt]] except for the [[Sinai Peninsula]], which would later be conquered by [[Trajan]]. Aegyptus was bordered by the provinces of [[Crete and Cyrenaica]] to the west and [[Judea (Roman province)|Judea]] (later [[Arabia Petraea]]) to the East.

The province came to serve as a major producer of [[grain]] for the empire and had a highly developed urban economy. Aegyptus was by far the wealthiest Eastern Roman province,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rXmdAAAAQBAJ|title=Ancient Egypt: From Prehistory to the Islamic Conquest|last=Publishing|first=Britannica Educational|date=2010-04-01|publisher=Britannica Educational Publishing|isbn=9781615302109|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yDiDfipV4AIC&amp;pg=PT461|title=The Inheritance of Rome: A History of Europe from 400 to 1000|last=Wickham|first=Chris|date=2009-01-29|publisher=Penguin UK|isbn=9780141908533|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by far the wealthiest Roman province outside of [[Roman Italy|Italia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Angus Maddison|Maddison, Angus]] (2007), ''Contours of the World Economy, 1–2030 AD: Essays in Macro-Economic History'', p. 55, table 1.14, [[Oxford University Press]], {{ISBN|978-0-19-922721-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Alexandria]], its capital, it possessed the largest [[port]], and the second largest city of the Roman Empire. 

The population of Roman Egypt is unknown; estimates vary from 4 to 8 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Janzen |first1=Mark |title=Ancient Egypt Population Estimates: Slaves and Citizens |url=https://thetorah.com/ancient-egypt-population-estimates-slaves-and-citizens/ |website=TheTorah.com |accessdate=18 August 2019 |date=2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Roman rule in Egypt ==
{{Multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| header    = Maps of Roman Egypt
| width     = 350
| image1    = Roman Africa.JPG
| width1    =
| alt1      =
| caption1  = Northern Africa under Roman rule
| image2    = Roman Empire 125.png
| width2    =
| alt2      =
| caption2  = The Roman Empire during the reign of [[Hadrian]] (117 – 138). Two [[Roman legion|legions]] were deployed in the [[imperial province]] of '''Ægyptus''' (Egypt) in the year 125.
}}
As a key province, but also the 'crown domain' where the emperors succeeded the divine [[Pharaoh]]s, Egypt was ruled by a uniquely styled [[Praefectus augustalis]] ('Augustal prefect'), instead of the traditional senatorial governor of other [[Roman provinces]]. The prefect was a man of [[equestrian rank]] and was appointed by the Emperor. The first prefect of Aegyptus, [[Gaius Cornelius Gallus]], brought Upper Egypt under Roman control by force of arms, and established a [[protectorate]] over the southern frontier district, which had been abandoned by the later Ptolemies.

The second prefect, [[Aelius Gallus]], made an unsuccessful expedition to conquer [[Arabia Petraea]] and even [[Arabia Felix]]. The [[Red Sea]] coast of Aegyptus was not brought under Roman control until the reign of [[Claudius]]. The third prefect, [[Gaius Petronius]], cleared the neglected canals for irrigation, stimulating a revival of agriculture. Petronius even led a campaign into present-day central [[Sudan]] against the [[Kingdom of Kush]] at [[Meroe]], whose [[Kandake|queen]] [[Amanirenas|Imanarenat]] had previously attacked Roman Egypt. Failing to acquire permanent gains, in 22 BC he razed the city of [[Napata]] to the ground and retreated to the north.

From the reign of [[Nero]] onward, Aegyptus enjoyed an era of prosperity which lasted a century. Much trouble was caused by religious conflicts between the Greeks and the [[Jew]]s, particularly in [[Alexandria]], which after the destruction of [[Jerusalem]] in 70 became the world centre of Jewish religion and culture. Under [[Trajan]] a [[Kitos War|Jewish revolt]] occurred, resulting in the suppression of the Jews of Alexandria and the loss of all their privileges, although they soon returned. [[Hadrian]], who twice visited Aegyptus, founded [[Antinopolis|Antinoöpolis]] in memory of his drowned lover [[Antinous]]. From his reign onward buildings in the [[Greco-Roman world|Greco-Roman]] style were erected throughout the country.

Under [[Antoninus Pius]] oppressive taxation led to a revolt in 139, of the native [[Egyptians]], which was suppressed only after several years of fighting. This Bucolic War, led by one [[Isidorus]], caused great damage to the economy and marked the beginning of Egypt's economic decline. [[Avidius Cassius]], who led the Roman forces in the war, declared himself emperor in 175, and was acknowledged by the armies of [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]] and Aegyptus.

On the approach of Marcus Aurelius, Cassius was deposed and killed and the clemency of the emperor restored peace. A similar revolt broke out in 193, when [[Pescennius Niger]] was proclaimed emperor on the death of [[Pertinax]]. The Emperor [[Septimius Severus]] gave a constitution to Alexandria and the provincial capitals in 202.{{clarify|date=January 2013}}

[[Caracalla]] (211–217) granted Roman citizenship to all Egyptians, in common with the other provincials, but this was mainly to extort more taxes, which grew increasingly onerous as the needs of the emperors for more revenue grew more desperate.

There was a series of revolts, both military and civilian, through the 3rd century. Under [[Decius]], in 250, the Christians again suffered from persecution, but their religion continued to spread. The prefect of Aegyptus in 260, [[Mussius Aemilianus]], first supported the [[Macriani (disambiguation)|Macriani]], [[Gallienus usurpers|usurpers during the rule of Gallienus]], and later, in 261, became a [[Roman usurper|usurper]] himself, but was defeated by Gallienus.

[[Zenobia]], queen of [[Palmyra]], took the country away from the Romans when she conquered Aegyptus in 269, declaring herself the Queen of [[Egypt]] also. This warrior queen claimed that Egypt was an ancestral home of hers through a familial tie to [[Cleopatra VII]]. She was well educated and familiar with the culture of Egypt, its religion, and its language. She lost it later when the Roman emperor, [[Aurelian]], severed amicable relations between the two countries and retook Egypt in 274.

Two generals based in Aegyptus, [[Marcus Aurelius Probus|Probus]] and [[Domitius Domitianus]], led successful revolts and made themselves emperors. [[Diocletian]] captured Alexandria from Domitius in 298 and reorganised the whole province. His edict of 303 against the Christians began a new era of persecution. This was the last serious attempt to stem the steady growth of Christianity in Egypt, however.

== Roman government in Egypt ==
{{Further|List of governors of Roman Egypt}}

As Rome overtook the Ptolemaic system in place for areas of Egypt, they made many changes. The effect of the Roman conquest was at first to strengthen the position of the Greeks and of [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenism]] against Egyptian influences. Some of the previous offices and names of offices under the Hellenistic Ptolemaic rule were kept, some were changed, and some names would have remained but the function and administration would have changed.

The [[Roman Empire|Romans]] introduced important changes in the administrative system, aimed at achieving a high level of efficiency and maximizing [[revenue]]. The duties of the prefect of Aegyptus combined responsibility for military security through command of the [[Roman legion|legion]]s and [[Cohort (military unit)|cohorts]], for the organization of finance and taxation, and for the administration of justice.

The reforms of the early 4th century had established the basis for another 250 years of comparative prosperity in [[Egypt|Aegyptus]], at a cost of perhaps greater rigidity and more oppressive state control. Aegyptus was subdivided for administrative purposes into a number of smaller provinces, and separate civil and military officials were established; the [[praeses]] and the [[dux]]. The province was under the supervision of the count of the Orient (i.e. the vicar) of the diocese headquartered in Antioch in Syria.

Emperor Justinian abolished the diocese of Egypt in 538 and re-combined civil and military power in the hands of the [[dux]] with a civil deputy (the praeses) as a counterweight to the power of the church authorities. All pretense of local [[autonomy]] had by then vanished. The presence of the soldiery was more noticeable, its power and influence more pervasive in the routine of town and village life.

== Economy ==
[[File:Periplous of the Erythraean Sea.svg|thumb|450px|[[Indo-Roman trade and relations|Roman trade with India]] started from Aegyptus according to the [[Periplus of the Erythraean Sea]] (1st century).]]
The economic resources that this imperial government existed to exploit had not changed since the [[Ptolemaic period]], but the development of a much more complex and sophisticated [[tax|taxation system]] was a hallmark of Roman rule. Taxes in both cash and kind were assessed on land, and a bewildering variety of small taxes in cash, as well as customs dues and the like, was collected by appointed officials.

A massive amount of Aegyptus's grain was shipped downriver (north) both to feed the population of [[Alexandria]] and for export to the Roman capital. There were frequent complaints of oppression and extortion from the taxpayers.

The Roman government had actively encouraged the [[privatization]] of land and the increase of private enterprise in manufacture, commerce, and trade, and low tax rates favored private owners and entrepreneurs. The poorer people gained their livelihood as tenants of state-owned land or of property belonging to the emperor or to wealthy private landlords, and they were relatively much more heavily burdened by rentals, which tended to remain at a fairly high level.

Overall, the degree of monetization and complexity in the economy, even at the [[village]] level, was intense. Goods were moved around and exchanged through the medium of coin on a large scale and, in the towns and the larger villages, a high level of industrial and commercial activity developed in close conjunction with the exploitation of the predominant agricultural base. The volume of trade, both internal and external, reached its peak in the 1st and 2nd centuries.

By the end of the 3rd century, major problems were evident. A series of debasements of the imperial currency had undermined confidence in the coinage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Erik |last=Christiansen |title=Coinage in Roman Egypt: The Hoard Evidence |location= |publisher=Aarhus University Press |year=2004 |url={{Google books |plainurl=yes |id=VkVmAAAAMAAJ }} }}&lt;/ref&gt; and even the government itself was contributing to this by demanding more and more irregular tax payments in kind, which it channeled directly to the main consumers, the army personnel. Local administration by the [[Committee|councils]] was careless, recalcitrant, and inefficient; the evident need for firm and purposeful reform had to be squarely faced in the reigns of [[Diocletian]] and [[Constantine I]].

== Military ==
This wealthiest of provinces could be held militarily by a very small force; and the threat implicit in an embargo on the export of grain supplies, vital to the provisioning of the city of Rome and its populace, was obvious. Internal security was guaranteed by the presence of three Roman legions (later reduced to two, then one [[Legio II Traiana]]) stationed at the grand capital Alexandria. Each of these numbered around 5000 strong, and several units of auxiliaries.

In the first decade of Roman rule the spirit of Augustan imperialism looked farther afield, attempting expansion to the east and to the south. Most of the early Roman troops stationed there were Greco-Macedonians and native Egyptians once part of the dissolved Ptolemaic army finding service for Rome. Eventually Romans or Romanized people were a majority.

== Social structure in early Roman Egypt ==
{{See also|Fayum mummy portraits}}
[[File:Egyptian - Mummy Portrait of a Man - Walters 323.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Citizen of Roman Egypt ([[Fayum mummy portrait]])]]
[[File:Bust of Roman Nobleman, ca. 30 B.C.E.– 50 C.E., 54.51.jpg|thumbnail|Bust of Roman Nobleman, c. 30 BC–50 AD, [[Brooklyn Museum]]]]
[[File:Egipto Hadrianeum.JPG|right|thumb|Possible depiction of the province of Egypt from the Hadrianeum in Rome]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Octavian Karnak.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A depiction of [[Augustus]] wearing the [[nemes]] like Egyptian pharaohs.]] --&gt;

The social structure in Aegyptus under the Romans was both unique and complicated. On the one hand, the Romans continued to use many of the same organizational tactics that were in place under the leaders of the Ptolemaic period. At the same time, the Romans saw the Greeks in Aegyptus as “Egyptians”, an idea that both the native Egyptians and Greeks would have rejected.&lt;ref name="Oxyrhynchus and Rome, p.3"&gt;{{cite journal |first=E. G. |last=Turner |title=Oxyrhynchus and Rome |journal=[[Harvard Studies in Classical Philology]] |volume=79 |issue= |year=1975 |pages=1–24 [p. 3] |jstor=311126 |doi=10.2307/311126 }}&lt;/ref&gt; To further compound the whole situation, Jews, who themselves were very Hellenized overall, had their own communities, separate from both Greeks and native Egyptians.&lt;ref name="Oxyrhynchus and Rome, p.3" /&gt;

The Romans began a system of social hierarchy that revolved around ethnicity and place of residence.  Other than Roman citizens, a Greek citizen of one of the Greek cities had the highest status, and a rural Egyptian would be in the lowest class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Richard |last=Alston |s2cid=163149248 |title=Philo's In Flaccum: Ethnicity and Social Space in Roman Alexandria |journal=Greece and Rome |series=Second Series |volume=44 |issue=2 |year=1997 |pages=165–175 [p. 166] |doi=10.1093/gr/44.2.165 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In between those classes was the metropolite, who was almost certainly of Hellenic origin. Gaining citizenship and moving up in ranks was very difficult and there were not many available options for ascendancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Naphtali |last=Lewis |chapter=Greco-Roman Egypt: Fact or Fiction? |title=On Government and Law in Roman Egypt |location=Atlanta |publisher=Scholars Press |year=1995 |page=145 |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the routes that many followed to ascend to another caste was through enlistment in the army. Although only Roman citizens could serve in the legions, many Greeks found their way in. The native Egyptians could join the auxiliary forces and attain citizenship upon discharge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Idris H. |last=Bell |title=Hellenic Culture in Egypt |journal=[[Journal of Egyptian Archaeology]] |volume=8 |issue=3/4 |year=1922 |pages=139–155 [p. 148] |jstor=3853691 |doi=10.2307/3853691 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The different groups had different rates of taxation based on their social class. The Greeks were exempt from the [[Tax per head|poll tax]], while Hellenized inhabitants of the nome capitals were taxed at a lower rate than the native Egyptians, who could not enter the army, and paid the full poll tax.&lt;ref&gt;Bell, p.148&lt;/ref&gt;

The social structure in Aegyptus is very closely linked to the governing administration. Elements of centralized rule that were derived from the Ptolemaic period lasted into the 4th century.  One element in particular was the appointment of [[strategoi]] to govern the ‘[[Nome (Egypt)|nome]]s’, the traditional administrative divisions of Egypt.  [[Boulai]], or town councils, in Egypt were only formally constituted by [[Septimius Severus]].  It was only under [[Diocletian]] later in the 3rd century that these boulai and their officers acquired important administrative responsibilities for their nomes. The Augustan takeover introduced a system of compulsory public service, which was based on ''poros'' (property or income qualification), which was wholly based on social status and power. The Romans also introduced the poll tax which was similar to tax rates that the Ptolemies levied, but the Romans gave special low rates to citizens of metropolises.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, p.141&lt;/ref&gt; The city of [[Oxyrhynchus]] had many papyri remains that contain much information on the subject of social structure in these cities.  This city, along with Alexandria, shows the diverse set-up of various institutions that the Romans continued to use after their takeover of Egypt.

Just as under the Ptolemies, Alexandria and its citizens had their own special designations. The capital city enjoyed a higher status and more privileges than the rest of Egypt. Just as it was under the Ptolemies, the primary way of becoming a citizen of Roman Alexandria was through showing when registering for a [[deme]] that both parents were Alexandrian citizens. Alexandrians were the only Egyptians that could obtain Roman citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=A. N. |last=Sherwin-White |title=The Roman Citizenship |url=https://archive.org/details/romancitizenship0000sher |url-access=registration |location=Oxford |publisher=Clarendon Press |year=1973 |page=[https://archive.org/details/romancitizenship0000sher/page/391 391] |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

If a common Egyptian wanted to become a Roman citizen he would first have to become an Alexandrian citizen. The Augustan period in Egypt saw the creation of urban communities with “[[Ancient Greece|Hellenic]]” landowning elites. These landowning elites were put in a position of privilege and power and had more self-administration than the Egyptian population. Within the citizenry, there were gymnasiums that Greek citizens could enter if they showed that both parents were members of the gymnasium based on a list that was compiled by the government in 4–5 AD.&lt;ref name="Roman Oxyrhynchus, p. 84"&gt;{{cite journal |first=E. G. |last=Turner |title=Roman Oxyrhynchus |journal=[[Journal of Egyptian Archaeology]] |volume=38 |issue= |pages=78–93 [p. 84] |jstor=3855498 |year=1952 |doi=10.1177/030751335203800110 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The candidate for the gymnasium would then be let into the [[ephebus]]. There was also the council of elders known as the [[gerousia]]. This council of elders did not have a boulai to answer to. All of this Greek organization was a vital part of the metropolis and the Greek institutions provided an elite group of citizens. The Romans looked to these elites to provide municipal officers and well-educated administrators.&lt;ref name="Roman Oxyrhynchus, p. 84" /&gt; These elites also paid lower poll-taxes than the local native Egyptians, [[fellahin]]. It is well documented that Alexandrians in particular were able to enjoy lower tax-rates on land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Diana |last=Delia |title=Alexandrian Citizenship During the Roman Principate |location=Atlanta |publisher=Scholars Press |year=1991 |page=31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

These privileges even extended to corporal punishments. Romans were protected from this type of punishment while native Egyptians were whipped. Alexandrians, on the other hand, had the privilege of merely being beaten with a rod.&lt;ref&gt;Delia, pp.31–32&lt;/ref&gt; Although Alexandria enjoyed the greatest status of the Greek cities in Egypt, it is clear that the other Greek cities, such as Antinoopolis, enjoyed privileges very similar to the ones seen in Alexandria.&lt;ref&gt;Delia, p.32&lt;/ref&gt;  All of these changes amounted to the Greeks being treated as an ally in Egypt and the native Egyptians were treated as a conquered race.

The Gnomon of the Idios Logos shows the connection between law and status. It lays out the revenues it deals with, mainly fines and confiscation of property, to which only a few groups were apt. The Gnomon also confirms that a freed slave takes his former master's social status. The Gnomon demonstrates the social controls that the Romans had in place through monetary means based on status and property.

== Christian Egypt (33 AD–4th century) ==
{{anchor|Christian Egypt}}
{{History of Egypt}}

The [[patriarch of Alexandria|Patriarchate of Alexandria]] is traditionally held to be founded by [[Mark the Evangelist]] around 42. Evidence for a bishopric before the third century is however slight given the importance of the city's presbyters. Bishops often named their successors (e.g. Peter, his brother, by Athanasius in 373) or the succession was effected by imposing the hands of a deceased bishop on the one chosen to follow him. 

By 200 it is clear that Alexandria was one of the great Christian centres. The Christian [[apologist]]s [[Clement of Alexandria]] and [[Origen]] both lived part or all of their lives in that city, where they wrote, taught, and debated.

With the [[Edict of Milan]] in 313, [[Constantine I (emperor)|Constantine I]] ended the persecution of Christians. Over the course of the 5th century, paganism was suppressed and lost its following, as the poet [[Palladas]] bitterly noted. It lingered underground for many decades: the final edict against paganism was issued in 435, but graffiti at [[Philae]] in Upper Egypt proves worship of [[Isis]] persisted at its temples into the 6th century. Many Egyptian Jews also became Christians, but many others refused to do so, leaving them as the only sizable religious minority in a Christian country.

No sooner had the Egyptian Church achieved freedom and supremacy than it became subject to a [[Schism (religion)|schism]] and prolonged conflict which at times descended into civil war. Alexandria became the centre of the first great split in the Christian world, between the [[Arianism|Arians]], named for the Alexandrian priest [[Arius]], and their opponents, represented by [[Athanasius]], who became Archbishop of Alexandria in 326 after the [[First Council of Nicaea]] rejected Arius's views. The Arian controversy caused years of riots and rebellions throughout most of the 4th century. In the course of one of these, the great [[Serapeum#Destruction of the Alexandrian Serapeum|temple of Serapis]], the stronghold of paganism, was destroyed. Athanasius was alternately expelled from Alexandria and reinstated as its Archbishop between five and seven times.

Patristic authorship was dominated by Egyptian contributions: Athanasius, Didymus the Blind and Cyril, and the power of the Alexandrian see embodied in Athanasius, Theophilus,  his nephew, Cyril and shortly by Dioscuros.

Egypt had an ancient tradition of religious speculation, enabling a variety of controversial religious views to thrive there. Not only did Arianism flourish, but other doctrines, such as [[Gnosticism]] and [[Manichaeism]], either native or imported, found many followers. Another religious development in Egypt was the [[monasticism]] of the [[Desert Fathers]], who renounced the material world in order to live a life of poverty in devotion to the Church.

Egyptian Christians took up monasticism with such enthusiasm that the Emperor [[Valens]] had to restrict the number of men who could become monks. Egypt exported monasticism to the rest of the Christian world. Another development of this period was the development of [[Coptic language|Coptic]], a form of the Ancient Egyptian language written with the Greek alphabet supplemented by several signs to represent sounds present in Egyptian which were not present in Greek. It was invented to ensure the correct pronunciation of magical words and names in pagan texts, the so-called [[Greek Magical Papyri]]. Coptic was soon adopted by early Christians to spread the word of the gospel to native Egyptians and it became the liturgical language of Egyptian Christianity and remains so to this day.

Christianity was quickly accepted by the people who were oppressed in first-century Roman Egypt. Christianity eventually spread out west to the Berbers. The Coptic Church was established in Egypt. Since Christianity blended with local traditions it never truly united the people against Arabian forces in the seventh and eight centuries. Later on in the seventh and eighth centuries, Christianity spread out to Nubia. &lt;ref&gt;History of Africa written by Kevin Shillington&lt;/ref&gt;

== Later Roman Egypt (4th–6th centuries) ==
[[File:NE 565ad.jpg|thumb|450px|A map of the Near East in 565, showing Byzantine Egypt and its neighbors.]]
{{further|Diocese of Egypt}}

The reign of Constantine also saw the founding of [[Constantinople]] as a new capital for the Roman Empire, and in the course of the 4th century the Empire was divided in two, with Egypt finding itself in the Eastern Empire with its capital at Constantinople. Latin, never well established in Egypt, would play a declining role with Greek continuing to be the dominant language of government and scholarship. During the 5th and 6th centuries the [[Eastern Roman Empire]], known historiographically as the [[Byzantine Empire]], gradually transformed itself into a thoroughly Christian state whose culture differed significantly from its pagan past.

The [[Fall of Rome|fall of the Western Empire]] in the 5th century further isolated the Egyptian Romans from Rome's culture and hastened the growth of Christianity. The triumph of Christianity led to a virtual abandonment of pharaonic traditions: with the disappearance of the Egyptian priests and priestesses who officiated at the temples, no-one could read the [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|hieroglyphs]] of Pharaonic Egypt, and its temples were converted to churches or abandoned to the desert.

The Eastern Empire became increasingly "oriental" in style as its links with the old Græco-Roman world faded. The Greek system of local government by citizens had now entirely disappeared. Offices, with new Byzantine names, were almost hereditary in the wealthy land-owning families. Alexandria, the second city of the empire, continued to be a centre of religious controversy and violence.

[[Cyril of Alexandria|Cyril]], the [[patriarch of Alexandria]], convinced the city's governor to expel the Jews from the city in 415 with the aid of the mob, in response to the Jews' alleged night-time massacre of many Christians. {{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} The murder of the philosopher [[Hypatia]] in March 415 marked a dramatic turn in classical Hellenic culture in Egypt but philosophy thrived in sixth century Alexandria.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} Another schism in the Church produced prolonged disturbances  and may have alienated Egypt from the Empire. The countless [[papyrus]] finds mark the continuance of Greek culture and institutions at various levels.

The new religious controversy was over the [[Christ]]'s human and divine nature. The issue was whether He had two natures, human and divine, or a combined one ([[hypostatic union]] from His humanity and divinity).  In an intensely religious age it was enough to divide an empire. The [[Miaphysite]] controversy arose after the [[First Council of Constantinople]] in 381 and continued until well after the [[Council of Chalcedon]] in 451, which ruled in favour of the position that Christ was "one person in two natures" as opposed to Monophysitism (a single nature).

Monophysite belief was not held by the 'miaphysites' as they stated that Jesus was out of two natures in one nature called, the "Incarnate Logos of God". Many of the 'miaphysites' claimed that they were misunderstood, that there was really no difference between their position and the Chalcedonian position, and that the Council of Chalcedon ruled against them because of political motivations alone. The Church of Alexandria split from the Churches of Rome and Constantinople over this issue, creating what would become the Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria, which remains a major force in Egyptian religious life today.&lt;ref name="georgetown1"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/resources/countries/egypt |title=Egypt |publisher=[[Berkley Center for Religion, Peace, and World Affairs]] |accessdate=2011-12-14 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111220145046/http://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/resources/countries/egypt |archive-date=2011-12-20 |url-status=dead }} See drop-down essay on "Islamic Conquest and the Ottoman Empire"&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt and Syria remained hotbeds of Miaphysite sentiment, and organised resistance to the Chalcedonian view was not suppressed until the 570s.

Egypt nevertheless continued to be an important economic center for the Empire supplying much of its agriculture and manufacturing needs as well as continuing to be an important center of scholarship. It would supply the needs of the Byzantine Empire and the Mediterranean as a whole. The reign of [[Justinian I|Justinian]] (527&amp;ndash;565) saw the Empire recapture [[Rome]] and much of [[Italy]] from the barbarians, but these successes left the empire's eastern flank exposed. The Empire's "bread basket" now lacked protection.

== Episcopal sees ==
Ancient episcopal sees of the Roman province of '''Aegyptus Primus (I)''' listed in the ''[[Annuario Pontificio]]'' as [[titular see]]s, &lt;ref name=AP&gt;''Annuario Pontificio 2013'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana 2013 {{ISBN|978-88-209-9070-1}}), "Sedi titolari", pp. 819-1013&lt;/ref&gt; suffragans of the Patriarchate of Alexandria : The list here however does not cover other provinces such as Augustamnica, Arcadia and Thebais.
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Agnus (Egypt)|Agnus]]
* [[Andropolis, Egypt|Andropolis]] (Kherbeta)
* [[Butus]] (near Desuq? Com-Casir?)
* [[Cleopatris]] (Sersina)
* [[Coprithis]] (Cabrit, Cobrit)
* [[Damanhur|Hermopolis Parva]]
* [[Letopolis]]
* [[Phatanus]] (El-Batanu, El-Batnu)
* [[Mariotes]] (Lake Mariout)
* [[Menelaite]] (Idku)
* [[Metelis]] (Kom el-Ghoraf)
* [[Naucratis]]
* [[Nicius]] (Ibshadi)
* [[Onuphis]] (Menouf)
* [[Petra in Aegypto]] (Hagar-En-Nauatiyeh)
* [[Sais, Egypt|Sais]]
* [[Taua]] (Thaouah? near Ebiar?)
* [[Terenuthis]]
* [[Thois]] (Tideh)
}}

Ancient episcopal sees of the Roman province of '''Aegyptus Secundus (II)''' listed in the ''[[Annuario Pontificio]]'' as [[titular see]]s :&lt;ref name=AP/&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Busiris (Lower Egypt)|Busiris]] (Abu-Sir)
* [[Cabasa]] (Chahbas-Esch-Choada)
* [[Cynopolis in Aegypto]] (Banâm Benâ)
* *[[:de:Tell el-Balamun|Diospolis Inferior]] (*Tell el-Balamun)
* [[Pachnemunis]] (Kom el-Khanziri)
* [[Phragonis]] (Tell-El-Faraïn, Côm-Faraïn)
* [[Schedia]]
* [[Sebennytus]] (Sebennytos)
* [[Xois]]
}}

== Sassanian Persian invasion (619 AD) ==
[[File:626Byzantium.JPG|thumb|450px|The [[Byzantine Empire]] in 629 after [[Heraclius]] had reconquered Syria, Palestine and Egypt from the [[Sassanid Empire]].]]
{{Main|Roman–Persian Wars|Sasanian Egypt}}
The [[Sasanian conquest of Egypt|Persian conquest of Egypt]], beginning in AD 619 or 618, was one of the last [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] triumphs in the Roman-Persian Wars against [[Byzantium]]. From 619 - 628, [[Sasanian Egypt|they incorporated Egypt once again within their territories]], the previous (much longer) time being under the [[Twenty-seventh Dynasty of Egypt|Achaemenids]]. [[Khosrow II]] Parvêz had begun [[Byzantine–Sasanian War of 602–628|this war]] in retaliation for the assassination of Emperor [[Maurice (emperor)|Maurice]] (582–602) and had achieved a series of early successes, culminating in the conquests of [[Siege of Jerusalem (614)|Jerusalem]] (614) and [[Siege of Alexandria (619)|Alexandria]] (619).

A Byzantine counteroffensive launched by Emperor [[Heraclius]] in the spring of 622 shifted the advantage, and the war was brought to an end by the fall of Khosrow on 25 February 628.&lt;ref&gt;Frye, pp.&amp;nbsp;167–70{{full|date=July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Egyptians had no love of the emperor in Constantinople and put up little resistance. Khosrow's son and successor, [[Kavadh II]] Šêrôe (Šêrôy), who reigned until September, concluded a peace treaty returning territories conquered by the Sassanids to the [[Eastern Roman Empire]].

The Persian conquest allowed [[Miaphysitism]] to resurface in the open in Egypt, and when imperial rule was restored by Emperor Heraclius in 629, the Miaphysites were persecuted and their patriarch expelled. Egypt was thus in a state of both religious and political alienation from the Empire when a new invader appeared.

== Arab Islamic conquest (639–646 AD) ==
[[File:Byzantiumby650AD.svg|thumb|450px|The Mediterranean world in 650, after the Arabs had conquered Egypt and Syria from the Byzantines.]]
{{Main|Muslim conquest of Egypt}}

An army of 4,000 [[Arabs]] led by [[Amr Ibn Al-Aas]] was sent by the [[Caliph]] [[Umar]], successor to [[Muhammad]], to spread Islamic rule to the west. Arabs crossed into Egypt from Palestine in December 639, and advanced rapidly into the [[Nile Delta]]. The Imperial garrisons retreated into the walled towns, where they successfully held out for a year or more.

The Arabs sent for reinforcements, and in April 641 they [[Siege of Alexandria (641)|besieged and captured Alexandria]]. The Byzantines assembled a fleet with the aim of recapturing Egypt, and won back [[Alexandria]] in 645. The Muslims retook the city in 646, completing the [[Muslim conquest of Egypt]]. 40,000 civilians were evacuated to Constantinople with the imperial fleet. Thus ended 975 years of [[Greco-Roman]] rule over Egypt.

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Mummy Mask of a Man, early 1st century C.E.,72.57.jpg|Mummy Mask of a Man, early 1st century AD, 72.57, [[Brooklyn Museum]]
File:FuneraryMasksRomanEgypt.jpg|[[Death mask|Funerary masks]] uncovered in [[Faiyum]], 1st century.
File:As-Hadrian-Aegyptus-RIC 0839,As.jpg|[[Hadrian]] coin celebrating Ægyptus Province, struck c. 135. In the obverse, Egypt is personified as a reclining woman holding the [[sistrum]] of [[Hathor]]. Her left elbow rests on a basket of grain, while an [[ibis]] stands on the column at her feet.
File:Denarius-Zenobia-s3290.jpg|[[Zenobia]] coin reporting her title as queen of Egypt (''[[Augusta (honorific)|Augusta]]''), and showing her diademed and draped bust on a crescent. The obverse shows a standing figure of Ivno Regina ([[Juno (mythology)|Juno]]) holding a [[patera]] in her right hand and a sceptre in her left hand, with a peacock at her feet and a brilliant star on the left.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Greek and Roman Egypt]]
* [[Roman pharaoh]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Angold, Michael. 2001. ''Byzantium : the bridge from antiquity to the Middle Ages''. 1st US Edition. New York : St. Martin's Press
* Bowman, Alan Keir. 1996. ''Egypt After the Pharaohs: 332 BC–AD 642; From Alexander to the Arab Conquest''. 2nd ed. Berkeley: University of California Press
* Bowman, Alan K. and Dominic Rathbone. “Cities and Administration in Roman Egypt.” ''The Journal of Roman Studies'' 82 (1992): 107–127. Database on-line. JSTOR, GALILEO; accessed October 27, 2008
* Chauveau, Michel. 2000. ''Egypt in the Age of Cleopatra: History and Society under the Ptolemies''. Translated by David Lorton. Ithaca: Cornell University Press
* El-Abbadi, M.A.H. “The Gerousia in Roman Egypt.” ''The Journal of Egyptian Archaeology'' 50 (December 1964): 164–169. Database on-line. JSTOR, GALILEO; accessed October 27, 2008.
* Ellis, Simon P. 1992. ''Graeco-Roman Egypt''. Shire Egyptology 17, ser. ed. Barbara G. Adams. Aylesbury: Shire Publications Ltd.
* Hill, John E. 2003. "Annotated Translation of the Chapter on the Western Regions according to the ''Hou Hanshu''." 2nd Draft Edition. [http://depts.washington.edu/uwch/silkroad/texts/hhshu/hou_han_shu.html]
* Hill, John E. 2004. ''The Peoples of the West from the Weilue'' 魏略 ''by Yu Huan'' 魚豢'': A Third Century Chinese Account Composed between 239 and 265 CE'' Draft annotated English translation. [http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/weilue/weilue.html]
* Hölbl, Günther. 2001. ''A History of the Ptolemaic Empire''. Translated by Tina Saavedra. London: Routledge Ltd.
* Lloyd, Alan Brian. 2000. "The Ptolemaic Period (332–30 BC)". In ''The Oxford History of Ancient Egypt'', edited by Ian Shaw. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press. 395–421
* Peacock, David. 2000. "The Roman Period (30 BC–AD 311)". In ''The Oxford History of Ancient Egypt'', edited by Ian Shaw. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press. 422–445
* Riggs, Christina, ed. (2012). ''The Oxford Handbook of Roman Egypt''. Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-19-957145-1}}.
*[[Jane Rowlandson|Rowlandson, Jane]]. 1996. ''Landowners and Tenants in Roman Egypt: The social relations of agriculture in the Oxyrhynchite nome''. Oxford University Press
*[[Jane Rowlandson|Rowlandson, Jane]]. 1998. (ed) ''Women and Society in Greek and Roman Egypt: A Sourcebook.'' Cambridge University Press.

== External links ==
{{commons category|Roman Egypt|&lt;br/&gt;Roman Egypt|position=left}}
* [http://www.annourbis.com/maps/map000.html Detailed Map of Aegyptus]

{{Ancient Egypt topics}}
{{Roman provinces AD 117}}
{{Late Roman Provinces}}
{{Egypt topics}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Roman Egypt}}
[[Category:Roman Egypt| ]]
[[Category:New Testament places]]
[[Category:Provinces of the Roman Empire|Egypt]]
[[Category:Provinces of the Byzantine Empire|Egypt]]
[[Category:Late Roman provinces]]
[[Category:States and territories established in the 1st century BC]]
[[Category:30 BC]]
[[Category:1st-century BC establishments in Roman Egypt|*]]
[[Category:1st-century BC establishments in Egypt]]
[[Category:States and territories disestablished in the 7th century]]
[[Category:640s disestablishments in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:641 disestablishments]]
[[Category:7th-century disestablishments in Egypt]]</text>
      <sha1>fjfu3ulyobdlycldoo483drtromsq9x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
