<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Maya dance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>336974</id>
    <revision>
      <id>956919943</id>
      <parentid>956919908</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-16T01:29:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Red Phoenix</username>
        <id>5170388</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/76.169.72.47|76.169.72.47]] ([[User talk:76.169.72.47|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13237" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Ceremonial dance in pre-Columbian Maya civilization}}
{{multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=March 2016}}
{{Cleanup|date=September 2009}}
}}

{{Maya civilization}}
In [[Pre-Columbian era|pre-Columbian]] [[Maya civilization]], ceremonial dance had great importance. However, since dance is a transient [[art]], it is inherently difficult for [[Archaeology|archeologist]]s to find and evaluate evidence of its role. There is little material information left behind, beyond a few paintings on murals and vases. This lack of direct evidence leads to several different archaeological interpretations.

[[Dance]] was a central component of social, religious, and political endeavors for the ancient [[Maya peoples|Maya]]. The entire community danced, including [[ajaw|kings]], [[Nobility|nobles]], and common people. Dance served many functions such as creating [[Hierotopy|sacred space]], closing the gap between here and the otherworld, and releasing the dead from the grasp of the Xibalbans (see [[Xibalba]]).

==Overview==
Dance from pre-Columbian Maya culture still exists in various altered forms today. However, dancing in the ancient world carried a much deeper significance in their sophisticated culture. Records of these dances have come to light through various [[mural]]s, codices, and especially the [[Spanish people|Spaniards]] who first recorded their observations. 
	
[[Spirit]]s of the super-natural world and their relationship with [[Maya civilization|Maya culture]] played an important role in [[ritual]] dance. Just as well, [[Megafauna|beasts]] were usually [[Mimicry|mimicked]] in ceremonial dance. The attire worn to some dances as depicted in murals show the links Maya dancers make to the natural world and to their worshipped gods who often took the form of animals. This is evident especially in the frescoes of [[Bonampak]].
	
The elements as well were worshipped through Maya dance. In the [[Tzʼutujil people|Tzutujil]] Maya culture, it was believed that a spirit controlled the power of [[volcano]]es. When the [[mountain]] began to grumble and shake, the Tzutujil [[priest]]s would pick young women and [[girl]]s who would partake in a large dance ceremony before being sacrificed into the burning mountain. Maya dance rituals often included [[sacrifice]]. For instance, the Tun-teleche¬ dance included victims whose [[heart]]s were removed before they died as a gift to [[underworld]] [[demon]]s. On the other hand, some public ritual dances were even [[Eroticism|erotic]] in nature. Common throughout most all dances though was the importance of [[Maya death gods|deities]] and the relationship between man and god.  
	
Dancing includes many different aspects of other rituals into the moves and actions they do during them. [[Bloodletting|Blood-letting]] was used to help demonstrate the bravery of the warriors. They would also put their captives in their dances; the captives would be killed in a public ritual normally after the bloodletting. Ball games were also involved in dances. Some ball players would be in similar positions as dancers' sometimes confusing people analyzing them . Instruments were also including in depictions of ball games further supporting the connection of dancing, ball games, and warfare are connected in the life style as they all share very similar depictions of what they are.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  
	
In the [[Creation myth|book of creation]], ''[[Popol Vuh]]'', it is recounted that the dances of the Twin Brothers were part of a miracle ceremony. Just as well, the dances of '[[Armadillo|The Armadillo]]', '[[Nightjar|the Poorwill]]', and '[[Weasel|the Weasel]]' pleased the lords of [[death]] immensely.
	
Dance in Maya culture has also acted as a bridge between the ancient and post-Columbian eras. [[Spanish conquest of Yucatán|Spanish missionaries and lords]] as late as the 18th century were trying to eliminate the practice of ancient dance; however, natives maintained roots with their [[ancestor]]s by practicing in secret. Even after the relatively complete conversion to [[Catholicism]] after the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] influence arrived, Maya people still respect their ancient deities through ceremonial dance, which has persisted through the generations since the golden age of ancient Maya.

==Research==
In 1966, [[Michael D. Coe]] and [[Elizabeth P. Benson]] described a dancing scene showing several important [[lord]]s standing with one heel raised.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In 1992, [[Nikolai Grube]] deciphered the [[glyph]] for “dance” (read as ''akʼot'') in [[Maya script]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Some interesting depictions of Maya dance of the Classic era are found on [[Maya ceramics]] and in the famous murals of [[Bonampak]].

The word was in a picture that depicts [[Bird Jaguar IV]], a [[Yaxchilan]] ruler, in a pose that would be described as dancing holding a writhing snake. The words around the man read chan chan or “celestial snake”. Many of the texts or stelae would be installed on places that the performance the picture had captured would be ideally done at like platforms, plazas or stairways.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Looper, George, Matthew. (2009) ''To Be Like Gods, Dancing in Ancient Maya Civilization''. University of Texas Press,&lt;/ref&gt;

Dancing on designs has been hard to find at first. It has been discovered that pictures of people dancing have been found to be standing still in the pictures or with a leg raised and just barely touching the ground. The physical location of where the image is gives hints to its reason. Symbols around and in the image also give helpful hints to the decoding of the image. Some depictions of dances come in a story like format around temples, like the 40 days after Bird Jaguar IV's accession which spans many panels and includes a few different temples.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Technique==
Ancient Maya dance is often characterized by transformations of human beings into supernatural (god like) beings by means of visionary [[altered state of consciousness|trance]].  Some think that [[Hallucinogen|hallucinogenic drugs]] or  medicines were used to put the performer into an altered state of [[mind]]. Once in this state of mind the participants were transformed into their ''[[wayob]]'' or soul companions. These [[soul]] companions were depicted through the [[mask]]s and the costumes people wore in the dance. Some scenes are painted on [[pottery]] such as that from the myriad ritual meals of Classic festivals. These vessels depict humans, both kings and nobles, dressed in costumes.  Their human faces are shown in cutaway view inside the costumes of the fantastic creatures they have become through the transformation of the dance. Some of these ''wayob'' are recognizable as animals like [[jaguar]]s and [[Bird of prey|birds of prey]], but others just look like strange [[monster]]s.

For the Maya, dance was a very public affair. It induced visionary trances where either individuals or groups went into an altered state of mind that allowed them to communicate with the other world. Those who were strong enough to travel there, told stories about how the land had things like [[river]]s and [[tree]]s in this [[earth|world]]. Some of the great lords depicted themselves dancing out over the [[abyss (religion)|abyss]] that leads into the otherworld.

The distinction between the humans and [[supernatural]] beings was never sharply made. Through dance, [[people]] became [[god]]s and gods became people even if it were only for a moment. It is important to note that these were more than just acts of civic [[pride]] or [[piety]]. They were considered to be direct connections to the otherworld.

With the written form of dance poses play a big part on how they describe and depict the dance. The gesture of holding the double headed serpent would be described as a gesture of concentration, calm and tranquility. The pose to dancing was discovered to be a lifted heel while still touching the ground. This was discovered in 1911 but wasn't brought to questions till 1981 by Virginia Miller who defined the pose. This pose was started in the Early Classic period on a small scale while in the eight century started to appear in large scale depiction. This pictures show one heel raised, very rarely is both raised, and the arms in a dynamic pose with the body gazing outwards.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== Writing of dance ==
The “stepping” pose is also closely connected to dance. This pose is a profile of the person with their right foot on the ground while the left is bent with the ball if the foot on the ground. This pose uses lots of context to discover the meaning. This pose could also be used for walking but the presence of instruments and dance costumes separate the two from each other.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The legs aren't the only part of the body that mattered when it comes to dance poses. The arm and elbow were used while the hand and fingers are not always shown  while almost all people are shown with arms. One dance position of the arms is the arms out towards the way the person is facing or next to the face while another one is a hand by the head with the other on the hip. The arms would be used of the artist didn't want to raise the heel of the person while still giving the [[symbol]] of dance. The use of just arms as a form of dance is used to show the dancing of someone who isn't normally a dancer, like a baby or a [[Gods|god]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

With all things there are situations that break the pattern. If the poses for dance are used without certain contexts the meanings of these poses changes. A lifted heel without [[Musical instrument|instruments]] or dance costumes could be used to describe [[Alcohol intoxication|drunkenness]]. Warriors and battles also use this pose as a sign to capture enemies as well as to signal a [[spear]] being thrown.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Meanings within dances==
The Snake Dance was also celebrated by the lords of [[Palenque]]. This time the dance was done with a male who has an ax in one hand and a serpent in the other, and a woman who is grasping the lower body of the snake.  These dancers wore costumes of [[First father]] and [[First Mother]], the deities whose actions enabled the final [[Creation myth|creation]] and the birth of all the [[gods]]. This depiction is thought to point toward the role of dance in the story of Creation.

The most important instrument of mayan music is the rain stick.

The story of the [[Popol Vuh]] exhibits examples of this idea.  After the [[Hero Twins]] are killed they come back to life as vagabonds and quickly enchant the people of [[Xibalba]] with their dancing and magic.  The Twins danced such dances as the Dance of the [[Poorwill]], the [[Weasel]] and the [[Armadillo]] and they are able to bring things back to life.  All of this fame caught the attention of the [[Lords of Death]] who command the Twins to perform.  As the twins perform, the Lords are amazed by their powers and finally ask the Twins to sacrifice them.  The Twins do, but this time they do not bring them back to life, limiting the Xibalbans power over humans forever.

Dancers are very specific on where they do their rituals. Certain dances are more private while other are public events that fill stadiums. One [[Spaniards|Spanish]] [[Exploration|explorer]] describes a performance he watched as eight hundred heavy warriors danced in a giant stadium. Not one of the warriors were off beat as they danced all day with food and drink brought to them as they danced. Diego Garcia de Palacio compared a courtyard enclosed by stairways in [[Copán|Copan]] to the [[Colosseum]] in Rome. Dances were mostly public rituals showing community by people being different social classes on stage. These stages were normally large centers, public zones or palace compounds which the elites would use more.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Much of [[Maya civilization|Mayan]] ceremonial architecture contains pieces of art containing figures doing ritual dances. The architect of these building holds figures of what the rooms are normally used for. Some set of staircase contain pictures of captives walking down them giving the idea the rooms here were used to store prisoners. The East Court of the [[Acropolis]] in Copan is believed to have been used for dance rituals. The room was used by a dictionary of colonial Yucatec described the acropolis as a community house where they learned to discuss public interest and well as learn to dance.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin|indent=yes}}&lt;!--BEGIN biblio format. If indent param. is used,  Pls use a colon (:) instead of asterisk (*) for bullet markers in the references list --&gt;
:{{cite book |author=Looper, Matthew G.   |title=To be like Gods |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-292-70988-1 |publisher=University of Texas Press |location=Austin, Texas |oclc=690595806}}
:Krystal, Matthew. (2012) ''Indigenous Dance and Dancing Indians: Contested Representation in the Global Era.'' University Press of Colorado.
{{Refend}}&lt;!-- END biblio format style --&gt;

{{Maya}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Maya Dance}}
[[Category:Maya society|Dance]]
[[Category:Mesoamerican art]]
[[Category:Ritual dances]]
[[Category:Maya art|Dance]]</text>
      <sha1>rvswldmgdq6zgsg09swkr24nrwqgrtu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
