<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mars habitat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42302371</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961771882</id>
      <parentid>961771823</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-10T09:49:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>141.168.46.126</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="55992" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|A facility where humans could live on Mars}}
[[File:Mars Ice Home concept.jpg|thumb|300px|[https://cloudsao.com/MARS-ICE-HOME Mars Ice Home] design for a Mars base  (NASA LaRC / Clouds Architecture Office, 2016)|alt=]]
[[File:S89 51054.jpg|thumb|right|Various components of the [[Mars Outpost]] proposal. (M. Dowman, 1989)&lt;ref name=NASA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/images/mars/marsbases/html/s89_51054.html |title=Photo-s89_51054 |publisher=Spaceflight.nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Mars design reference mission 3.jpg|thumb|1990s era NASA design featuring 'spam can' type habitat landers. The downside may be minimal shielding for crew, and two ideas are to use Mars materials, such as ice to increase shielding, and another is move underground, perhaps caves]]
A '''Mars habitat''' is a place that humans can live in on [[Mars]].&lt;ref name="hyperallergic1"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.cnet.com/news/3d-printable-ice-house-could-be-our-home-on-mars/|title = 3D-printable ice house could be our home on Mars|publisher = cnet.com|date = September 29, 2015|accessdate = 2015-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mars habitats must contend with surface conditions that include almost no oxygen in the [[air]], extreme cold, low pressure, and high radiation.&lt;ref name=psh&gt;{{cite web|last=Fecht |first=Sarah |url=http://www.popsci.com/8-printable-martian-habitat-designs-that-we-want-to-live-in |title=8 Printable Martian Habitat Designs That We Want To Live In &amp;#124; Popular Science |publisher=[[Popsci.com]] |date=2015-09-16 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alternatively, the habitat may be placed underground, which helps solve some problems but creates new difficulties.&lt;ref name=wired1&gt;{{cite web|last=Shubber |first=Kadhim |url=https://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2013-09/06/underground-mars-habitat |title=Concept for underground Mars habitat marks dawn of Martian mole-people (Wired UK) |publisher=Wired.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One challenge is the extreme cost of building materials for Mars, which by the 2010s was estimated be about US$2 million per brick to the surface of Mars.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.structuremag.org/?p=12389|title=STRUCTURE magazine {{!}} Structural Challenges for Space Architecture|website=www.structuremag.org|language=en-US|access-date=2017-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the gravity on Mars is lower than that on [[Earth]], there is increased solar radiation, temperature cycles, and the high internal forces needed for pressurized habitats to contain air.&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"&gt;[http://www.structuremag.org/?p=12389]&lt;/ref&gt;

To contend with these constraints, architects have worked to understand the right balance between in-situ materials and construction, and ex-situ to Mars.&lt;ref name="spacearchitect.org"&gt;[http://www.spacearchitect.org/pubs/ICES-2016-019.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, one idea is to use the locally available [[regolith]] to shield against radiation exposure, and another idea is to use transparent ice to allow non-harmful light to enter the habitat.&lt;ref name="spacearchitect.org"/&gt; Mars habitat design can also involve the study of local conditions, including pressures, temperatures, and local materials, especially water.&lt;ref name="spacearchitect.org"/&gt;

==Overview==
[[File:EXPO TOWER.JPG|thumb|A unique tower design for this World fair structure, highlights the alternative forms structure's in new environments might take]]
Significant challenges for Mars habitats are maintaining an artificial environment and shielding from intense [[solar radiation]]. Humans require a pressurized environment at all times and protection from the toxic Martian atmosphere. Connecting habitats is useful, as moving between separate structures requires a pressure suit or perhaps a Mars rover. One of the largest issues lies in simply getting to Mars, which means escaping Earth's atmosphere, sustaining the journey to Mars, and finally landing on the surface of Mars. One helpful aspect is the Mars atmosphere, which allows for aerobraking, meaning less need for using propellant to slow a craft for safe landing. However, the amount of energy required to transfer material to the surface of Mars is an additional task beyond simply getting into orbit. During the late 1960s, the United States produced the Saturn V rocket, which was capable of launching enough mass into orbit required for a single-launch trip holding a crew of three to the surface of the Moon and back again. This feat required a number of specially designed pieces of hardware and the development of a technique known as the [[Lunar orbit rendezvous|Lunar Orbit Rendezvous]]. The Lunar Orbit Rendezvous was a plan to coordinate the descent and ascent vehicles for a rendezvous in Lunar orbit. Referring to Mars, a similar technique would require a [[Mars Excursion Module]], which combines a crewed  descent-ascent vehicle and short stay surface habitat. Later plans have separated the descent-ascent vehicle and surface habitat, which further developed into separate descent, surface stay, and ascent vehicles using a new design architecture. In 2010 the [[Space Launch System]], or growth variants therefore, is envisioned as having the payload capacity and qualities needed for human Mars missions, utilizing the [[Orion (spacecraft)|Orion]] capsule.

One of the challenges for Mars habitats is maintaining the climate, especially the right temperature in the right places.&lt;ref name="discovermagazine1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/fieldnotes/2013/07/15/the-challenges-of-climate-control-in-a-mars-habitat/#.Vj50gPBdgnc |title=The Challenges of Climate Control in a Mars Habitat - Field Notes |publisher=Blogs.discovermagazine.com |date=2013-07-15 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Electronic devices and lights generate heat that rises in the air, even as there are extreme temperature fluctuations outside.&lt;ref name="discovermagazine1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/feature/eight-universities-selected-2016-x-hab-challenge |title=Eight Universities Selected for NASA's 2016 X-Hab Academic Innovation &amp;#124; NASA |publisher=Nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One idea for a Mars habitat is to use a Martian cave or [[lava tube]], and an inflatable air-lock was proposed by [[Caves of Mars Project]] for making use of such a structure.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070807050052/http://www.highmars.org/niac/airlock.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of living in lava tubes has been suggest later, noted for its potential to provide increased protection from [[radiation]], temperature fluctuation, Martian sunlight, etc.&lt;ref name="lightsinthedark.com"&gt;[https://lightsinthedark.com/2015/03/04/could-humans-set-up-camp-in-martian-lava-tubes/]&lt;/ref&gt; An advantage of living underground is that it avoids the need to create a radiation shield above ground.&lt;ref name="marsdaily.com"&gt;[http://www.marsdaily.com/reports/NASA_Chief_Were_Closer_to_Sending_Humans_on_Mars_Than_Ever_Before_999.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Another idea is to use robots to construct the base in advance of human's arrival.&lt;ref name="marsdaily.com"/&gt;

{{pquote|Get your ass to Mars|Buzz Aldrin&lt;ref name="lightsinthedark.com"/&gt;}}

[[File:PressurizedRoversOnMars.jpg|thumb|A mobile habitat on the move, such as for a circumnavigation of the planet]]
The use of living plants or other living biologicals to aid in the air and food supply if desired can have major impact on the design.&lt;ref name="science.nasa.gov"&gt;[https://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2004/25feb_greenhouses]&lt;/ref&gt; An example of how [[engineering]] demands and operational goals can interact, is a reduced-pressure green house area. This would reduce the structural demands of maintaining [[air pressure]], but require the relevant plants to survive at that lower pressure.

Taken to an extreme, the question remains just how a low a pressure could a plant survive in and still be useful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2004/25feb_greenhouses|title=Greenhouses for Mars {{!}} Science Mission Directorate|website=science.nasa.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Mars habitat may need to focus on keeping a certain type of plant alive, for example, as part of supporting its inhabitants.&lt;ref name="The Caves of Mars"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.highmars.org/niac/niac04.html|title=The Caves of Mars - Flat Crops for Mars|date=2007-07-01|access-date=2018-01-08|url-status=bot: unknown|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070701234427/http://www.highmars.org/niac/niac04.html|archivedate=2007-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NASA Caves of Mars study suggested the following aspects to a bio support for inhabitant food in their example:&lt;ref name="The Caves of Mars"/&gt;

*Rapid growth
*survival in low light 
*wide [[pH]] range
*high [[nutrition]] 
*minimal waste

The study noted two plants, [[Lemnoideae|duckweed]] (''Lemna minor'') and water fern (''[[Azolla filiculoides]]''), as particularly suitable, and they grow on the surface of water.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070701234427/http://www.highmars.org/niac/niac04.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The Mars habitat would have support the conditions of this food source, possible incorporating elements from greenhouse design or farming.

Historically, space missions tend to have a non-growing food supply eating out of set amount of rations like [[Skylab]], replenished with resupply from Earth. Using plants to affect the atmosphere and even enhance food supply was experimented with the 2010s aboard the International Space Station.

Another issue is waste management. On Skylab all waste was put in a big tank; on Apollo and the [[Space Shuttle]] urine could be vented out into space or pushed away in bags to re-enter Earth's atmosphere.

Considerations for maintaining the environment in a closed system included, removal of carbon dioxide, maintaining air pressure, supply of oxygen, temperature and humidity, and stopping fires. Another issue with closed system is keeping it free from contamination from emissions from different materials, dust, or smoke. One concern on Mars is the effect of the fine Martian dust working its way into the living quarters or devices. The dust is very fine and accumulates on solar panels, amongst other surfaces.{{Citation needed|date=January 2018}} (see also [[Martian soil]])

[[File:PIA23302-FirstHumansOnMars-ArtistConcept.jpg|thumb|500px|left|A Mars habitat in conjunction with other surface elements on Mars (artwork)]]
{{Clear}}

===Relevant technologies===
[[File:ArtemisI_Orion_EMI_Feb.jpg|thumb|[[Orion spacecraft]]]]
Some possible areas of needed technology or expertise:
*[[3D Printing]] 
*[[Mars atmospheric entry]]
*[[Caves of Mars Project]]
*[[Mars Excursion Module]]
*[[Aerospace engineering]]
*[[Space capsule]]
*[[Plants in space]]

===Context===
A Mars habitat is often conceived as part of an ensemble of Mars base and infrastructure technologies.&lt;ref name="Bossinas"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/multimedia/artgallery/art_feature_004_C91-8781.html|title=NASA - Multifunction Mars Base|last=Bossinas|first=Les|website=www.nasa.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some examples include Mars EVA suits, Mars rover, aircraft, landers, storage tanks, communication structures, mining, and Mars-movers (e.g. [[Heavy equipment|Earth-moving equipment]]).&lt;ref name="Bossinas"/&gt;

A Mars habitat might exist in the context of a human expedition, outpost, or colony on Mars.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"&gt;[https://history.nasa.gov/DPT/Technology%20Priorities%20Recommendations/Mars%20Medical%20Status%20DPT%20%20Aug_99.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air===
[[Image:Soda bubbles macro.jpg|thumb|right|Bubbles of [[gas]] in a [[soft drink]] (soda pop)]]
[[File:Aquabulle 4.jpg|thumb|People inside a clear diving bell on Earth]]
In creating a habitat for people, some considerations are maintaining the right air temperature, the right air pressure, and the composition of that atmosphere.

While it is possible for humans to breathe pure oxygen, a pure oxygen atmosphere was implicated in the [[Apollo 1]] fire. As such, Mars habitats may have a need for additional gases. One possibility is to take [[nitrogen]] and [[argon]] from the [[atmosphere of Mars]]; however, they are hard to separate from each other.&lt;ref name=gas/&gt; As a result, a Mars habitat may use 40% argon, 40% nitrogen, and 20% oxygen.&lt;ref name=gas&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highmars.org/niac/niac02.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070724100724/http://www.highmars.org/niac/niac02.html|title=The Caves of Mars - Martian Air Breathing Mice|archivedate=24 July 2007|work=highmars.org|accessdate=12 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Argox]], for the argon breathing gas mixture used in scuba diving

A concept to scrub {{CO2}} from the breathing air is to use re-usable [[amine]] bead [[carbon dioxide scrubber]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s.&lt;ref name="spectrum.ieee.org2"&gt;[https://spectrum.ieee.org/aerospace/space-flight/suiting-up-for-the-red-planet]&lt;/ref&gt; While one carbon dioxide scrubber filters the astronaut's air, the other can vent scrubbed {{CO2}} to the Mars atmosphere, once that process is completed another one can be used, and the one that was used can take a break.&lt;ref name="spectrum.ieee.org"&gt;{{cite web|last=Courtland |first=Rachel |url=https://spectrum.ieee.org/aerospace/space-flight/suiting-up-for-the-red-planet |title=Suiting Up for the Red Planet - IEEE Spectrum |publisher=Spectrum.ieee.org |date=2015-09-30 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Martian habitat with colonists.jpg|thumb|Mars habitats with astronauts]] 
One unique structural force that Mars habitats must contend with if pressurized to Earth's atmosphere, is the force of air on the inside walls.&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"/&gt; This has been estimated at over 2,000 pounds per square foot for a pressurized habitat on the surface of Mars, which is radically increased compared to Earth structures.&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"/&gt; A closer comparison can be made to crewed high-altitude aircraft, which must withstand forces of 1,100 to 1,400 pounds per square foot when at altitude.&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"/&gt;

At about 150 thousand feet of altitude (28 miles (45&amp;nbsp;km))  on Earth,  the atmospheric pressure starts to be equivalent to the surface of Mars.&lt;ref name="hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu"&gt;[http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/Kinetic/barfor.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable plainrowheaders" style="float:left; margin-right:20px"
|+ [[Atmospheric pressure]] comparison
! scope="col" | Location
! scope="col" | Pressure
|-
! scope="row" | [[Olympus Mons]] summit
| {{Convert|0.03|kPa|abbr=on|lk=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | Mars average
| {{Convert|0.6|kPa|abbr=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | [[Hellas Planitia]] bottom
| {{Convert|1.16|kPa|abbr=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | '''[[Armstrong limit]]'''
| {{Convert|6.25|kPa|abbr=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | [[Mount Everest]] summit&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John B. West|url=http://jap.physiology.org/content/86/3/1062.full| title=John B. West – '''Barometric pressures on Mt. Everest: new data and physiological significance''' (1998)| publisher=Jap.physiology.org|date=1 March 1999|accessdate=15 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| {{Convert|33.7|kPa|abbr=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | Earth sea level
| {{Convert|101.3|kPa|abbr=on}}
|-
! scope="row" | Surface of [[Venus]]&lt;ref name=Basilevsky2003&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Basilevsky|first1=Alexandr T.|last2=Head|first2=James W.|title=The surface of Venus|journal=Rep. Prog. Phys.|year=2003|volume=66|issue=10|pages=1699–1734|doi=10.1088/0034-4885/66/10/R04|bibcode = 2003RPPh...66.1699B|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/13e87bf184cd5ab307423190918ae68f05a13667}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| {{Convert|9200|kPa|abbr=on}}
|}

{{clear}}
See also [[Effects of high altitude on humans]]

;Temperature

One of the challenges for a Mars habitat is for it to maintain suitable temperatures in the right places in a habitat.&lt;ref name="discovermagazine1"/&gt; Things like electronics and lights generate heat that rises in the air, even as there are extreme temperature fluctuation outside.&lt;ref name="discovermagazine1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/feature/eight-universities-selected-2016-x-hab-challenge |title=Eight Universities Selected for NASA's 2016 X-Hab Academic Innovation &amp;#124; NASA |publisher=Nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; There can be large temperature swings on Mars, for example at the equator it may reach  70 degrees F (20 degrees C) in the daytime but then go down to minus 100 degrees F (−73 C) at night.&lt;ref name="space.com"&gt;[https://www.space.com/16907-what-is-the-temperature-of-mars.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of Mars surface temperatures:&lt;ref name="space.com"/&gt;
*Average −80 degrees Fahrenheit (−60 degrees Celsius).
*Polar locations in winter  −195 degrees F (−125 degrees C).
*Equator in summer daytime High 70 degrees F (20 degrees C)

===Temporary vs permanent habitation===
[[File:MarsGroundHabitat.jpg|thumb|500px|A vision for habitats published by NASA from ''CASE FOR MARS'' from the 1980s, featuring the re-use of landing vehicles, in-situ soil use for enhanced radiation shielding, and green houses. A bay for a Mars rover is also visible.]]
[[File:Lander Landed Image2.jpg|thumb|A human landing on Mars would necessitate different levels of support for habitation]]
A short term stay on the surface of Mars does not require a habitat to have a large volume or complete shielding from radiation. The situation would be similar to the [[International Space Station#Radiation|International Space Station]], where individuals receive an unusually high amount of radiation for a short duration and then leave.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adl.gatech.edu/research/tff/radiation_shield.html&lt;/ref&gt; A small and light habitat can be transported to Mars and used immediately.

Long term permanent habitats require much more volume (i.e.:[[greenhouse]]) and thick shielding to minimize the annual dose of radiation received. This type of habitat is too large and heavy to be sent to Mars, and must be constructed making use of some local resource. Possibilities include covering structures with ice or soil, excavating subterranean spaces or sealing the ends of an existing [[Martian lava tube|lava tube]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.zaarchitects.com/en/other/103-mars-colonization.html&lt;/ref&gt;

A larger settlement may be able to have a larger medical staff, increasing the ability to deal with health issues and emergencies.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; Whereas a small expedition of 4–6 may be able to have 1 medical doctor, an outpost of 20 might be able to have more than one and nurses, in addition to those with emergency or paramedic training.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; A full settlement may be able to achieve the same level of care as a contemporary Earth hospital.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt;

===Medical===
One problem for medical care on Mars missions, is the difficulty in returning to Earth for advanced care, and providing adequate emergency care with a small crew size.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; A crew of six might have only trained at the level of Emergency medical and one physician, but for a mission that would last years.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; In addition, consultations with Earth would be hampered by a 7 to 40 minute time lag.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; Medical risks include exposure to radiation and reduced gravity, and one deadly risk is a [[Solar particle event|Solar Particle Event]] that can generate a lethal dose over the course of several hours or days if the astronauts do not have enough shielding.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; The effect of radiation on stored pharmaceuticals and medical technology would have to be taken into account also.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt;

One of the medical supplies that may be needed is [[intravenous fluid]], which is mostly water but contains other things so it can be added directly to the human blood stream. If it can be created on the spot from existing water then it could spare the weight of hauling earth-produced units, whose weight is mostly water.&lt;ref name=ivegen&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/research/news/IVGEN.html |title=A Solution for Medical Needs and Cramped Quarters in Space IVGEN Undergoes Lifetime Testing in Preparation For Future Missions |work=NASA |accessdate=12 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prototype for this capability was tested on the [[International Space Station]] in 2010.&lt;ref name=ivegen /&gt;

On some of the first crewed missions, three types of medications that were taken into orbit were an anti-nausea, a pain-killer, and a stimulant.&lt;ref name="IFLScience"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.iflscience.com/space/what-medicines-would-we-pack-trip-mars/|title=What Medicines Would We Pack For A Trip To Mars?|work=IFLScience|access-date=2018-03-07|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time of ISS, space crew-persons had almost 200 medications available, with separate pill cabinets for Russians and Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iflscience.com/space/what-medicines-would-we-pack-trip-mars/]&lt;/ref&gt; One of the many concerns for crewed  Mars missions is what pills to bring and how the astronauts would respond to them in different conditions.&lt;ref name="IFLScience"/&gt;

In 1999, NASA's Johnson Space Center published ''Medical Aspects of Exploration Missions'' as part of the [[Decadal survey|Decadal Survey]].&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; On a small mission it might be possible to have one be a medical doctor and another be a paramedic, out of a crew of perhaps 4–6 people, however on a larger mission with 20 people there could also be a nurse and options like minor surgery might be possible.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; Two major categories for space would be emergency medical care and then more advanced care, dealing with a wide range concerns due to space-travel.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; For very small crews its difficult to treat a wide range issues with advanced care, whereas with a team with an overall size of 12–20 on Mars there could be multiple doctors and nurses, in addition to EMT-level certifications.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt; While not at the level of a typical Earth hospital this would transition medical are beyond basic options typical of very small crew sizes (2–3) where the accepted risk is higher.&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt;

One idea to enhance under-qualified crew who might need to perform an advanced surgery, is to have a robotic surgery machine on Mars which would be operated by a crew-member with help via telecommunications from Earth.&lt;ref name="Hollingham"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20151125-the-challenges-of-carrying-out-surgery-in-space|title=The grim and gory reality of surgery in space|last=Hollingham|first=Richard|language=en|access-date=2018-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two examples of medical-care situations that been mentioned in regard to people on Mars is how to deal with a broken leg and an [[appendicitis]].&lt;ref name="Hollingham"/&gt; One concern is to stop what would otherwise be a minor injury becoming life-threatening due to restrictions on the amount of [[medical equipment]], training, and the time-delay in communication with Earth.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20151125-the-challenges-of-carrying-out-surgery-in-space]&lt;/ref&gt; The time delay for a one way message ranges from 4 to 24 minutes, depending.&lt;ref name="blogs.esa.int"&gt;[http://blogs.esa.int/mex/2012/08/05/time-delay-between-mars-and-earth/]&lt;/ref&gt; A response to a message takes that time, the delay processing the message and creating a reply, plus the time for that message to travel to Mars (another 4 to 24 minutes).&lt;ref name="blogs.esa.int"/&gt;

Examples of acute medical emergency possibilies for Mars missions:&lt;ref name="history.nasa.gov"/&gt;
*Wounds, lacerations, and burns
*Exposure to a toxin
*Acute allergic reactions ([[anaphylaxis]])
*[[Acute radiation syndrome|Acute radiation sickness]]
*Dental 
*Eye ([[Ophthalmologic]]) 
*Psychiatric

An example of  spaceflight related health emergency was the [[inert gas asphyxiation]] with nitrogen gas aboard Space Shuttle Columbia in 1981, when it was undergoing preparations for its launch &lt;ref name="wired.com"&gt;[https://www.wired.com/2009/03/march-19-1981-shuttle-columbias-first-fatalities/]&lt;/ref&gt; In that case, a routine purge with nitrogen to decrease risk of fire lead to 5 medical emergencies and 2 deaths.&lt;ref name="wired.com"/&gt; Another infamous space related accident is the [[Apollo 1]] incident, when a pure oxygen atmosphere ignited in the interior of space capsule during tests on the ground, three died.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.space.com/17338-apollo-1.html]&lt;/ref&gt; A 1997 study of about 280 space travelers between 1988 and 1995, found that only 3 did not have some sort of medical issue on their spaceflight.&lt;ref name="jeromegroopman.com"&gt;[http://jeromegroopman.com/ny-articles/MedicineOnMars-02142000.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; A medical risk for a Mars surface mission is how, after several months in zero gravity, they astronauts will handle operations on the surface.&lt;ref name="jeromegroopman.com"/&gt; On Earth, astronauts must often be carted from the spacecraft and take a long time to recover.&lt;ref name="jeromegroopman.com"/&gt;

See [[Space medicine]]

===Library===
[[File:Library Tower - Flickr - treegrow.jpg|thumb|Library Tower of Biodome 2, an Earth analog space habitat tested in the 1990s]]
One idea for a Mars missions is a [[library]] sent to the surface of that planet.&lt;ref name="planetary.org"&gt;[http://www.planetary.org/press-room/releases/2008/0527_Phoenix_Takes_Image_of_First_Library_on.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The Phoenix lander, which landed on the North polar surface of Mars in 2008, included a DVD library that was heralded as the first library on Mars.&lt;ref name="planetary.org"/&gt; The Phoenix library DVD would be taken by future explorers who could access the content on the disk.&lt;ref name="planetary.org"/&gt; The disc, both a memorial to the past and a message to the future, took 15 years to produce.&lt;ref name="planetary.org"/&gt; The content on the disc includes ''Visions of Mars''.&lt;ref name="planetary.org"/&gt; One idea for exploration is [[knowledge ark]]s for space, a sort of back-up of knowledge in case something happens to Earth.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2007/08/070814-lunar-ark.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Biodome 2 spaceflight and closed-loop biosphere test included a library with the living quarters.&lt;ref name="insidetucsonbusiness.com"&gt;[https://www.insidetucsonbusiness.com/news/once-threatened-biosphere-continues-mission-under-ua/article_5581b3a7-11c1-5c5c-aadb-65eec80e58f0.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The library was positioned at the top of a tower, and known as Library tower.&lt;ref name="insidetucsonbusiness.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://suncruisermedia.com/Home/rv-travel/biospere-2/]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Meteor impacts===
[[File:PIA11176 - A Recent Cluster of Impacts.jpg|thumb|left|Fresh impact craters detected in the early 2000s by Mars satellites]]
Another consideration for Mars habitats, especially for long-term stay, is the need to potentially deal with a meteor impact.&lt;ref name="O'Neill"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.seeker.com/mars-meteorite-impact-crater-nasa-mro-hirise-image-2248298212.html|title=Mars Was Recently Hit by a Meteorite 'Shotgun' Blast|last=O'Neill|first=Ian|date=2017-02-08|work=Seeker|access-date=2018-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"/&gt;
The atmosphere is thinner so more meteors make it to the surface, so one concern is if a meteor punctured the surface of the habitat causing a loss of pressure or damaging systems.&lt;ref name="O'Neill"/&gt;&lt;ref name="structuremag.org"/&gt;

In the 2010s it was determined that something struck the surface of Mars, creating a spattering pattern of larger and smaller craters between 2008 and 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.seeker.com/mars-meteorite-impact-crater-nasa-mro-hirise-image-2248298212.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In this case the atmosphere only partially disintegrated the meteor before it struck the surface.&lt;ref name="O'Neill"/&gt;

{{clear}}

===Radiation===
Radiation exposure is a concern for astronauts even on the surface, as Mars lacks a strong magnetic field and atmosphere is thin to stop as much radiation as Earth. However, the planet does reduce the radiation significantly especially on the surface, and it is not detected to be radioactive itself.

It has been estimated that sixteen feet (5 meters) of Mars regolith stops the same amount of radiation as Earth's atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.spacesafetymagazine.com/space-exploration/mars-mission/earthlings-martians-living-red-planet-affect-human-bodies/|title=How Will Living On Mars Affects Our Human Body?|date=2014-02-11|work=Space Safety Magazine|access-date=2018-01-14|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Power===
[[File:Astronauts approach Viking 2.jpg|thumb|Space art illustrating a group approaching the Viking 2 lander probe, which were supported by RTG power]]
For a 500-day crewed Mars mission NASA has studied using solar power and nuclear power for its base, as well as power storage systems (e.g. batteries).&lt;ref name="ntrs.nasa.gov"&gt;[https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/20120012929.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the challenges for solar power include a reduction in solar intensity because Mars is farther from the sun, dust accumulation, and periodic dust storms, in addition to the usual challenges of solar power such as storing power for the night-time.&lt;ref name="ntrs.nasa.gov"/&gt; One of the difficulties is enduring the global Mars dust storms, which cause lower temperatures and reduce sunlight reaching the surface.&lt;ref name="ntrs.nasa.gov"/&gt; Two ideas for overcoming this are to use an additional array deployed during a dust storm and to use some nuclear power to provide base-line power that is not affected by the storms.&lt;ref name="ntrs.nasa.gov"/&gt; NASA has studied nuclear-power fission systems in the 2010s for Mars surface missions.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.space.com/37348-nasa-fission-power-mars-colony.html|title=NASA to Test Fission Power for Future Mars Colony|work=Space.com|access-date=2018-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; One design was planned for an output of 40 kilowatts, and its more independent of the sunlight reaching the surface of Mars which can be affected by dust storms.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/nasa-seeks-nuclear-power-for-mars/|title=NASA Seeks Nuclear Power for Mars|last=Klotz, SPACE.com|first=Irene|work=Scientific American|access-date=2018-03-25|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another idea for power is to beam the power to the surface, a solar power satellite would send the power down to the surface to a  rectifying antenna (aka [[rectenna]]) receiver.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.researchgate.net/publication/23884970_Construction_of_Power_Receiving_Rectenna_Using_Mars-_In-Situ_Materials_A_Low_Energy_Materials_Processing_Approach]&lt;/ref&gt; 245&amp;nbsp;GHz, laser, in-situ rectenna construction, and 5.8&amp;nbsp;GHz designs have been studied.&lt;ref name="Curreri"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Curreri|first=Peter|last2=Franklin Rose|first2=M|date=2001-02-01|title=Construction of Power Receiving Rectenna Using Mars- In-Situ Materials; A Low Energy Materials Processing Approach|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/23884970}}&lt;/ref&gt; One idea is combine this technology to with Solar Electric Propulsion to achieve a lower mass that the surface solar power.&lt;ref name="Curreri"/&gt; The big advantage is that the rectennas should be immune to dust and weather changes, and with the right orbit, a solar power Mars satellite could beam power down continuously to the surface.&lt;ref name="Curreri"/&gt;

Technology to clean dust off the solar panels was considered for [[Mars Exploration Rover]]'s development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.newscientist.com/blogs/shortsharpscience/2008/11/why-dont-the-mars-rovers-have.html |title=Why don't the Mars rovers have dust wipers? |work=New Scientist |first=Henry |last=Spencer |date=17 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 21st century there have been proposed ways of cleaning off solar panels on the surface Mars that are accumulating dust.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ceramics.org/ceramic-tech-today/mars-cleaning-tech-offers-method-to-sweep-dust-off-earths-solar-panels |title=Mars cleaning tech offers method to sweep dust off Earth's solar panels |publisher=The American Ceramic Society |date=25 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The  effects of [[Martian soil|Martian surface dust]] on [[solar cell]]s was studied in the 1990s by the [[Materials Adherence Experiment]] on [[Mars Pathfinder]].&lt;ref name="Results"&gt;{{cite conference |title=Dust on Mars: Materials Adherence Experiment results from Mars Pathfinder |conference=Photovoltaic Specialists Conference. 29 September-3 October 1997. Anaheim, California. |first1=G. A. |last1=Landis |first2=P. P. |last2=Jenkins |date=1997 |doi=10.1109/PVSC.1997.654224}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Science"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Characterization of the Martian surface deposits by the Mars Pathfinder rover, Sojourner |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |first1=J. R. |last1=Matijevic |first2=J. |last2=Crisp |first3=D. B. |last3=Bickler |first4=R. S. |last4=Banes |first5=B. K. |last5=Cooper |display-authors=etal |volume=278 |issue=5344 |pages=1765–1768 |date=December 1997 |doi=10.1126/science.278.5344.1765 |bibcode=1997Sci...278.1765M |pmid=9388171|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ualr.edu/mkmazumder/research.html |title=UALR Particulate Science Research |publisher=University of Arkansas at Little Rock |date=2013 |accessdate=20 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable plainrowheaders" style="float:left; margin-right:20px"
|+ Lander power (''examples'')
! scope="col" | Name
! scope="col" | Main Power
|-
! scope="row" | Viking 1 &amp; 2
| Nuclear – RTG
|-
! scope="row" | Mars Pathfinder
| Solar panels 
|-
! scope="row" | MER A &amp; B
| Solar panels 
|-
! scope="row" | Phoenix
| Solar panels
|-
! scope="row" | MSL 
| Nuclear – RTG
|-
|}
{{clear}}

==History==
[[File:PIA23302-FirstHumansOnMars-ArtistConcept.jpg|{{largethumb}}|&lt;div align="center"&gt;NASA vision for the first Humans On Mars&lt;br /&gt;(Artist Concept; 2019)&lt;/div&gt;]]
One early idea for a Mars habitat was to use put short stay accommodation in a Mars ascent-descent vehicle. This combination was called a [[Mars Excursion Module]], and also typically featured other components such as basic rover and science equipment. Later missions tended to shift to a dedicated descent/ascent with a separate habitat.

In 2013 ZA architects proposed having digging robots build a Mars habitat underground.&lt;ref name=wired1/&gt; They chose an interior inspired by [[Fingal's Cave]] and noted the increased protection from high-energy radiation below ground.&lt;ref name=wired1/&gt; On the other hand, the issue of the difficulty of sending digging robots that must construct the habitat versus landing capsules on the surface was also noted.&lt;ref name=wired1/&gt; An alternative may be to build above ground, but use thick ice to shield from radiation but with advantage that it lets visible light in.&lt;ref name="hyperallergic1"/&gt;

In 2015 the SHEE project noted the idea of autonomous construction and preparation for Mars habitat versus human construction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.space.com/30553-self-deploying-mars-habitats-shee.html Future Mars Explorers Could Live in Habitats That Build Themselves ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==NASA==
[[File:Tri-ATHLETE (2010).jpg|thumb|NASA six-legged mobile habitat module (TRI-ATHLETE)]]
[[File:Habitat Demonstration Unit (2010) cropped androtated.jpg|thumb|Habitat Demonstration Unit of the [[Desert Research and Technology Studies]]]]
In early 2015 NASA outlined a conceptual plan for three stage Mars habitat design and construction award program.&lt;ref name="techtimes1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.techtimes.com/articles/54113/20150519/know-design-3d-printed-habitat-mars-nasa-2-25-million.htm |title=NASA Offers $2.25 Million For Martian Habitat Design - How Could This Contest Help People On Earth? : SCIENCE |publisher=Tech Times |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first stage is a design only, then in the next stage a construction technology based using discarded spacecraft components is conducted, and finally building an actual habitat for Mars using 3D printing technology.&lt;ref name="techtimes1"/&gt;

In September 2015, NASA announced the winners of its 3-D Printed Habitat Challenge.&lt;ref name=nasa1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/directorates/spacetech/centennial_challenges/3DPHab/2015winners.html |title=NASA Awards Top Three Design Finalists in 3D Printed Habitat Challenge &amp;#124; NASA |publisher=Nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The winning submission titled '''Mars Ice House''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cloudsao.com/MARS-ICE-HOUSE|title=MARS ICE HOUSE - Clouds Architecture Office|website=www.cloudsao.com|access-date=2017-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; by Clouds Architecture Office / SEArch proposed a 3D-printed double ice shell surrounding a lander module core.&lt;ref name="hyperallergic1"/&gt; Two European teams were awarded runner up prizes.&lt;ref name=nasa1/&gt; The contenders explored many possibilities for materials, with one suggesting separately refining iron and silica from the Martian dust and using the iron to make a lattice-work filled in with silca panels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Fecht |first=Sarah |url=http://www.popsci.com/8-printable-martian-habitat-designs-that-we-want-to-live-in?image=3 |title=8 Printable Martian Habitat Designs That We Want To Live In &amp;#124; Popular Science |publisher=Popsci.com |date=2015-09-16 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were 30 finalists selected from an initial pool of 165 entries in the habitat challenge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.sciencealert.com/3d-printed-ice-habitat-concept-for-mars-draws-acclaim-from-nasa |title=3D-printed ice habitat concept for Mars draws acclaim from NASA |publisher=ScienceAlert |date=2015-10-02 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second-place winner proposed the printing robots build a shield out of in-situ materials around inflatable modules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/picture-galleries/11896687/Top-10-Mars-habitats-from-NASA-space-habitat-challenge.html?frame=3456077 |title=Top 10 Mars habitats from NASA space habitat challenge |newspaper=Telegraph |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another NASA project that has developed extraterrestrial surface habitats is the X-Hab challenge and the [[Habitation Systems Project]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/exploration/technology/deep_space_habitat/xhab/index.html#.Vj53HPBdgnc |title=NASA - eXploration Habitat (X-Hab) Academic Innovation Challenge |publisher=Nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/exploration/technology/deep_space_habitat/ |title=NASA - Habitation Systems Project - NASA's Deep Space Habitat |publisher=Nasa.gov |date=2012-12-11 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Sfero House by Fabulous also a contender in the 3D Mars Habitat program, featured levels above and below ground level.&lt;ref name=dezsfero&gt;[http://www.dezeen.com/2015/09/11/fabulous-double-domed-3d-printed-sfero-bubble-house-mars-red-planet/ 3D-printed bubble house proposed for living on Mars]&lt;/ref&gt; The proposed location was Gale crater (of Curiosity rover fame) with a focus on using both in-situ iron and water which would hopefully be available there.&lt;ref name=dezsfero/&gt; It has a double walled spherical design filled with water to both keep the higher-pressure of Mars habitat in, but help protect against radiation.&lt;ref name=dezsfero/&gt;

In 2016, NASA awarded the first prize of its In-Situ Materials Challenge to University of Southern California engineering professor [[Behrokh Khoshnevis]] "for Selective Separation Sintering -- a 3D-printing process that makes use of powder-like materials found on Mars." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2017/02/21/tech/nasa-3d-printing-colony-mars |title=Meet the man working with NASA to 3D print a colony on Mars |publisher=[[CNN]] |date=2017-02-22 |accessdate=2017-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016 NASA Langley showed the Mars Ice Dome, which used in-situ water to make an ice structure part of the design a Mars habitat.&lt;ref name="Gillard"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nasa.gov/feature/langley/a-new-home-on-mars-nasa-langley-s-icy-concept-for-living-on-the-red-planet|title=A New Home on Mars: NASA Langley's Icy Concept for Red Planet Living|last=Gillard|first=Eric|date=2016-12-13|work=NASA|access-date=2018-01-20|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Igloo]])

In June 2018, NASA selected the top ten finalists of Phase 3: Level 1 in the [[3D-Printed Habitat Challenge]].&lt;ref name="Harbaugh"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/spacetech/centennial_challenges/3DPHab/top-10-virtual-model-stage|title=Top 10 Teams Selected in Virtual Stage of 3D-Printed Habitat Challenge|last=Harbaugh|first=Jennifer|date=2018-06-28|work=NASA|access-date=2018-07-14|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phase 3: Level 1 Winners:&lt;ref name="Harbaugh"/&gt;
*ALPHA Team – Marina Del Rey, California
*[[Colorado School of Mines]] and ICON – Golden, Colorado
*Hassell &amp; EOC – San Francisco, California
*Kahn-Yates – Jackson, Mississippi
* Mars Incubator – New Haven, Connecticut
*AI. SpaceFactory – New York, New York
*[[Northwestern University]] – Evanston, Illinois
*SEArch+/Apis Cor – New York, New York
*Team Zopherus – Rogers, Arkansas
*X-Arc – San Antonio, Texas

In May 2019, NASA announced that the top winner of the 3D Printed Habitat Challenge was from AI SpaceFactory, with an entry called "Marsha," and there was several other prizes awarded also.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.space.com/nasa-3d-printed-habitat-competition-winners.html|title=Here's the Winner of NASA's 3D-Printed Mars Habitat Challenge|last=Tech|first=Elizabeth Howell 2019-05-10T13:00:06Z|website=Space.com|language=en|access-date=2019-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the final challenge contestants had 30 hours to build 1/3 scale models using robotic construction technology.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Mars analogs and analog habitat studies==
[[File:Wiki bio2 sunset 001.jpg|thumb|[[Biosphere 2]] tested a closed-loop greenhouse and accommodation in the early 1990s]]
{{main|Mars analog habitat}}
Mock Mars missions or Mars analog missions typically construct terrestrial habitats on Earth and conduct mock missions, taking steps to solve some of the problems that could be faced for one on Mars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/news/mock-mars-mission-utah-habitat-simulates-life-on-red-planet/ |title=Mock Mars mission: Utah habitat simulates life on red planet |publisher=[[CBS News]] |date=2014-01-03 |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this was the original mission of [[Biosphere 2]], which was  meant to test closed ecological systems to support and maintain human life in outer space.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/science-and-technology/biology-and-genetics/environmental-studies/biosphere-ii-project|title=Biosphere II Project facts, information, pictures {{!}} Encyclopedia.com articles about Biosphere II Project|website=www.encyclopedia.com|language=en|access-date=2017-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biosphere 2 tested several people living in closed loop biological system, with several biological areas in support including rainforest,  savannah,  ocean,  desert,  marsh, agriculture,  and  in an area in support of a living space.&lt;ref name="Alling 250–260"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Alling|first=Abigail|last2=Van Thillo|first2=Mark|last3=Dempster|first3=William|last4=Nelson|first4=Mark|last5=Silverstone|first5=Sally|last6=Allen|first6=John|date=2005-01-01|title=Lessons Learned from Biosphere 2 and Laboratory Biosphere Closed Systems Experiments for the Mars On Earth Project|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/242368741|journal=Biological Sciences in Space|volume=19|issue=4|pages=250–260|doi=10.2187/bss.19.250|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of Mars analog comparison mission is [[HI-SEAS]] of the 2010s. Other Mars analog studies include [[Mars Desert Research Station]] and [[Arctic Mars Analog Svalbard Expedition]]

*[[Australia Mars Analog Research Station]]
*[[Flashline Mars Arctic Research Station]]
*[[MARS-500]]
*[[Concordia Station]]

The ISS has also been described as a predecessor to Mars expedition, and in relation to a Mars habitat the study importance and nature of operation a closed system was noted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin J.L. Turner|title=Expedition Mars|url=https://archive.org/details/expeditionmars00turn|url-access=registration|year=2004|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-1-85233-735-3|page=[https://archive.org/details/expeditionmars00turn/page/298 298]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At about 28 miles (45&amp;nbsp;km,  150 thousand feet ) Earth altitude the pressure starts to be equivalent to Mars surface pressure.&lt;ref name="hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu"/&gt;

An example of regolith simulant is [[Martian regolith simulant]] (further information about Mars analogs [[List of Mars analogs]])

==Biodomes==
[[Image:Paranal residencia.jpg|221x221px|thumb|left|Interior of the [[ESO Hotel]] which has been called a "boarding house on Mars", because the desert surroundings are Mars-like; it houses observatory staff at an observatory in the high Chilean desert.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bayferrox.com/uploads/tx_lxsmatrix/CCW_Case-Study_ESO-Hotel-CL_de_en_2009_03.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; ]]
[[File:Mars Food Production - Bisected.jpg|thumb|400px|Illustration of plants growing in a Mars base.]]
One example concept that is or is in support of habitat is a Mars biodome, a structure that could hold life generating needed oxygen and food for humans.&lt;ref name="techtimes2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.techtimes.com/articles/53120/20150514/oxygen-mars-bacteria.htm |title=Need Oxygen On Mars? Get It From Bacteria! : SCIENCE |publisher=Tech Times |date= |accessdate=2015-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; An example of activity in support of this goals, was a program to develop bacteria that could convert the Martian regolith or ice into [[oxygen]].&lt;ref name="techtimes2"/&gt; Some issues with biodomes are the rate at which gas leaks out and the level of oxygen and other gases inside it.&lt;ref name="Alling 250–260"/&gt;

One question for Biodomes is how low the pressure could be lowered to, and the plants still be useful.&lt;ref name="science.nasa.gov"/&gt; In one study where air pressure was lowered to 1/10 of Earth's air pressure at the surface, the plants had a higher rate of evaporation from its leaves.&lt;ref name="science.nasa.gov"/&gt; This triggered the plant to think there was drought, despite it having a steady supply of water.&lt;ref name="science.nasa.gov"/&gt; An example of a crop NASA tested growing at lower pressure is lettuce, and in another test [[green beans]] were grown at a standard air pressure, but in low Earth orbit inside the International Space Station.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nasa.gov/vision/earth/livingthings/25feb_greenhouses.html|title=NASA - Greenhouses for Mars|last=Science@NASA|website=www.nasa.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DLR found that some [[lichen]] and bacteria could survive in simulated Martian conditions, including air composition, pressure, and solar radiation spectrum.&lt;ref name="dlr.de"&gt;[http://www.dlr.de/dlr/en/desktopdefault.aspx/tabid-10081/151_read-3409#/gallery/5671]&lt;/ref&gt; The Earth organisms survived for over 30 days under Mars conditions, and while it was not known if they would survive beyond this, it was noted they seemed to be performing [[photosynthesis]] under those conditions.&lt;ref name="dlr.de"/&gt; 

To convert the entirety of Mars into a biodome directly, scientists have suggested the [[cyanobacteria]] [[Chroococcidiopsis]].&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2001/ast26jan_1/|title=Greening of the Red Planet {{!}} Science Mission Directorate|website=science.nasa.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; This would help convert the regolith into soil by creating an organic element.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; That bacteria is known to survive in extremely cold and dry conditions on Earth, so might provide a basis for bioengineering Mars into a more habitable place.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; As the bacteria reproduces the dead ones would create an organic layer in the regolith potentially paving the way for more advanced life.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

A study published in 2016 showed that crypto[[endolith]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;ic [[Fungus|fungi]] survived for 18 months in simulated Mars conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.csmonitor.com/Science/2016/0128/Could-fungi-survive-on-Mars|title=Could fungi survive on Mars?|date=2016-01-28|work=Christian Science Monitor|access-date=2018-01-20|issn=0882-7729}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Onofri|first=Silvano|last2=de Vera|first2=Jean-Pierre|last3=Zucconi|first3=Laura|last4=Selbmann|first4=Laura|last5=Scalzi|first5=Giuliano|last6=Venkateswaran|first6=Kasthuri J.|last7=Rabbow|first7=Elke|last8=de la Torre|first8=Rosa|last9=Horneck|first9=Gerda|date=2015-12-01|title=Survival of Antarctic Cryptoendolithic Fungi in Simulated Martian Conditions On Board the International Space Station|journal=Astrobiology|volume=15|issue=12|pages=1052–1059|doi=10.1089/ast.2015.1324|pmid=26684504|issn=1531-1074|bibcode=2015AsBio..15.1052O}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On Earth, plants that utilize the C4 photosynthesis reaction account for 3% of flowering plant species but 23% of carbon that is fixed, and includes species popular for human consumption including [[maize|corn (aka maize)]] and [[sugar cane]]; certain types of plants may be more productive at producing food for a given amount of light.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|date=2013-07-22|title=C4 photosynthesis|journal=Current Biology|language=en|volume=23|issue=14|pages=R594–R599|doi=10.1016/j.cub.2013.04.066|pmid=23885869|issn=0960-9822|last1=Kellogg|first1=Elizabeth A.|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Plants noted for colonizing the barren landscape in the aftermath of the Mt Saint Helen's eruption included [[Asteraceae]] and [[Epilobium]], and especially [[Lupinus lepidus]] for its (symbiotic) ability to fix its own nitrogen.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=del Moral|first=Roger|last2=Wood|first2=David M.|date=1993|title=Early Primary Succession on the Volcano Mount St. Helens|journal=Journal of Vegetation Science|volume=4|issue=2|pages=223–234|doi=10.2307/3236108|jstor=3236108|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/3240385f0c7bbc4e8dff534d7de899bf0e4b2352}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[:Category:Nitrogen-fixing crops]], [[Rhizobia]], [[Nitrogen fixation]])

==In-situ resources==
[[File:Combination Lander Concept on Mars Surface.png|thumb|A concept for a combined surface habitat and ascent vehicle from the 1990s era [[NASA Design Reference Mission 3.0|Design Reference Mission 3.0]]-based mission, that integrated in-situ resources production in this case for propellant]]
[[File:Colonization of Mars.jpg|thumb|left|Pine trees have been suggested, in combination with other techniques for creating more hospitable atmosphere on Mars.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"&gt;[http://scienceillustrated.com.au/blog/science/a-new-era/]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In situ [[In situ resource utilization|resource utilization]] involves using materials encountered on Mars to produce materials needed. One idea for supporting a Mars habitat is to extract subterranean water, which, with sufficient power, could then be split into hydrogen and oxygen, with the intention of mixing the oxygen with nitrogen and argon for breathable air. The hydrogen can be combined with carbon dioxide to make plastics or methane for rocket fuel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/07/01/tech/mars-life-support-system-study/|title=Breathing perfect air on Mars is possible, study says |first=Ben |last=Brumfield|work=CNN|access-date=2018-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iron has also been suggested as a building material for 3D printed Mars habitats.&lt;ref name=dezsfero/&gt;

In the 2010s the idea of using in-situ water to build an ice shield for protection from radiation and temperature, etc. appeared in designs.&lt;ref name="Gillard"/&gt;

A material processing plant would use Mars resources to reduce reliance on Earth provided material.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/multimedia/artgallery/art_feature_004_C91-8781.html|title=NASA - Multifunction Mars Base|last=Bossinas|first=Les|website=www.nasa.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The planned [[Mars 2020]] mission includes [[Mars Oxygen ISRU Experiment]] (MOXIE), which would convert Mars carbon dioxide into oxygen.

To convert the whole of Mars into a habitat, increased air could come from vaporizing materials in the planet.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt; In time lichen and moss might be established, and then eventually pine trees.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt;

There is a theory to make rocket fuel on Mars, by the [[Sabatier reaction|Sabatier process]].&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt; In this process hydrogen and carbon dioxide are used to make methane and water.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt; In the next step, the water is split into hydrogen and oxygen, with the oxygen and methane being used for a Methane-Oxygen rocket engine, and the hydrogen could be re-used.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt; This process requires a large input of energy, so an appropriate power source would be needed in addition to the reactants.&lt;ref name="scienceillustrated.com.au"/&gt;

==See also==
*{{annotated link|Crewed Mars rover}}, has some of the same requirements as habitats
*{{annotated link|Climate of Mars}}
*{{annotated link|Colonization of Mars}}
*{{annotated link|Health threat from cosmic rays}}
*{{annotated link|List of Mars analogs}}
*{{annotated link|Mars analog habitat}}
*{{annotated link|Martian lava tube}}
*{{annotated link|Space architecture#Martian}}
*{{annotated link|ISS ECLSS}} (International Space Station life support system)
*{{annotated link|List of artificial objects on Mars}}
*{{annotated link|Mars Excursion Module}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
*[http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/710Boston.pdf Human utilization of subsurface extraterrestrial environments] (2002 NIAC Paper on living underground on Mars)
*[http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/library/meetings/annual/nov03/710Boston.pdf Human Utilization of Subsurface Extraterrestrial Environments]
*[http://3dpchallenge.tumblr.com/ 30 concepts for 3D printed habs]
*[http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/research/news/meals_ready_to_eat Plants for food in space]
*[http://www.astrotecture.com/Welcome_files/AIAA-2015-4517.First%20Mars%20Habitat%20Architecture.pdf First Mars Habitat Architecture (AIAA-2015-4517)] (reviews various Mars habs and technology, 2015]
*[https://www.nasa.gov/johnson/HWHAP/living-off-the-land Living off the land (in space)] (Podcast transcript, July 27, 2018, NASA Johnson Space Center)

==External links==
*[http://www.nasa.gov/audience/foreducators/son/habitat/sealed/F_Living_in_a_Sealed_Container_prt.htm Life in a sealed container – NASA (2010)]
*[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/picture-galleries/11896687/Top-10-Mars-habitats-from-NASA-space-habitat-challenge.html?frame=3456038 Telegraph Photo Gallery of Mars Habitats]
*[http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/images/exploration/xhab/html/jsc2011e056018.html Habitat Demonstration Unit (NASA)]
*[http://www.spacearchitect.org/pubs/NASA-CR-189985.pdf Mars Habitat NASA-CR-189985] (.pdf)
*[http://www.marsicehouse.com/ Mars Ice House by SEArch and Clouds AO project site]
*[https://oig.nasa.gov/audits/reports/FY16/IG-16-003.pdf Human health and radiation report (October 2015)] (NASA)
*[http://www.dezeen.com/2015/09/25/foster-partners-concept-3d-printed-mars-habitat-robots-regolith/ Norman and Fosters 3d printed Mars habitat design]
*[https://www.nasa.gov/centers/ames/news/releases/2004/mars/mars.html NASA Ames Mars Habitat images]

{{Human missions to Mars}}

[[Category:Mars]]
[[Category:Colonization of Mars|Habitat]]
[[Category:Human habitats]]</text>
      <sha1>2ek4ad4aowwp1fh6allegqbkzoaqpw9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
