<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Roman technology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14901914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962821973</id>
      <parentid>957098448</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-16T06:33:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ShelfSkewed</username>
        <id>1152308</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed/updated links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="69759" xml:space="preserve">'''Roman technology''' is the collection of techniques, skills, methods, processes, and engineering practices utilized and developed by the civilization of ancient Rome (753 BC – 476 AD).The [[Roman Empire]] was a technologically advanced civilization of antiquity. The Romans incorporated technologies from the [[Ancient Greece|Greeks]], [[Etruscans]], and [[Celts]]. The technology developed by a civilization is limited by the available sources of energy, and the Romans were no different in this sense. Accessible sources of energy, determine the ways in which power is generated. The main types of power accessed by the ancient Romans were human, animal, and water.
[[File:PantheonRoma.jpg|thumb|Artistic rendition of the Pantheon]]
With these limited sources of power, the Romans managed to build impressive structures, some of which survive to this day. The durability of Roman structures, such as roads, dams, and buildings, is accounted for the building techniques and practices they utilized in their construction projects. Rome and her surrounding area contained various types of volcanic materials, which Romans experimented with the creation of building materials, particularly cements and mortars. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Lancaster|first=Lynn|title=Engineering and Technology in the Classical World|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2008|isbn=9780195187311|location=New York|pages=260-266}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with concrete, the Romans used stone, wood, and marble as building materials. They used these materials to construct civil engineering projects for their cities and transportation devices for land and sea travel.

The Romans also contributed to the development of technologies of the battlefield. Warfare was an essential aspect of Roman society and culture. The military was not only used for territorial acquisition and defense, but also as a tool for civilian administrators to use to help staff provincial governments and assist in construction projects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Davies|first=Gwyn|title=Engineering and Technology in the Classical World|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2008|isbn=9780195187311|location=New York|pages=707-710}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Romans adopted, improved, and developed military technologies for foot soldiers, cavalry, and siege weapons for land and sea environments.

Having familiar relations with warfare, the Romans became accustomed to physical injuries. To combat physical injuries sustained in civilian and military spheres, the Romans innovated medical technologies, particularly surgical practices and techniques.  

== Types of power ==

=== Human power ===
The most readily available sources of power to the ancients were human power and animal power. An obvious utilization of human power is the movement of objects. For objects ranging from 20 to 80 pounds a single person can generally suffice. For objects of greater weight, more than one person may be required in the transition of location of the object. A limiting factor in using multiple people in the movement of said object, is the available amount of grip space. To overcome this limiting factor, mechanical devices were developed to assist in the manipulation of objects. One device being the [[windlass]] which used ropes and pulleys to manipulate objects. The device was powered by multiple people pushing or pulling on [[Handspike|handspikes]] attached to a cylinder.

Human power was also a factor in the movement of ships, in particularly warships. Though wind-powered sails were the dominate form of power in water transportation, rowing was often used by military craft during battle engagements.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Landels|first=John G.|title=Engineering in the Ancient World|publisher=Chatto &amp; Windus|year=1978|isbn=0701122218|location=London|pages=9 - 32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Animal power ===
The primary usage of animal power was for transportation. Several species of animals were used for differing tasks. Oxen are strong creatures that do not require the finest pasture. Being strong and cheap to maintain, oxen were used to farm and transport large masses of good. A disadvantage to using oxen is that they are slow. If speed was desired, horses were called upon. The main environment which called for speed was the battlefield, with horses being used in the cavalry and scouting parties. For carriages carrying passengers or light materials, donkeys or mules were generally used, as they were faster than oxen and cheaper on fodder than horses. Other than being used as a means of transportation, animals were also employed in the operation of rotary mills.
[[File:Overshot water wheel schematic ml.svg|left|thumb|Schematic of an Overshot water wheel]]
Beyond the confines of the land, a schematic for a ship propelled by animals has been discovered. The work known as Anonymus [[De rebus bellicis|De Rebus Bellicus]] describes a ship powered by oxen. Wherein oxen are attached to a rotary, moving in a circle on a deck floor, spinning two paddle wheels, one on either side of the ship. The likelihood that such a ship was ever built is low, due to the impracticality of controlling animals on a watercraft.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

=== Water power ===
Power from water was generated through the use of a [[water wheel]]. A water wheel had two general designs: the undershot and the overshot. The undershot water wheel generated power from the natural flow of a running water source pushing upon the wheel’s submerged paddles. The overshot water wheel generated power by having water flow over its buckets from above. This was usually achieved by building an aqueduct above the wheel. Although it is possible to make the overshot water wheel 70 percent more efficient than the undershot, the undershot was generally the preferred water wheel. The reason being, the economic cost to building an aqueduct was too high for the mild benefit of having the water wheel turn faster. The primary purpose of water wheels were to generate power for milling operations and to raise water above a system’s natural height. Evidence also exists that water wheels were used to power the operation of saws, though only scant descriptions of such devices remain.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;
[[File:Hero's Aeolipile, 1st century AD, Alexandria (reconstruction).jpg|thumb|Reconstruction of Hero of Alexandria's steam machine the Aeolipile, 1st century CE]]

=== Wind power ===
Wind power was used in the operation of watercraft, through the use of sails. Windmills do not appear to have been created in Ancient times.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

=== Solar power ===
The Romans used the Sun as a heat source for buildings, such as bath houses. Thermae were built with large windows facing southwest, the location of the Sun at the hottest time of day.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nikolic|first=Milorad|title=Themes in Roman Society and Culture|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2014|isbn=9780195445190|location=Canada|pages=355 - 375}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Theoretical types of power ===

==== Steam power ====
The generation of power through steam remained theoretical in the Roman world. [[Hero of Alexandria]] published schematics of a steam device that rotated a ball on a pivot. The device used heat from a cauldron to push steam through a system of tubes towards the ball. The device produced roughly 1500 rpm but would never be practical on an industrial scale as the labour requirements to operate, fuel and maintain the heat of the device would have been too great of a cost.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; 

==Technology as a craft==
Roman technology was largely based on a system of crafts. Technical skills and knowledge were contained within the particular trade, such as stonemasons. In this sense, knowledge was generally passed down from a tradesman master to a tradesman apprentice. Since there are only a few sources from which to draw upon for technical information, it is theorized that tradesmen kept their knowledge a secret. [[Vitruvius]], [[Pliny the Elder]] and [[Frontinus]] are among the few writers who have published technical information about Roman technology.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; There was a corpus of manuals on basic mathematics and science such as the many books by [[Archimedes]], [[Ctesibius]], [[Hero of Alexandria|Heron (a.k.a. Hero of Alexandria)]], [[Euclid]] and so on. Not all of the manuals which were available to the Romans have survived, as [[lost works]] illustrate.

==Engineering and construction==
{{further information|Roman architecture|Roman engineering}}

=== Building materials and instruments ===
[[File:Roemerkran.jpg|thumb|Reconstruction of a 10.4-metre-high Roman [[treadwheel crane|construction crane]] at [[Bonn]], [[Germany]]|alt=|193x193px|left]]
==== Wood ====
The Romans created fireproof wood by coating the wood with [[alum]].&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Neubuger, Albert|first=and Brose, Henry L|title=The Technical Arts and Sciences of the Ancients|publisher=Macmillan Company|year=1930|isbn=|location=New York|pages=397 - 408}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Stone ====
It was ideal to mine stones from quarries that were situated as close to the site of construction as possible, to reduce the cost of transportation. Stone blocks were formed in quarries by punching holes in lines at the desired lengths and widths. Then, wooden wedges were hammered into the holes. The holes were then filled with water so that the wedges would swell with enough force to cut the stone block out of the Earth. Blocks with the dimensions of 23yds by 14ft by 15ft have been found, with weights of about 1000 tons. There is evidence that saws were developed to cut stone in the Imperial age. Initially, Romans used saws powered by hand to cut stone, but later went on to develop stone cutting saws powered by water.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

====Cements====
The ratio of the mixture of Roman lime mortars depended upon where the sand for the mixture was acquired. For sand gathered at a river or sea, the mixture ratio was two parts sand, one part lime, and one part powdered shells. For sand gathered further inland, the mixture was three parts sand and one part lime. The lime for mortars was prepared in limekilns, which were underground pits designed to block out the wind.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

Another type of Roman mortar is known as [[pozzolana]] mortar. Pozzolana is a volcanic clay substance located in and around Naples. The mixture ratio for the cement was two parts pozzolana and one part lime mortar. Due to its composition, pozzolana cement was able to form in water and has been found to be as hard as natural forming rock.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==== Cranes ====
[[Crane (machine)#Roman Empire|Cranes]] were used for construction work and possibly to load and unload ships at their ports, although for the latter use there is according to the “present state of knowledge” still no evidence.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Matheus: "Mittelalterliche Hafenkräne," in: Uta Lindgren (ed.): Europäische Technik im Mittelalter. 800–1400, Berlin 2001 (4th ed.), pp. 345–48 (345)&lt;/ref&gt; Most cranes were capable of lifting about 6–7 tons of cargo, and according to a relief shown on [[Trajan's column]] were worked by [[treadwheel]].

=== Buildings ===
[[File:Pantheon,_Rome_2.jpg|thumb|The Pantheon constructed 113 - 125 CE|alt=|253x253px]]
==== The Pantheon ====
{{Further information|The Pantheon}}The Romans designed the Pantheon thinking about the concepts of beauty, symmetry, and perfection. The Romans incorporated these mathematical concepts into their public works projects. For instance, the concept of perfect numbers were used in the design of the Pantheon by embedding 28 coffers into the dome. A perfect number is a number where its factors add up to itself. So, the number 28 is considered to be a perfect number, because its factors of 1, 2, 4, 7, and 14 add together to equal 28. Perfect numbers are extremely rare, with there being only one number for each quantity of digits (one for single digits, double digits, triple digits, quadruple digits, etc.). Embodying mathematical concepts of beauty, symmetry, and perfection, into the structure conveys the technical sophistication of Roman engineers. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Marder, Tod A., and|first=Wilson Jones, Mark|title=The Pantheon: From Antiquity to the Present|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2014|isbn=9780521809320|location=New York|pages=102}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cements were essential to the design of the Pantheon. The mortar used in the construction of the dome is made up of a mixture of lime and the volcanic powder known as, pozzolana. The concrete is suited for the use in constructing thick walls as it does not require to be completely dry in order to cure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Marder, Tod A|first=Wilson Jones, Mark|title=The Pantheon: From Antiquity to the Present|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2014|isbn=9780521809320|location=New York|pages=126}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The construction of the Pantheon was a massive undertaking, requiring large quantities of resources and man-hours. Delaine estimates the amount of total manpower needed in the construction the Pantheon to be about 400 000 man-days.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Marder, Tod A|first=Wilson Jones, Mark|title=The Pantheon: From Antiquity to the Present|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2014|isbn=9780521809320|location=New York|pages=173}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
[[File:Hagia Sophia Mars 2013.jpg|left|thumb|Hagia Sophia constructed 537 CE]]

==== Hagia Sophia ====
{{Further information|Hagia Sophia}}Although the Hagia Sophia was constructed after the fall of the Western empire, its construction incorporated the building materials and techniques signature to ancient Rome. The building was constructed using pozzolana mortar. Evidence for the use of the substance comes from the sagging of the structures arches during construction, as a distinguishing feature of pozzalana mortar is the large amount of time it needs to cure. The engineers had to remove decorative walls in order to let the mortar cure.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Livingston|first=R|date=1993|title=Materials Analysis Of The Masonry Of The Hagia Sophia Basilica, Istanbul|journal=WIT Transactions on the Built Environment|volume=3|pages=20-26|via=ProQuest}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pozzalana mortar used in the construction of the Hagia Sophia does not contain volcanic ash but instead crushed brick dust. The composition of the materials used in pozzalana mortar leads to an increased tensile strength. A mortar composed of mostly lime has a tensile strength of roughly 30 psi whereas pozzalana mortar using crushed brick dust has a tensile strength of 500 psi. The advantage of using pozzalana mortar in the construction of the Hagia Sophia is the increase in strength of the joints. The mortar joints used in the structure are wider than one would expect in a typical brick and mortar structure. The fact of the wide mortar joints suggests the designers of the Hagia Sophia knew about the high tensile strength of the mortar and incorporated it accordingly.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt;

=== Waterworks ===

====Aqueducts====
{{further information|Roman aqueduct|Aqueduct (bridge)}}The Romans constructed numerous aqueducts to supply water. The city of [[Rome]] itself was supplied by eleven aqueducts made of limestone that provided the city with over 1 million cubic metres of water each day, sufficient for 3.5 million people even in modern-day times,{{sfn|GRST-engineering}} and with a combined length of {{convert|350|km|mi}}.{{sfn|Frontinus}}
[[File:Roman Aqueduct Segovia 2012 Spain.jpg|thumb|Roman Segovia Aqueduct in modern-day Spain, constructed 1st century CE]]
Water inside the aqueducts depended entirely on gravity. The raised stone channels in which the water traveled were slightly slanted. The water was carried directly from mountain springs. After it had gone through the aqueduct, the water was collected in tanks and fed through pipes to fountains, toilets, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, Fiona "The Usborne Internet Linked Encyclopedia of the Roman World", page 80. Usborne Publishing 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

The main aqueducts in Ancient Rome were the Aqua Claudia and the Aqua Marcia.&lt;ref&gt;Forman, Joan "The Romans", page 34. Macdonald Educational Ltd. 1975&lt;/ref&gt; Most aqueducts were constructed below the surface with only small portions above ground supported by arches.{{sfn|Water History}} The longest Roman aqueduct, {{convert|178|km|mi}} in length, was traditionally assumed to be that which supplied the city of [[Carthage]]. The complex system built to supply Constantinople had its most distant supply drawn from over 120&amp;nbsp;km away along a sinuous route of more than 336&amp;nbsp;km.&lt;ref&gt;J. Crow 2007 "Earth, walls and water in Late Antique Constantinople" in ''Technology in Transition AD 300–650'' in ed. L.Lavan, E.Zanini &amp; A. Sarantis Brill, Leiden&lt;/ref&gt;

Roman aqueducts were built to remarkably fine tolerances, and to a technological standard that was not to be equaled until modern times. Powered entirely by [[gravity]], they transported very large amounts of water very efficiently. Sometimes, where depressions deeper than 50 metres had to be crossed, [[Inverted siphon|inverted siphons]] were used to force water uphill.{{sfn|Water History}} An aqueduct also supplied water for the overshot wheels at [[Barbegal aqueduct and mill|Barbegal]] in [[Roman Gaul]], a complex of water mills hailed as "the greatest known concentration of mechanical power in the ancient world".&lt;ref name="Greene 2000 393"&gt;{{harvnb|Greene|2000|p=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Roman aqueducts conjure images of water travelling long distances across arched bridges, however; only 5 percent of the water being transported along the aqueduct systems traveled by way of bridges. Roman engineers worked to make the routes of aqueducts as practical as possible. In practice, this meant designing aqueducts that flowed ground level or below surface level, as these were more cost effective than building bridges considering the cost of construction and maintenance for bridges was higher than that of surface and sub-surface elevations. Aqueduct bridges were often in need of repairs and spent years at a time in disuse. Water theft from the aqueducts was a frequent problem which led to difficulties in estimating the amount of water flowing through the channels.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Smith|first=Norman|date=1978|title=Roman Hydraulic Technology|journal=Scientific American|volume=238, no. 5|pages=154 - 61|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; To prevent the channels of the aqueducts from eroding, a plaster known as opus signinum was used.&lt;ref name=":52"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nikolic|first=Milorad|title=Themes in Roman Society and Culture|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2014|isbn=9780195445190|location=Canada|pages=355 - 375}}&lt;/ref&gt; The plaster incorporated crushed terracotta in the typical Roman mortar mixture of pozzolana rock and lime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Lancaster|first=Lynn|title=The Oxford Handbook of Engineering and Technology in the Classical World|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2008|isbn=9780195187311|location=New York|pages=261}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Embalse_de_Proserpina,_Mérida_(2015).JPG|thumb|[[Proserpina Dam]] was constructed during the first to second century CE and is still in use today.|alt=|left|205x205px]]

====Dams====
{{Main|List of Roman dams and reservoirs}}
The Romans built [[dams]] for water collection, such as the [[Subiaco Dams]], two of which fed [[Anio Novus]], one of the largest aqueducts of [[Rome]]. They built 72 dams in just one country, [[Spain]] and many more are known across the Empire, some of which are still in use. At one site, Montefurado in [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]], they appear to have built a dam across the river Sil to expose alluvial gold deposits in the bed of the river. The site is near the spectacular Roman gold mine of [[Las Medulas]]. Several earthen dams are known from [[Great Britain|Britain]], including a well-preserved example from Roman Lanchester, [[Longovicium]], where it may have been used in industrial-scale [[smithing]] or [[smelting]], judging by the piles of slag found at this site in northern England. Tanks for holding water are also common along aqueduct systems, and numerous examples are known from just one site, the gold mines at [[Dolaucothi]] in west [[Wales]]. Masonry dams were common in [[North Africa]] for providing a reliable water supply from the [[wadi]]s behind many settlements.

The Romans built dams to store water for irrigation. They understood that spillways were necessary to prevent the erosion of earth-packed banks. In Egypt, the Romans adopted the water technology known as wadi irrigation from the [[Nabataeans]]. Wadis were a technique developed to capture large amounts of water produced during the seasonal floods and store it for the growing season. The Romans successfully developed the technique further for a larger scale.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

====Sanitation====
[[File:Baños Romanos, Bath, Inglaterra, 2014-08-12, DD 39-41 HDR.JPG|thumb|Roman baths in the English city of Bath. A temple was initially constructed on the site in 60 CE with the bathing complex being built up over time.]]
The Romans did not invent plumbing or toilets, but instead borrowed their waste disposal system from their neighbors, particularly the Minoans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.themodernantiquarian.com/site/10854/knossos.html#fieldnotes&lt;/ref&gt; A waste disposal system was not a new invention, but rather had been around since 3100 BCE, when one was created in the Indus River Valley &lt;ref&gt;Bruce, Alexandra. 2012: Science or Superstition: The Definitive Guide to the Doomsday Phenomenon, pg 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman public [[bathing|baths]], or ''[[thermae]]'' served hygienic, social and cultural functions. The baths contained three main facilities for bathing. After undressing in the [[apodyterium]] or changing room, Romans would proceed to the [[tepidarium]] or warm room. In the moderate dry heat of the tepidarium, some performed warm-up exercises and stretched while others oiled themselves or had slaves oil them. The tepidarium’s main purpose was to promote sweating to prepare for the next room, the [[caldarium]] or hot room. The caldarium, unlike the tepidarium, was extremely humid and hot. Temperatures in the caldarium could reach 40 degrees [[Celsius]] (104 degrees Fahrenheit). Many contained steam baths and a cold-water fountain known as the [[Labrum (architecture)|labrum]]. The last room was the [[frigidarium]] or cold room, which offered a cold bath for cooling off after the caldarium.
The Romans also had [[flush toilet]]s.

==== Roman baths ====
{{Further information|Thermae}}The containment of heat in the rooms was important in the operation of the baths, as to avoid patrons from catching colds. To prevent doors from being left open, the door posts were installed at an inclined angle so that the doors would automatically swing shut. Another technique of heat efficiency was the use of wooden benches over stone, as wood conducts away less heat.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Neuburger, Albert and|first=Brose, Henry L|title=The Technical Arts and Sciences of the Ancients|publisher=Macmillan Company|year=1930|isbn=|location=New York|pages=366 - 76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transportation ===
[[File:RomaViaAppiaAntica03 retouched.jpg|left|thumb|The Via Appia constructed 312–264 BCE |alt=]]

====Roads====
{{Main|Roman road}}
The Romans primarily built roads for their military. Their economic importance was probably also significant, although wagon traffic was often banned from the roads to preserve their military value. In total, more than {{Convert|400,000|km|mi|abbr=}} of roads were constructed, {{Convert|80,500|km|mi|abbr=}} of which were stone-paved.&lt;ref&gt;Gabriel, Richard A. ''The Great Armies of Antiquity''. Westport, Conn: Praeger, 2002. [https://books.google.com/books?id=y1ngxn_xTOIC&amp;pg=PA9 Page 9.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Way stations providing refreshments were maintained by the government at regular intervals along the roads. A separate system of changing stations for official and private couriers was also maintained. This allowed a dispatch to travel a maximum of {{convert|800|km|mi}} in 24 hours by using a relay of horses.

The roads were constructed by digging a pit along the length of the intended course, often to [[bedrock]]. The pit was first filled with rocks, gravel or sand and then a layer of concrete. Finally, they were paved with polygonal rock slabs. Roman roads are considered the most advanced roads built until the early 19th century. Bridges were constructed over waterways. The roads were resistant to floods and other environmental hazards. After the fall of the Roman Empire the roads were still usable and used for more than 1000 years.

Most Roman cities were shaped like a square. There were 4 main roads leading to the center of the city, or forum. They formed a cross shape, and each point on the edge of the cross was a gateway into the city. Connecting to these main roads were smaller roads, the streets where people lived.

====Bridges====
{{Further information|Roman bridge|List of Roman bridges}}
Roman bridges were built with stone and/or concrete and utilized the [[arch]]. Built in 142 BC, the [[Pons Aemilius]], later named ''Ponte Rotto'' (broken bridge) is the oldest Roman stone bridge in Rome, Italy. The biggest Roman bridge was [[Trajan's bridge]] over the lower Danube, constructed by [[Apollodorus of Damascus]], which remained for over a millennium the longest bridge to have been built both in terms of overall and span length. They were most of the time at least {{convert|60|ft}} above the body of water.

==== Carts ====
[[File:Bridge Alcantara.JPG|thumb|Alcantara Bridge constructed in 104 to 106 CE, was built in a similar in style to Trajan's Bridge.|alt=]]
Roman carts had many purposes and came in a variety of forms. Freight carts were used to transport goods. Barrel carts were used to transport liquids. The carts had large cylindrical barrels laid horizontally with their tops facing forward. For transporting building materials, such as sand or soil, the Romans used carts with high walls. Public transportation carts were also in use with some designed with sleeping accommodations for up to six people.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rossi, Cesare, Thomas Chondros|first=G. Milidonis, Kypros Savino, and F. Russo|date=2016|title=Ancient Road Transport Devices: Developments from the Bronze Age to the Roman Empire|journal=Frontiers of Mechanical Engineering|volume=11, no.1|pages=12 - 25|via=Springer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Romans developed a railed cargo system for transporting heavy loads. The rails consisted of grooves embedded into existing stone roadways. The carts used in such a system had large block axles and wooden wheels with metal casings.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Carts also contained brakes, elastic suspensions and bearings. The elastic suspension systems used leather belts attached bronze supports to suspend the carriage above the axles. The system helped to create a smoother ride by reducing the vibration. The Romans adopted bearings developed by the Celts. The bearings decreased rotational friction by using mud to lubricate stone rings.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; 

=== Industrial ===
[[File:Rosia Montana Roman Gold Mines 2011 - Galleries.jpg|left|thumb|Rosia Montana Roman Gold Mine]]

====Mining====
{{further information|Roman metallurgy|Roman mining}}

The Romans also made great use of aqueducts in their extensive mining operations across the empire, some sites such as [[Las Medulas]] in north-west Spain having at least 7 major channels entering the minehead. Other sites such as [[Dolaucothi]] in south [[Wales]] was fed by at least 5 [[leat]]s, all leading to reservoirs and tanks or [[cistern]]s high above the present opencast. The water was used for [[hydraulic mining]], where streams or waves of water are released onto the hillside, first to reveal any gold-bearing ore, and then to work the ore itself. Rock debris could be sluiced away by [[hushing]], and the water also used to douse fires created to break down the hard rock and veins, a method known as [[fire-setting]].

Alluvial [[gold]] deposits could be worked and the [[gold]] extracted without needing to crush the ore. Washing tables were fitted below the tanks to collect the gold-dust and any nuggets present. Vein gold needed crushing, and they probably used crushing or stamp mills worked by water-wheels to comminute the hard ore before washing. Large quantities of water were also needed in deep mining to remove waste debris and power primitive machines, as well as for washing the crushed ore. [[Pliny the Elder]] provides a detailed description of gold mining in book xxxiii of his [[Naturalis Historia]], most of which has been confirmed by [[archaeology]]. That they used water mills on a large scale elsewhere is attested by the flour mills at [[Barbegal]] in southern [[France]], and on the [[Janiculum]] in [[Rome]].

==Military Technology==
{{further information|Technological history of the Roman military|Roman military engineering}}The Roman military technology ranged from personal equipment and armament to deadly siege engines.

=== Foot Soldier ===

==== Weaponry ====
[[Pilum]] (spear): The Roman heavy spear was a weapon favored by legionaries and weighed approximately five pounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thudscave.com/npaa/articles/howhard_10-04.pdf|title=HOW Hard Does It Hit? A Study of Atlatl and Dart Ballistics|last=Hrdlicka|first=Daryl|date=October 29, 2004|website=Thudscave (PDF)|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The innovated javelin was designed to be used only once and was destroyed upon initial use. This ability prevented the enemy from reusing spears. All soldiers carried two versions of this weapon: a primary spear and a backup. A solid block of wood in the middle of the weapon provided legionaries protection for their hands while carrying the device. According to [[Polybius]], historians have records of "how the Romans threw their spears and then charged with swords".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Zhmodikov|first=Alexander|date=September 5, 2017|title=Roman Republican Heavy Infantrymen in Battle (IV-II Centuries B.C.)|url=|journal=Historia: Zeitschrift für Alte Geschichte|volume=49|issue=1|pages=67–78|jstor=4436566}}&lt;/ref&gt; This tactic seemed to be common practice among Roman infantry.

==== Armour ====
[[File:Roman scale armour detail.JPG|thumb|Roman Scale Armour]]
While heavy, intricate armour was not uncommon ([[cataphracts]]), the Romans perfected a relatively light, full torso armour made of segmented plates ([[lorica segmentata]]). This segmented armour provided good protection for vital areas, but did not cover as much of the body as [[lorica hamata]] or chainmail. The lorica segmentata provided better protection, but the plate bands were expensive and difficult to produce and difficult to repair in the field. Generally, chainmail was cheaper, easier to produce, and simpler to maintain, was one-size-fits-all, and was more comfortable to wear – thus, it remained the primary form of armour even when lorica segmentata was in use.

==== Tactics ====
'''[[Testudo formation|Testudo]]''' is a tactical military maneuver original to Rome. The tactic was implemented by having units raise their shields in order to protect themselves from enemy projectiles raining down on them. The strategy only worked if each member of the testudo protected his comrade. Commonly used during siege battles, the “sheer discipline and synchronization required to form a Testudo” was a testament to the abilities of legionnaires.&lt;ref name=":15"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.realmofhistory.com/2016/11/11/10-roman-military-innovations-facts/|title=10 Incredible Roman Military Innovations You Should Know About|last=M|first=Dattatreya|last2=al|date=2016-11-11|website=Realm of History|access-date=2017-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Testudo, meaning tortoise in Latin, “was not the norm, but rather adopted in specific situations to deal with particular threats on the battlefield”.&lt;ref name=":15" /&gt; The Greek phalanx and other Roman formations were a source of inspiration for this maneouver.

=== Cavalry ===
The Roman cavalry saddle had four horns [http://www.caerleon.net/history/army/page9.html] and is believed to have been copied from [[Celts|Celtic]] peoples.

=== Siege warfare ===
Roman siege engines such as [[Ballista|ballistas]], [[Scorpio (dart-thrower)|scorpions]] and [[Onager (siege weapon)|onagers]] were not unique. But the Romans were probably the first people to put ballistas on carts for better mobility on campaigns. On the battlefield, it is thought that they were used to pick off enemy leaders. There is one account of the use of artillery in battle from Tacitus, Histories III,23:&lt;blockquote&gt;On engaging they drove back the enemy, only to be driven back themselves, for the Vitellians had concentrated their artillery on the raised road that they might have free and open ground from which to fire; their earlier shots had been scattered and had struck the trees without injuring the enemy. A ballista of enormous size belonging to the Fifteenth legion began to do great harm to the Flavians' line with the huge stones that it hurled; and it would have caused wide destruction if it had not been for the splendid bravery of two soldiers, who, taking some shields from the dead and so disguising themselves, cut the ropes and springs of the machine''.''&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.livius.org/articles/concept/corvus/|title=Corvus – Livius|website=www.livius.org|language=en|access-date=2017-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;In addition to innovations in land warfare, the Romans also developed the [[Corvus (boarding device)]] a movable bridge that could attach itself to an enemy ship and allow the Romans to board the enemy vessel. Developed during the [[First Punic War]] it allowed them to apply their experience in land warfare on the seas.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

==== Ballistas and onagers ====
{{Further information|Ballista}}While core artillery inventions were notably founded by the Greeks, Rome saw opportunity in the ability to enhance this long range artillery. Large artillery pieces such as Carroballista and Onagers bombarded enemy lines, before full ground assault by infantry. The manuballista would "often be described as the most advanced two-armed torsion engine used by the Roman Army”.&lt;ref name=":122"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.realmofhistory.com/2016/11/11/10-roman-military-innovations-facts/|title=10 Incredible Roman Military Innovations You Should Know About|last=M|first=Dattatreya|last2=al|date=2016-11-11|website=Realm of History|access-date=2017-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The weapon often looks like a mounted crossbow capable of shooting projectiles. Similarly, the onager “named after the wild ass because of its ‘kick’," was a larger weapon that was capable of hurling large projectiles at walls or forts.&lt;ref name=":122" /&gt; Both were very capable machines of war and were put to use by the Roman military.[[File:Helepolis.png|thumb|Computer model of a helepolis|alt=|left]]

==== The Helepolis ====
{{Further information|helepolis}}The helepolis was a transportation vehicle used to besiege cities. The vehicle had wooden walls to shield soldiers as they were transported toward the enemy’s walls. Upon reaching the walls, the soldiers would disembark at the top of the 15m tall structure and drop on to the enemy’s ramparts. To be effective in combat, the helepolis was designed to be self-propelled. The self-propelled vehicles were operated using two types of motors: an internal motor powered by humans, or a counterweight motor powered by gravity. The human-powered motor used a system of ropes that connected the axles to a capstan. It has been calculated that at least 30 men would be required to turn the capstan in order to exceed the force required to move the vehicle. Two capstans may have been used instead of just the one, reducing the amount of men needed per capstan to 16, for a total of 32 to power the helepolis. The gravity-powered counterweight motor used a system of ropes and pulleys to propel the vehicle. Ropes were wrapped around the axles, strung through a pulley system that connected them to a counterweight hanging at the top of the vehicle. The counterweights would have been made of lead or a bucket filled with water. The lead counterweight was encapsulated in a pipe filled with seeds to control its fall. The water bucket counterweight was emptied when it reached the bottom of the vehicle, raised back to the top, and filled with water using a reciprocating water pump, so that motion could again be achieved. It has been calculated that to move a helepolis with a mass of 40000kg, a counterweight with a mass of 1000kg was needed.&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rossi, Cesare, Thomas Chondros|first=G. Milidonis, Kypros Savino, and F. Russo|date=2016|title=Ancient Road Transport Devices: Developments from the Bronze Age to the Roman Empire|journal=Frontiers of Mechanical Engineering|volume=11, no.1|pages=12 - 25|via=Springer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Greek fire ====
{{Further information|Greek fire}}Originally an incendiary weapon adopted from the Greeks in 7th century AD, the Greek fire “is one of the very few contrivances whose gruesome effectiveness was noted by”&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.realmofhistory.com/2016/11/11/10-roman-military-innovations-facts/|title=10 Incredible Roman Military Innovations You Should Know About|last=M|first=Dattatreya|last2=al|date=2016-11-11|website=Realm of History|access-date=2017-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; many sources. Roman innovators made this already lethal weapon even more deadly. Its nature is often described as a “precursor to napalm".&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; Military strategists often put the weapon to good use during naval battles, and the ingredients to its construction “remained a closely guarded military secret”.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; Despite this, the devastation caused by Greek fire in combat is indisputable.
[[File:Roman Pontoon Bridge, Column of Marcus Aurelius, Rome, Italy.jpg|thumb|Depiction of a Roman Pontoon Bridge on the Column of Marcus Aurelius, constructed 193 CE|alt=]]

=== Transportation ===

==== Pontoon bridge ====
{{Further information|Pontoon bridge}}Mobility, for a military force, was an essential key to success. Although this was not a Roman invention, as there were instances of "ancient Chinese and Persians making use of the floating mechanism”,&lt;ref name=":14"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.realmofhistory.com/2016/11/11/10-roman-military-innovations-facts/|title=10 Incredible Roman Military Innovations You Should Know About|last=M|first=Dattatreya|last2=al|date=2016-11-11|website=Realm of History|access-date=2017-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roman generals used the innovation to great effect in campaigns. Furthermore, engineers perfected the speed at which these bridges were constructed. Leaders surprised enemy units to great effect by speedily crossing otherwise treacherous bodies of water. Lightweight crafts were “organized and tied together with the aid of planks, nails and cables”.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt; Rafts were more commonly used instead of building new makeshift bridges, enabling quick construction and deconstruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hodges|first=Henry|title=Technology in the Ancient World|publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble Publishing|year=1992|isbn=|location=|pages=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; The expedient and valuable innovation of the pontoon bridge also accredited its success to the excellent abilities of Roman Engineers.

== Medical technology ==
[[File:Graeco-Roman surgical instruments. Wellcome L0012385.jpg|thumb|189x189px|Surgical instruments used by ancient Romans]]
{{Further information|Military medicine}}

=== Surgery ===
Although various levels of medicine were practiced in the ancient world,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cuomo|first=S.|title=Technology and Culture in Greek and Roman Antiquity|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2007|isbn=|location=Cambridge, U.K.|pages=17–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Romans created or pioneered many innovative surgeries and tools that are still in use today such as hemostatic tourniquets and arterial surgical clamps.&lt;ref name=":022"&gt;{{Cite news|last=Andrews|first=Evan|url=http://www.history.com/news/history-lists/10-innovations-that-built-ancient-rome|title=10 Innovations That Built Ancient Rome|date=November 20, 2012|work=The History Channel|access-date=2017-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rome was also responsible for producing the first battlefield surgery unit, a move that paired with their contributions to medicine made the Roman army a force to be reckoned with.&lt;ref name=":022" /&gt; They also used a rudimentary version of antiseptic surgery years before its use became popular in the 19th century and possessed very capable doctors.&lt;ref name=":022" /&gt;

==Technologies developed or invented by the Romans==
{| class="wikitable mw-collapsible"
|-
! Technology
! Comment
|-
| [[Roman abacus|Abacus, Roman]]
| Portable.
|-
| [[Alum]]
| The production of alum (KAl(SO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.12H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O) from alunite (KAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;(SO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;.&lt;/sup&gt;(OH)&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;) is archaeologically attested on the island Lesbos.&lt;ref&gt;A. Archontidou 2005 Un atelier de preparation de l'alun a partir de l'alunite dans l'isle de Lesbos in L'alun de Mediterranee ed P.Borgard et al.&lt;/ref&gt; This site was abandoned in the 7th century but dates back at least to the 2nd century AD.
|-
| [[Amphitheatre]]
| See e.g. [[Colosseum]].
|-
| [[Roman aqueduct|Aqueduct]], true arch
| [[Pont du Gard]], [[Segovia]] etc.
|-
| [[Arch]], monumental
|
|-
| Bath, monumental public ([[Thermae]])
| See e.g. [[Baths of Diocletian]]
|-
| Book ([[Codex]])
| First mentioned by [[Martial]] in the 1st century AD. Held many advantages over the scroll.
|-
| Brass
| The Romans had enough understanding of [[zinc]] to produce a [[brass]] denomination coinage; see [[sestertius]].
|-
| [[Roman bridge|Bridge, true arch]]
| See e.g. [[Roman bridge in Chaves]] or the [[Severan Bridge]].
|-
| Bridge, segmental arch
| More than a dozen Roman bridges are known to feature segmental (=flat) arches. A prominent example was [[Trajan's bridge]] over the Danube, a lesser known the extant [[Limyra Bridge]] in Lycia
|-
| Bridge, pointed arch
| Constructed in the early [[Byzantine]] era, the earliest known bridge featuring a pointed arch is the 5th or 6th century AD [[Karamagara Bridge]]&lt;ref name="Galliazzo 1995, 92"&gt;{{harvnb|Galliazzo|1995|p=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Camel harness
| The harnessing of camels to ploughs is attested in North Africa by the 3rd century AD&lt;ref&gt;R.W.Bulliet, The Camel and the Wheel 1975; 197&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Cameo (carving)|Cameos]]
| Probably a Hellenistic innovation e.g. [[Cup of the Ptolemies]] but taken up by the Emperors e.g. [[Gemma Augustea]], [[Gemma Claudia]] etc.
|-
| Cast Iron
| Recently archaeologically detected in the Val Gabbia in northern Lombardy from the 5th and 6th centuries AD.&lt;ref&gt;Giannichedda 2007 "Metal production in Late Antiquity" in ''Technology in Transition AD 300–650'' ed L. Lavan E.Zanini &amp; A. Sarantis Brill, Leiden; p200&lt;/ref&gt; This technically interesting innovation appears to have had little economic impact. But archaeologists may have failed to recognize the distinctive slag, so the date and location of this innovation may be revised.
|-
| [[Cement]]
[[Concrete]]
| [[Pozzolana]] variety
|-
| [[Crank (mechanism)|Crank]] handle
| A Roman iron crank handle was excavated in [[Augusta Raurica]], Switzerland. The 82.5&amp;nbsp;cm long piece with a 15&amp;nbsp;cm long handle is of yet unknown purpose and dates to no later than c. 250 AD.&lt;ref name="Laur-Belart 1988"&gt;{{harvnb|Laur-Belart|1988|pp=51–52, 56, fig. 42}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Crank and [[connecting rod]]
| Found in several water-powered [[saw mill]]s dating from the late 3rd ([[Hierapolis sawmill]]) to 6th century AD (at [[Ephesus]] respectively [[Gerasa]]).&lt;ref name="Ritti, Grewe, Kessener 2007, 161"&gt;{{harvnb|Ritti|Grewe|Kessener|2007|p=161}}; {{harvnb|Grewe|2009|pp=429–454}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Crane (machine)#Roman Empire|Crane, treadwheel]]
|
|-
| [[Arch dam|Dam, Arch]]&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|1971|pp=33–35}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1978|p=31}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1987a|p=12}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1987c|p=80}}; {{harvnb|Hodge|1992|p=82, table 39}}; {{harvnb|Hodge|2000|p=332, fn. 2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Currently best attested for [[Glanum Dam|the dam at Glanum]], France dated c. 20 BC.&lt;ref&gt;S. Agusta-Boularot et J-l. Paillet 1997 "le Barrage et l'Aqueduc occidental de Glanum: le premier barrage-vout de l'historire des techniques?" ''Revue Archeologique'' pp 27–78&lt;/ref&gt; The structure has entirely disappeared. Its existence attested from the cuts into the rock on either side to key in the dam wall, which was 14.7 metres high, 3.9m thick at base narrowing to 2.96m at the top. Earliest description of arch action in such types of dam by [[Procopius]] around 560 AD, the [[Dara Dam]]&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schnitter|1978|p=32}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1987a|p=13}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1987c|p=80}}; {{harvnb|Hodge|1992|p=92}}; {{harvnb|Hodge|2000|p=332, fn. 2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Arch-gravity dam|Dam, Arch-gravity]]
| Examples include curved dams at Orükaya,&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{harvnb|Schnitter|1987a|p=12}}; {{harvnb|James|Chanson|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Çavdarhisar]], both Turkey (and 2nd century)&lt;ref name="ReferenceA" /&gt;[[Kasserine Dam]] in Tunisia,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|1971|pp=35f.}}; {{harvnb|James|Chanson|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Puy Foradado Dam]] in Spain (2nd–3rd century)&lt;ref name="Arenillas &amp; Castillo 2003"&gt;{{harvnb|Arenillas|Castillo|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Dam, Bridge
| The Band-i-Kaisar, constructed by Roman prisoners of war in Shustar, Persia, in the 3rd century AD,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schnitter|1987a|p=13}}; {{harvnb|Hodge|2000|pp=337f.}}&lt;/ref&gt; featured a [[weir]] combined with an arch bridge, a multifunctional hydraulic structure which subsequently spread throughout Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Vogel|1987|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Buttress dam|Dam, Buttress]]
| Attested in [[List of Roman dams and reservoirs|a number of Roman dams]] in Spain,&lt;ref name="Arenillas &amp; Castillo 2003" /&gt; like the 600&amp;nbsp;m long [[Consuegra Dam]]
|-
| [[Arch dam#Variations|Dam, Multiple Arch Buttress]]
| [[Esparragalejo Dam]], Spain (1st century AD) earliest known&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schnitter|1978|p=29}}; {{harvnb|Schnitter|1987b|pp=60, table 1, 62}}; {{harvnb|James|Chanson|2002}}; {{harvnb|Arenillas|Castillo|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Dome]], monumental
| See e.g. [[Pantheon, Rome|Pantheon]].
|-
| ''Flos Salis''
| A product of salt evaporation ponds ''[[Dunaliella salina]]''&lt;ref&gt;I. Longhurst 2007 ''Ambix'' 54.3 pp. 299–304 The identity of Pliny's ''Flos salis'' and Roman Perfume&lt;/ref&gt; used in the perfume industry (Pliny ''Nat. Hist. 31,90'')
|-
| [[Force pump]] used in fire engine
| See image of pointable nozzle
|-
| [[Glass blowing]]
| This led to a number of innovations in the use of glass. Window glass is attested at Pompeii in AD 79. In the 2nd century AD&lt;ref&gt;C-H Wunderlich "Light and economy: an essay about the economy of pre-historic and ancient lamps" in ''Nouveautes lychnologiques 2003''&lt;/ref&gt; hanging glass oil lamps were introduced. These used floating wicks and by reducing self-shading gave more lumens in a downwards direction. Cage cups (see photograph) are hypothesised as oil lamps.
|-
|
| Dichroic glass as in the [[Lycurgus Cup]]. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070403121640/http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/science/lycurguscup/sr-lycugus-p1.html] Note, this material attests otherwise unknown chemistry (or other way?) to generate nano-scale gold-silver particles.
|-
|
| Glass mirrors ([[Pliny the Elder]] [[Naturalis Historia]] 33,130'')
|-
| Greenhouse cold frames
| ([[Pliny the Elder]] [[Naturalis Historia]] 19.64; [[Columella]] on Ag. 11.3.52)
|-
| [[Water organ|Hydraulis]]
| A water organ. Later also the pneumatic organ.
|-
| [[Hushing]]
| Described by [[Pliny the Elder]] and confirmed at [[Dolaucothi]] and [[Las Médulas]]
|-
| [[Hydraulic mining]]
| Described by [[Pliny the Elder]] and confirmed at [[Dolaucothi]] and [[Las Médulas]]
|-
| [[Hydrometer]]
| Mentioned in a letter of [[Synesius]]
|-
| [[Hypocaust]]
| A floor and also wall heating system. Described by [[Vitruvius]]
|-
| Knife, multifunctional
| [https://web.archive.org/web/20081207064108/http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/opac/search/cataloguedetail.html?&amp;priref=70534&amp;_function_=xslt&amp;_limit_=10]
|-
| Lighthouses
| The best surviving examples are those at [[Dover castle]] and the [[Tower of Hercules]] at [[A Coruña]]
|-
| Leather, Tanned
| The preservation of skins with vegetable tannins was a pre-Roman invention but not of the antiquity once supposed. (Tawing was far more ancient.) The Romans were responsible for spreading this technology into areas where it was previously unknown such as Britain and [[Qasr Ibrim]] on the Nile. In both places this technology was lost when the Romans withdrew.&lt;ref&gt;C. van Driel-Murray Ancient skin processing and the impact of Rome on tanning technology in ''Le Travail du cuir de la prehistoire'' 2002 Antibes&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Mills
| M.J.T.Lewis presents good evidence that water powered vertical pounding machines came in by the middle of the 1st century AD for [[fulling]], grain hulling (Pliny ''Nat. Hist. 18,97'') and ore crushing (archaeological evidence at [[Dolaucothi Gold Mines]] and Spain).
|-
|
| Grainmill, rotary. According to Moritz (p57) rotary grainmills were not known to the ancient Greeks but date from before 160 BC. Unlike reciprocating mills, rotary mills could be easily adapted to animal or water power. Lewis (1997) argues that the rotary grainmill dates to the 5th century BC in the western Mediterranean. Animal and water powered rotary mills came in the 3rd century BC.
|-
|
| Sawmill, water powered. Recorded by 370 AD. Attested in [[Decimus Magnus Ausonius|Ausonius's]] poem Mosella. Translated [http://www.parsonsd.co.uk/moselle12.php]"''the Ruwer sends mill-stones swiftly round to grind the corn, And drives shrill saw-blades through smooth marble blocks''". Recent archaeological evidence from Phrygia, Anatolia, now pushes back the date to the 3rd century AD and confirms the use of a crank in the sawmill.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ritti|Grewe|Kessener|2007|p=154}}; {{harvnb|Grewe|2009|pp=429–454}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
| Shipmill, (though small, the conventional term is "shipmill" not boat mill, probably because there was always a deck, and usually an enclosed superstructure, to keep the flour away from the damp) where water wheels were attached to [[boat]]s, was first recorded at Rome in 547 AD in [[Procopius of Caesarea]]'s ''Gothic Wars'' (1.19.8–29) when [[Belisaurius]] was besieged there.
|-
| Essentials of the [[Steam engine]]
| By the late 3rd century AD, all essential elements for constructing a steam engine were known by Roman engineers: steam power (in [[Hero of Alexandria|Hero]]'s [[aeolipile]]), the crank and connecting rod mechanism (in the [[Hierapolis sawmill]]), the cylinder and piston (in metal force pumps), non-return valves (in water pumps) and gearing (in water mills and clocks)&lt;ref name="RittiGrewe"&gt;{{harvnb|Ritti|Grewe|Kessener|2007|p=156, fn. 74}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
| [[Watermill]]. Improvements upon earlier models. For the largest mill complex known see [[Barbegal]]
|-
| Mercury [[Gilding]]
| as in the [[Horses of San Marco]]
|-
| Newspaper, rudimentary
| See [[Acta Diurna]].
|-
| [[Odometer]]
|
|-
| [[Paddle steamer|Paddle wheel boats]]
| In [[de Rebus Bellicis]] (possibly only a paper invention).
|-
| [[Pewter]]
| Mentioned by [[Pliny the Elder]] ([[Naturalis Historia]] 34, 160–1). Surviving examples are mainly Romano-British of the 3rd and 4th centuries e.g.[https://web.archive.org/web/20080506121240/http://www.romanbaths.co.uk/index.cfm?fuseAction=collection.disp&amp;objectID=batrm_1983_13_c_4] and [http://www.wessexarch.co.uk/projects/cambridgeshire/cambourne/pewter.html]. Roman pewter had a wide range of proportions of tin but proportions of 50%, 75% and 95% predominate (Beagrie 1989).
|-
| Pleasure lake
| An artificial reservoir, highly unusual in that it was meant for recreational rather than utilitarian purposes was created at [[Subiaco, Italy|Subiaco]], Italy, for emperor [[Nero]] (54–68 AD). The dam remained the highest in the [[Roman Empire]] (50&amp;nbsp;m),&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|1970|pp=60f.}}; {{harvnb|Smith|1971|p=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the world until its destruction in 1305.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hodge|1992|p=87}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Plough]]
|
|-
|
| [[iron]]-bladed (A much older innovation (e.g. Bible; I Samuel 13, 20–1) that became much more common in the Roman period)
|-
|
| wheeled ([[Pliny the Elder]] [[Naturalis Historia]] 18. 171–3) (More important for the Middle Ages, than this era.)
|-
| Pottery, glossed
| i.e. [[Samian ware]]
|-
| [[Reaper]]
| An early harvesting machine: ''vallus'' ([[Pliny the Elder]] [[Naturalis Historia]] 18,296, [[Rutilius Taurus Aemilianus Palladius|Palladius]] ''7.2.2–4'' [https://web.archive.org/web/20080505210942/http://www.gnrtr.com/tendencies/en/t08.html])
|-
| [[Fore-and-aft rig|Sails, fore-and-aft rig]]
| Introduction of fore-and-aft rigs 1) the [[Lateen]] sail 2) the [[Spritsail]], this last already attested in 2nd century BC in the northern [[Aegean Sea]]&lt;ref&gt;Casson, Lionel (1995). ''Ships and Seamanship in the Ancient World''. The Johns Hopkins University Press. {{ISBN|0-8018-5130-0}}, Appendix&lt;/ref&gt; Note: there is no evidence of any combination of fore-and-aft rigs with square sails on the same Roman ship.
|-
| [[Lateen sail|Sails, Lateen]]
| Representations show lateen sails in the Mediterranean as early as the 2nd century AD. Both the quadrilateral and the triangular type were employed.&lt;ref name="Casson 1995, 243–245"&gt;{{harvnb|Casson|1995|pp=243–245}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Casson|1954|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|White|1978|p=255}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Campbell|1995|pp=8–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Basch|2001|pp=63–64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Makris|2002|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Friedman|Zoroglu|2006|pp=113–114}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pryor|Jeffreys|2006|pp=153–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Castro|Fonseca|Vacas|Ciciliot|2008|pp=1–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Whitewright|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Roller bearings
| Archaeologically attested in the Lake [[Nemi ships]]&lt;ref&gt;''Il Museo delle navi romane di Nemi'' : Moretti, Giuseppe, d. 1945. Roma : La Libreria dello stato&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Rudder, stern-mounted
| See image for something very close to being a sternpost rudder
|-
| Sausage, fermented dry (probably)
| See [[salami]].
|-
| Screw press
| An innovation of about the mid-1st century AD&lt;ref&gt;H Schneider Technology in ''The Cambridge Economic History of the Greco-Roman World'' 2007; p157 CUP&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Sanitary sewer|Sewers]]
| See for example [[Cloaca Maxima]]
|-
| Soap, hard (sodium)
| First mentioned by [[Galen]] (earlier, potassium, soap being Celtic).
|-
| [[Stairway#Spiral and helical stairs|Spiral staircase]]
| Though first attested as early as the 5th century BC in Greek [[Selinunte]], spiral staircases only become more widespread after their adoption in [[Trajan's column]] and the [[Column of Marcus Aurelius]].
|-
| [[Stenography]], a system of
| See [[Tironian notes]].
|-
| Street map, early
| See [[Forma Urbis Romae]] (Severan Marble Plan), a carved marble ground plan of every architectural feature in ancient Rome.&lt;ref&gt;[http://formaurbis.stanford.edu/ Stanford University: Forma Urbis Romae]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Sundial, portable
| See [[Theodosius of Bithynia]]
|-
| [[Surgical instruments]], various
|
|-
| Tooth implants, iron
| From archaeological evidence in Gaul&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/43705.stm BBC: Tooth and nail dentures]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Towpath
| e.g. beside the Danube, see the "road" in [[Trajan's bridge]]
|-
| Tunnels
| Excavated from both ends simultaneously. The longest known is the {{convert|5.6|km|mi|adj=on}} drain of the [[Fucine lake]]
|-
| Vehicles, one wheeled
| Solely attested by a Latin word in 4th century AD [[Scriptores Historiae Augustae]] Heliogabalus 29. As this is fiction, the evidence dates to its time of writing.
|-
| [[Wood veneer]]
| Pliny ''Nat. Hist. 16. 231–2''
|}

==See also==
{{too many see alsos|date=January 2017}}

* [[Maritime hydraulics in antiquity]]
* ''[[De Architectura]]''
* [[Ancient Greek technology]]
* [[History of science in Classical Antiquity]]
* [[List of Byzantine inventions]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{ citation | doi = 10.2307/3184857 | last = Wilson | first = Andrew | author-link = Andrew Wilson (classical archaeologist) | year = 2002 | title = Machines, Power and the Ancient Economy | periodical = [[The Journal of Roman Studies]] | volume = 92 | pages = 1–32 | jstor = 3184857 | publisher = Society for the Promotion of Roman Studies, Cambridge University Press }}
* {{ citation | doi = 10.1111/1468-0289.00151 | last = Greene | first = Kevin | year = 2000 | title = Technological Innovation and Economic Progress in the Ancient World: M.I. Finley Re-Considered | periodical = The Economic History Review | volume = 53 | issue = 1 | pages = 29–59 }}
* Derry, Thomas Kingston and Trevor I. Williams. ''A Short History of Technology: From the Earliest Times to A.D. 1900.'' New York : Dover Publications, 1993
* Williams, Trevor I. ''A History of Invention From Stone Axes to Silicon Chips.'' New York, New York, Facts on File, 2000
* {{citation | last = Lewis | first = M. J. T. | contribution = Railways in the Greek and Roman world | title = Early Railways. A Selection of Papers from the First International Early Railways Conference | editor-last = Guy | editor-first = A. | editor2-last = Rees | editor2-first = J. | pages = 8–19 (10–15) | year = 2001 | url = http://www.sciencenews.gr/docs/diolkos.pdf | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://www.webcitation.org/5oAdDX3dj | archivedate = 2010-03-12 }}
* {{ citation | last = Galliazzo | first = Vittorio | title = I ponti romani | volume = Vol. 1 | year = 1995 | publisher = Edizioni Canova | location = Treviso | isbn = 88-85066-66-6 | pages = 92, 93 (fig. 39) }}
* {{ citation | last = Werner | first = Walter | title = The largest ship trackway in ancient times: the Diolkos of the Isthmus of Corinth, Greece, and early attempts to build a canal | journal = [[Nautical Archaeology Society#International Journal of Nautical Archaeology|The International Journal of Nautical Archaeology]] | volume = 26 | issue = 2 | pages = 98–119 | year = 1997 | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-9270.1997.tb01322.x }}
* Neil Beagrie, "The Romano-British Pewter Industry", ''Britannia'', Vol. 20 (1989), pp.&amp;nbsp;169–91
* {{citation | last = Grewe | first = Klaus | editor-last = Bachmann | editor-first = Martin | contribution = Die Reliefdarstellung einer antiken Steinsägemaschine aus Hierapolis in Phrygien und ihre Bedeutung für die Technikgeschichte. Internationale Konferenz 13.−16. Juni 2007 in Istanbul | title = Bautechnik im antiken und vorantiken Kleinasien | url = http://www.freundeskreis-roemerkanal.de/Text/BAUTECHNIK%20IM%20ANTIKEN%20UND.pdf | series = Byzas | volume = 9 | publisher = Ege Yayınları/Zero Prod. Ltd. | location = Istanbul | year = 2009 | isbn = 978-975-8072-23-1 | pages = 429–454 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110511200049/http://www.freundeskreis-roemerkanal.de/Text/BAUTECHNIK%20IM%20ANTIKEN%20UND.pdf | archivedate = 2011-05-11 }}
* Lewis, M.J.T., 1997, ''Millstone and Hammer'', University of Hull Press
* Moritz, L.A., 1958, ''Grainmills and Flour in Classical Antiquity'', Oxford
* {{ citation | last = Ritti | first = Tullia | last2 = Grewe | first2 = Klaus | last3 = Kessener | first3 = Paul | title = A Relief of a Water-powered Stone Saw Mill on a Sarcophagus at Hierapolis and its Implications | journal = Journal of Roman Archaeology | pages = 138–163 | volume = 20 | year = 2007 | doi = 10.1017/S1047759400005341 }}
* Oliver Davies, "Roman Mines in Europe", Clarendon Press (Oxford), 1935.
* Jones G. D. B., I. J. Blakey, and E. C. F. MacPherson, "Dolaucothi: the Roman aqueduct," ''Bulletin of the Board of Celtic Studies'' 19 (1960): 71–84 and plates III-V.
* Lewis, P. R. and G. D. B. Jones, "The Dolaucothi gold mines, I: the surface evidence," ''The Antiquaries Journal'', 49, no. 2 (1969): 244–72.
* Lewis, P. R. and G. D. B. Jones, "Roman gold-mining in north-west Spain," ''Journal of Roman Studies'' 60 (1970): 169–85.
* Lewis, P. R., "The Ogofau Roman gold mines at Dolaucothi," The National Trust Year Book 1976–77 (1977).
* Barry C. Burnham,  "[https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/britannia/article/roman-mining-at-dolaucothi-the-implications-of-the-19913-excavations-near-the-carreg-pumsaint/26D2795D09E90E8899EA6E10AE309368 Roman Mining at Dolaucothi: the Implications of the 1991–3 Excavations near the Carreg Pumsaint]", ''Britannia'' 28 (1997), 325–336
* A.H.V. Smith, "Provenance of Coals from Roman Sites in England and Wales", ''Britannia'', Vol. 28 (1997), pp.&amp;nbsp;297–324
* {{ citation | last = Basch | first = Lucien | editor-last = Tzalas | editor-first = H. | contribution = La voile latine, son origine, son évolution et ses parentés arabes | title = Tropis VI, 6th International Symposium on Ship Construction in Antiquity, Lamia 1996 proceedings | year = 2001 | pages = 55–85 | place = Athens | publisher = Hellenic Institute for the Preservation of Nautical Tradition }}
* {{ citation | last = Campbell | first = I.C. | year = 1995 | title = The Lateen Sail in World History | periodical = Journal of World History | volume = 6 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–23 | url = http://www.uhpress.hawaii.edu/journals/jwh/jwh061p001.pdf }}
* {{ citation | last = Casson | first = Lionel | author-link = Lionel Casson | year = 1954 | title = The Sails of the Ancient Mariner | periodical = Archaeology | volume = 7 | issue = 4 | pages = 214–219 }}
* {{ citation | last = Casson | first = Lionel | author-link = Lionel Casson | year = 1995 | title = Ships and Seamanship in the Ancient World | publisher = Johns Hopkins University Press | isbn = 0-8018-5130-0 }}
* {{ citation | last1 = Castro | first1 = F. | last2 = Fonseca | first2 = N. | last3 = Vacas | first3 = T. | last4 = Ciciliot | first4 = F. | year = 2008 | title = A Quantitative Look at Mediterranean Lateen- and Square-Rigged Ships (Part 1) | periodical = The International Journal of Nautical Archaeology | volume = 37 | issue = 2 | pages = 347–359 | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-9270.2008.00183.x }}
* {{ citation | last1 = Friedman | first1 = Zaraza | last2 = Zoroglu | first2 = Levent | year = 2006 | title = Kelenderis Ship. Square or Lateen Sail? | periodical = The International Journal of Nautical Archaeology | volume = 35 | issue = 1 | pages = 108–116 | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-9270.2006.00091.x }}
* {{ citation | last = Makris | first = George | editor-last = Laiou | editor-first = Angeliki E | author-link =  | year = 2002 | title = The Economic History of Byzantium. From the Seventh through the Fifteenth Century | contribution = Ships | publisher = Dumbarton Oaks | volume = 2 | pages = 89–99 | isbn = 0-88402-288-9 }}
* {{ citation | last = Pomey | first = Patrice | year = 2006 | title = The Kelenderis Ship: A Lateen Sail | periodical = The International Journal of Nautical Archaeology | volume = 35 | issue = 2 | pages = 326–335 | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-9270.2006.00111.x }}
* {{ citation | last1 = Pryor | first1 = John H. | last2= Jeffreys | first2 = Elizabeth M. | title = The Age of the ΔΡΟΜΩΝ: The Byzantine Navy ca. 500–1204 | publisher = Brill Academic Publishers | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-90-04-15197-0 }}
* Toby, A.Steven "Another look at the Copenhagen Sarcophagus", ''International Journal of Nautical Archaeology'' 1974 vol.3.2: 205–211
* {{citation | last = White | first = Lynn | author-link = Lynn Townsend White, Jr. | year = 1978 | title = Medieval Religion and Technology. Collected Essays | contribution = The Diffusion of the Lateen Sail | publisher = University of California Press | pages = [https://archive.org/details/medievalreligion00whit/page/255 255–260] | isbn = 0-520-03566-6 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/medievalreligion00whit/page/255 }}
* {{ citation | last = Whitewright | first = Julian | year = 2009 | title = The Mediterranean Lateen Sail in Late Antiquity | periodical = The International Journal of Nautical Archaeology | volume = 38 | issue = 1 | pages = 97–104 | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-9270.2008.00213.x }}
* Drachmann, A. G., ''Mechanical Technology of Greek and Roman Antiquity'', Lubrecht &amp; Cramer Ltd, 1963 {{ISBN|0-934454-61-2}}
* Hodges, Henry., ''Technology in the Ancient World'', London:  The Penguin Press, 1970
* Landels, J.G., ''Engineering in the Ancient World'', University of California Press, 1978
* White, K.D., ''Greek and Roman Technology'', Cornell University Press, 1984
* {{ citation | author1 = Sextus Julius Frontinus | authorlink1 = Sextus Julius Frontinus | author2 = R. H. Rodgers (translator) | year = 2003 | title = De Aquaeductu Urbis Romae |trans-title=On the water management of the city of Rome | publisher = University of Vermont | url = http://www.uvm.edu/~rrodgers/Frontinus.html | accessdate = 16 August 2012 | ref = {{sfnRef|Frontinus}} }}
* {{ citation | title = Water and Wastewater Systems in Imperial Rome | chapter= International Water History Association | chapter-url = http://www.iwha.net | url = http://www.waterhistory.org/histories/rome/
  |author= Roger D. Hansen | accessdate = 2005-11-22 | ref = {{sfnRef|Water History}} }}
* {{ citation | title = Greek and Roman Science and Technology: Engineering | last = Rihll | first = T.E. | date = 2007-04-11 | publisher = [[Swansea University]] | url = http://www.swan.ac.uk/grst/Specific%20subjects/Engineering/engineering.htm | accessdate = 2008-04-13 | ref = {{sfnRef|GRST-engineering}} }}
* {{ citation | last1 = Arenillas | first1 = Miguel | last2 = Castillo | first2 = Juan C. | title = Dams from the Roman Era in Spain. Analysis of Design Forms (with Appendix) | journal = 1st International Congress on Construction History [20th–24th January] | location = Madrid | year = 2003 | url = http://www.traianvs.net/textos/presas_in.htm#_ednref4 }}
* {{ citation | last = Hodge | first = A. Trevor | title = Roman Aqueducts &amp; Water Supply | place = London | publisher = Duckworth | year = 1992 | isbn = 0-7156-2194-7 }}
* {{ citation | last = Hodge | first = A. Trevor | editor-last = Wikander | editor-first = Örjan | editor-link = Örjan Wikander | contribution = Reservoirs and Dams | title = Handbook of Ancient Water Technology | series = Technology and Change in History | volume = 2 | year = 2000 | publisher = Brill | location = Leiden | isbn = 90-04-11123-9 | pages = 331–339 }}
* {{ citation | last1 = James | first1 = Patrick | last2 = Chanson | first2 = Hubert | title = Historical Development of Arch Dams. From Roman Arch Dams to Modern Concrete Designs | journal = Australian Civil Engineering Transactions | volume = CE43 | year = 2002 | pages = 39–56 | url = http://www.traianvs.net/textos/archdams_en.htm }}
* {{ citation | last = Laur-Belart | first = Rudolf | title = Führer durch Augusta Raurica | place = Augst | year = 1988 | edition = 5th }}
* {{ citation | last = Schnitter | first = Niklaus | title = Römische Talsperren | journal = Antike Welt | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 25–32 | year = 1978 }}
* {{ citation | last = Schnitter | first = Niklaus | editor-last = Garbrecht | editor-first = Günther | contribution = Verzeichnis geschichtlicher Talsperren bis Ende des 17. Jahrhunderts | title = Historische Talsperren | place = Stuttgart | publisher = Verlag Konrad Wittwer | year = 1987a | pages = 9–20 | isbn = 3-87919-145-X }}
* {{ citation | last = Schnitter | first = Niklaus | editor-last = Garbrecht | editor-first = Günther | contribution = Die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Pfeilerstaumauer | title = Historische Talsperren | place = Stuttgart | publisher = Verlag Konrad Wittwer | year = 1987b | pages = 57–74 | isbn = 3-87919-145-X }}
* {{ citation | last = Schnitter | first = Niklaus | editor-last = Garbrecht | editor-first = Günther | contribution = Die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Bogenstaumauer | title = Historische Talsperren | place = Stuttgart | publisher = Verlag Konrad Wittwer | year = 1987c | pages = 75–96 | isbn = 3-87919-145-X }}
* {{ citation | doi = 10.2307/3102810 | last = Smith | first = Norman | title = The Roman Dams of Subiaco | journal = Technology and Culture | volume = 11 | issue = 1 | pages = 58–68 | year = 1970 | jstor = 3102810 }}
* {{ citation | last = Smith | first = Norman | title = A History of Dams | place = London | publisher = Peter Davies | year = 1971 | pages = 25–49 | isbn = 0-432-15090-0 }}
* {{ citation | last = Vogel | first = Alexius | editor-last = Garbrecht | editor-first = Günther | contribution = Die historische Entwicklung der Gewichtsmauer | title = Historische Talsperren | place = Stuttgart | publisher = Verlag Konrad Wittwer | year = 1987 | pages = 47–56 | isbn = 3-87919-145-X }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Library resources box |by=no |onlinebooks=yes |others=yes |about=yes |label=Roman technology
  |viaf= |lccn= |lcheading= |wikititle= }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080528061612/http://traianus.rediris.es/ Traianus] – Technical investigation of Roman public works
* [http://www.humanist.de/rome/rts/index.html Roman Traction Systems] – Horse, harness, wagon
* [http://www.humanist.de/rome/harnessing/collar.html Roman Horse Harnesses] – With pictorial evidence
* [http://www.romanconcrete.com/ Roman Concrete] – Roman concrete buildings

{{Ancient Rome topics}}
{{History of technology}}

[[Category:Technology-related lists]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman technology| ]]</text>
      <sha1>naarm3gpl8c7fthhnpaoqh227ijwtha</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
