<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Panic of 1873</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>184959</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961147184</id>
      <parentid>960968785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-06T21:22:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]] (prndis)) #IABot (v2.0.1) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="33840" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Financial crisis}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
[[File:Panic of 1873 bank run.jpg|thumb|A [[bank run]] on the Fourth National Bank No. 20 [[Nassau Street (Manhattan)|Nassau Street]], New York City, from ''[[Frank Leslie's Weekly|Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper]]'', 4 October 1873]]

The '''Panic of 1873''' was a [[financial crisis]] that triggered an [[Depression (economics)|economic depression]] in [[Europe]] and [[North America]] that lasted from 1873 until 1877, or until 1879 in [[France]] and in [[Great Britain|Britain]]. In Britain, the panic started two decades of [[Economic stagnation|stagnation]] known as the "[[Long Depression]]" that weakened the country's economic leadership.&lt;ref&gt;Musson (1959)&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United States]], the Panic was known as the "Great Depression" until the [[Great Depression|events of 1929 and the early 1930s]] set a new standard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/what-history-teaches-us-about-the-welfare-state/2011/07/01/AGGfhFuH_story.html?wprss=rss_opinions |title=What history teaches us about the welfare state |work=The Washington Post |date=29 August 2011 |accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Panic of 1873 and the subsequent depression had several underlying causes, of which [[Economic history|economic historians]] debate the relative importance. American [[inflation]], rampant [[speculation|speculative investments]] (overwhelmingly in [[Rail transport|railroads]]), the [[Legal tender#Demonetization|demonetization]] of silver in [[Germany]] and the United States, ripples from economic dislocation in Europe resulting from the [[Franco-Prussian War]] (1870–71), and major property losses in the [[Great Chicago Fire|Chicago (1871)]] and [[Great Boston Fire of 1872|Boston (1872)]] fires helped to place massive strain on [[bank reserves]], which plummeted in [[New York City]] in September and October 1873 from $50 million to $17 million.

The first symptoms of the crisis were financial failures in [[Vienna]], which spread to most of Europe and North America by 1873.

==United States==
===Factors===
The [[American Civil War]] (1861-1865) was followed by a [[economic boom|boom]] in railroad construction. {{Convert|33000|mi}} of [[History of rail transport in the United States#Civil War and Reconstruction, 1861–1877|new track were laid]] across the country between 1868 and 1873, &lt;ref&gt;Richardson (2007) p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; with much of the craze in railroad investment being driven by government land grants and subsidies to the railroads.&lt;ref&gt;White (2011) p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the railroad industry was the nation's largest employer outside of agriculture, and it involved large amounts of money and risk: a large infusion of cash from speculators caused spectacular growth in the industry as well as in construction of docks, factories and ancillary facilities, while most [[capital (economics)|capital]] was involved in projects offering no immediate or early returns.&lt;ref&gt;Oberholtzer, ''A History of the United States Since the Civil War'' (1926) 3:79–122&lt;/ref&gt;

===Coinage Act of 1873===
A period of post-Civil War economic over-expansion arose from the Northern railroad boom before a series of economic setbacks: the [[Black Friday (1869)|Black Friday panic of 1869]], the [[Great Chicago Fire|Chicago fire of 1871]], an outbreak of [[equine influenza]] and the [[Great Boston fire of 1872|Boston fire of 1872]], and the [[Coinage Act of 1873|demonetization of silver in 1873]].

The decision of the German Empire to cease minting silver [[thaler]] coins in 1871 caused a drop in demand and downward pressure on the value of silver; this, in turn, affected the United States, where much of the supply of silver was [[Silver mining in the United States|mined]]. As a result, the [[United States Congress]] passed the [[Coinage Act of 1873]], which changed the country's silver policy. 

Before this Act, the United States had backed its currency with both gold and silver, and it minted both types of coins. The Act moved the United States to a ''de facto'' [[gold standard]], which meant it would no longer buy silver at a statutory price or [[Free Silver|convert silver from the public into silver coins]] (though it would still mint silver dollars for export in the form of [[Trade Dollar (United States coin)|trade dollars]]).&lt;ref&gt;Unger (1964) ch 8&lt;/ref&gt;

The Act had the immediate effect of depressing silver prices. This hurt Western mining interests, who labeled the Act "The Crime of '73", but its effect was offset somewhat by the introduction of a silver trade dollar for use in Asia, and by the discovery of new silver deposits at [[Virginia City, Nevada]], resulting in new investment in mining activity.&lt;ref&gt;Loomis (1968), pp. 219–220, 224–225.&lt;/ref&gt; But the coinage law also reduced the domestic [[money supply]], thereby raising interest rates and hurting farmers and others who normally carried heavy debt loads. The resulting outcry raised serious questions about how long the new policy would last.&lt;ref&gt;Silver coinage was resumed under the [[Bland–Allison Act]] of 1878.&lt;/ref&gt; This perception of instability in United States monetary policy caused investors to shy away from long-term obligations, particularly long-term [[Bond (finance)|bonds]]. The problem was compounded by the railroad boom, which was in its later stages at the time.

In September 1873, the [[Economy of the United States|U.S. economy]] entered a crisis.

====Jay Cooke &amp; Company fails====
In September 1873, [[Jay Cooke &amp; Company]], a major component of the United States banking establishment, found itself unable to market several million dollars in [[Northern Pacific Railway]] bonds. [[Jay Cooke|Cooke's]] firm, like many others, had invested heavily in the railroads. At a time when [[Investment banking|investment banks]] were anxious for more capital for their enterprises, [[Presidency of Ulysses S. Grant|President Ulysses S. Grant]]'s [[monetary policy]] of contracting the money supply (again, also thereby raising interest rates) made matters worse for those in debt. While businesses were expanding, the money they needed to finance that growth was becoming scarcer.

Cooke and other entrepreneurs had planned to build the second transcontinental railroad, called the [[Northern Pacific Railway]]. Cooke's firm provided the financing, and ground for the line was broken near [[Duluth, Minnesota]], on 15 February 1870. But just as Cooke was about to swing a US$300 million government loan in September 1873, reports circulated that his firm's credit had become nearly worthless. On 18 September, the firm declared bankruptcy.&lt;ref&gt;Wheeler (1973), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Effect on the Insurance Industry====
Many US insurance companies went out of business as deteriorating financial conditions created solvency problems for life insurers. The surviving companies all had a
unique feature, they all offered [[Tontine]]s.&lt;ref name="The Performance of Life Insurance Companies: 1860-1905"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Yang |first1=Tony |date=2009 |page=5 |title=The Performance of Life Insurance Companies: 1860-1905 |url=http://www.americasmutualbanks.com/images/0714_YangPaper.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effects===
[[File:Tompkins square riot 1874.jpg|thumbnail|New York police violently attacking unemployed workers in [[Tompkins Square Riot (1874)|Tompkins Square Park]], 1874]]
The failure of the Jay Cooke bank, followed quickly by that of [[Henry Clews]], set off a chain reaction of bank failures and temporarily closed the New York stock market. Factories began to lay off workers as the United States slipped into depression. The effects of the panic were quickly felt in New York, and more slowly in Chicago, [[Virginia City, Nevada]] (where silver mining was active), and San Francisco.&lt;ref&gt;Loomis (1968), pp. 119–120.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Masur (1970), p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[New York Stock Exchange]] closed for ten days starting 20 September.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Poor Kindleberger, ''Historical Economics: Art or Science?'' Berkeley, CA: University of California Press, 1990; pg. 321.&lt;/ref&gt; By November 1873 some 55 of the nation's railroads had failed, and another 60 went bankrupt by the first anniversary of the crisis.&lt;ref name=Kleppner1556&gt;Paul Kleppner, "The Greenback and Prohibition Parties," in Arthur M. Schlesinger (ed.), ''History of U.S. Political Parties: Volume II, 1860–1910, The [[Gilded Age]] of Politics.'' New York: Chelsea House/R.R. Bowker Co., 1973; pg. 1556.&lt;/ref&gt; Construction of new rail lines, formerly one of the backbones of the economy, plummeted from 7,500 miles (12,070&amp;nbsp;km) of track in 1872 to just 1,600 miles (2,575&amp;nbsp;km) in 1875.&lt;ref name=Kleppner1556 /&gt; 18,000 businesses failed between 1873 and 1875. Unemployment peaked in 1878 at 8.25%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lord Keynes |url=http://socialdemocracy21stcentury.blogspot.com/2012/01/us-unemployment-18691899.html |title=Social Democracy for the 21st Century: A Post Keynesian Perspective: US Unemployment, 1869–1899 |publisher=Socialdemocracy21stcentury.blogspot.com |date=2012-01-26 |accessdate=2013-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Building construction was halted, wages were cut, real estate values fell and corporate profits vanished.&lt;ref&gt;Rezneck (1950)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Railroad strike===
{{more citations needed|section|date=May 2018}}&lt;!--only first paragraph has citations--&gt;
In 1877, steep wage cuts led American railroad workers to launch the [[Great Railroad Strike of 1877|Great Railroad Strike]]. Initial protests broke out in [[Martinsburg, West Virginia]] when the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] (B&amp;O) cut worker's pay for the third time in a year. West Virginia Governor [[Henry M. Mathews]] sent militia under Colonel [[Charles J. Faulkner]] to restore order, but was unsuccessful largely due to militia sympathies with the workers. 

As the workers began rioting, with reports of looting and attacks on civilians and police, the governor then called on President [[Rutherford B. Hayes]] for federal assistance, and Hayes dispatched federal troops. This restored peace to Martinsburg but proved controversial, with many newspapers critical of the governor's characterization of the strikes as an 'insurrection' rather than an act of desperation. One notable paper recorded a striking worker's perspective that, "[he] had might as well die by the bullet as
to starve to death by inches." Within the week, similar protests had erupted in Maryland, New York, Pennsylvania, Illinois, and Missouri.&lt;ref name= Bellesiles&gt;Bellesiles, Michael A. (2010). "1877: America's Year for Living Violently. The New Press, 2010. p 149. https://books.google.com/books?id=rf4q5LjLbHIC&amp;pg=PA149 Retrieved November 27, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://npgallery.nps.gov/pdfhost/docs/NHLS/Text/03001045.pdf |title=The Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Martinsburg Shops NATIONAL HISTORIC LANDMARK NOMINATION
 |last=Caplinger |first=Michael |date=2003 |website= |publisher= |page=40–45|access-date= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In July 1877, the market for lumber crashed, leading to several Michigan lumber companies going bankrupt.&lt;ref&gt;Among the lumbering firms that failed were the Danaher &amp; Melendy Company and Oliver O. Stanchfield of [[Ludington, Michigan]], and Cushman, Calkins &amp; Company and Tyson, Sweet &amp; Company of [[Manistee, Michigan]]. ''History of Manistee, Mason and Oceana Counties, Michigan'' (1882), "History of Mason County", p. 50, and "History of Manistee County", pp. 52, 53 (separate pagination).&lt;/ref&gt; Within a year, the effects of this second business slump reached all the way to California.&lt;ref&gt;Loomis (1968), pp. 241–243.&lt;/ref&gt;

The depression lifted in the spring of 1879, but tension between workers and the leaders of banking and manufacturing interests lingered on.

Poor economic conditions also caused voters to turn against the [[History of the United States Republican Party|Republican Party]]: in the [[1874 United States House of Representatives elections|1874 congressional elections]], the [[History of the Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] assumed control of the House for the first time since the Civil War. 

Public opinion made it difficult for the Grant administration to develop a coherent policy regarding the Southern states, and the North began to steer away from [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]]. With the depression, ambitious railroad building programs crashed across the South, leaving most states deep in debt and burdened with heavy taxes. Retrenchment was a common response of southern states to state debts during the depression. One by one, each Southern state fell to the Democrats, and the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] lost power.

The end of the crisis coincided with the beginning of the great wave of immigration into the United States, which lasted until the early 1920s.

==Europe==
The panic and depression hit all industrial nations.

===Germany and Austria-Hungary===
[[File:Schwarzer Freitag Wien 1873.jpg|thumb|Black Friday, 9 May 1873, [[Wiener Börse|Vienna Stock Exchange]] ]]

A similar process of over-expansion took place in Germany and Austria, where the period from [[Unification of Germany|German unification]] in 1870{{endash}}71 to the crash in 1873 came to be called the ''{{lang|de|[[Gründerzeit|Gründerjahre]]}}'' ("founders' years"). A liberalized incorporation law in Germany gave impetus to the foundation of new enterprises, such as the {{lang|de|[[Deutsche Bank]]}}, and the incorporation of already established ones. Euphoria over the military victory against France in 1871 and the influx of capital from the payment by France of [[French indemnity|war reparations]] fueled stock market speculation in railways, factories, docks, steamships – the same industrial branches that expanded unsustainably in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Masur (1970), pp. 63–65.&lt;/ref&gt; It was in the immediate aftermath of [[Otto von Bismarck]]'s [[Franco-Prussian War|victory against France]] that he began the process of silver demonetization. The process began on 23 November 1871 and culminated in the introduction of the [[German gold mark|gold mark]] on 9 July 1873 as the currency for the new united Reich, replacing the silver coins of all constituent lands. Germany was now on the [[gold standard]].&lt;ref name="madhouse"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.silver-investor.com/charlessavoie/cs_3-29-05_monetarymadhouse.htm |title=Monetary Madhouse |author=Charles Savoie |publisher=Silver-Investor.com |date=April 2005 |accessdate=10 September 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227014729/http://www.silver-investor.com/charlessavoie/cs_3-29-05_monetarymadhouse.htm |archive-date=27 February 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Demonetization of silver was thus a common element in the crises on both sides of the Atlantic Ocean.

On 9 May 1873, the [[Wiener Börse|Vienna Stock Exchange]] crashed, unable to sustain the bubble of false expansion, insolvencies, and dishonest manipulations.  A series of Viennese bank failures ensued, causing a contraction of the money available for business lending. One of the more famous private individuals who went bankrupt in 1873 was Stephan [[House of Keglević|Keglevich]] of Vienna.  He was a relative of Gábor Keglevich, who had been the [[master of the treasury|master of the royal treasury]] (1842–1848), and who in 1845 had founded, with some others, a financing association to fund the expansion of Hungarian industry and to protect the loan repayments, similar to the ''Kreditschutzverband'' of 1870 (Austria's association for the protection of creditors and for the protection of the interests of its members in cases of bankruptcy). That made it possible for a number of new Austrian banks to be established in 1873 after the Vienna Stock Exchange crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{lang|de|Fünfundzwanzig Jahre oesterreichischer Finanzpolitik: (1848 bis 1873) : ein historischer Rückblick, Wilhelm Emil Angerstein, Luckhardt'sche Verlagsbuchhandlung}}, 1874. {{in lang|de}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Berlin, the railway empire of [[Bethel Henry Strousberg]] crashed after a ruinous settlement with the [[Romania]]n government, bursting the speculation bubble in Germany. The contraction of the German economy was exacerbated by the conclusion of war reparations payments to Germany by France in September 1873. Coming two years after the foundation of the German Empire, the panic became known as the ''{{lang|de|Gründerkrach}}'' or "founders' crash".&lt;ref&gt;Manchester (1968), p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marek (1974), pp. 181–182.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Masur (1970), pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt; Keglevich and Strousberg had come in the year 1865 in direct competition in a project in today's Slovakia, whereupon, in 1870, the Government of Hungary and finally in 1872 the Emperor-King [[Franz Joseph I of Austria]] resolved the question of these competing projects.&lt;ref&gt;Technické noviny, číslo 46, rok 1988, ročník 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Historické štúdie, Volume 1–2, p.239, Slovenská akadémia vied, Historický ústav SAV., Československá akademie věd, Vyd-vo Slovenskej akadémie vied, Bratislava 1955.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the collapse of the foreign loan financing had been foreshadowed, the anticipatory events of that year were in themselves comparatively unimportant. [[Buda]], the old capital of Hungary, and [[Óbuda]] were officially united with [[Pest, Hungary|Pest]],&lt;ref&gt;Kinga Frojimovics, Géza Komoróczy, Jewish Budapest: monuments, rites, history, Central European University Press, 1999 p.67 [https://books.google.com/books?id=-wUg6rlWS2kC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;dq=Buda+%C3%B3buda+pest+1873&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=AKHQTJmcMMLBswbc9NXNCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEwQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; thus creating the new metropolis of [[Budapest]] in 1873. The difference in stability between [[Vienna]] and Berlin had the effect that the French indemnity to Germany overflowed thence to Austria and Russia, but these indemnity payments aggravated the crisis in Austria, which had been benefited by the accumulation of capital not only in Germany, but also in England, the Netherlands, Belgium, France and Russia.&lt;ref&gt;British Economic History, 1870–1914, W.H.B. Court, Cambridge University Press 1965.&lt;/ref&gt;

Recovery from the crash occurred much more quickly in Europe than in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Marek (1974), pp. 182–183.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Masur 1970, pp. 74–75"&gt;Masur (1970), pp. 74–75.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, German businesses managed to avoid the sort of deep wage cuts that embittered American labor relations at the time.&lt;ref name="Masur 1970, pp. 74–75" /&gt; There was an anti-Semitic component to the economic recovery in Germany and Austria as small investors blamed the Jews for their losses in the crash.&lt;ref&gt;Marek (1974), p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Masur (1970), pp. 75–76.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon more luxury hotels and villas were built in [[Opatija]] and a new railway line was extended in 1873 from the Vienna–[[Trieste]] line to [[Rijeka]], from where it was possible to go by tram to Opatija. The strong increase of port traffic generated a permanent request for expansion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Unconnected transport networks: European intermodal traffic junctions 1800–2000 |page=146 |first=Hans-Liudger |last=Dienel |publisher=Campus Verlag |location=Frankfurt/Main |year=2004 |isbn=3-593-37661-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Suez Canal]] was opened in 1869.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Suez-Canal|title=Suez Canal {{!}} canal, Egypt|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2017-11-24|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1875–90 became "''the golden years''" of [[Giovanni de Ciotta]] in [[Fiume]] ([[Rijeka]]).

===Britain===
The opening of the [[Suez Canal]] in 1869 was one of the causes of the Panic of 1873, because goods from the Far East had been carried in sailing vessels around the [[Cape of Good Hope]] and were stored in British warehouses. As sailing vessels were not adaptable for use through the Suez Canal because the prevailing winds of the Mediterranean Sea blow from west to east, British [[entrepôt]] trade suffered.&lt;ref&gt;The economic development of the American nation, p. 356, Reginald Charles McGrane, Ginn &amp; Co., Boston 1950.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Britain the [[Long Depression]] resulted in bankruptcies, escalating unemployment, a halt in public works, and a major trade slump that lasted until 1897.&lt;ref&gt;W. B Sutch, ''The long depression, 1865–1895'' (1957)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Comparison with Germany====
During the years from 1873 to 1896, a period sometimes referred to as "Long Depression", most European countries experienced a drastic fall in prices. Still, many corporations were able to reduce production costs and achieve better productivity rates, and, as a result, industrial production increased by 40% in Britain and by over 100% in Germany.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} A comparison of capital formation rates in the two countries helps to account for the different industrial growth rates. During the depression the British ratio of net national capital formation to net national product fell from 11.5% to 6.0% while Germany's rose from 10.6% to 15.9%.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} In essence, during the course of the depression, Britain took the course of static supply adjustment while Germany stimulated effective demand and expanded industrial supply capacity by increasing and adjusting capital formation. For example, Germany dramatically increased investment with regard to [[social overhead capital]], such as in the management of electric power transmission lines, roads, and railroads, while this input stagnated or decreased in Britain and the investment helped to stimulate industrial demand in Germany. The resulting difference in capital formation accounts for the divergent levels of industrial production in the two countries and the different growth rates during and after the depression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Young Goo |last=Park |title=Depression and capital formation: The United Kingdom and Germany, 1873–96 |journal=Journal of European Economic History |year=1997 |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=511–534 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
The discovery of large quantities of silver in the United States and several European colonies caused the panic of 1873 which resulted in a decline in the [[Relative value (economics)|value]] of [[Silver as an investment|silver relative]] to gold, devaluing India's standard currency. This event was known as "[[Indian_rupee#1800s|the fall of the rupee]]".

===Ottoman Empire===
In the periphery, the [[Ottoman Empire]]'s economy also suffered. Rates of growth of foreign trade dropped, external terms of trade deteriorated, declining wheat prices affected peasant producers, and the establishment of European control over Ottoman finances led to large debt payments abroad. The growth rates of agricultural and aggregate production were also lower during the Long Depression as compared to the later period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Sevket |last=Pamuk |title=The Ottoman Empire in the 'Great Depression' of 1873–1896 |journal=[[Journal of Economic History]] |year=1984 |volume=44 |issue=1 |pages=107–118 |doi=10.1017/S0022050700031399 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latin Monetary Union===
The general demonetisation and cheapening of silver caused the [[Latin Monetary Union]] in 1873 to suspend the conversion of silver to coins.

==Global protectionism==
After the 1873 depression, agricultural and industrial groups lobbied for [[Protectionism|protective]] [[tariff]]s. The 1879 tariffs protected these interests, stimulated economic revival through state intervention and refurbished political support for the conservative politicians [[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]] and [[John A. Macdonald]] (the Canadian prime minister). Chancellor Bismarck gradually veered away from [[Classical liberalism|classical liberal]] economic policies in the 1870s, embracing many [[Economic interventionism|economic interventionist]] policies, including high tariffs, [[nationalization]] of railroads, and compulsory social insurance.&lt;ref&gt;Eyck (1950), pp. 223–236, 252–261.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Masur (1970), pp. 75–80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richter (1962), pp. 219–220, 255–256.&lt;/ref&gt; This political and [[economic nationalism]] also reduced the fortunes of the German and Canadian [[Classical liberalism|classical liberal]] parties. France, like Britain, also entered into a prolonged stagnation that extended to 1897. The French also attempted to deal with their economic problems through the implementation of tariffs. New French laws in 1880 and in 1892 imposed stiff tariffs on many agricultural and industrial imports, an attempt at protectionism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Yves |last=Breton |title=La Longue Stagnation en France: L'Autre Grande Depression, 1873–1897|language=fr |year=1997 |location= Paris |publisher=Économica |isbn=2-7178-3130-4 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S., still in the period after the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], continued to be very [[Protectionism|protectionist]].&lt;ref&gt;Marc-William Palen, "[http://dh.oxfordjournals.org/content/37/2/217 Foreign Relations in the Gilded Age: A British Free-Trade Conspiracy?]" ''Diplomatic History'' 37 (April 2013): 217-247.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=H. Wayne |last=Morgan |title=From Hayes to McKinley: National Party Politics, 1877–1896 |location=Syracuse |publisher=University Press |year=1969 |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Banks}}
* [[Panic of 1857]]
* [[Panic of 1893]]
* [[Black Friday (1869)]] – Also referred to as the Gold Panic of 1869
* [[Second-term curse]]
* [[Workingmen's Party of Illinois]]

==References==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*{{cite journal |last=Barreyre |first=Nicolas |year=2011 |title=The Politics of Economic Crises: The Panic of 1873, the End of Reconstruction, and the Realignment of American Politics |journal=Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era |volume=10 |issue=4 |pages=403–423 |doi=10.1017/S1537781411000260 }}
* Davies, Hannah Catherine. ''Transatlantic Speculations: Globalization and the Panics of 1873'' (Columbia UP, 2018) [https://eh.net/?s=%22Transatlantic+Speculations%22  online review]
*{{cite book |last=Eyck |first=Erich |year=1950 |title=Bismarck and the German Empire |location= }}
*{{cite book |last=Fawcett |first=W. L. |year=1877 |title=Gold and Debt; An American Hand-Book of Finance |url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924013815802 |location= |publisher= Chicago, S.C. Griggs and company}}
*{{cite journal |last=Fels |first=Rendigs |year=1949 |title=The Long-Wave Depression, 1873–97 |journal=[[Review of Economics and Statistics]] |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=69–73 |jstor=1927196 |doi=10.2307/1927196 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Fels |first=Rendigs |year=1951 |title=American Business Cycles, 1865–79 |journal=[[American Economic Review]] |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=325–349 |jstor=1802106 }}
*{{cite book |authorlink=Eric Foner |last=Foner |first=Eric |year=1990 |title=A Short History of Reconstruction 1863–1877 |location=New York |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=0060964316 |url=https://archive.org/details/shorthistoryofre00eric }}
*{{Cite book | title = Business Cycles and Depressions: An Encyclopedia | editor1-last = Glasner | editor1-first = David | editor2-last = Cooley | editor2-first = Thomas F. | year = 1997 | location = New York | publisher = Garland Publishing | chapter = Crisis of 1873 | last = Glasner | first = David | pages = [https://archive.org/details/businesscyclesde00glas/page/132 132–133] | isbn = 0-8240-0944-4 | chapter-url = https://archive.org/details/businesscyclesde00glas/page/132 }}
*{{cite book |last=Kindleberger |first=Charles P. |title=Manias, Panics and Crashes: A History of Financial Crises |url=https://archive.org/details/maniaspanicscras00kind_182 |url-access=limited |edition=5th |location=New York |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |year=2005 |page=[https://archive.org/details/maniaspanicscras00kind_182/page/n146 137] |isbn=0471467146 }}
*{{cite book |last=Kirkland |first=Edward Chase |year=1967 |title=Industry Comes of Age: Business, Labor, and Public Policy 1860–1897 |location=Chicago |publisher=Quadrangle Books }}
*{{cite book |last=Loomis |first=Noel M. |year=1968 |title=Wells Fargo }}
*{{cite book |last=Lubetkin |first=M. John |year=2006 |title=Jay Cooke's Gamble: The Northern Pacific Railroad, the Sioux, and the Panic of 1873 |location= |publisher= |isbn= }} Focused on construction in the West.
* {{cite book|author=Lucibello, Alan. (2014) "Panic of 1873." in Daniel Leab, ed. |title=Encyclopedia of American Recessions and Depressions|date=15 January 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qI6dAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA227|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9781598849462}} pp 227–76
*{{cite book |authorlink=William Manchester |last=Manchester |first=William |year=1968 |title=The Arms of Krupp |title-link=The Arms of Krupp |location= |isbn=978-0-316-52940-2 }}
*{{cite book |authorlink=George Richard Marek |last=Marek |first=George R. |year=1974 |title=The Eagles Die: Franz Joseph, Elisabeth, and Their Austria |publisher=[[Harper (publisher)|Harper &amp; Row]] |isbn=978-0-246-10880-7 }}
*{{cite book |last=Masur |first=Gerhard |year=1970 |title=Imperial Berlin |location=New York |publisher=Basic Books |isbn=0465032095 |url=https://archive.org/details/imperialberlin0000masu }}
*{{cite journal |last=Mixon |first=Peter |title=The Crisis of 1873: Perspectives from Multiple Asset Classes |journal=[[Journal of Economic History]] |volume=68 |issue=3 |year=2008 |pages=722–757 |doi=10.1017/S0022050708000624 }}
*{{cite book |last=Moseley |first=Fred |year=1997 |chapter=Depression of 1873–1879 |editor1-first=David |editor1-last=Glasner |editor2-first=Thomas F. |editor2-last=Cooley |title=Business Cycles and Depressions: An Encyclopedia |pages=[https://archive.org/details/businesscyclesde00glas/page/148 148–149] |isbn=0-8240-0944-4 |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/businesscyclesde00glas/page/148 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Musson |first=A. E. |year=1959 |title=The Great Depression in Britain, 1873–1896: A Reappraisal |journal=Journal of Economic History |volume=19 |issue=2 |pages=199–228 |doi=10.1017/S0022050700109994 |jstor=2114975 }}
*{{cite book |authorlink=Ellis Paxson Oberholtzer |last=Oberholtzer |first=Ellis Paxson |year=1907 |title=Jay Cooke: Financier of the Civil War |volume=2 |pages=378–430 }} {{Google books |id=8jHiEwVmB8MC |title=Available }}
*{{cite book |last=Oberholtzer |first=Ellis Paxson |year=1926 |title=A History of the United States Since the Civil War: Volume 3 1872-1878 |url=https://archive.org/details/historyofuniteds03ober|pages=[https://archive.org/details/historyofuniteds03ober/page/69 69]–122 |publisher=New York, Macmillan }}
*{{cite journal |last=Persons |first=Warren M. |last2=Tuttle |first2=Pierson M. |last3=Frickey |first3=Edwin |year=1920 |title=Business and Financial Conditions Following the Civil War in the United States |journal=[[Review of Economic Statistics]] |volume=2 |issue=Supplement 2 |pages=5–21 |jstor=1928610 |doi=10.2307/1928610 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Rezneck |first=Samuel |title=Distress, Relief, and Discontent in the United States during the Depression of 1873–78 |journal=[[Journal of Political Economy]] |volume=58 |issue=6 |year=1950 |pages=494–512 |jstor=1827088 |doi=10.1086/257012 }}
*{{cite book |last=Richardson |first=Heather Cox |year=2007 |title=West From Appomattox: The Reconstruction of America After the Civil War |isbn=978-0-300-11052-4 }}
*{{cite book |authorlink=Hans Werner Richter |last=Richter |first=Hans Werner |year=1962 |title=Bismarck }}
*{{cite journal |last=Scott |first=Ira O., Jr. |title=A Comparison of Production during the Depressions of 1873 and 1929 |journal=American Economic Review |volume=42 |issue=4 |year=1952 |pages=569–576 |jstor=1810159 }}
*{{cite book |last=Sprague |first=Oliver Mitchell Wentworth |year=1910 |title=History of crises under the national banking system |url=https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_Q4AsAAAAYAAJ |location= |publisher= |pages=[https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_Q4AsAAAAYAAJ/page/n237 1]–107 }} {{Google books|Q4AsAAAAYAAJ|Available}}
*{{cite book |authorlink=Irwin Unger |last=Unger |first=Irwin |title=The Greenback Era: A Social and Political History of American Finance, 1865–1879 |title-link=The Greenback Era: A Social and Political History of American Finance, 1865–1879 |year=1964 |pages=213–228 }}
*{{cite book |last=Wheeler |first=Keith |year=1973 |title=The Railroaders |url=https://archive.org/details/railroaders00time |url-access=registration |location=New York |publisher=Time-Life Books }}
*{{cite book |last=White |first=Richard |year=2011 |title=Railroaded: The Transcontinentals and the Making of Modern America |location= |publisher= Norton|isbn=978-0-393-06126-0 |url=https://archive.org/details/railroadedtransc00whit_0 }}
{{refend}}
* Wicker, Elmus. ''Banking panics of the [[gilded age]]'' (Cambridge University Press, 2006) [https://web.archive.org/web/20140323075727/http://www.langtoninfo.co.uk/web_content/9780521025478_frontmatter.pdf contents]

===Yearbooks===
* {{Google books|c6QoAAAAYAAJ|''Appleton's Annual Cyclopedia...for 1873'' (1879)}}
* {{Google books|2WcMAAAAYAAJ|''Appleton's Annual Cyclopedia...for 1875'' (1877)}}
* {{Google books|r6MYAAAAIAAJ|''Appleton's Annual Cyclopedia...for 1876'' (1885)}}
* {{Google books|Do4EAAAAYAAJ|''Appleton's Annual Cyclopedia...for 1877'' (1878)}}

{{Financial crises}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Panic Of 1873}}
[[Category:1873 in economics]]
[[Category:1873 in the United States]]
[[Category:Economic crises in the United States]]
[[Category:Financial crises]]
[[Category:History of banking in the United States]]
[[Category:History of rail transportation in the United States]]
[[Category:Presidency of Ulysses S. Grant]]
[[Category:Stock market crashes|1873]]</text>
      <sha1>cgmv4jahz46m8lft6mtsv5mf5gljm2j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
