<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mars Exploration Program</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32506368</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959721715</id>
      <parentid>958324564</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-30T08:03:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MyShadowedSpirit</username>
        <id>39399771</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* List */Fixed typo:
Mars Global Surveyor was launched on 07 Nov 1996 not 1995</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="35441" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Uncrewed spaceflight program by NASA focused on scientific exploration of Mars using orbiters, landers, and rovers}}
{{Use American English|date=May 2020}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2020}}
{{United States space program sidebar}}

'''Mars Exploration Program''' ('''MEP''') is a long-term effort [[Exploration of Mars|to explore the planet Mars]], funded and led by [[NASA]]. Formed in 1993, MEP has made use of orbital [[spacecraft]], [[lander (spacecraft)|landers]], and [[Mars rovers]] to explore the possibilities of [[life on Mars (planet)|life on Mars]], as well as the planet's [[climate]] and [[natural resource]]s.&lt;ref name=strategy9520&gt;{{cite web|last=Shirley|first=Donna|title=Mars Exploration Program Strategy: 1995–2020|url=http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/23620/1/96-0064.pdf|publisher=[[American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics]]|accessdate=18 October 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130511200249/http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/23620/1/96-0064.pdf|archivedate=11 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The program is managed by NASA's [[Science Mission Directorate]] by [[Doug McCuistion]] of the [[NASA Planetary Science Division|Planetary Science Division]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCuistion|first=Doug|title=Doug McCuistion, Director, NASA Mars Exploration Program|url=http://solarsystem.nasa.gov/people/profile.cfm?Code=McCuistionD|publisher=[[NASA]]|accessdate=18 October 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151019071032/http://solarsystem.nasa.gov/people/profile.cfm?Code=McCuistionD|archive-date=19 October 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of 40% cuts to NASA's budget for fiscal year 2013, the [[Mars Program Planning Group]] (MPPG) was formed to help reformulate the MEP, bringing together leaders of NASA's technology, science, human operations, and science missions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hubbard|first=G. Scott|title=A Next Decade Mars Program|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/g-scott-hubbard/mars-exploration_b_1837961.html|publisher=The Huffington Post|accessdate=18 October 2012|date=2012-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Garvin|first=James|title=About the Mars Program Planning Group|url=http://www.nasa.gov/offices/marsplanning/about/index.html|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Governance ==
First convening in October 1999, the Mars Exploration Program Analysis Group (MEPAG) enables the scientific community to provide input for the planning and prioritizing of the Mars Exploration Program. Mars exploration missions, as do most NASA missions, can be fairly costly. For example, NASA's [[Curiosity rover|''Curiosity'' rover]] (landed on Mars in Aug 2012) has a budget exceeding $2.5 billion.&lt;ref name="costs 1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Leone|first=Dan|title=Mars Science Lab Needs $44M More To Fly, NASA Audit Finds|url=http://www.spacenews.com/civil/110608-msl-needs-more-nasa-audit.html|publisher=[[Space News]]|accessdate=24 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; NASA also has goals of collaborating with the [[European Space Agency]] (ESA) in order to conduct a mission involving returning a sample of Mars soil to Earth, which would likely cost at least $5 billion and take ten years to complete.&lt;ref name="costs 10 bil"&gt;{{cite web|last=de Selding|first=Peter|title=Study: Mars Sample Return Would Take 10 Years, Cost $5 Billion-Plus|url=http://www.spacenews.com/archive/archive08/marssamplemain_0714.html|publisher=Space News|accessdate=24 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Objectives ===
{{Multiple image
| total_width = 400
| image1      = NASA Mars Rover.jpg
| image2      = Mars Science Laboratory, 2011-Present.jpg
| footer      = [[Astrobiology]], [[climatology]], and [[geology]] have been common themes in Mars Exploration Program missions, such as [[Mars Exploration Rover]] (left) and [[Mars Science Laboratory]] (right)
}}
According to NASA, there are four broad goals of the MEP, all having to do with understanding the potential for [[life]] on Mars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Mars Exploration Program's Science Theme|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/science/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Determine if life ever arose on Mars''' – In order to understand Mars' [[Planetary habitability|habitability potential]], it must be determined whether or not there ever was [[life on Mars]], which begins with assessing the planet's suitability for life. The main strategy regarding the MEP, nicknamed "Follow the Water," is the general idea that where life is present, there is water (at least in instances on Earth). It is likely that if life ever did arise on Mars, there would need to be a supply of water that was present for a substantial amount of time. Therefore, a prominent goal of the MEP is to look for places where water is, was, or could possibly be, such as dried up riverbeds, under the planetary surface, and in Mars' polar ice caps. Aside from water, life also needs sources of energy to survive. The abundance of [[superoxides]] makes life on the surface of Mars very unlikely, which essentially rules out sunlight as a possible source of energy for life. Therefore, alternative sources of energy must be searched for, such as [[geothermal energy|geothermal]] and [[chemical energy]]. These sources, which are both used by life forms on Earth, could be used by [[microorganism|microscopic life forms]] living under the Mars' surface. Life on Mars can also be searched for by finding signatures of past and present life or [[biosignature]]s. Relative carbon abundance and the location and forms that it can be found in can inform where and how life may have developed. Also, the presence of [[carbonate minerals]], along with the fact that [[atmosphere of mars|Mars' atmosphere]] is made up largely of [[carbon dioxide]], would tell scientists that water may have been on the planet long enough to foster the development of life.&lt;ref name="goal 1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Goal 1: Determine if Life Ever Arose On Mars|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/science/goal1/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Characterize the climate of Mars''' – Another goal of the MEP is to characterize both the current and past [[climate of Mars]], as well as factors that influence climate change on Mars. Currently what is known is that the climate is regulated by seasonal changes of Mars' ice caps, movement of dust by the atmosphere, and the exchange of water vapor between the surface and the atmosphere. To understand these climatic phenomena means helping scientists more effectively model Mars' past climate, which brings a higher degree of understanding of the dynamics of Mars.&lt;ref name="goal 2"&gt;{{cite web|title=Goal 2: Characterize the Climate of Mars|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/science/goal2/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Characterize the geology of Mars''' – The [[geology of Mars]] is differentiable from that of Earth by, among other things, its extremely large volcanoes and lack of crust movement. A goal of the MEP is to understand these differences from Earth along with the way that wind, water, volcanoes, tectonics, [[impact crater|cratering]] and other processes have shaped the surface of Mars. Rocks can help scientists describe the sequence of events in Mars' history, tell whether there was an abundance of water on the planet through identifying minerals that are formed only in water, and tell if Mars once had a [[magnetosphere|magnetic field]] (which would point toward Mars at one point being a dynamic Earth-like planet).&lt;ref name="goal 3"&gt;{{cite web|title=Goal 3: Characterize the Geology of Mars|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/science/goal3/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Prepare for the human exploration of Mars''' – A [[human mission to Mars]] presents a massive engineering challenge. With Mars' surface containing superoxides and lacking a [[magnetosphere]] and an [[ozone layer]] to protect from radiation from the Sun, scientists would have to thoroughly understand as much of Mars' dynamics as possible before any action can be taken toward the goal of putting humans on Mars.&lt;ref name="goal 4"&gt;{{cite web| title=Goal 4: Prepare for the Human Exploration of Mars| url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/science/goal4/| work=Mars Exploration program| publisher=NASA| accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Challenges ===
[[File:Entry.jpg|thumb|Mars' thinner atmosphere makes [[Atmospheric entry|entry, descent, and landing]] operations of arriving in-situ surface spacecraft more challenging]]
Mars exploration missions have historically had some of the highest failure rates for NASA missions,&lt;ref name=chronology /&gt; which can be attributed to the immense engineering challenges of these missions as well as some bad luck.{{Ambiguous|date=September 2018}}&lt;ref name="mars curse"&gt;{{cite web|last=O'Neill|first=Ian|title=The Mars Curse|url=http://www.universetoday.com/13267/the-mars-curse-why-have-so-many-missions-failed/|publisher=[[Universe Today]]|accessdate=18 October 2012|date=2008-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; With many of the goals of the MEP involving entry, descent, and landing of spacecraft (EDL) on the surface of Mars, factors like the planet's atmosphere, uneven surface terrain, and high cost of replicating Mars-like environments for testing come into play.&lt;ref name=challenges&gt;{{cite journal|last=Braun|first=Robert|title=Mars Exploration Entry, Descent and Landing Challenges|journal=Journal of Spacecraft and Rockets|volume=44|issue=2|pages=310|url=http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/39664/1/05-3869.pdf|accessdate=18 October 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100526014618/http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/39664/1/05-3869.pdf|archivedate=26 May 2010|bibcode=2007JSpRo..44..310B|year=2007|doi=10.2514/1.25116|citeseerx=10.1.1.463.8773}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compared to the Earth, the [[atmosphere of Mars]] is about 100 times thinner. As a result, if a landing craft were to descend into Mars' atmosphere, it would decelerate at a much lower altitude, and depending on the object's mass, may not have enough time to reach terminal velocity. In order to deploy super- or subsonic decelerators, velocity must be below a threshold or they will not be effective. Therefore, technologies must be developed so that a landing craft can be decelerated enough to allow adequate time for other necessary landing processes to be carried out before landing.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt; Mars' atmosphere varies significantly over the course of a [[Timekeeping on Mars|Mars year]], which prevents engineers from being able to develop a system for EDL common among all missions. Frequently-occurring dust storms increase lower atmospheric temperature and lessen atmospheric density, which, coupled with the extremely variable elevations on Mars' surface, forces a conservative selection of a landing site in order to allow for sufficient craft deceleration.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt; With Mars EDL sequences only lasting about 5–8 minutes, the associated systems must be unquestionably reliable. Ideally, this would be verified by data obtained by carrying out large-scale tests of various components of the EDL systems on Earth-based testing. However, the costs of reproducing environments in which this data would be relevant in terms of Mars' environment are considerably high, resulting in testing being purely ground-based or simulating results of tests involving technologies derived from past missions.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt;

[[File:Rocky Mars Surface.jpeg|thumb|The often uneven and rocky terrain of Mars makes landing on, and traversing, the planet's surface a significant challenge]]
The surface of Mars is extremely uneven, containing [[rock (geology)|rocks]], mountainous terrain, and craters. For a landing craft, the ideal landing area would be flat and debris-free. Since this terrain is almost impossible to find on Mars, landing gear must be very stable and have enough ground clearance to prevent problems with tipping over and instability upon landing. In addition, the deceleration systems of these landers would need to include thrusters that are pointed at the ground. These thrusters must be designed so that they only need to be active for an extremely short amount of time; if they are active and pointed at rocky ground for more than a few milliseconds, they start to dig trenches, launch small rocks up into the landing gear, and cause destabilizing backpressure to be forced upon the lander.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt; 

Finding an adequate landing site means being able to estimate rock size from orbit. The technology to accurately determine rock size under 0.5 meters in diameter from orbit has not yet been developed, so instead rock size distribution is inferred from its relationship to thermal inertia, based on thermal response of the landing site measured by satellites currently orbiting Mars. The [[Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter]] also helps this cause in the sense that its cameras can see rocks larger than 0.5 m in diameter.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt; Along with the possibility of the lander tipping over on sloped surfaces, large topographical features like hills, mesas, craters and trenches pose the problem of interference with ground sensors. Radar and Doppler radar can falsely measure altitude during descent and the algorithms that target the touchdown point of the lander can be "tricked" into releasing the lander too early or late if the craft passes over mesas or trenches while descending.&lt;ref name=challenges /&gt;

== History ==
=== Background ===
[[File:Mars Observer.jpg|thumb|The loss of ''[[Mars Observer]]'' in 1993 prompted the formation of a cohesive Mars Exploration Program]]
While it was observed in ancient times by the [[Babylonians]], [[Egyptians]], [[Greeks]], and others, it was not until the invention of the [[telescope]] in the 17th century that Mars was studied in depth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mars Exploration History|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/allaboutmars/mystique/history/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first attempt at sending a probe to the surface of Mars, nicknamed [[Mars 1M|"Marsnik 1,"]] was by the [[USSR]] in 1960. The probe failed to reach [[Earth]] orbit, and the mission was ultimately unsuccessful. Failure to complete mission objectives has been common in missions designed to explore Mars; roughly two-thirds of all spacecraft destined for Mars have failed before any observation could begin.&lt;ref name=chronology&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of Mars Exploration|url=https://history.nasa.gov/marschro.htm|publisher=NASA History Program Office|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mars Exploration Program itself was formed officially in the wake of the failed [[Mars Observer]] in September 1992,&lt;ref name=strategy9520 /&gt; which had been NASA's first Mars mission since the [[Viking 1]] and [[Viking 2]] projects in 1975. The spacecraft, which was based on a modified Earth-orbiting commercial communications [[satellite]] (i.e., SES's [[Astra 1A]] satellite), carried a payload of instruments designed to study the geology, geophysics, and climate of Mars from orbit. The mission ended in August 1993 when communications were lost three days before the spacecraft had been scheduled to enter [[orbit]].&lt;ref name="mars obsvr"&gt;{{cite web|title=Mars Observer|url=http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/programmissions/missions/past/observer/|work=Mars Exploration Program|publisher=NASA|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2000s ===
In the 2000s, NASA established the Mars Scout Program as a campaign under the Mars Exploration Program to send a series of small, low-cost robotic missions to [[Mars]], competitively selected from innovative proposals by the scientific community with a budget cap of US$485 million. The first [[robotic spacecraft]] in this program was ''[[Phoenix (spacecraft)|Phoenix]]'', which utilised a [[lander (spacecraft)|lander]] originally manufactured for the canceled [[Mars Surveyor 2001]] mission. ''Phoenix'' was one of four finalists selected out of 25 proposals.&lt;ref name=ms&gt;[http://spaceflightnow.com/news/n0212/06marsscouts/ NASA selects four Mars Scout mission concepts for study]&lt;/ref&gt; The four finalists were Phoenix, MARVEL, [[Sample Collection for Investigation of Mars|SCIM]] ([[Sample Collection for Investigation of Mars]]), and the [[Aerial Regional-scale Environmental Survey|ARES]] ("Aerial Regional-scale Environmental Survey") Mars airplane.&lt;ref name=ms/&gt; SCIM was a sample return mission that would have used a free-return trajectory and aerogel to capture Mars dust and return it to Earth&lt;ref name=ms/&gt; (see also: the ''[[Stardust (spacecraft)|Stardust]]'' mission). MARVEL was an orbiter that would have searched for volcanism as well as analyzed various components of the Mars atmosphere.&lt;ref name=ms/&gt; The name is an acronym for ''Mars Volcanic Emission and Life Scout'', and it was intended to detect gases from life if it was there.&lt;ref name=ms/&gt; ARES was an aircraft concept for Mars to study the lower atmosphere and surface.&lt;ref name=ms/&gt; On September 15, 2008, NASA announced that it had selected [[MAVEN]] for as the second mission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/mars/news/maven_20080915.html |title=NASA Selects 'MAVEN' Mission to Study Mars Atmosphere |publisher=NASA |date=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasa.gov/home/hqnews/2007/jan/HQ_07003_Mars_missions.html NASA Selects Proposals for Future Mars Missions and Studies]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/home/hqnews/2007/dec/HQ_07283_Mars_Scout_Missions.html |title=NASA Delays Mars Scout Mission to 2013 |publisher=NASA |date=2007-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; This mission was budgeted at no more than US$475 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.cfm?release=2007-002 JPL.NASA.GOV: News Release]&lt;/ref&gt; After only two selections, the NASA Science Directorate announced in 2010 that Mars Scout would be incorporated into the [[Discovery program]], which was re-scoped to allow Mars missions to be proposed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.softpedia.com/news/NASA-s-Scout-Program-Discontinued-149866.shtml NASA's Scout Program Discontinued.]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[InSight]]'', a Mars seismology and geology mission, was ultimately chosen as the twelfth Discovery program mission.

{| class="wikitable collapsible collapsed"
! colspan="2"| Proposed Mars Scout program missions (2003–10)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marsnews.com/missions/scout/ Scout Missions - Mars News]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/planetary/text/nasa_pr_20010613.txt NASA SELECTS FIRST MARS SCOUT CONCEPTS FOR FURTHER STUDY (2001)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- bgcolor="#efefef"
! Mission Name
! Description
|-
| nowrap | The Great Escape (TGE)
||The mission would have directly determined the basic processes in Martian atmospheric evolution by measuring the structure and dynamics of the upper atmosphere. In addition, potentially biogenic atmospheric constituents such as [[methane]] would have been measured. The principal investigator is Alan Stern, Southwest Research Institute, Boulder, Colorado. Southwest Research Institute, San Antonio, would have provided project management.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swri.org/9what/releases/2007/marsscout.htm Southwest Research Institute proposal for Mars Scout orbiter mission selected for study by NASA]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||Artemis
||This mission would launch up to four saucer-shaped landers, two feet (0.61m) in diameter, from a "mother ship" orbiting Mars. Each would parachute onto the surface, analyzing the soil and atmosphere. Two of the four landers would be targeted at the polar regions.
|-
||[[Aerial Regional-scale Environmental Survey|ARES]]
||This mission concept proposed to send an unmanned airplane into the Martian atmosphere to observe the planet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://marsairplane.larc.nasa.gov/index.html|title=ARES - A Proposed Mars Scout Mission|publisher=NASA|date=2007-01-17|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100328015409/http://marsairplane.larc.nasa.gov/index.html|archivedate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dmZiOKjYMyI ARES Mars Aircraft] youtube.com video of model and test flight&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||Chronos
||This mission would consist of a probe designed to melt through a polar ice cap using heated jets. It would travel up to 100 yards (91m) below the surface, analyzing the melted water to determine the climatic history of Mars.&lt;ref&gt;[http://planetary.chem.tufts.edu/chronos.html CHRONOS - A Journey Through Martian History]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||KittyHawk
||This mission would create three or four winged gliders with approximately six-foot (1.83m) wingspans and would explore the [[Valles Marineris]] canyon system. The gliders would carry infrared spectrometers and cameras.
|-
||MOO
||With infrared telescopes on Earth and a spectrometer on the [[Mars Express Orbiter]], [[Mars#Atmosphere|methane]] was discovered in the Martian atmosphere. The presence of methane on Mars is very intriguing, since as an unstable gas it indicates that there must be an active source of the gas on the planet. The latest research suggests that the methane destruction lifetime is as long ~4 Earth years and as short as ~0.6 Earth years.&lt;ref name=plumes&gt;{{cite journal |title=Strong Release of Methane on Mars in Northern Summer 2003 |journal=Science |date=20 February 2009 |last1=Mumma |first1=Michael J. |volume=323 |issue= 5917 |pages=1041–1045 |doi= 10.1126/science.1165243 |url=http://images.spaceref.com/news/2009/Mumma_et_al_Methane_Mars_wSOM_accepted2.pdf |pmid=19150811 |bibcode = 2009Sci...323.1041M }}&lt;/ref&gt; In either case, the destruction lifetime for methane is much shorter than the timescale (~350 years) estimated for photochemical ([[UV]] radiation) destruction.&lt;ref name=plumes /&gt; The Mars Organics Observer would use an orbiter to characterize the Martian methane: where it is being emitted, how much is being emitted and how often it is being emitted.  
|-
||The Naiades
||Named for [[nymph]]s of springs, lakes, and rivers from Greek mythology, this mission would send two landers to a region which likely holds groundwater. The landers would search for the groundwater using low-frequency electromagnetics and other instruments.
|-
||[[Sample Collection for Investigation of Mars|SCIM]]
||A sample return mission that would briefly pass into the Martian atmosphere to scoop up about 1000 dust grains and a few liters of air without slowing from escape velocity.
|-
||[http://thor.asu.edu THOR]
||Similar to NASA's ''[[Deep Impact (spacecraft)|Deep Impact]]'', this mission would impact two copper spheres into Mars' surface to create craters in a region known to have water ice, and maybe liquid water, a few meters under the surface. An accompanying orbiter would analyze the craters from orbit. Although this mission was not selected, ice was later observed in fresh natural impacts.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=qK_4mNve1DYC&amp;pg=PA148&amp;dq=mons+olympus+height&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=YzCQT-GpIcH22AXz852ABQ&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=mons%20olympus%20height&amp;f=false Neil F. Comins -'''Discovering the Essential Universe''' (2012) - Page 148]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||Urey
||This mission calls for a lander/rover pair designed to analyze the ages of rocks. It would be targeted for the [[Cerberus (Martian Albedo Feature)|Cerberus Highlands]] region, and would look for specific minerals to help scientists compare the cratering of Mars with that of the Moon.
|-
||MARVEL
||Orbiter with spectrometers would look for volcanic emissions and life
|-
||CryoScout
||Melt probe for ice caps
|-
||Pascal
||24 mini weather stations. Also proposed in the [[Discovery Program]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2000came.work..135H R. Haberle, et al. - The Pascal Discovery Mission: A Mars Climate Network Mission (2000)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|MEO
||Mars Environmental Orbiter{{mdash}}study atmosphere and hydrology
|-
|MACO
||Mars Atmospheric Constellation Observatory{{mdash}}a network of [[Microsatellite (spaceflight)|microsatellites]] study the atmosphere
|-
|MSR
|Mars Scout Radar{{mdash}}Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) to study sub-surface
|-
|Hailstorm
||Six [[Deep Space 2]]-like hard impact landers with subsurface penetrators&lt;ref&gt;[http://soliton.ae.gatech.edu/people/rbraun/classes/spacesystems05/Proposals/HailstormProposal.pdf Hailstorm Proposal]{{dead link|date=November 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} (.pdf)&lt;/ref&gt; 
|}

=== 2010s ===
A significant budget cut of US$300 million to NASA's planetary science division occurred in FY2013, which prompted the cancellation of the agency's participation in ESA's [[ExoMars]] program, and a reevaluation of the Mars Exploration Program as a whole.&lt;ref name="where we been where goin"&gt;{{cite web|last=Brown|first=Adrian|title=MSL and the NASA Mars Exploration Program: Where we've been, where we're going|url=http://www.thespacereview.com/article/2129/1|publisher=The Space Review|accessdate=24 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Frank | last = Morning Jr. | title = NASA Units Hope For 2018 Robotic Mars Mission | date = Feb 14, 2012 | url = http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story_generic.jsp?channel=aerospacedaily&amp;id=news/asd/2012/02/14/02.xml&amp;headline=NASA%20Units%20Hope%20For%202018%20Robotic%20Mars%20Mission | work = [[Aviation Week]] | accessdate = 2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='about'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nasa.gov/offices/marsplanning/about/index.html | title = About the Mars Program Planning Group | accessdate = 2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2012, the Mars Program Planning Group (MPPG) was convened in Washington, D.C. to discuss candidate mission concepts for the 2018 or 2020 launch window,&lt;ref name='New Generation'/&gt;&lt;ref name='about'/&gt; in an initiative known as Mars Next Generation.&lt;ref name='New Generation'&gt;{{cite news | first = Dan | last= Leone| title = NASA Raids Outer Planets Budget To Fund Fast Start on Mars Reboot | date = 24 February 2012 | url = http://www.spacenews.com/civil/120224-nasa-raids-outer-planets-budget-fund-mars.html | work = Space News | accessdate = 2012-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nature&gt;{{cite news | author = Eric Hand | title = Beset by budget cuts, US Mars scientists look to possible 2018 mission | date = 28 February 2012 | url = http://blogs.nature.com/news/2012/02/beset-by-budget-cuts-us-mars-scientists-look-to-possible-2018-mission.html | work = Nature | accessdate = 2012-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author= Kate Taylor | title = NASA calls for ideas for future Mars missions | date = 16 April 2012 | url = http://www.tgdaily.com/space-features/62755-nasa-calls-for-ideas-for-future-mars-missions | work = TG Daily | accessdate = 2012-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of the MPPG was to develop foundations for a program-level architecture for robotic exploration of Mars that is consistent with the [[Presidency of Barack Obama|Obama administration]]'s challenge of sending humans to Mars orbit in the decade of the 2030s,&lt;ref name='about'/&gt; yet remain responsive to the primary scientific goals of the 2011 NRC Decadal Survey for Planetary Science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://solarsystem.nasa.gov/2013decadal/ |title=Science Strategy &amp;#124; NASA Solar System Exploration |website=Solarsystem.nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2016-02-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721054020/http://solarsystem.nasa.gov/2013decadal/ |archive-date=2011-07-21 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The MPPG used non-consensus, individual inputs of both NASA civil servant and contractor employees, with resulting decisions being the exclusive responsibility of NASA. 

The immediate focus of the MPPG was on the collection of multiple mission concept options for the 2018 and 2020 Mars launch window.&lt;ref name='about'/&gt; At a budget envelope of $700 million [[USD]], including a [[launch vehicle]], it was presumed that the mission would be limited to an [[orbiter]].&lt;ref name=nature/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author= Stephen Clark | title = Sample return remains focus of NASA's Mars program | date = September 27, 2012 | url = http://www.spaceflightnow.com/news/n1209/27mppg/ | work = Space Flight Now | accessdate = 2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Near-term ideas were taken into consideration for early mission planning in the 2018-2024 timeframe, while mid- to longer-term ideas informed program-level architecture planning for 2026 and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.astrobio.net/pressrelease/4785/concepts-for-future-mars-missions |title=Concepts for Future Mars Missions - Astrobiology Magazine |website=Astrobio.net |date=2012-05-29 |accessdate=2016-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Strategies explored for such a mission included a [[Mars sample-return mission|sample-return mission]] where soil samples are placed in Mars orbit in the late 2020s or early 2030s, an in-situ soil analysis, and a study of Mars' surface and deep interior preceding a sample-return mission and/or crewed mission.&lt;ref name='about'/&gt; Concept missions that were studied that fit the budget requirement of US$700 million to US$800 million included the [[Next Mars Orbiter]] (NeMO) to replace aging satellites' telecommunication services, and a stationary lander to investigate and select samples suitable for a later return to Earth.&lt;ref name='about'/&gt; Prior to the findings of the MPPG, the [[United States House Committee on Appropriations|House Appropriations Committee's]] Commerce-Justice-Science subcommittee approved a budget in April 2012 that reinstated US$150 million to the Planetary Science budget, with a caveat that a sample-return mission be mandated.&lt;ref name="where we been where goin" /&gt; The MPPG's final report was drafted in August 2012 and published in September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/offices/marsplanning/milestones/index.html |title=NASA - Mars Program Planning Group Milestones |website=Nasa.gov |date= |accessdate=2016-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spacenews.com/civil/120925-mars-planning-group-endorses-sample-return.html ]{{dead link|date=February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/pdf/691580main_MPPG-Integrated-v13i-Summary%20Report-9-25-12.pdf |format=PDF |title=Summary of the Final Report |date=2012-09-25 |accessdate=2016-02-23 |website=Nasa.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Ultimately endorsing a sample-return mission, the recommendation influenced NASA's FY2014 budget process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/pdf/654110main_CAPS%20MPPG%20May%202012%20final%20with%20MEP%20extract.pdf |format=PDF |title=NRC Committee on Astrobiology and Planetary Science (CAP+S) |date=2012-05-23 |accessdate=2016-02-23 |website=Nasa.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Missions ==
=== List ===
{| class="wikitable sortable" style="font-size:90%"
|-
! scope="col" | Mission
! scope="col" class="unsortable" | Patch
! scope="col" | Vehicle
! scope="col" | Launch
! scope="col" | Launch pad
! scope="col" | Launch vehicle{{efn|name="serial"|Serial number displayed in parentheses.}}
! scope="col" | Status
! scope="col" | Duration
|-
! scope="row" | [[Mars Global Surveyor]]
| [[File:Mars Global Surveyor - patch transparent.png|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''Mars Global Surveyor''
| data-sort-value="01" | November 7, 1996, 17:00 UTC
| [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station|Cape Canaveral]] [[Cape Canaveral Space Launch Complex 17|LC-17A]]
| [[Delta II|Delta II 7925]]
| {{Success|Completed}}
| data-sort-value="04" | 3,647 days
|-
! scope="row" rowspan="2" | [[Mars Surveyor '98]]
| rowspan="2" | [[File:M98patch.png|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''[[Mars Climate Orbiter]]''
| data-sort-value="02" | December 11, 1998, 18:45 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17A
| Delta II 7425
| {{Failure}}
| data-sort-value="10" | 286 days
|-
| ''[[Mars Polar Lander]]''
| data-sort-value="03" | January 3, 1999, 20:21 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17A
| Delta II 7425
| {{Failure}}
| data-sort-value="09" | 334 days
|-
! scope="row" | [[2001 Mars Odyssey]]
| [[File:2001 Mars Odyssey - mars-odyssey-logo-sm.png|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''Mars Odyssey''
| data-sort-value="04" | April 7, 2001, 15:02 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17A
| Delta II 7925-9.5
| {{Operational}}
| data-sort-value="01" | {{Age in days|2001|04|07|format=commas}} days
|-
! scope="row" rowspan="2" | [[Mars Exploration Rover]]
| rowspan="2" |
| ''[[Spirit (rover)|Spirit]]''
| data-sort-value="05" | June 10, 2003, 17:58 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17A
| Delta II 7925-9.5
| {{Success|Completed}}
| data-sort-value="06" | 2,695 days
|-
| ''[[Opportunity (rover)|Opportunity]]''
| data-sort-value="06" | July 7, 2003, 03:18 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17B 
| Delta II 7925H-9.5
| {{Success|Completed}}
| data-sort-value="02" | 5,498 days
|-
! scope="row" | [[Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter]]
| [[File:Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter insignia.png|center|frameless|upright=0.10]]
| ''Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter''
| data-sort-value="07" | August 12, 2005, 11:43 UTC
| Cape Canaveral [[Cape Canaveral Space Launch Complex 41|LC-41]]
| [[Atlas V|Atlas V 401]] ([[List of Atlas launches (2000–2009)#2005|AV-007]])
| {{Operational}}
| data-sort-value="03" | {{Age in days|2005|08|15|format=commas}} days
|-
! scope="row" | [[Phoenix (spacecraft)|Phoenix]]{{Efn|name=Mars Scout|Mission conducted as part of the Mars Scout Program.}}
| [[File:Phoenix mission logo.png|center|frameless|upright=0.14]]
| ''Phoenix''
| data-sort-value="08" | August 4, 2007 09:26 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-17A
| Delta II 7925
| {{Success|Completed}}
| data-sort-value="08" | 457 days
|-
! scope="row" | [[Mars Science Laboratory]]
| [[File:Mars Science Laboratory mission logo.png|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''[[Curiosity (rover)|Curiosity]]''
| data-sort-value="09" | November 26, 2011, 15:02 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-41
| Atlas V 541 ([[List of Atlas launches (2010–2019)#2012|AV-028]])
| {{Operational}}
| data-sort-value="05" | {{Age in days|2012|11|26|format=commas}} days
|-
! scope="row" | [[MAVEN]]{{Efn|name=Mars Scout}}
| [[File:MAVEN Mission Logo.png|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''MAVEN''
| data-sort-value="10" | November 18, 2013, 18:28 UTC
| Cape Canaveral LC-41
| Atlas V 401 ([[List of Atlas launches (2010–2019)#2013|AV-038]])
| {{Operational}}
| data-sort-value="07" | {{Age in days|2013|11|18|format=commas}} days
|-
! scope="row" rowspan="2" | [[Mars 2020]]
| rowspan="2" | [[File:Mars 2020 JPL second insignia.svg|center|frameless|upright=0.15]]
| ''[[Perseverance (rover)|Perseverance]]''
| rowspan="2" data-sort-value="11" | July 2020
| rowspan="2" | Cape Canaveral LC-41
| rowspan="2" | Atlas V 541 ([[List of Atlas launches (2020–2029)#2020|AV-088]])
| {{Planned|Future}}
| {{Color|grey|N/A}}
|-
| ''[[Mars Helicopter Ingenuity|Ingenuity]]''
| {{Planned|Future}}
| {{Color|grey|N/A}}
|}

=== Timeline ===
{{Mars Exploration Program}}

== See also ==
*[[Exploration of Mars]]
{{Portal bar|Astronomy|Biology|Solar System|Spaceflight|United States}}

== References ==
'''Notes'''
{{Notelist}}
'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/ Mars Exploration Program] at the [[Jet Propulsion Laboratory]]
* [http://mepag.jpl.nasa.gov/ Mars Exploration Program Analysis Group (MEPAG)] at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory

{{Mars}}
{{NASA planetary exploration programs}}
{{NASA space program}}
{{Use American English|date=January 2014}}

[[Category:Exploration of Mars]]
[[Category:NASA programs]]</text>
      <sha1>d84khp00c2lqfweojw3z76gi5xzoq3c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
