<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Republican faction (Spanish Civil War)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31596058</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960849144</id>
      <parentid>960471778</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-05T07:10:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Havsjö</username>
        <id>35067771</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="18073" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Flag of Spain 1931 1939.svg|right|thumb|State [[flag of the Second Spanish Republic]]. [[File:FIAV historical.svg|23px]] [[File:FIAV 011011.svg|20px]]]]
The '''Republican faction''' ({{lang-es|Bando republicano}}), also known as the '''Loyalist faction''' ({{lang-es|Bando leal}} or ''bando gubernamental''), was the side in the [[Spanish Civil War]] of 1936 to 1939 that supported the elected government of the [[Second Spanish Republic]] against the far-right [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|Nationalist]] or rebel faction of the military rebellion.&lt;ref name="Antony Beevor 1982 revised 2006"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Battle for Spain|author=Antony Beevor|publisher=Orion|year=2006|isbn=978-0-7538-2165-7|origyear=1982|author-link=Antony Beevor}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name '''Republicans''' ({{lang|es|republicanos}}) was mainly used by its members and supporters, while its opponents used the term '''''Rojos''''' ([[red]]s) to refer to this faction due to its left-leaning ideology, including far-left communist and [[anarchism in Spain|anarchist]] groups, and the support it received from the [[Soviet Union]].

==Participants==

===Political groups===

====Popular Front====
[[File:Flag of the Popular Front (Spain).svg|thumb|160px|Popular Front]]
{{main|Popular Front (Spain)}}

====Nationalists====
''Not to be confused with "Nacionales", one of the names adopted by the [[rebel faction]].''
=====Basque=====
* [[Basque nationalism]]
** [[Basque Nationalist Party]]
** [[Basque Nationalist Action]]

=====Catalan=====
[[File:Flag of Catalonia.svg|thumb|160px|Catalonia]]
* [[Catalan nationalism]]
** [[Republican Left of Catalonia]]
** [[Acció Catalana Republicana]]
** [[Estat Català]]

===Unions===

====CNT/FAI====
{{main|Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|Federación Anarquista Ibérica}}
[[File:Bandera CNT-FAI.png|thumb|160px|CNT/FAI]]

====UGT====
{{main|Unión General de Trabajadores}}
[[File:UGT flag.svg|thumb|160px|UGT]]

===Military===
{{main|Spanish Republican Armed Forces}}

====People's Republican Army====
In October 1936 the republican government in [[Vitoria-Gasteiz|Vitoria]] began a reorganization process of the fragmented army. The self-denominated [[People's Republican Army]] ({{lang-es|Ejército Popular de la República}}, EPR) consisted of those [[Spanish Republican Army]] units that had remained loyal to the Republic and [[militia]] members who were integrated into the new structure.

====Other branches====
* [[Spanish Republican Navy]]
* ''[[Carabineros]]''; one of the units of law enforcement where the 1936 [[Spanish coup of July 1936|coup of the pro-Fascist generals]] found the least support.&lt;ref&gt;Alejandro de Quesada, ''The Spanish Civil War 1936–39 (2): Republican Forces'', p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henry Buckley &amp; Paul Preston, ''The Life and Death of the Spanish Republic: A Witness to the Spanish Civil War'', I.B. Tauris, 2013 {{ISBN|978-1780769318}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Civil Guard (Spain)|Civil Guard]]
* [[Guardias de Asalto]]
* [[Spanish Republican Air Force]]

====The International Brigades and other foreign volunteers====
{{main|International Brigades|Foreign involvement in the Spanish Civil War}}
[[File:Flag of the International Brigades.svg|thumb|160px|International Brigades]]
At least 40,000 individual volunteers from 52 nations,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.yale.edu/opa/arc-ybc/v30.n22/story13.html |title=''Yale Bulletin &amp; Calendar'' (2002), "Exhibit documents volunteers' role in Spanish Civil War" (March 15), vol. 30, no. 22. (6 December 2012). |access-date=6 December 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160820064117/http://www.yale.edu/opa/arc-ybc/v30.n22/story13.html |archive-date=20 August 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; usually socialists, communists or anarchists, fought for the Republican side.

The vast majority of these, an estimated 32,000 men and women,&lt;ref name="Thomas 2001 p. 942"&gt;''Thomas'' (2001) p. 942&lt;/ref&gt; served in the [[International Brigades]], organized in close conjunction with the [[Comintern]].

About another 3,000 foreign volunteers fought as members of militias belonging to the [[Anarcho-syndicalism|anarcho-syndicalist]] [[trade union|labor/trade union]] ''[[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]]'' and the [[Anti-Stalinist left|anti-Stalinist Marxist]] ''[[POUM]]''.&lt;ref name="Thomas 2001 p. 942"/&gt;  Those fighting with POUM included one of the most famous veterans of the war, [[George Orwell]].&lt;ref&gt;Orwell, George. ''Homage to Catalonia''. New York: Harcourt, Brace, 19&lt;/ref&gt;

====Regional armies====
[[File:Flag of the Basque Country.svg|thumb|160px|Basque Country]]
* [[Basque Army]]
* [[Basque Auxiliary Navy]]
* [[People's Army of Catalonia]]

==Direct foreign support==
===Mexico===
[[File:Flag of Mexico (1934-1968).svg|thumb|160px|[[Mexico|United Mexican States]]]]
Mexico supported fully and publicly the claim of the Madrid government and the Republicans.  Mexico refused to follow the Anglo-French non-intervention proposals. President [[Lázaro Cárdenas]] saw the war as similar to Mexico's own revolution although a large part of Mexican society wanted a Nationalist victory. Mexico's attitude gave immense moral comfort to the Republic, especially since the major Latin American governments—those of [[Argentina]], Brazil, [[Chile]], and [[Peru]]—sympathized more or less openly with the Nationalists. But Mexican aid could mean relatively little in practical terms if the French border were closed and if Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy remained free to supply the Nationalists with a quality and quantity of weapons far beyond the power of Mexico.

Mexico furnished $2,000,000 in aid and provided some material assistance, which included a small number of American-made aircraft such as the [[Bellanca CH-300]] and [[Spartan 8W Zeus|Spartan Zeus]] that had previously served in the [[Mexican Air Force]]. Not all of these aircraft reached the Republicans.

===Soviet Union===
[[File:Flag of the Soviet Union (1936-1955).svg|thumb|190px|[[Soviet Union|Union of Soviet Socialist Republics]]]]
The [[Soviet Union]] primarily provided material assistance to the Republican forces. In total the USSR provided Spain with 806 planes, 362 tanks, and 1,555 artillery pieces.&lt;ref&gt;Academy of Sciences of the USSR, International Solidarity with the Spanish Republic, 1936–1939 (Moscow: Progress, 1974), 329–30&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union ignored the League of Nations embargo and sold arms to the Republic when few other nations would do so; thus it was the Republic's only important source of major weapons. [[Joseph Stalin]] had signed the [[Non-Intervention Agreement]] but decided to break the pact. However, unlike Hitler and Mussolini who openly violated the pact, Stalin tried to do so secretly.&lt;ref name="Arms for Spain Gerald Howson"&gt;Arms for Spain Gerald Howson&lt;/ref&gt;  He created a section X of the Soviet Union military to head the operation, coined [[Operation X (Spanish Civil War)|Operation X]]. However, while a new branch of the military was created especially for Spain, most of the weapons and artillery sent to Spain were antiques. Stalin also used weapons captured in past conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). pp. 152–53.&lt;/ref&gt; However, modern weapons such as [[BT-5]] tanks&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Polikarpov I-16|I-16]] fighter aircraft were also supplied to Spain.

Many of the Soviet deliveries were lost, or were smaller than Stalin had ordered. He only gave short notice, which meant many weapons were lost in the delivery process.&lt;ref name="Arms for Spain Gerald Howson"/&gt; Lastly, when the ships did leave with supplies for the Republicans, the journey was extremely slow. Stalin ordered the builders to include false decks in the design of ships. Then, once the ship left shore it was required to change its flag and change the color of parts of the ship to avoid capture by the Nationalists.&lt;ref name="Arms for Spain Gerald Howson"/&gt; However, in 1938, Stalin withdrew his troops and tanks as Republican government policy floundered. Historian [[Hugh Thomas (writer)|Hugh Thomas]] comments "had they been able to purchase and transport good arms from US, British, and French manufacturers, the socialist and republican members of the Spanish government might have tried to cut themselves loose from [[Joseph Stalin|Stalin]]".&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (2003) p. 683.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Republic had to pay for Soviet arms with the official gold reserves of the [[Bank of Spain]], in an affair that would become a frequent subject of Francoist propaganda afterward (see [[Moscow Gold]]). The cost to the Republic of Soviet arms was more than US $500 million (in 1936 prices); the entire of Spain's gold reserve, the fourth-largest in the world. 176 tonnes was transferred through France.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). pp. 153–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviet Union also sent a number of military advisers to Spain (2,000&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;–3,000&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen. The Spanish Civil War. A very short introduction. Oxford University Press. New York. 2005. p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;).&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (2003). p. 944.&lt;/ref&gt; While Soviet troops amounted to no more than 500 men at a time, Soviet volunteers often operated Soviet-made Republican tanks and aircraft, particularly at the beginning of the war.&lt;ref name="thomas637"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 637.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the Soviet Union directed Communist parties around the world to organize and recruit the International Brigades. Another significant Soviet involvement was the pervasive activity of the [[NKVD]] all along the Republican rearguard. Communist figures like [[Vittorio Vidali]] ("Comandante Contreras"), [[Iosif Grigulevich]] and, above all, [[Aleksandr Mikhailovich Orlov|Alexander Orlov]] led those not-so-secret operations, that included murders like those of [[Andreu Nin]] and [[José Robles]].

==Ambivalent support==

===France===
{{see also|Escuadrilla España}}
[[File:Flag of France (1794–1815, 1830–1958).svg|thumb|160px|[[French Third Republic|French Republic]]]]
The French position towards the Spanish Republic was characterized by its hesitant attitude and its ambivalence. Thus the government of France did not send direct support to the Spanish Republicans and towards the end of the beleaguered republic ended up turning against it, instead recognizing the [[Francoist]] State. President [[Albert Lebrun]] opposed direct assistance, but the left-wing government of [[Prime Minister of France|French Prime Minister]] [[Léon Blum]] was sympathetic to the Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Antony Beevor, ''The Battle for Spain''. Orion. (1982 revised 2006). {{ISBN|978-0-7538-2165-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blum considered both sending military aid and technology to the Republicans including aircraft and utilizing the [[French Navy]] to blockade the Franco-led [[Army of Africa (Spain)|Spanish Army of Africa]] from crossing from [[Spanish Morocco]] to Spain.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 14"&gt;Michael Alpert (1994). ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England: MacMillan Press; New York: St. Martin’s  Press, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Also upon the outbreak of civil war the Spanish Republican government and the government of France in diplomatic messages discussed a potential transfer of French aircraft to Spanish Republican forces.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 14"/&gt;

The Blum government feared that the success of Francoist forces in Spain would result in the creation of an ally state of Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy that would allow German and Italian military forces to be based in the [[Canary Islands|Canary]] and [[Balearic Islands]].&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 14"/&gt; Right-wing politicians, however, heard of the French government's intention to send military support to the Spanish Republicans in the war and opposed the French government's actions by means of a vicious campaign against the Blum government for its alleged support of the Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert (1994). ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London: MacMillan Press; New York: St. Martin’s Press. pp. 14–15.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 July 1936, British officials had discussed with Prime Minister Blum their position on the war and convinced Blum not to send arms to the Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert (1994). ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London: MacMillan Press; New York: St. Martin’s Press. p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, on 27 July, the French government declared that it would not send military aid, technology, or forces.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert. ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England, UK: MACMILLAN PRESS, LTD; New York, New York, USA: ST. MARTIN'S PRESS, INC, 1994. Pp. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; However Blum made clear that France reserved the right to provide aid should it wish, and indicated also indicated his support for the Republic, saying:
{{quote|We could have delivered arms to the Spanish Government [(Republicans)], a legitimate government...We have not done so, in order not to give an excuse to those who would be tempted to send arms to the rebels.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 41"&gt;Michael Alpert. ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England, UK: MACMILLAN PRESS, LTD; New York, New York, USA: ST. MARTIN'S PRESS, INC, 1994. Pp. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 1 August 1936, a pro-Republican rally of 20,000 people confronted Blum demanding that he send aircraft to the Spanish Republicans at the same time as right-wing politicians attacked Blum for supporting the Republic and being responsible for provoking [[Kingdom of Italy#Fascism (1922–1943)|Fascist Italian]] intervention on the side of Franco.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 41"/&gt;

[[Nazi Germany]] informed the French ambassador in Berlin that Germany would hold France responsible if it supported what it described as "the maneuvers of Moscow" by supporting the Spanish Republicans.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 43"&gt;Michael Alpert. ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England, UK: MACMILLAN PRESS, LTD; New York, New York, USA: ST. MARTIN'S PRESS, INC, 1994. Pp. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, on 21 August 1936, France, the UK, and Italy (under pressure from both France and the UK) signed the [[Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War|Non-Intervention proposals]] involving the Spanish Civil War.&lt;ref name="Michael Alpert 1994. Pp. 43"/&gt;

However, the Blum government provided military assistance to the Spanish Republicans through covert means by supplying obsolete [[Potez 54]], [[Dewoitine]] and [[Loire 46]] aircraft to the [[Spanish Republican Air Force]] from 7 August 1936 to December of that year.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert. ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England, UK: MACMILLAN PRESS, LTD; New York, New York, USA: ST. MARTIN'S PRESS, INC, 1994. Pp. 46-47.&lt;/ref&gt; Often with their weapons removed, these almost useless and vulnerable planes rarely survived three months of air missions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airaces.narod.ru/spane/desnitsk.htm Air Aces - Semyon Desnitsky]&lt;/ref&gt; Also, until 8 September 1936, aircraft could freely pass from France into Spain if they were bought in other countries.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert. ''A New International History of the Spanish Civil War''. Hampshire and London, England, UK: MACMILLAN PRESS, LTD; New York, New York, USA: ST. MARTIN'S PRESS, INC, 1994. Pp. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the half-hearted and largely ineffective support by France to the Republicans ended in December 1936, German intelligence reported to Franco and his faction that the French military was engaging in open discussions about intervention in the war.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley G. Payne. ''Franco and Hitler: Spain, Germany, and World War II''. Yale University Press, 2008. p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Allegedly in 1938 Franco feared an immediate French intervention against a potential Francoist victory in Spain through French occupation of [[Catalonia]], the Balearic Islands, and Spanish Morocco.&lt;ref&gt;Igor Lukeš, Erik Goldstein (1999). The Munich crisis, 1938: prelude to World War II. London &amp; Portland, OR: Frank Cass. p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards the end of the Civil War, most seagoing vessels of the [[Spanish Republican Navy]] were evacuated to [[Bizerte]] in the [[French protectorate of Tunisia]] where the fleet was impounded by the [[French Third Republic|French authorities]] and later handed over to the Francoist faction.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh. ''The Spanish Civil War''. Penguin Books. 2001. London. p. 877&lt;/ref&gt; Except for a few crewmen who were put on guard duty on the ships, the Spanish Republican seamen and their officers were interned in a [[concentration camp]] at [[Meknassy|Meheri Zabbens]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://marinarepublicana.blogspot.com/2011/08/almirante-valdes-vs-o-av.html Almirante Valdés (VS o AV)]&lt;/ref&gt;  Defeated members of other branches of the [[Spanish Republican Armed Forces]] who escaped were arrested by French authorities and interned in concentration camps in Southern France, such as the [[Camp de concentration d'Argelès-sur-Mer]] which at one time held about 100,000 defeated Spanish Republicans. From there some managed to go into exile or went to join the [[Allies of World War II|armies of the Allies]] to fight against the [[Axis powers]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pourlamemoire.com/reportages-tempoignages.php 24 au 26 août 1944 Libération de Paris par les chars... espagnols de la nueve]{{dead link|date=April 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; while others ended up in [[Nazi concentration camps]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xtec.cat/iesrovira-forns/documents/EstimadaSisqueta.pdf "Republicans deportats als camps de concentració nazis"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130528190203/http://www.xtec.cat/iesrovira-forns/documents/EstimadaSisqueta.pdf |date=2013-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Spanish Civil War}}

[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Republicanism in Spain]]
[[Category:Communism in Spain]]
[[Category:Anti-fascism in Spain]]
[[Category:Far-left politics]]</text>
      <sha1>c8zukhb4zw088h43nqddaf3y8h7bh9t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
