<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Tubes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>275478</id>
    <revision>
      <id>958499934</id>
      <parentid>958138893</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-24T04:29:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.113.233.249</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Debut album */added content</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="49384" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the American rock band|the band's first album|The Tubes (album)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2015}}
{{More citations needed|date=July 2010}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name             = The Tubes
| image            = Tubes_29111977_33_300x200.jpg
| caption          = The Tubes in [[Oslo]], [[Norway]], in 1977
| image_size       = 250
| landscape        = Yes
| background       = group_or_band
| origin           = [[San Francisco]], [[California]], United States
| genre            = {{hlist|[[Rock music|Rock]]|[[hard rock]]|[[experimental rock]]|[[proto-punk]]|[[glam rock]]}}
| years_active     = 1972–present
| label            = {{hlist|[[A&amp;M Records|A&amp;M]]|[[Capitol Records|Capitol]]}}
| associated_acts  = 
| website          = [http://www.thetubes.com/ Official website]
| current_members  = {{ubl|Roger Steen|[[Prairie Prince]]|Rick Anderson|[[Fee Waybill]]|David Medd}}
| past_members     = {{ubl|[[Vince Welnick]]|[[Bill Spooner]]|Michael Cotten|Bob Mcintosh|Re Styles|[[Mingo Lewis]]|[[Jane Dornacker]]|David Killingsworth|Gary Cambra}}
}}

'''The Tubes''' are a [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]]-based [[Rock music|rock]] [[musical ensemble|band]]. Their eponymous 1975 debut [[The Tubes (album)|album]] included the single "[[White Punks on Dope]]," while their 1983 single "[[She's a Beauty]]" was a top-10 U.S. hit and its music video was frequently played in the early days of [[MTV]]. The band also performed in the 1980 film ''[[Xanadu (film)|Xanadu]]'', singing the rock portion of the cross-genre song "Dancin'" opposite a [[big band]].

==History==

The Tubes formed in 1972 in San Francisco, California, featuring members from two Phoenix, Arizona, bands who had relocated to San Francisco in 1969. One, The Beans, included Bill Spooner, Rick Anderson, Vince Welnick, Frank Martinez, Scott Hornbeck and Bob Macintosh. The other, the Red White and Blues Band, featured Prairie Prince, Roger Steen, and David Killingsworth. After performing at [[Expo '70]] in Japan, Killingsworth left the Red, White and Blues Band, leaving Steen and Prince to audition new bass players, albeit unsuccessfully. Before moving to San Francisco the Beans had been a local favorite in Phoenix, selling out shows with a tongue-in-cheek concept rock show called "The Mother of Ascension" featuring costumes and props. After moving, Bill Spooner worked at the [[Fillmore West]] sweeping floors in between Beans shows at the Longshoremen's Hall and other minor venues. The band's loud, heavy jamming style didn't attract attention, and the band needed to go back home to Phoenix. There they would sell out shows, which provided enough money to pay their rent. The Beans' manager and former [[Alice Cooper]] Group drummer, John Speer, suggested they add Prince and Steen along with their roadie John Waybill to one of these shows. Waybill's nickname among the band was "Fee," short for "[[Fiji]]," thanks to his copious head of hippie hair.

"The Radar Men from Uranus" played the [[Celebrity Theatre]] in Phoenix, as well as a show in Mexico where they were run out of town by the police. Rick Anderson almost drowned after he was washed out to sea while swimming. The group would stick together and play shows at biker bars such as The Inn of The Beginning. The vocals at this time were shared by Spooner, Steen and Waybill as different characters. Prairie Prince and Phoenix high school friend Michael Cotten were attending art school at the [[San Francisco Art Institute]] at this time; they attracted local press attention by painting a mural of crashing waves on the side of the [[Cliff House (San Francisco, California)|Cliff House]] Restaurant. Cotten was asked by Spooner to buy an [[ARP synthesizer]] instead of a film camera and began to perform with the band as well as create props and costumes.

One of the first "Tubes" shows was at the Art Institute cafeteria as part of an art show for classmate and future Hollywood director [[Kathryn Bigelow]]. While experimenting with their stage show and art, Prince and Michael met model Re Styles while painting the Cliff House Mural. Styles has appeared in both [[Alejandro Jodorowsky]]'s ''[[The Holy Mountain (1973 film)|The Holy Mountain]]'' and [[Sun Ra]]'s ''[[Space Is the Place]]'' and posed for ''[[Playboy]]'' and ''[[Penthouse (magazine)|Penthouse]]'' magazines. Prince and Styles began dating and she started performing with the band, playing [[Patty Hearst]] and dressing in wild leather outfits during the "Mondo Bondage" dance with Waybill. After several years of playing biker bars, the band needed help. They had a temporary agreement with producer [[David Rubinson]] and played on bills with [[The Pointer Sisters]] and [[Sylvester (singer)]], but were still trying to find an audience. Prince had been hired by newly formed fusion rock band [[Journey (band)|Journey]] to record demos, and approached their manager [[Herbie Herbert]], a former [[Santana (band)|Santana]] roadie and [[Bill Graham (promoter)|Bill Graham]] employee. Herbert made a deal with Graham that if the Tubes could sell out three local shows, Graham would give him an opening slot on the show of his choice.

Herbert booked shows at a local club called the Village, which sold out thanks to themes inspired by the San Francisco post-hippie underground culture such as "The Streaker's Ball" and "Mondo Bondage." Much to Graham's dismay, Herbert chose an opening slot for the upcoming [[Led Zeppelin]] show at [[Kezar Stadium]]. The band pulled out the stops, including Waybill dressed as an early version of "Quay Lewd" throwing "[[Cocaine]]" (flour) and "Pills" (candy) at the crowd, who threw it back. Graham threatened Herbert that the band would never play in San Francisco again but calmed down and eventually fell in love with the band, booking them at [[Winterland]] and other California venues for New Year's shows and Halloween. After the 1973 Led Zeppelin show, Herbert wanted to manage the band, but Spooner and the group went with local management team Mort Moriarty and Gary Peterson, also known as "Bag O' Bucks." Moriarty was interested in the use of video in rock music and saw the Tubes' stage show as the future of music videos. Bob Macintosh died of cancer at this time, leaving Prince as the only drummer.

In 1974, Bag O' Bucks filmed a Tubes show at the [[California Hall]] and shopped the "video demo" around Los Angeles. [[George Daly (music executive)|George Daly]], [[Columbia Records]] head of A&amp;R in San Francisco, made some Tubes demos, but NY [CBS] Corporate would not agree to signing the Tubes to Columbia due to the radical nature of their art. After 18 months, with no success at his own label, Daly, at the suggestion of [[Rick Wakeman]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b08hckcd | title=BBC Radio 2 - Sounds of the 70s with Johnnie Walker, Rick Wakeman}}&lt;/ref&gt; finally pitched the group to competitor [[A&amp;M Records]], where his former Columbia East Coast A&amp;R colleague and friend, [[Kip Cohen]], had recently headed the A&amp;R division. Daly personally flew managers Moriarity and Petersen down to LA, and Cohen signed The Tubes to A&amp;M, a rare example of cross-company support by major label executives. Working with lawyer [[Greg Fischbach]], the band signed with A&amp;M Records.

===Debut album===

The Tubes' first album, ''[[The Tubes (album)|The Tubes]]'' (1975), was produced by [[Al Kooper]]. The track "[[White Punks on Dope]]" was an "absurd anthem of wretched excess" and ridiculed the Hollywood kids of the rich and famous. Since then the song has been [[cover version|covered]] by [[Mötley Crüe]], and the German rock musician [[Nina Hagen]] took the tune and set new lyrics to it (not a translation of the original lyrics), titled her work "[[TV-Glotzer]]" ("[[Couch potato|Couch Potato]]"), using this song as the opening track of her own debut album ''[[Nina Hagen Band (album)|Nina Hagen Band]]'' (1978). The album track "What Do You Want from Life?," which became another of the Tubes' signature songs, satirizes consumerism and celebrity culture and climaxes in a "hard-sell" monologue by Waybill, which name-checks celebrities such as [[Bob Dylan]], [[Paul Williams (songwriter)|Paul Williams]] and [[Randolph Mantooth]], as well as well-known products of the period, including the Dynagym exercise machine and a host of American vehicles such as "...a herd of [[Winnebago Industries|Winnebago]]'s and a [[Mercury Montclair]]...".

By late 1975, the band created a stage show unlike any other after hiring [[Kenny Ortega]] to direct and choreograph, comedian [[Jane Dornacker]] and her band "Lelia and the Snakes," and event support/video pioneer T.J. McHose to run a live video feed with films for each song. The show was critically acclaimed and broke them into show business in Los Angeles during sold out runs at the [[Roxy Theatre (West Hollywood)|Roxy Theater]], David Allen's Boarding House and [[Bimbo's]] in San Francisco, as well as [[The Bottom Line (venue)|The Bottom Line]] in New York City. Compared at the time to ''[[The Rocky Horror Picture Show]]'', the Tubes' stage show was closer to ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' with its mix of topical satire and subversive postmodern [[Andy Kaufman]]-like routines such as Waybill beating up a couple in the front row (who were planted) during the "Crime Medley," then taking off his disguise as the band launched into "Mondo Bondage" and a huge stack of "Kill Amplifiers" (cardboard) falling on Quay Lewd during the finale of "White Punks on Dope."

The band was part of the mid-'70s underground comedy scene that included [[The Credibility Gap]], [[Firesign Theater]], [[Ace Trucking Company]], [[Kentucky Fried Theater]], [[Groundlings]], [[Ken Shapiro]]'s Channel One Video Theatre and [[National Lampoon (magazine)|National Lampoon]]. The L.A. Connection Comedy Theatre performed during the Tubes show intermission many times. In 1975, the Tubes were offered a spot on ''[[Saturday Night Live with Howard Cosell]]'' and ''[[Saturday Night Live|NBC's Saturday Night]]'', but manager Mort Moriarty wanted the band to be able to play several songs in a row to show off how tight their transitions were; both shows declined, and without major network TV appearances, the Tubes missed out on huge TV exposure, cementing their "cult" status until the early '80s. The band's touring crew was up to 24 people at this point, making it hard to tour for the standard weeks on end most bands of the era were committing to build a fan base.

===''Young and Rich''===

The Tubes' second album, ''[[Young and Rich]]'' (1976) on [[A&amp;M Records]], was [[record producer|produced]] by [[Ken Scott]]. It featured "Don't Touch Me There," a suggestive duet between Waybill and Re Styles, which was [[arrangement|arranged]] in classic "[[Wall of Sound]]" style by [[Jack Nitzsche]]. The song was co-written by [[Ron Nagle]] and Tubes dancer/vocalist [[Jane Dornacker]].

The band toured America with a new stage show including new numbers "Slipped My Disco," "Madam, I'm Adam" and "Pimp." They also played several sold out nights at [[Shrine Auditorium|The Shrine]] in Los Angeles and Bimbo's in San Francisco. Mingo Lewis joined the band after performing several shows with them at Bimbos.

===''Now'', ''What Do You Want From Live'', ''Remote Control''===

The Tubes' third album ''[[Now (The Tubes)|Now]]'' (1977) was an attempt to write less satirical songs with the band sharing song writing duties with Bill Spooner. It was recorded while the band was playing a special engagement on weekends at [[The Whiskey]] in Los Angeles. They played a small American tour of the west coast and a month-long run at San Francisco's [[Palace of Fine Arts]] featuring the band's most elaborate stage show to date. The band had met manager Rikki Farr at a show opening for Alice Cooper. Farr fell in love with the band's stage show and agreed to manage them after they sued Bag O' Bucks to get out of their contract. He used his fame in England to promote them as "America's Answer to [[Punk rock|Punk]]."

The band created a new "best of" stage show and finally played a tour of Europe. They were banned in several towns and attracted front page press attention for their dark satirical stage show that spoofed America's consumer culture with dancers, video and sketches. They appeared on ''[[The Old Grey Whistle Test]]'' and played "God-Bird-Change" and "White Punks on Dope."

After their live record ''[[What Do You Want from Live]]'' (1978), recorded during their record-breaking run at the [[Hammersmith Odeon]], London, England, the band toured America and played a sold out run at [[Pantages Theatre (Hollywood)|The Pantages Theater]] in Hollywood, which attracted celebrities such as the cast of ''[[Laverne and Shirley]]'', [[Cher]], [[Kate Jackson]] and [[Gene Simmons]]. The stage show had reached new levels of lewdness with Quay Lewd's large [[dildo]] hanging out of his costume and a fake bomb threat number called "The Terrorists of Rock," which caused Cher to flee the theater, believing the threat was real. She later asked the band to appear in her next TV special ''Cher...Special''. The band returned to Europe to follow up their big splash but it was cancelled after Waybill fell off stage and broke his leg. The band returned and played the dates in the fall before headlining the [[Concerts at Knebworth House|Knebworth Rock Festival]] with [[Frank Zappa]], [[Peter Gabriel]] and [[Boomtown Rats]].

The fourth album for A&amp;M, ''[[Remote Control (The Tubes album)|Remote Control]]'' (1979) was a [[concept album]] produced by [[Todd Rundgren]] about a television-addicted idiot-savant, inspired on the Jerzy Kosinski novel ''[[Being There (novel)|Being There]]'' (which was later made into [[Being There|a movie]] starring [[Peter Sellers]]). The cover of ''Remote Control'' (1979) shows a baby (Rikki Farr's son) in a specially made "Vidi-Trainer" (a car seat/TV with a baby bottle nipple) created by Michael Cotten and Dave Mellot. Much of the new music was rewritten by Rundgren and the band in studio, including "Turn Me On" (formerly "Get Over It"); "The Terrorists of Rock" number was cannibalized to become "Telecide."

Waybill and Re Styles shared vocals on "Prime Time," although Rundgren had tried to record a version with just Styles. When Waybill found out, he demanded to sing as well. The band performed the song on "[[Top of the Pops]]" and on tour in Europe before cutting it from the set due to tensions between Waybill and Styles.

The band rehearsed a new multimedia stage show for the "Remote Control" tour and tested it at several shows at UCLA's [[Royce Hall]] but it was scrapped after Steen and Waybill complained about the show overtaking the music. This would lead to a stripped-down tour in the U.S, Japan and Europe with [[Squeeze (band)|Squeeze]] as the support act. The band also played two shows at the [[Greek Theatre (Los Angeles)|Greek Theatre]] in Los Angeles with [[Yellow Magic Orchestra]] as support; that show was released on home video in 1982. The band held an auction of Tubes stage props and costumes in 1980 at the Boarding House before the band attempted to play as a straight rock act for several sold out shows at The Roxy in Los Angeles.

===Music videos===

[[John Tobler]] said that with their media savvy and theatrical skills, the Tubes were born to create rock video but arrived several years too early.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Tobler |first=John |authorlink=John Tobler |title=MTV Music Television: Who's Who in Rock Video |year=1984 |publisher=Quill |isbn=978-0688040420}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the band did produce at least one collection of music videos, which were issued on the 1982 RCA [[Capacitance Electronic Disc]] and Pioneer Laserdisc ''The Tubes Video'', containing versions of twelve of the band's hits, including "White Punks on Dope," "Mondo Bondage," "Talk to Ya Later," and most of ''The Completion Backward Principle'' album, in slickly produced music videos based on the group's stage shows). It was directed by [[Russell Mulcahy]] and filmed at [[Shepperton Studios]].

===Stage show production pioneers===

The Tubes put their creativity and art skills mainly into their live performances, in which songs could be full-fledged production numbers with props and costumes built at The Tubes Warehouse by the band, crew and friends. Everything was satirized, from a beach movie [[parody]] for "Sushi Girl," to leather clad [[Sadism and masochism|S&amp;M]] hijinks in "Mondo Bondage," to the [[game show]] antics of "What Do You Want from Life?" At their peak, their live act featured dozens of other performers, including [[tap dancer]]s and [[acrobatics|acrobats]]. The Tubes' stage productions were choreographed by [[Kenny Ortega]] and featured cast members [[Jane Dornacker]], LeRoy Jones, [[Michael Holman (filmmaker)|Michael Holman]], Michael Springer, Cindi Osborn, Heline Gouax, and Mary Niland from 1975-1977.{{Citation needed|date=July 2017}}

From 1978-1979, the cast included Sharon Collins, Caty Bevan, and Loryanna Catalano. The ''Completion Backward'' tour featured Shelly Pang, Cheryl Hangland, Joey Richards, and [[Cynthia Rhodes]]. From 1983-1985, Michelle Gray (who later married Todd Rundgren) and Cheryl Hangland were principal dancers. Several crew members — including Tour Manager Steve "Chopper" Borges, Lee Collins, and Gail Lowe — made frequent appearances on stage in various roles as well.{{citation needed|date=February 2009}}

The Tubes' live shows in the late 1970s and early 1980s were rife with allusions to mainstream film: ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'' (1964), ''[[Rollerball (1975 film)|Rollerball]]'' (1975), ''[[Saturday Night Fever]]'' (1977), ''[[Grease (film)|Grease]]'' (1978)] then-forgotten B-movies [''[[Wild Women of Wongo]]'' (1958), ''[[Attack of the 50 Foot Woman]]'' (1958)], music ([[Tom Jones (singer)|Tom Jones]], [[punk rock]], a medley of [[Nelson Riddle]] television themes), contemporary pop culture ([[Patty Hearst]], the Viking program), television (''[[Let's Make a Deal]]'', ''[[Fernwood 2Nite]]'', the [[anime]] ''[[Raideen]]''), and literature ([[Nelson Algren]]'s ''[[A Walk on the Wild Side]]'').{{citation needed|date=February 2009}}

These shows were expensive to produce, however, and while they earned the band a reputation for being one of the most entertaining live acts of the time, by the early 1980s, they'd left the band in debt to A&amp;M Records, even after they'd sold their song rights for tour support.

===Dropped by A&amp;M Records and signing with Capitol Records===

The band's fifth studio album, the self-produced ''Suffer for Sound'', was meant to complete the group's contract with A&amp;M. The [[Early 1980s recession|recession]] had affected the music industry, and many other bands were cut from A&amp;M at the end of the 1970s. The band owed A&amp;M a large amount of money and after playing the new record for [[Jerry Moss]], Rikki Farr insulted Moss' taste in music to ensure that the band was let go and able to sign with a new label. Tubes friend Matt Leach compiled the outtakes, [[B-side]]s, and oddities selection ''[[T.R.A.S.H. (Tubes Rarities and Smash Hits)]]'' (1981).&lt;ref name=Gold&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cal-list.com/SF_Herald/columnists/gold/gold-03-01.htm |first=Kimberlye |last=Gold |title=He'll Talk to Ya Now! |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120426070920/http://www.cal-list.com/SF_Herald/columnists/gold/gold-03-01.html |archivedate=April 26, 2012 |accessdate=September 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band was signed to [[Capitol Records]] by Bruce Garfield and [[Bobby Colomby]], toning down the X-rated sketches for the live shows and redesigning itself as a leaner ensemble with a view to release more accessible hits. The band worked with Bobby Colomby to find a new musical direction and then met with possible producers including [[Jeff "Skunk" Baxter]] before deciding on [[David Foster]].

===New label, mainstream success===

''[[The Completion Backward Principle]]'' (1981) was engineered by [[Humberto Gatica]] and produced by [[David Foster]] ([[Earth, Wind and Fire]]). It featured the [[classic rock]] radio staple "Talk to Ya Later," written by Waybill, Foster and Toto guitarist [[Steve Lukather]]. The songwriting credits were shared again but included input from all members, including "Attack of the 50 Foot Woman" by Prince, "Think About Me" by Cotten, "Don't Want to Wait Anymore" by [[Vince Welnick]] and "Matter of Pride" by Steen. The album was a satire of Reagan's "[[Morning in America]]" corporate movement and included pictures of the band members cleaned up and wearing suits.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://myspace.com/tubeslive/music/album/the-completion-backward-principle-18861709 | title=The Completion Backward Principle}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band also had their first [[Top 40]] hit in the United States in 1981, "Don't Want to Wait Anymore," with vocals by Spooner. The band returned to the road in America and Europe with a new stage show designed by Cotten, Prince and Kenny Ortega, featuring new dancers including [[Cynthia Rhodes]], who would leave soon after to star in ''[[Flashdance]]'' and [[Staying Alive (1983 film)|''Staying Alive'']]. Re Styles was not asked to perform with the band but was still dating Prince. While on tour in Italy the band was forced off stage by local police with machine guns and they escaped the country with the promoter's money after he failed to deliver professional shows. The single "Sports Fans" was recorded live during halftime of the legendary [[San Francisco 49ers]] "[[The Catch (American Football)|The Catch]]" game; Tubes crew members can be seen on the side lines in the slow motion replay.

As the band gained more mainstream popularity, Waybill auditioned for roles in ''[[Night Shift (1982 film)|Night Shift]]'' and ''[[Streets of Fire]]'' and also appeared on ''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' twice.

''[[Outside Inside (The Tubes album)|Outside Inside]]'' (1983) was produced by David Foster and included the number 10 US hit "[[She's a Beauty]]."&lt;ref name="Larkin"&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Encyclopedia of Popular Music|The Virgin Encyclopedia of Popular Music]]|editor=[[Colin Larkin (writer)|Colin Larkin]]|publisher=[[Virgin Books]]|date=1997|edition=Concise|isbn=1-85227-745-9|page=1193}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album was recorded with several studio musicians, including members of [[Chicago (band)|Chicago]] and [[Toto (band)|Toto]]. The slicker sound added to the tension between the "art" oriented members of the group (Cotton, Spooner and Prince) and the pop-music fans (Steen and Waybill). The band performed "[[The Monkey Time]]" with Martha Davis of [[the Motels]] sharing vocals with Waybill on ''[[Solid Gold (TV series)|Solid Gold]]'', and toured the United States, mostly playing theme parks like [[Six Flags Magic Mountain]] and colleges for a new generation of fans. The band also filmed an hour-long concert special at the Kabuki Theatre in San Francisco which played on MTV and was directed by Jim Yukich. "She's a Beauty" won song of the year and the Tubes performed live at the [[BAM (magazine)|''BAM'']] music awards.

===''Love Bomb'' and departure from Capitol Records===
In 1984, the band teamed up with Todd Rundgren again for their eighth album, ''[[Love Bomb (The Tubes album)|Love Bomb]]'' (1985).&lt;ref name="Larkin"/&gt; Tired of spending money at other recording studios, the band built their own studio with Rundgren called "Cavum Soni" and [[XTC]] recorded several tracks for ''[[Skylarking]]'' there with Todd. [[Glen Tilbrook]] of [[Squeeze (band)|Squeeze]] sings back up on "Night People." The entire recording process was video taped by a camera crew on [[Betamax]]. Bruce Garfield and [[Bobby Colomby]] were dropped by Capitol in the company-wide layoffs that took place pre-reorganization, and like many of their label mates, the Tubes were also released; however, this occurred just as they were going on tour in support of the album. The band found it necessary to self-finance the tour as a matter of respect to honor their commitment to their fans. Between this tour's self-financing and the band's continued self-financing of their San Francisco recording studio built in 1980, the tour left the band a half million dollars in debt, obliging them to play less expensive and smaller venues for a year to pay off their financial commitments.&lt;ref name=Gold/&gt; The Tubes also recorded several songs for movie soundtracks including ''[[Hardbodies]],'' ''[[My Science Project]]'', and ''[[She's Out of Control]]''. Bill Spooner also recorded a solo album titled ''First Chud'', released on [[The Residents]]' record label Ralph Records. For Spooner’s next solo project he recorded ''Mall to Mars'' with coproducer Jim Blake, featuring fellow Tubes member Prairie Prince on drums. The concept album released on Visible Records (a label owned by Richard Kaye long-time Tubes music publishing associate/copyright administrator) has Spooner doing several covers including: "Theme From Star Trek," "Dimming of the Day," and "They Kicked Me Out of the Band" (that Bill claims is not true… he says, he actually quit the Tubes).

===Waybill departs===

Fee Waybill had already released an unsuccessful solo album (''Read My Lips'', Capitol Records) in 1984 and was on-camera talent for the 1985 [[MTV Video Awards]]. He had also happily enjoyed a fruitful writing partnership with fellow Capitol Records label mate [[Richard Marx]], their most popular and well known collaboration being "[[Vixen (Vixen album)|Edge of a Broken Heart]]," recorded by the female band [[Vixen (band)|Vixen]]. Waybill left The Tubes in 1986{{citation needed|date=February 2009}}, leaving the band without a lead singer. Waybill also recorded songs for the soundtracks of ''[[St. Elmo's Fire (film)|St. Elmo's Fire]]'', ''[[Running Scared (1986 film)|Running Scared]]'', ''[[Dream a Little Dream (film)|Dream a Little Dream]]'', and ''[[Nobody's Perfect (1990 film)|Nobody's Perfect]]''.

===Personnel changes===

Later in the year, the remaining members of the band hired longtime friend from Phoenix, Arizona, David Killingsworth, as lead vocalist. Killingsworth had been the singer in the Red and White Blues Band with Prince and Steen. The band appeared on ''[[The Late Show Starring Joan Rivers]]'' on Fox in 1987 and played "Talk to Ya Later," a new song called "No Baby's Gonna Break My Heart," and were also interviewed.

Michael Cotten relocated to [[New York City]] to pursue a career based on his artwork, stage design and production, and is considered one of the country's top production designers.

In the fall of 1988, Bill Spooner traveled his final tour with the band and left in early 1989. Vince Welnick departed as well to take to the road with [[Todd Rundgren]] in 1989 and then joined the [[Grateful Dead]] in 1990. Gary Cambra joined on keyboards and guitar in 1989. He and Roger Steen took over most of the lead vocal duties after Killingsworth left in early 1990.

In 1993, Fee Waybill rejoined the band. This lineup toured Europe and released two albums, a compilation and the 1996 album ''[[Genius of America]]''. David Medd joined in 1996 to play keyboards alongside Cambra. In 2001, the band released a live CD, ''The Tubes World Tour 2001'', and continued to tour.

===2000-present===
The band has toured the United States each year with a line-up of Waybill, Steen, Anderson, Medd, Gary Cambra and Prince. Cambra left in 2006.

After a 2004 tour of the UK, the London show was released as a live album and DVD called ''Wild in London''.

On June 2, 2006, former keyboardist Vince Welnick died by suicide.

In September 2007, the remaining members reunited in Phoenix for induction into the Arizona Music and Entertainment Hall Of Fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=West|first1=Jim|title=The Tubes - Arizona Music &amp; Entertainment Hall Of Fame|url=http://www.azmusichalloffame.org/inductees/the-tubes/|website=azmusichalloffame.org|accessdate=29 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They toured the UK in 2009, and the UK and Europe in 2012. In July 2015, they started a 40th anniversary European tour, including dates in Germany, Sweden and the UK. Dates in the U.S. followed.
In 2017, they toured Europe as support for [[Alice Cooper]], also playing some sole warm-up gigs in the UK.

On March 11. 2019, they announced a spring USA tour and will perform their ''The Completion Backward Principle'' album in its entirety &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.musicnewsnet.com/2019/03/the-tubes-to-perform-iconic-the-completion-backward-principle-in-its-entirety-on-current-tour.html|title=The Tubes To Perform Iconic "The Completion Backward Principle" In Its Entirety On Current Tour|website=Music News Net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 25, 2019, ''[[The New York Times Magazine]]'' listed The Tubes among hundreds of artists whose material was reportedly destroyed in the [[2008 Universal fire]].&lt;ref name="Rosen2"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Rosen |first1=Jody |title=Here Are Hundreds More Artists Whose Tapes Were Destroyed in the UMG Fire |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/25/magazine/universal-music-fire-bands-list-umg.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=28 June 2019 |date=25 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Tubes Project and other milestones==

Michael Cotten started "The Tubes Project" in 2005, to save and digitize the band's reel to reel and video tape archive. The collection had been kept in the closet of Tubes fan club president Marylin Wood's son after being discarded in the late 1980s. Included in the vault are full color shows taped for TV at Bimbos in San Francisco, 1975 and VARA TV from the 1977 European tour. Over 70 interviews were conducted with band members, crew, managers, cast and colleagues such as Re Styles, Todd Rundgren, [[Al Kooper]], [[Devo]] and David Foster. Hundreds of photos were scanned and compiled from band members and fan collections for use in the hour and half documentary.

After leaving the band, [[Jane Dornacker]] performed as stand-up comedian and later worked as a traffic reporter with the team that replaced [[Howard Stern]] at WNBC. She was killed in a helicopter crash in 1986, while giving a live report. A benefit show was held for her daughter at the Warfield in San Francisco with the Tubes and Todd Rundgren.

On November 10, 2009, ''Mondo Birthmark,'' a CD of previously unreleased rarities, was released through the label [[Fuel 2000]]. The package was designed by Michael Cotten and [[Prairie Prince]] with rare photos and interviews of the group. The demos also feature former member Bob Macintosh on drums.

On July 24, 2019, Kenny Ortega was awarded a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame. Fee, Michael Cotton and Michael Holman attended the ceremony.

==Career highlights==
{{prose|section|date=October 2018}}
* 1972: Tubes appear in [[Mitchell brothers]] pornographic film ''[[Resurrection of Eve]]'' as Jesus Bongo and the Millionaires.
* 1973: Opened for the [[New York Dolls]] at the Matrix, [[Iggy Pop]] at Bimbos, and [[Led Zeppelin]] at [[Kezar Stadium]] in San Francisco.
* 1974: Tubes shoot "[[video]] demo" at California Hall, which lands a record deal at [[A&amp;M Records]], Cotten/Prince paint "Flying Record" mural on A&amp;M sound stage.
* 1975: Tubes play for two weeks of shows at David Allen's nightclub [[The Boarding House (nightclub)|The Boarding House]] in San Francisco, several sell-out dates at [[The Roxy Theatre|The Roxy]] in Los Angeles and [[The Bottom Line (venue)|The Bottom Line]] in New York. On December 31, they sell out Bill Graham's [[Winterland Ballroom]] with the Stanford University marching band.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.concertvault.com/the-tubes/winterland-december-31-1975.html |title=The Tubes Winterland San Francisco, CA Dec 31, 1975 |website=Concert Vault |accessdate=September 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1976: Held residency at Bimbos in San Francisco for one month, Prairie Prince dubbed "The One, The Only" by columnist [[Herb Caen]]. Tubes hold "Talent Hunt" at the Boarding House hosted by [[Martin Mull]]; [[Robin Williams]] is contestant but loses.
* 1977: Held residency at the [[Palace of Fine Arts]] in San Francisco for one month, the [[Whisky a Go Go]] nightclub in Los Angeles for two shows a night for one month, and [[Hammersmith Odeon]] in London for a week.
* 1977: Waybill breaks his leg during the recording of concert LP ''What Do You Want from Live?'', leading to the cancellation of the rest of the tour
* 1978: Headlined the [[Knebworth Festival]] (with special guest [[Dolly Parton]]), with [[Frank Zappa]] and [[Peter Gabriel]].
* 1978: The Tubes performed  on ''[[Cher... Special]]'' (with special guest [[Dolly Parton]])
* 1979: Tubes play Japan; Cotten/Welnick/Prince/Styles appear on Japanese soap opera. Tubes appear in [[Andy Warhol]]'s ''[[Interview (magazine)|Interview]]'' magazine.
* 1980: Made an appearance in the film ''[[Xanadu (film)|Xanadu]]'' singing the rock portion of the cross-genre song "Dancin'" opposite a [[big band]].
* 1980: Sold out the Roxy Theatre for 12 shows
* 1981: Record [[Grammy]] nominated "The Tubes Video" at [[Shepperton Studios]], one of the first long form [[video disc]]s.
* 1981: Sang "Sushi Girl" and "Talk to Ya Later" on the television sketch comedy program ''[[Second City Television|SCTV]]'', Episode #86 airing July 24.
* 1981: Played "Sushi Girl" and "Don't Want to Wait Anymore" on ''[[Tomorrow (TV series)|Tomorrow]]'' with [[Tom Snyder]]. Waybill, Spooner and Mike are interviewed by Tom.
* 1981: Compose the song "Road Map of My Tears" for the film ''[[Ladies and Gentlemen, The Fabulous Stains]]'', in which Waybill and Welnick appear, among other musicians, as the fictional rock group The Metal Corpses.
* 1982: Appeared in a commercial for Activision's video game ''[[Megamania]]''.
* 1983: Opened several dates for [[David Bowie]] on the ''[[Serious Moonlight Tour|Serious Moonlight]]'' tour and on this tour, among other highlights, they were the first artists to ever play the newly opened [[Tacoma Dome]] in Tacoma, Washington. At the end of the Bowie tour, they played a few shows featuring their classic no-holds-barred theatrics in Portland, Oregon, and other west-coast cities.
* 1985: Tour in a double bill with Todd Rundgren's [[Utopia (band)|Utopia]], including a date at [[Radio City Music Hall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://concerts.fandom.com/wiki/Todd_Rundgren_Concerts_1980s|title=Todd Rundgren Concerts 1980s|website=Concerts Wiki}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==

===Albums===

{|class="wikitable"
|-
! rowspan="2" style="width:33px;"| Year
! rowspan="2" style="width:215px;"| Album details
! colspan="6" | Peak chart positions
! rowspan="2" style="width:125px;"| [[Music recording sales certification|Certifications]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[List of music recording sales certifications|sales thresholds]])&lt;/small&gt;
|-
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Billboard 200|US]]
&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/music/the-tubes|title=The Tubes|last=|first=|date=|website=Billboard|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[UK Albums Chart|UK]]
&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.officialcharts.com/artist/16600/tubes/|title=TUBES|last=|first=|date=|website=Official Charts|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[GfK Entertainment charts|GER]]
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Dutch Charts|DUT]]
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://dutchcharts.nl/search.asp?cat=a&amp;cat2=s&amp;search=the+tubes|title=Dutch Charts|last=|first=|date=|website=Dutch Charts|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Kent Music Report|AUS]]
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Recorded Music NZ|NZ]]
|-
| 1975
| ''[[The Tubes (album)|The Tubes]]''
* Released: June 1975
* Label: [[A&amp;M Records|A&amp;M]]
| style="text-align:center;"| 113
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 1976
| ''[[Young and Rich]]''
* Released: April 1976
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| 46
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 1977
| ''[[Now (The Tubes album)|Now]]''
* Released: May 1977
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| 122
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 1979
| ''[[Remote Control (The Tubes album)|Remote Control]]''
* Released: March 1979
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| 46
| style="text-align:center;"| 40
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 46
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 1981
| ''[[The Completion Backward Principle]]''
* Released: April 1981
* Label: [[Capitol Records|Capitol]]
| style="text-align:center;"| 36
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 28&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.offiziellecharts.de/album-details-33990|title=THE TUBES - THE COMPLETION BACKWARD PRINCIPLE|last=|first=|date=|website=Offizielle Deutsche Charts|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 4&lt;ref name=rmnz1981&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nztop40.co.nz/index.php/chart/albums?chart=2979|title=OFFICIAL TOP 40 ALBUMS|date=1982-01-24|publisher=Recorded Music NZ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=chartsnz1981&gt;{{cite web|url=https://charts.nz/showitem.asp?interpret=The+Tubes&amp;titel=The+Completion+Backward+Principle&amp;cat=a|title=THE TUBES - THE COMPLETION BACKWARD PRINCIPLE (ALBUM)|website=Charts.nz}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Music Canada|CAN]]: Gold&lt;ref name="CRIA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cria.ca/cert_db_search.php |title=Gold and Platinum |website=Cria.ca |date= |accessdate=March 27, 2012 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100501065534/http://www.cria.ca/cert_db_search.php |archivedate=May 1, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://musiccanada.com/gold-platinum/?_gp_search=the%20tubes|title=Gold/Platinum|last=|first=|date=|website=music Canada|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
NZ: Gold&lt;ref name=rmnz1981 /&gt;&lt;ref name=chartsnz1981 /&gt;
|-
| 1983
| ''[[Outside Inside (The Tubes album)|Outside Inside]]''
* Released: April 4, 1983
* Label: Capitol
| style="text-align:center;"| 18
| style="text-align:center;"| 77
| style="text-align:center;"| 44&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.offiziellecharts.de/album-details-33144|title=THE TUBES - OUTSIDE INSIDE|last=|first=|date=|website=Offizielle Deutsche Charts|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 22&lt;ref name=rmnz1983&gt;{{cite web|url= https://nztop40.co.nz/index.php/chart/albums?chart=3048|title=OFFICIAL TOP 40 ALBUMS|date=1983-06-05|publisher=Recorded Music NZ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=chartsnz1983&gt;{{cite web|url= https://charts.nz/showitem.asp?interpret=The+Tubes&amp;titel=Outside+Inside&amp;cat=a|title=THE TUBES - OUTSIDE INSIDE (ALBUM)|website=Charts.nz}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|CAN: Gold&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
|-
| 1985
| ''[[Love Bomb (The Tubes album)|Love Bomb]]''
* Released: February 1985
* Label: Capitol
| style="text-align:center;"| 87
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 59&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.offiziellecharts.de/album-details-33139|title=THE TUBES - LOVE BOMB|last=|first=|date=|website=Offizielle Deutsche Charts|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 1996
| ''[[Genius of America]]''
* Released: October 15, 1996
* Label: Critique
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| 2009
| ''Mondo Birthmark''
* Released: November 10, 2009
* Label: Fuel
* Rarities 
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|
|-
| colspan="11" style="text-align:center; font-size:8pt;" | "—" denotes releases that did not chart.
|}

===Compilation albums===

{|class="wikitable"
|-
! rowspan="2" style="width:33px;"| Year
! rowspan="2" style="width:215px;"| Album details
! Peak chart positions
|-
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Billboard 200|US]]
&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
|-
|  1981
| ''[[T.R.A.S.H. (Tubes Rarities and Smash Hits)]]''
* Released: November 1981
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| 148
|-
| 1992
| ''The Best of the Tubes''
* Released: November 17, 1992
* Label: Capitol
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2000
| ''Millennium Collection: The Tubes''
* Released: October 17, 2000
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| —

|-
| 2002
| ''Hoods from Outer Space''
* Released: May 22, 2002
* Label: Brilliant
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2003
| ''White Punks on Dope''
* Released: November 24, 2003
* Label: Acadia Records
* Budget re-release of ''The Tubes'' and ''Young and Rich''
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2008
| ''Goin' Down the Tubes''
* Released: June 10, 2008
* Label: Cherry Red
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|}

===Live albums===

{|class="wikitable"
|-
! rowspan="2" style="width:33px;"| Year
! rowspan="2" style="width:215px;"| Album details
!colspan="2"| Peak chart positions
|-
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Billboard 200|US]]
&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[UK Albums Chart|UK]]
&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
|-
| 1978
| ''[[What Do You Want from Live]]''
* Released: February 1978
* Label: A&amp;M
| style="text-align:center;"| 82
| style="text-align:center;"| 38
|-
| 2001
| ''The Tubes World Tour 2001 (live)''
* Released: October 10, 2000
* Label: [[CMC International|CMC]]
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2005
| ''[[Wild in London]]''
* Released: October 2, 2006
* Label: Snapper
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2006
| ''Alive in America''
* Released: '76 live broadcast from LA Shrine
* Label: (unsanctioned) Renaissance
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|-
| 2020
| ''Live in San Francisco''
* Released: '83 live broadcast from Kabuki Theater
* Label: Notlob (unsanctioned) 
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
|}

===Singles===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! rowspan="2" | Year
! rowspan="2" | Song
! colspan="5" | Peak chart positions
! rowspan="2" | Album
|-
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Billboard Hot 100|US]]
&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Mainstream Rock Tracks|US&lt;br&gt;Main.&lt;br&gt;Rock]]
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/music/the-tubes/chart-history/hot-mainstream-rock-tracks|title=The Tubes Chart History|last=|first=|date=|website=Billboard|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[UK Singles Chart|UK]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="British Hit Singles &amp; Albums"&gt;{{cite book|title=British Hit Singles &amp; Albums|last=Roberts|first=David|publisher=Guinness World Records Limited|year=2006|isbn=978-1-904994-10-7|edition=19th|location=London|page=568}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Kent Music Report|AUS]]
!style="width:2em;font-size:75%"| [[Recorded Music NZ|NZ]]
|-
| 1976
| "Don't Touch Me There"
| style="text-align:center;"|61
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|26&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://rateyourmusic.com/list/Badgerdarkness/australian_top_100_singles___24_january_1977/|title=Australian Top 100 Singles - 24 January 1977|date=1977-01-24|work=Kent Music Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| ''[[Young and Rich]]''
|-
| 1977
| "[[White Punks on Dope]]"
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 28
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| ''[[The Tubes (album)|The Tubes]]''
|-
| 1979
| "Prime Time"
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| 34
| style="text-align:center;"| 49&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://rateyourmusic.com/list/Badgerdarkness/australian_top_100_singles___16_july_1979/|title=Australian Top 100 Singles - 16 July 1979|date=1979-07-16|work=Kent Music Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| ''[[Remote Control (The Tubes album)|Remote Control]]''
|-
| rowspan="3" | 1981
| "Don't Want to Wait Anymore"
| style="text-align:center;"| 35
| style="text-align:center;"| 22
| style="text-align:center;"| 60
| style="text-align:center;"| 36&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://rateyourmusic.com/list/Badgerdarkness/australian-top-100-singles-26-october-1981/|title=Australian Top 100 Singles - 26 October 1981|date=1981-10-26|work=Kent Music Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| rowspan=2|''[[The Completion Backward Principle]]''
|-
| "[[Talk to Ya Later]]"
| style="text-align:center;"| 101
| style="text-align:center;"| 7
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
|-
| "Gonna Get It Next Time"
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| ''Sports Fans''
|-
| rowspan="3" | 1983
| "[[She's a Beauty]]"
| style="text-align:center;"| 10
| style="text-align:center;"| 1
| style="text-align:center;"| 79
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"| 37&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nztop40.co.nz/chart/singles?chart=3052|title=OFFICIAL TOP 40 SINGLES|date=1983-07-03|publisher=Recorded Music NZ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://charts.nz/showitem.asp?interpret=The+Tubes&amp;titel=She%27s+A+Beauty&amp;cat=s|title=THE TUBES - SHE'S A BEAUTY (SONG)|website=Charts.nz}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rowspan=3|''[[Outside Inside (The Tubes album)|Outside Inside]]''
|-
| "Tip of My Tongue"
| style="text-align:center;"| 52
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
|-
| "[[The Monkey Time]]"
| style="text-align:center;"| 68
| style="text-align:center;"| 16
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
|-
| 1985
| "Piece by Piece"
| style="text-align:center;"| 87
| style="text-align:center;"| 25
| style="text-align:center;"| —
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| style="text-align:center;"|—
| ''[[Love Bomb (The Tubes album)|Love Bomb]]''
|-
| colspan="11" style="text-align:center; font-size:8pt;"| "—" denotes releases that did not chart.
|}

===Video albums===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! style="width:20px;"| Year
! style="width:220px;"| Video details
|-
| 1981
| ''[[The Tubes Video]]''
* Released: November 15, 1981
* Label: Thorn EMI Video (Betamax and VHS), Pioneer Artists (LaserDisc), [[RCA Corporation]] (CED)
* Format: [[Betamax]], [[VHS]], [[LaserDisc]], [[Capacitance Electronic Disc|CED]]
* Nominated for a Grammy
|-
| 1982
| ''The Tubes: Live at the Greek''
* Released: November 1982
* Label: [[Monterey Home Video]]
* Format: Betamax, VHS
|-
| 2016
| ''The Tubes: German TV 1981''
* Released: October 2016
* Label: [[MVD]]
* Format: [[DVD]]
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Rock music}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://home.earthlink.net/~tubesmuseum/index.html Tubes Museum, complete timeline]
* [https://www.youtube.com/user/TheTubesOnMV The Tubes] at the Bill Graham Video Archive 1975-79.
* [http://www.billspooner.com/ Bill Spooner's website], with Tubes images.
* [http://www.mcotten.com/ Michael Cotten Studio].
* [http://prairieprince.com/ Prairie Prince's website].
* [http://www.onamrecords.com/gallery/view/Tubes The Tubes on A&amp;M Records].
* [http://www.blogtalkradio.com/runt/2007/10/18/Special-guest-Prairie-Prince 2007 Prairie Prince radio interview] on Rundgren Radio.
* [http://www.blogtalkradio.com/runt/2009/02/04/Rundgren-Radio 2009 Prairie Prince radio interview] on Rundgren Radio.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140308030647/http://www.sixtiespix.com/subhomepage.html  1970s Tubes photographs on and off stage].
* [http://www.kmelforever.com/paul-vincent.html KMEL DJ Paul Vincent interviews Fee Waybill].
* {{cite web|title=The Tubes - Arizona Music &amp; Entertainment Hall Of Fame|url=http://www.azmusichalloffame.org/inductees/the-tubes/}} – Inductee Biography
* [http://www.namm.org/library/oral-history/michael-cotten Michael Cotten Interview] NAMM Oral History Library (2017)

{{The Tubes}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tubes, The}}
[[Category:The Tubes| ]]
[[Category:Rock music groups from Arizona]]
[[Category:Protopunk groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups from San Francisco]]
[[Category:Musicians from Phoenix, Arizona]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1972]]
[[Category:A&amp;M Records artists]]
[[Category:Capitol Records artists]]</text>
      <sha1>nhyy4gzrm3859j22b8guugcdg240r76</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
