<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Final offensive of the Spanish Civil War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32580812</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961731638</id>
      <parentid>952752733</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-10T03:09:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2001:8003:59DB:4100:5DF5:6BF3:3C52:2F9A</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="22065" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2019}}
{{short description|1939 campaign in the Iberian Peninsula}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Final offensive
| partof      = the [[Spanish Civil War]]
| image= GCE frente en feb 1939.svg
| image_size = 250
| caption     = Map of Spain in March 1939.
:::::{{Leftlegend|#ffd5d5|Republican territory}}{{Leftlegend|#e9ddaf|Nationalist territory}}
| date        = Casado's ''coup'': 5–13 March 1939&lt;br&gt;Final offensive: 26 March – 1 April 1939
| place       = Southeastern Spain (provinces of Madrid, Ciudad Real, Cuenca, Albacete, Valencia, Alicante, Murcia, Jaen, Almeria, and parts of Toledo, Guadalajara, Granada and Castellon).
| result      = *Decisive Nationalist victory. End of the war.&lt;br&gt;
*Dissolution of the Second Spanish Republic and beginning of the [[Francoist Spain|Francoist regime]].
| combatant1  = {{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[Second Spanish Republic|Spanish Republic]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Nationalist Spain|1938}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Condor Legion]]&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.395&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Corpo Truppe Volontarie|CTV]]
| commander1  = '''Negrín's Government:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Spain|1931}} [[Luis Barceló]]{{executed}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Spain|1931}} [[Francisco Galán]]{{Surrendered}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[Colonel Antonio Ortega|Antonio Ortega]]{{executed}}&lt;hr&gt;'''Council of National Defense:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[Segismundo Casado]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[Manuel Matallana]]{{Surrendered}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[José Miaja]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Spain|1931}} [[Cipriano Mera]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Nationalist Spain|1938}} [[Francisco Franco]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nationalist Spain|1938}} [[Juan Yagüe]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nationalist Spain|1938}} [[José Solchaga]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nationalist Spain|1938}} [[Rafael García Valiño]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Gastone Gambara]]
| strength1   = 250,000&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p. 475&lt;/ref&gt;−500,000 men&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.861&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;40 aircraft
| strength2   = 1,000,000 men&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.838&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;600 aircraft
| casualties1 =Casado's ''coup'': 230&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.884&lt;/ref&gt;–2,000 dead&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.394&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; Final offensive: 150,000 captured&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.404&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 1,223 dead (sinking of the ''Castillo de Olite'')&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.391&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Spanish Civil War}}
The '''final offensive of the Spanish Civil War''' took place between 26  March and 1 April 1939, towards the end of the [[Spanish Civil War]]. On 5 March 1939, the [[Spanish Republican Army|Republican Army]], led by Colonel [[Segismundo Casado]] and the politician [[Julián Besteiro]], rose against the Socialist prime minister [[Juan Negrín]], and formed a [[military junta]], the [[National Defence Council (Spain)|National Defence Council]] (''Consejo Nacional de Defensa'' or ''CND'') to negotiate a peace deal. Negrín fled to France but the Communist troops around Madrid rose against the junta, starting a civil war within the civil war. Casado defeated them and started peace negotiations with [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|the Nationalists]]. [[Francisco Franco]], however, was prepared to accept only an unconditional surrender. On 26 March, the Nationalists started a general offensive and by 31 March, they controlled all of Spanish territory. Hundreds of thousands of Republicans were arrested and interned in [[Francoist concentration camps|concentration camp]]s.

==Background==
===Fall of Catalonia===
After the [[Catalonia Offensive|fall of Catalonia]] in February 1939, the military situation of the Republic was hopeless. Despite still having the capital city and approximately 30% of Spanish territory, it had lost 220,000 soldiers, the second most populated city in the country and the industrial resources of Catalonia.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p..854&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, on 27 February, President [[Manuel Azaña]] resigned. The [[United Kingdom]] and [[Third French Republic|France]] then recognised the Nationalist government.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen 2005. p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military situation===
The Republican army still had between 250,000&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p. 475&lt;/ref&gt; and 500,000 men&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.861&lt;/ref&gt; but only 40 aircraft (three [[Polikarpov R-Z|''Natasha'']] and two [[Tupolev SB|''Katiuska'']] bomber squadrons, and 25 [[Polikarpov I-15|''Chatos'']] and [[I-16 Rata|''Moscas'']] fighters),&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.868&lt;/ref&gt; little artillery and few automatic weapons.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.861&lt;/ref&gt; Many soldiers were unarmed (in December 1938, the Republican army had only 225,000 rifles),&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.488&lt;/ref&gt; and lacked shoes and overcoats.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.866&lt;/ref&gt; In Madrid, there was food for only two months and no water, heating, medicine or surgical dressings.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.869&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the Nationalist army had more than a million men at the end of 1938, with.35,000 Moroccans, 32,000 Italians and 5,000 Germans,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p. 838&lt;/ref&gt; as well as 600 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.866&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposition to continued resistance===
On 16 February, the high command of the Republican Army told Prime Minister [[Juan Negrín]] that further military resistance was impossible.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.867–868&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the members of the Republican Army, the [[Partido Socialista Obrero Español|PSOE]], the [[Unión General de Trabajadores|UGT]] and the [[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]] believed that it was necessary to initiate peace negotiations.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul 2006. p.296&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Negrín, backed by the Communist [[Partido Comunista Español|PCE]], wanted to continue fighting because Franco rejected giving any guarantee against reprisals and [[World War II|another world war]] was believed to be imminent.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul 2006. p.296&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Negrín wanted to organise the evacuation of those who were most at risk.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen 2005. p.111&lt;/ref&gt;

==Casado’s ''coup''==
{{See also|National Defence Council (Spain)}}

===Plot===
From the end of February 1939, Colonel Segismundo Casado had been preparing a ''[[coup d'état|coup]]'' against the Negrín government to start peace negotiations with the Nationalists, believing that the government was too subordinate to the Communists. Colonel José Cendaño, a [[fifth column]] agent in the Republican army, promised to him that Franco would guarantee the lives of the Republican officers who had committed no crimes.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.870–871&lt;/ref&gt; Most noncommunist elements of the [[Popular Front (Spain)|Popular Front]] in Madrid supported the plot, including one of the leaders of the PSOE, Julián Besteiro, because they believed that continuing the war was useless.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p. 861&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, after the [[Battle of Minorca (1939)|surrender of Menorca]], many Republican officers in the central zone believed that they could negotiate a deal with the Nationalists.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2006. p. 861.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 March, Negrín announced a number of new appointments in the Central Zone.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p. 468&lt;/ref&gt; Colonel Casado and the communists [[Juan Modesto]] and [[Antonio Cordón García]] became generals, General [[Manuel Matallana]] was appointed as head of the central [[general staff]]&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p. 874&lt;/ref&gt; and communist officers were appointed to command the ports of Murcia ([[Manuel Tagüeña]]), Alicante ([[Etelvino Vega]]) and Cartagena ([[Francisco Galán]]).&lt;ref&gt;Thomas,  Hugh 2001. pp. 875-876&lt;/ref&gt;(according to Beevor, Francisco Galán was appointed military governor of Cartagena, Etelvino Vega governor of Alicante, [[Leocadio Mendiola]] commander of Murcia and [[Inocencio Curto]] commander of Albacete).&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p. 390&lt;/ref&gt; The noncommunist elements believed that the communists wanted to control the evacuation harbors&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p. 468&lt;/ref&gt; and joined the plot against Negrín.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. pp. 468–469&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Coup''===
On 5 March 1939, Colonel Segismundo Casado, supported by General Matallana, the CNT&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.873&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Cipriano Mera]]), the secret service of the Republic (the Military Investigation Service, ''Servicio de Investigación Militar'', or ''[[Servicio de investigación Militar|SIM]]''),&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.875&lt;/ref&gt; a section of the PSOE ([[Julian Besteiro]]) and a section of the UGT ([[Wenceslao Carrillo]]), deposed Negrín and formed a [[military junta]], the [[National Defence Council (Spain)|National Council of Defense]] (''Consejo Nacional de Defensa'') in order to negotiate a peace deal with Franco.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.876-878&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 March, Miaja joined the rebellion and was appointed president of the junta.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.878&lt;/ref&gt; The other members of the junta were Casado, Julian Besteiro, Wenceslao Carrillo, Gonzalez Marín and Eduardo Val (CNT), Antonio Perez (UGT), and the republicans Miguel San Andrés and Jose del Río.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. pp.392&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Julián Besteiro Fernández.jpg|thumb|150px| Julian Besteiro, one of the leaders of the PSOE, supported Casado's ''coup''.]]
Colonel [[Adolfo Prada]] was appointed commander of the [[Field army|Army]] of the Centre, the communist commanders of the I, II and III Army [[Corps]] of the Army of the Centre were relieved, the PCE's newspaper ''[[Mundo Obrero]]'' was closed  and Casado ordered massive arrests of communist [[political commissar|commissars]] and militants.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. pp.393–394&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically, Casado's justification for the coup was that Negrín and the PCE wanted to carry out a communist takeover, an identical justification to that of the Nationalist uprising, which began the Civil War, but in fact, he rose against the government because he wanted to negotiate peace and believed that removing Negrín and the communists was a precondition to negotiations with Franco. In addition to other assurances, the British government said to him that Franco would guarantee the lives of the Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul 2006. p.296&lt;/ref&gt; Casado had said to the commander of the [[Spanish Republican Air Force|Republican Air Force]], [[Hidalgo de Cisneros]]: "I give you my word...that I can obtain better terms from Franco than Negrín ever can. I can even assure you that they will res our ranks".&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.875&lt;/ref&gt;

After a failed attempt to negotiate with Casado, Negrín fled to France from the [[Monòver]]'s airfield, near [[Elda]], with Hidalgo de Cisneros, the leaders of the PCE ([[La Pasionaria]] and [[Vicente Uribe]]), and the foreign minister [[Julio Álvarez del Vayo]] on 6 March to avoid capture by the supporters of Casado&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. pp.392–393&lt;/ref&gt; (Casado wanted to arrest the government and the PCE's leaders and to hand them over to the Nationalists).&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.881&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fight in Madrid===
Casado's ''coup'' was supported by the commanders of the other three [[Field army|Armies]] of the Republican Army ([[Leopoldo Menéndez|Leopoldo Menéndez López]], commander of the Levante Army; [[Antonio Escobar Huertas|Antonio Escobar]], commander of the Estremadura Army; and [[Domingo Moriones]], commander of the Andalusia Army).&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.883&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the army units settled around Madrid and controlled by the PCE (the I corps of the Army of the Centre led by [[Luis Barceló]] and the Emilio Bueno’s II and [[Colonel Antonio Ortega]]’s III Corps), rose against the junta on 7 March, starting a brief civil war inside the Republic. Barceló appointed himself as commander of the Army of the Centre, and his troops closed all the entrances to Madrid, occupied most of the city centre and detained and shot three of Casado's colonels. Casado's supporters held only some government buildings and the southeast of the city.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.882&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Mera's IV corps counterattacked and occupied [[Torrejón de Ardoz|Torrejón]] and [[Alcalá de Henares]] as the Nationalists started an offensive towards the [[Manzanares (river)|Manzanares]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.884&lt;/ref&gt; By 10 March, Barceló's troops had been surrounded, and a ceasefire was arranged. On 11 March, after days of bloody combat, Casado, backed by the IV corps of Cipriano Mera, defeated Barceló’s troops. Barceló and his commissar, José Conesa, were arrested and executed.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.884&lt;/ref&gt; There were hundreds of dead (Thomas: 230,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.884&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson: 1,000,&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p.433&lt;/ref&gt; and Beevor: 2,000 dead&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.394&lt;/ref&gt;).

===Cartagena===
{{main|Cartagena Uprising}}
There was also combat in [[Ciudad Real]] and Cartagena. In Ciudad Real, Escobar's Extremadura Army crushed the communist resistance led by the deputy Martínez Cárton.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.884&lt;/ref&gt;
Nevertheless, in [[Cartagena Uprising|Cartagena]] (the main base of the [[Spanish Republican Navy]]), where the supporters of Casado, backed by elements of the a fifth column, had started the uprising against Negrín's government on 4 March, they were defeated by the PCE's 206th Brigade, of the IV Division, led by colonel Joaquín Rodríguez, after a brief battle, on 7 March. Nevertheless, on 5 March, the Republican Navy (three cruisers and eight destroyers), led by Admiral Buiza, had fled to Bizerte after a Nationalist aerial bombardment.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.876–877&lt;/ref&gt; One Nationalist transport ship, the ''[[SS Castillo de Olite|Castillo de Olite]]'', sent by the Nationalists in order to support the uprising, was sunk by the coastal batteries of Cartagena, killing 1,200 Nationalist soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.391&lt;/ref&gt;

===Peace negotiations with Franco===
After the defeat of Barceló's troops, the Council tried to start peace negotiations with Franco, hoping to achieve a guarantee against political reprisals. On 12 March, the Council proposed a peace deal with a guarantee against reprisals and a period of 25 days to allow anyone who wanted to leave Spain to do so. On 16 March, Franco answered that he would only accept an unconditional surrender.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. pp.394–395&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 March, the Council sent two negotiators to Burgos (Colonel Antonio Garijo and Major Leopoldo Ortega), and the Nationalists told them that on 25 March, the [[Spanish Republican Air Force|Republican Air Force]] had to be surrendered and by 27 March, the Republican troops had to raise the white flag.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.395&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, on 25 March, the Republicans did not surrender their Air Force because of bad weather and Franco then broke off negotiations with the junta.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.885–888&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.395&lt;/ref&gt;

==Final offensive==
On 26 March, Yagüe’s troops advanced in [[Sierra Morena]]. There was no resistance, and in one day they captured 200,000 km2 of land and 30,000 prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p. 867&lt;/ref&gt; The Junta ordered its soldiers not to resist the Nationalist advance, and the Republican soldiers threw away their weapons and abandoned the front.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.887&lt;/ref&gt; By 27 March, the Nationalists were advancing on all fronts without resistance. Solchaga's Navarra Corps, Gambara's CTV and Garcia Valiño's Army of Maestrazgo advanced from Toledo. On 28 March, Colonel Prada, commander of the Army of the Centre, surrendered to the Nationalist troops, who occupied Madrid.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p.509&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.888–889&lt;/ref&gt; Casado and the other members of the junta, except Besteiro, fled to Valencia.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.888&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 March, the Nationalists occupied [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]], Ciudad Real, [[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]], [[Albacete]] and [[Sagunto]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.890&lt;/ref&gt; 50,000 Republican refugees gathered at the harbours of [[Valencia, Spain|Valencia]], [[Alicante]], [[Cartagena, Spain|Cartagena]] and [[Gandia]]&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.889&lt;/ref&gt; but without the Republican navy, an evacuation was impossible since the French and the British governments refused to organise an evacuation.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.396&lt;/ref&gt; Only a minority, those who had money to pay for passage,&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen 2005. p.113&lt;/ref&gt; were evacuated by British ships (between 650&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.890&lt;/ref&gt; and more than 3,500&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.396&lt;/ref&gt;), Casado among them.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,760981-1,00.html |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |title=Aftermath |date=10 April 1939 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 March, the Nationalists occupied Valencia and Gambara’s troops entered Alicante, rounding up 15,000 Republican refugees.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.396&lt;/ref&gt; Italian General Gambara was prepared to permit the evacuation of political refugees, but on 31 March, the Nationalist troops arrived and took over jurisdiction from Gambara.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel 1967. p.477&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, many refugees committed suicide to avoid capture by the Nationalists.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen 2005. p.113&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.396&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.890&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 March, the Nationalists occupied [[Almeria]], [[Murcia]] and [[Cartagena, Spain|Cartagena]], controlling all Spanish territory except for an area of the port of Alicante, where thousands of Republicans expecting evacuation had assembled. They began giving themselves up on 31 March, but the operation was suspended for the night. The last 2000 surrendered the next morning, and approximately 25 committed suicide. By 1 April 1939, the war was effectively over.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. pp.886–890&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
On 1 April 1939, the day the war ended, the [[Soviet Union]] was the only major power that had not yet recognized Franco's government.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.894&lt;/ref&gt;  The new regime had signed a [[Iberian Pact|Non-Aggression Pact]] with [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Portugal]] and a treaty of friendship with [[Nazi Germany]] on 31 March,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.893&lt;/ref&gt; and on 6 April, Franco made public Spain's adherence to the [[Anti-Comintern Pact]].&lt;ref&gt;Graham Helen 2005. p.166&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 April, the [[Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War|Non-Intervention Committee]] was dissolved, and by June, both Italian and German troops had left Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001.  p.894&lt;/ref&gt; Francoist Spain remained in power until [[Spanish transition to democracy|Franco's death]] on 20 November 1975.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul. 1995. pp. 786–787&lt;/ref&gt;

Casado remained in exile in Venezuela until he returned to Spain in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.923&lt;/ref&gt; Cipriano Mera fled to Oran and Casablanca, but he was extradited to Spain in February 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p. 410&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943, he was condemned to death, a sentence that was changed for 30 years in prison; he was set free in 1946 and fled to France&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p. 410&lt;/ref&gt;, where he died in 1975. Matallana was detained and imprisoned by the Nationalists and died in Madrid in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.923&lt;/ref&gt; Besteiro, still at his post in the basement of the Revenue Building at 7 Alcalá Street in Madrid, was arrested by the Nationalists when they entered the city and faced a court martial. Sentenced to 30 years in prison,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh 2001. p.888&lt;/ref&gt; he died there of an infection that resulted from an injury to his hand in 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul 2006. p.319&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nationalists arrested hundreds of thousands of Republican soldiers and civilians, with 150,000 soldiers captured in the final offensive, and herded them into improvised concentration camps. There were between 367,000 and 500,000 prisoners in 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.404&lt;/ref&gt; In the first years after the war, 50,000 Republican prisoners were executed.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony 2006. p.405&lt;/ref&gt;

==In literature==
Casado's coup and the last days of the war are the background of the [[Max Aub]]'s novels, ''Campo del Moro''&lt;ref&gt;Aub, Max. 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Campo de los Almendros''.&lt;ref&gt;Aub, Max. 1981.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
*Aub, Max (1979) (in Spanish). ''Campo del moro.'' Madrid. Alfaguara. {{ISBN|9788420420226}}.
*Aub, Max (1981) (in Spanish). ''Campo de los almendros.'' Madrid. Alfaguara. {{ISBN|9788420420240}}.
*Beevor, Antony. (2006). ''The battle for Spain. The Spanish Civil war, 1936–1939.'' Penguin Books. London. {{ISBN|978-0-14-303765-1}}.
*Graham, Helen. (2005). ''The Spanish Civil War. A Very Short introduction.'' Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-19-280377-1}}.
*Jackson, Gabriel. (1967) ''The Spanish Republic and the Civil War, 1931–1939.'' Princeton University Press. Princeton. {{ISBN|978-0-691-00757-1}}.
*Preston, Paul. (1995). ''Franco.'' Fontana Press. London. {{ISBN|978-0-00-686210-9}}.
*Preston, Paul. (2006). ''The Spanish Civil War. Reaction, Revolution &amp; Revenge.'' Harper Perennial. London. {{ISBN|978-0-00-723207-9}}. {{ISBN|0-00-723207-1}}.
*Thomas, Hugh. (2001). ''The Spanish Civil War.'' Penguin Books. London. {{ISBN|978-0-14-101161-5}}.

==Further reading==
*[[Viñas, Ángel]]; and Hernández Sánchez, Fernando. (2009). ''El Desplome de la República.'' Editorial Crítica. Barcelona. {{ISBN|978-84-9892-031-4}}.

==External links==
*[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,760904,00.html TIME Casado's coup]
*[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,760981-1,00.html TIME Aftermath]
*[https://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2011/mar/29/archive-madrid-gives-itself-up-to-franco-1939 Madrid gives itself up to Franco. ''The Guardian'', March 1939]

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Battles of the Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:1939 in Spain]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1939]]
[[Category:March 1939 events]]
[[Category:April 1939 events]]</text>
      <sha1>h2skrhpd76q72igru2p2dfbl0exqpj0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
