<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Much Ado About Nothing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8781048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960042157</id>
      <parentid>956076639</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-31T20:57:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>109.146.43.116</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sources */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="38967" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{short description|comedy play by William Shakespeare}}
{{italic title}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox play
| name       = 
| image      = Much Ado Quarto.JPG
| alt        = 
| caption    = The title page from the first quarto edition of ''Much Adoe About Nothing'', printed in 1600.
| writer     = [[William Shakespeare]]
| chorus     = 
| characters = 
| mute       = 
| setting    = 
| premiere   = 1600
| place      = 
| orig_lang  = 
| series     = 
| subject    = 
| genre      = 
| web        = 
}}
[[File:JG-Benedick-1959.jpg|thumb|Gielgud as Benedick in a 1959 production]]
'''''Much Ado About Nothing''''' is a [[Shakespearean comedy|comedy]] by [[William Shakespeare]] thought to have been written in 1598 and 1599, as Shakespeare was approaching the middle of his career. The play was included in the ''[[First Folio]]'', published in 1623.

By means of "noting" (which, in Shakespeare's day, sounded similar to "nothing" as in the play's title,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |title = Much Ado About Nothing
  |chapter = Introduction
  |last = Shakespeare
  |first = William
  |authorlink = William Shakespeare
  |display-authors = 0
  |editor-last = McEachern
  |editor-first = Claire
  |publisher = [[Bloomsbury Publishing]]
  |series = [[The Arden Shakespeare]], Third Series
  |edition = 2nd revised
  |year = 2016
  |isbn = 978-1-903436-83-7
  |page = 2
  |ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |title = Much Ado About Nothing
  |last = Shakespeare
  |first = William
  |authorlink = William Shakespeare
  |display-authors = 0
  |editor1-last = Zitner
  |editor1-first = Sheldon P.
  |series = [[Oxford World's Classics]]
  |publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
  |location = Oxford
  |year = 2008
  |isbn = 978-0-19-953611-5
  |pages = 131–132
  |ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and which means gossip, rumour, and overhearing), Benedick and Beatrice are tricked into confessing their love for each other, and Claudio is tricked into rejecting Hero at the altar in the erroneous belief that she has been unfaithful. At the end, Benedick and Beatrice join forces to set things right, and the others join in a dance celebrating the marriages of the two couples.

==Characters==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* Benedick, ''a lord and soldier from [[Padua]]; companion of Don Pedro
* Beatrice, ''niece of Leonato''
* [[Don Pedro (Shakespeare character)|Don Pedro]], ''Prince of [[Aragon]]''
* Don John, ''"the [[wikt:bastard|Bastard]] Prince", brother of Don Pedro''
* Claudio, ''of [[Florence]]; a count, companion of Don Pedro, friend to Benedick''
* Leonato, ''governor of [[Messina]]; Hero's father''
* Antonio, ''brother of Leonato''
* Balthasar, ''attendant on Don Pedro, a singer''
* Borachio, ''follower of Don John''
* Conrade, ''follower of Don John''
* Innogen, ''a ‘[[ghost character]]’ in early editions as Leonato's wife''
* Hero, ''daughter of Leonato''
* Margaret, ''waiting-gentlewoman attendant on Hero''
* Ursula, ''waiting-gentlewoman attendant on Hero''
* [[Dogberry]], ''the constable in charge of Messina's night watch''
* Verges, ''the Headborough, Dogberry's partner''
* Friar Francis, ''a priest''
* a Sexton, ''the judge of the trial of Borachio''
* a Boy, ''serving Benedick''
* The Watch, ''watchmen of Messina''
* Attendants and Messengers
{{div col end}}

==Synopsis==
[[File: Shakespeare's Heroines - Beatrice.jpg|thumb|A painting of Beatrice by [[Frank Dicksee]], from ''The Graphic Gallery of Shakespeare's Heroines'']]
In [[Messina]], a messenger brings news that [[Don Pedro (Shakespeare character)|Don Pedro]], a prince from [[Aragon]], will return that night from a successful battle, alongside Claudio and Benedick. Beatrice, niece of Leonato, a governor of Messina, asks the messenger about Benedick and makes sarcastic remarks about his ineptitude as a soldier. Leonato explains that "There is a kind of merry war betwixt Signor Benedick and her."&lt;ref name="shakespeare-navigators.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/ado/AdoText11.html#61|title=Much Ado About Nothing: Act 1, Scene 1|work=shakespeare-navigators.com|accessdate=6 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon the soldiers' arrival, Leonato welcomes Don Pedro and invites him to stay for a month, Benedick and Beatrice resume their "merry war", and Pedro's illegitimate brother Don John is introduced. Claudio's feelings for Hero, Leonato's only daughter, are rekindled upon seeing her, and Claudio soon announces to Benedick his intention to court her. Benedick, who openly despises marriage, tries to dissuade his friend, but Don Pedro encourages the marriage. Benedick swears that he will never get married. Don Pedro laughs at him and tells him that when he has found the right person he shall get married.

A [[masquerade ball]] is planned in celebration of the end of the war, giving a disguised Don Pedro the opportunity to [[Courtship|woo]] Hero on Claudio's behalf. Don John uses this situation to get revenge on him by telling Claudio that Don Pedro is wooing Hero for himself. A furious Claudio confronts Don Pedro, but the misunderstanding is quickly resolved and Claudio wins Hero's hand in marriage.

Meanwhile, Benedick disguises himself and dances with Beatrice, who proceeds to tell this "mystery man" that Benedick is "the prince's jester, a very dull fool." Enraged by her words, Benedick swears he will have revenge. Don Pedro and his men, bored at the prospect of waiting a week for the wedding, concoct a plan to match-make between Benedick and Beatrice. They arrange for the former to overhear a conversation in which they declare that the latter is madly in love with him, but is too afraid to tell him as their pride is the main impediment to their courtship. Meanwhile, Hero and her maid, Ursula, ensure Beatrice overhears them discuss Benedick's undying love for her. The tricks have the desired effect: both Benedick and Beatrice are delighted to think they are the object of [[unrequited love]], and both accordingly resolve to mend their faults and reconcile.

Meanwhile, Don John, the "bastard prince", plots to stop the wedding, embarrass his brother, and wreak misery on Leonato and Claudio. He informs Don Pedro and Claudio that Hero is unfaithful, and arranges for them to see his associate, Borachio, enter her bedchamber and engage in an amorous liaison with her (though in reality it was Margaret, Hero's chambermaid). Claudio and Don Pedro are taken in, and the former vows to publicly humiliate Hero.

[[File:Much Ado About Nothing by Alfred Elmore 1846.jpg|thumbnail|left|Swooning of Hero in the Church scene by [[Alfred Elmore]]]]

At the wedding the next day, Claudio denounces Hero before the stunned guests and storms off with Don Pedro, causing Hero to faint. A humiliated Leonato expresses his wish for her to die. The presiding friar intervenes, believing Hero to be innocent. He suggests the family must fake Hero's death in order to extract the truth and Claudio's remorse. Prompted by the day's stressful events, Benedick and Beatrice confess their love for each other. Beatrice then asks Benedick to kill Claudio as proof of his devotion, since he has slandered her kinswoman. Benedick is disgusted and at first denies her request. Leonato and his brother Antonio blame Claudio for Hero's apparent death and challenge him to a duel. Benedick then does the same, following Beatrice's commands as he is one of the few who believe Hero. Luckily, on the night of Don John's treachery, the local Watch apprehended Borachio and his ally, Conrade. Despite the comic ineptness of the Watch (headed by constable [[Dogberry]], a master of [[malapropism]]s), they have overheard the duo discussing their evil plans. The Watch arrest the villains and eventually obtain a confession, informing Leonato of Hero's innocence. Though Don John has fled the city, a force is sent to capture him. Claudio, stricken with remorse at Hero's supposed death, agrees to her father's demand that he marry Antonio's daughter, "almost the copy of my child that's dead"&lt;ref name="shakespeare-navigators.com"/&gt; and carry on the family name.

At the wedding, the bride is revealed to be a still living Hero. Claudio is overjoyed. Beatrice and Benedick, prompted by their friends' interference, finally and publicly confess their love for each other. As the play draws to a close, a messenger arrives with news of Don John's capture, but Benedick proposes to postpone deciding Don John's punishment until tomorrow so the couples can enjoy their newfound happiness. Don Pedro expresses his loneliness since he hasn't found love, to which Benedick responds, "Get thee a wife."

==Sources==
Stories of lovers deceived into believing each other false were common currency in northern Italy in the sixteenth century. Shakespeare's immediate source could have been one of the ''Novelle'' ("Tales") by [[Matteo Bandello]] of [[Mantua]], dealing with the tribulations of Sir Timbreo and his betrothed Fenicia Lionata in Messina after [[Peter III of Aragon|King Piero's]] defeat of [[Charles of Anjou]], perhaps through the translation into French by [[François de Belleforest]].&lt;ref name="RasmussenShakespeare2007"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rasmussen|first1=Eric|authorlink1=|last2=Bate|first2=Jonathan|authorlink2=Jonathan Bate|title=The RSC Shakespeare: the complete works|year=2007|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York|isbn=978-0-230-00350-7|page=257|chapter=Much Ado About Nothing}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another version featuring lovers Ariodante and Ginevra, with the servant Dalinda impersonating Ginevra on the balcony, appears in Book V of ''[[Orlando Furioso]]'' by [[Ludovico Ariosto]], published in an English translation in 1591.&lt;ref name="Shakespeare1997"&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=G. Blakemore|authorlink=G. Blakemore Evans|title=The Riverside Shakespeare|year=1997|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|location=Boston|isbn=0-395-85822-4|page=361|chapter=Much Ado about Nothing}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The character of Benedick too has a counterpart in a commentary upon marriage in ''Orlando Furioso'',&lt;ref name="HoenselaarsMarrapodi1998"&gt;{{cite book|last=Dusinberre|first=Juliet|editor=Marrapodi, Michele|title=The Italian world of English Renaissance drama: cultural exchange and intertextuality|year=1998|publisher=University of Delaware Press|location=Newark|isbn=0-87413-638-5|page=244|chapter=Much Ado About Lying}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the witty wooing of Beatrice and Benedick is original and very unusual in style and syncopation.&lt;ref name="RasmussenShakespeare2007" /&gt; One version of the Claudio–Hero plot is told by [[Edmund Spenser]] in ''[[The Faerie Queene]]'' (Book II, Canto iv).&lt;ref name= "Harrison1968"&gt;{{cite book|editor=Harrison, GB|title=Shakespeare: the Complete Works|year=1968|publisher=Harcourt, Brace &amp; World, Inc.|location=New York|isbn=0-15-580530-4|page=[https://archive.org/details/shakespearecompl00shak/page/697 697]|chapter=Much Ado About Nothing introduction|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/shakespearecompl00shak/page/697}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Date and text==
The earliest printed text states that ''Much Ado About Nothing'' was "sundry times publicly acted" prior to 1600 and it is likely that the play made its debut in the autumn or winter of 1598–1599.&lt;ref&gt;See textual notes to ''Much Ado About Nothing'' in ''The Norton Shakespeare'' ([[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]], 1997 {{ISBN|0-393-97087-6}}) p.&amp;nbsp;1387&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest recorded performances are two that were given at Court in the winter of 1612–1613, during the festivities preceding the marriage of Princess [[Elizabeth of Bohemia|Elizabeth]] with [[Frederick V, Elector Palatine]] (14 February 1613). The play was published in [[book size|quarto]] in 1600 by the stationers [[Andrew Wise]] and [[William Aspley]]. This was the only edition prior to the [[First Folio]] in 1623.

==Analysis and criticism==

===Style===
The play is predominantly written in prose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://shakespeare.mit.edu/much_ado/full.html |title=Much Ado About Nothing: Entire Play |publisher=Shakespeare.mit.edu |date= |accessdate=12 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The substantial verse sections achieve a sense of decorum and provide energy to its audience.&lt;ref name=arden&gt;{{cite book|editor=A. R. Hunphreys| title=Much Ado About Nothing| publisher=Arden Edition| year=1981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Setting===
''Much Ado About Nothing'' is set in [[Messina]], a port on the island of [[Sicily]], which is next to the toe of [[Italy]]. Sicily was [[History of Sicily#Spanish period|ruled by Aragon]] at the time the play was set.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Bate|first=Jonathan|authorlink=Jonathan Bate|title=Soul of the Age: the Life, Mind and World of William Shakespeare|publisher=Viking|location=London|year=2008|page=305|isbn=978-0-670-91482-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The action of the play takes place mainly at the home and on the grounds of Leonato's Estate.

===Themes and motifs===

====Gender roles====
[[File:Kill Claudio.jpg|thumb|Drawing of [[Herbert Beerbohm Tree]] as Benedick and [[Winifred Emery]] as Beatrice in a 1905 production. Act II, Scene v: "Kill Claudio".]]
Benedick and Beatrice quickly became the main interest of the play, to the point where they are today considered the leading roles, even though their relationship is given equal or lesser weight in the script than Claudio and Hero's situation.  [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] even wrote 'Benedick and Beatrice' beside the title of the play in his copy of the [[Second Folio]].&lt;ref&gt;G. Blakemore Evans, ''The Riverside Shakespeare'', Houghton Mifflin, 1974; p.&amp;nbsp;327.&lt;/ref&gt; The provocative treatment of gender is central to the play and should be considered in its [[Renaissance]] context. While this was reflected and emphasized in certain plays of the period, it was also challenged.&lt;ref name="McEachern"&gt;McEachern, ''Much Ado About Nothing'', Arden; 3rd edition, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Amussen&lt;ref&gt;Amussen, ''Ordered Society'', Columbia University Press (15 April 1994).&lt;/ref&gt; notes that the undoing of traditional gender clichés appears to have inflamed anxieties about the erosion of social order. It seems that comic drama could be a means of calming such anxieties. Ironically, we can see through the play's popularity that this only increased people's interest in such behavior. Benedick wittily gives voice to male anxieties about women's "sharp tongues and proneness to sexual lightness".&lt;ref name="McEachern" /&gt; In the patriarchal society of the play, the men's loyalties were governed by conventional codes of honour and camaraderie and a sense of superiority to women.&lt;ref name="McEachern" /&gt; Assumptions that women are by nature prone to inconstancy are shown in the repeated jokes on [[cuckold]]ry and partly explain Claudio's readiness to believe the slur against Hero. This stereotype is turned on its head in Balthazar's song "Sigh No More," which presents men as the deceitful and inconstant sex that women must suffer.

====Infidelity====
A [[Theme (literature)|theme]] in Shakespeare is cuckoldry or the infidelity of a wife. Several of the characters seem to be obsessed by the idea that a man has no way to know if his wife is faithful and therefore women can take full advantage of that fact. Don John plays upon Claudio's pride and fear of cuckoldry, which leads to the disastrous first wedding. Many of the males easily believe that Hero is impure and even her father readily condemns her with very little proof. This [[Motif (narrative)|motif]] runs through the play, often in references to horns, a symbol of cuckoldry.

In contrast, Balthasar's song "[[Sigh No More (Much Ado About Nothing)|Sigh No More]]" tells women to accept men's infidelity and continue to live joyfully. Some interpretations say that Balthasar sings poorly, undercutting the message. This is supported by Benedick's cynical comments about the song, where he compares it to a howling dog. However, in the 1993 Branagh film Balthasar sings beautifully, the song is also given a prominent role in both the opening and finale and the message appears to be embraced by the women in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Deleyto|first1= Celestino|year= 1997|title= Men in Leather: Kenneth Branagh's Much Ado about Nothing and Romantic Comedy|journal= Cinema Journal|volume= 36|issue= 3|pages= 91–105|publisher= University of Texas Press |doi= 10.2307/1225677|jstor= 1225677}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Deception====
In ''Much Ado About Nothing'', there are many examples of deception and self-deception. The games and tricks played on people often have the best intentions{{snd}}to make people fall in love, to help someone get what they want, or to lead someone to realize their mistake. However, not all are meant well, such as when Don John convinces Claudio that Don Pedro wants Hero for himself, or when Borachio meets 'Hero' (who is actually Margaret, pretending to be Hero) in Hero's bedroom window. These modes of deceit play into a complementary theme of emotional manipulation and the ease with which the characters' sentiments are redirected and their propensities exploited as a means to an end. The characters' feelings for each other are played as vehicles to reach an ultimate goal of engagement rather than seen as an end in themselves.

====Masks and mistaken identity====
People are constantly pretending to be others or being mistaken for other people. An example of this is Margaret who is mistaken for Hero, which leads to Hero's public disgrace at her wedding with Claudio. However, during a masked ball in which everyone must wear a mask, Beatrice rants about Benedick to a masked man who turns out to be Benedick himself but she acts unaware of this at the time. During the same celebration, Don Pedro, masked, pretends to be Claudio and courts Hero for him. After Hero is announced "dead," Leonato orders Claudio to marry his "niece," who is actually Hero in disguise.

====Nothing====
[[File:Beatrice overhears Hero and Ursula.jpg|thumb|A watercolor by [[John Sutcliffe (artist)|John Sutcliffe]]: Beatrice overhears Hero and Ursula.]]

Another motif is the play on the words ''nothing'' and ''noting'', which in Shakespeare's day were near-[[homophone]]s.&lt;ref&gt;See Stephen Greenblatt's introduction to ''Much Ado about Nothing'' in ''The Norton Shakespeare'' ([[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]], 1997 {{ISBN|0-393-97087-6}}), p.&amp;nbsp;1383.&lt;/ref&gt; Taken literally, the title implies that a great fuss ("much ado") is made of something which is insignificant ("nothing"), such as the unfounded claims of Hero's infidelity and the unfounded claims that Benedick and Beatrice are in love with each other. The title could also be understood as ''Much Ado About Noting''. Much of the action centers around interest in and critique of others, written messages, [[Espionage|spying]], and [[eavesdropping]]. This attention on others is directly mentioned several times, particularly concerning "seeming," "fashion," and outward impressions.

''Nothing'' is also a [[double entendre]]; "an O-thing" (or "n othing" or "no thing") was Elizabethan slang for "[[vagina]]", evidently derived from the pun of a woman having "nothing" between her legs.&lt;ref name="RasmussenShakespeare2007" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See Gordon Williams ''A Glossary of Shakespeare's Sexual Language'' (Althone Press, 1997 {{ISBN|0-485-12130-1}}) at p.&amp;nbsp;219: "As Shakespeare's title ironically acknowledges, vagina and virginity are a nothing causing Much Ado."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/booknews/8313901/Title-Deed-How-the-Book-Got-its-Name.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Gary | last=Dexter | title=Title Deed: How the Book Got its Name | date=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of noting as noticing occur in the following instances: (1.1.131–132)
{{quote|'''Claudio:''' Benedick, didst thou note the daughter of Signor Leonato?&lt;br /&gt;
'''Benedick:''' I noted her not, but I looked on her.}}
and (4.1.154–157).
{{quote|'''Friar:''' Hear me a little,&lt;br /&gt;
For I have only been silent so long&lt;br /&gt;
And given way unto this course of fortune&lt;br /&gt;
By noting of the lady.}}

At (3.3.102–104), Borachio indicates that a man's clothing doesn't indicate his character:
{{quote|'''Borachio:''' Thou knowest that the fashion of a doublet, or a hat, or a cloak is nothing to a man.}}

A triple play on words in which noting signifies noticing, musical notes and nothing occurs at (2.3.47–52):
{{quote|'''Don Pedro:''' Nay pray thee, come;&lt;br /&gt;
Or if thou wilt hold longer argument,&lt;br /&gt;
Do it in notes.&lt;br /&gt;
'''Balthasar:''' Note this before my notes:&lt;br /&gt;
There's not a note of mine that's worth the noting.&lt;br /&gt;
'''Don Pedro:''' Why, these are very crotchets that he speaks –&lt;br /&gt;
Note notes, forsooth, and nothing!}}

Don Pedro's last line can be understood to mean, "Pay attention to your music and nothing else!" The complex layers of meaning include a pun on "crotchets," which can mean both "[[quarter note]]s" (in music) and whimsical notions.

The following are [[pun]]s on notes as messages: (2.1.174–176),
{{quote|'''Claudio:''' I pray you leave me.&lt;br /&gt;
'''Benedick:''' Ho, now you strike like the blind man – 'twas the boy that stole your meat, and you'll beat the post.}}
in which Benedick plays on the word ''post'' as a pole and as mail delivery in a joke reminiscent of Shakespeare's earlier advice "[[Shooting the messenger|Don't shoot the messenger]]"; and (2.3.138–142)

{{quote|'''Claudio:''' Now you talk of a sheet of paper, I remember a [[wikt:pretty|pretty]] jest your daughter told us of.&lt;br /&gt;
'''Leonato:''' O, when she had writ it and was reading it over, she found Benedick and Beatrice between the sheet?}}
in which Leonato makes a sexual innuendo concerning ''sheet'' as a sheet of paper (on which Beatrice's love note to Benedick is to have been written) and a bedsheet.

==Performance history==
[[File:Garrick as Benedick.jpg|thumb|[[David Garrick]] as Benedick, by {{Interlanguage link multi|Jean-Louis Fesch|fr}}, 1770]]

The play was very popular in its early decades, and continues to be a standard wherever Shakespeare is performed. In a poem published in 1640, [[Leonard Digges (writer)|Leonard Digges]] wrote, "[…] let but Beatrice&amp;nbsp;/ And Benedick be seen, lo in a trice&amp;nbsp;/ The [[Cockpit Theatre|Cockpit]] galleries, boxes, all are full."

[[File:Gielgud and Leighton in Much Ado 1959.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|[[John Gielgud]] and [[Margaret Leighton]] in the 1959 Broadway production of ''Much Ado About Nothing''.]]

After the theatres re-opened during the [[Restoration (England)|Restoration]], Sir [[William Davenant]] staged ''The Law Against Lovers'' (1662), which inserted Beatrice and Benedick into an adaptation of ''[[Measure for Measure]]''. Another adaptation, ''The Universal Passion'', combined ''Much Ado'' with a play by [[Molière]] (1737). Shakespeare's text had been revived by [[John Rich (producer)|John Rich]] at [[Lincoln's Inn Fields]] (1721). [[David Garrick]] first played Benedick in 1748 and continued to play him until 1776.&lt;ref&gt;[[F. E. Halliday]], ''A Shakespeare Companion 1564–1964.'' Baltimore, Penguin, 1964, pp.&amp;nbsp;326 f.&lt;/ref&gt;

The great nineteenth-century stage team [[Henry Irving]] and [[Ellen Terry]] counted Benedick and Beatrice as their greatest triumph and [[Charles Kemble]] also had a great success as Benedick. [[John Gielgud]] made Benedick one of his signature roles between 1931 and 1959, playing the part opposite the Beatrice of [[Diana Wynyard]], [[Peggy Ashcroft]], and [[Margaret Leighton]]. The longest running Broadway production is [[A. J. Antoon]]'s 1972 staging starring [[Sam Waterston]], [[Kathleen Widdoes]], and [[Barnard Hughes]], and [[Derek Jacobi]] won a [[Tony Award]] for playing Benedick in 1984. Jacobi had also played Benedick in the [[Royal Shakespeare Company]]'s highly praised 1982 production. Director [[Terry Hands]] produced the play on a stage-length mirror, against an unchanging backdrop of painted trees. [[Sinéad Cusack]] played Beatrice. In 2013 [[Vanessa Redgrave]] and [[James Earl Jones]] (then in their seventies and eighties, respectively) played Beatrice and Benedick on stage at [[The Old Vic]], London.
{{-}}

=== Actors, theatres and awards ===
[[File:Irving and Terry as Benedick and Beatrice.jpg|thumb|Print of [[Ellen Terry]] as Beatrice and [[Henry Irving]] as Benedick in an 1887 performance of the play.]]
* {{circa|1598}}: In the original production by the [[Lord Chamberlain's Men]], [[William Kempe]] played Dogberry and [[Richard Cowley]] played Verges.
* 1748: [[David Garrick]] played Benedick for the first time.
* 1887: [[Henry Irving]] and [[Ellen Terry]] played Benedick and Beatrice.
* 1931: [[John Gielgud, roles and awards|John Gielgud]] played Benedick for the first time at the [[Old Vic]] Theatre and it stayed in his repertory until 1959.
* 1960: A [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Play|Tony Award Nomination for "Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Play"]] went to [[Margaret Leighton]] for her role played in ''Much Ado''.
* 1973: A [[Tony Award for Best Featured Actor in a Play|Tony Award Nomination for "Best Featured Actor in a Play"]] went to [[Barnard Hughes]] as Dogberry in the [[New York Shakespeare Festival]] production.
* 1973: A Tony Award Nomination for "Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Play" went to [[Kathleen Widdoes]].
* 1983: The [[Evening Standard Award]] for the "Best Actor" went to [[Derek Jacobi]].
* 1985: A Tony Award Nomination for "Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Play" was received by [[Sinéad Cusack]].
* 1985: The [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Play|Tony Award for "Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Play"]] went to [[Derek Jacobi]] as Benedick.
*1987: Tandy Cronyn as Beatrice and [[Richard Monette]] as Benedick in a production at the [[Stratford Festival]] directed by Peter Moss&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/Theater/production/stage/3218/|title=Much Ado About Nothing (1987, Stratford Festival of Canada)|last=Somerset|first=Alan|date=3 January 2019|website=Internet Shakespeare Editions|publisher=University of Victoria|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=18 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1989: The Evening Standard Award for "Best Actress" went to [[Felicity Kendal]] as Beatrice in [[Elijah Moshinsky]]'s production at the [[Novello Theatre|Strand Theatre]].
* 1994: The [[Laurence Olivier Awards|Laurence Olivier Award]] for "Best Actor" went to [[Mark Rylance]] as Benedick in [[Matthew Warchus]]' production at the [[Queen's Theatre]].
* 2006: The Laurence Olivier Award for "Best Actress" was received by [[Tamsin Greig]] as Beatrice in the [[Royal Shakespeare Company]]'s production in the [[Royal Shakespeare Theatre]], directed by Marianne Elliott.
* 2007: [[Zoë Wanamaker]] appeared as Beatrice and [[Simon Russell Beale]] as Benedick in a [[Royal National Theatre|National Theatre]] production directed by [[Nicholas Hytner]].
* 2011: [[Eve Best]] appeared as Beatrice and [[Charles Edwards (English actor)|Charles Edwards]] as Benedick at [[Shakespeare's Globe]], directed by [[Jeremy Herrin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/theatre/theatre-reviews/8545980/Much-Ado-About-Nothing-Shakespeares-Globe-review.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Charles | last=Spencer | title=Much Ado About Nothing, Shakespeare's Globe, review | date=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2011: [[David Tennant]] as Benedick alongside [[Catherine Tate]] as Beatrice in a production of the play at the [[Wyndham's Theatre]], directed by [[Josie Rourke]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/theatre/theatre-features/8505416/David-Tennant-and-Catherine-Tate-interview-for-Much-Ado-About-Nothing.html |title=David Tennant and Catherine Tate interview for 'Much Ado About Nothing'|work=The Daily Telegraph |date=10 May 2011 |accessdate=28 May 2011 |location=London |first=Dominic |last=Cavendish}}&lt;/ref&gt; An authorized recording of this production is available to download and watch from [[Digital Theatre (website)|Digital Theatre]].
* 2012: [[Meera Syal]] as Beatrice and [[Paul Bhattacharjee]] as Benedick in an Indian setting, directed by Iqbal Khan for the [[Royal Shakespeare Company]], part of the [[World Shakespeare Festival]]
* 2013: [[Vanessa Redgrave]] as Beatrice and [[James Earl Jones]] as Benedick in a production at [[The Old Vic]] directed by [[Mark Rylance]].
* 2013: A German-language production (''Viel Lärm um Nichts''), translated and directed by [[Marius von Mayenburg]] at the [[Schaubühne am Lehniner Platz|Schaubuhne am Lehniner Platz]], Berlin.
* 2017: Beatriz Romilly as Beatrice and [[Matthew Needham]] as Benedick in a Mexican setting, at [[Shakespeare's Globe]], directed by Matthew Dunster.
* 2018: [[Mel Giedroyc]] as Beatrice and [[John Hopkins (actor)|John Hopkins]] as Benedick in a modern Sicilian setting, at the [[Rose Theatre, Kingston]], directed by Simon Dormandy.
* 2019: [[Danielle Brooks]] as Beatrice and Grantham Coleman as Benedick with an all Black cast set in contemporary Georgia, at [[The Public Theater]], directed by [[Kenny Leon]]. This version was broadcast on PBS [[Great Performances]] on 22 November 2019.

==Adaptations==
===Music===
The operas ''Montano et Stéphanie'' (1799) by [[Jean-Élie Bédéno Dejaure]] and [[Henri-Montan Berton]], ''[[Béatrice et Bénédict]]'' (1862) by [[Hector Berlioz]], ''Beaucoup de bruit pour rien'' (pub. 1898) by [[Paul Puget]] and ''[[Much Ado About Nothing (opera)|Much Ado About Nothing]]'' by Sir [[Charles Villiers Stanford]] (1901) are based upon the play.&lt;ref&gt;Daly, Karina, [https://books.google.com/books?ei=jEwiTPXyHJmosQbjqeG_BA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=l_sTAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=%22Much+Ado+about+Nothing%22+Wexford+opera&amp;q=%22Much+Ado+about+Nothing%22 ''Tom Walsh's Opera'': A history of the Wexford Festival, 1951–2004], Four Courts, 2004. {{ISBN|1-85182-878-8}}; the [http://imslp.org/wiki/Beaucoup_de_bruit_pour_rien_%28Puget,_Paul%29 Workpage for Puget's opera] at [[International Music Score Library Project|IMSLP]].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Erich Wolfgang Korngold]] composed music for a production in 1917 at the Vienna Burgtheater by [[Max Reinhardt]].

In 2006 the [[American Music Theatre Project]] produced ''[[The Boys Are Coming Home]],''&lt;ref&gt;[[Simonson, Robert]]. [http://www.playbill.com/news/article/99899-Cast-Set-for-Gary-Griffin-Directed-The-Boys-Are-Coming-Home-at-Northwesterns-American-Music-Theatre-Project "Cast Set for Gary Griffin-Directed ''The Boys Are Coming Home'', at Northwestern's American Music Theatre Project"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110605042253/http://www.playbill.com/news/article/99899-Cast-Set-for-Gary-Griffin-Directed-The-Boys-Are-Coming-Home-at-Northwesterns-American-Music-Theatre-Project |date=5 June 2011 }}. 28 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; a musical adaptation by Berni Stapleton and [[Leslie Arden]] that sets ''Much Ado About Nothing'' in America during the Second World War.

The title track of the 2009 [[Mumford &amp; Sons]] album ''[[Sigh No More (Mumford &amp; Sons album)|Sigh No More]]'' uses quotes from this play in the song. The title of the album is also a quotation from the play.

In 2015, [[Billie Joe Armstrong]] wrote the music for a [[rock opera]] adaptation of the play, ''These Paper Bullets'', which was written by [[Rolin Jones]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://atlantictheater.org/playevents/thesepaperbullets/ | title=These Paper Bullets!/Nov 20, 2015 – Jan 10, 2016 | publisher=Atlantic Theater Company | accessdate=30 April 2016 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160116065858/https://atlantictheater.org/playevents/thesepaperbullets/ | archive-date=16 January 2016 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Schulich School of Music|Opera McGill]] recently commissioned a new operatic adaptation of the play with music by James Garner and libretto adapted by Patrick Hansen which premieres in [[Montreal|Montréal]] in 2022.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.repercussiontheatre.com/2018/09/28/much-ado-opera-workshop/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://operanuova.ca/production/much-ado-2019-festival&lt;/ref&gt;

===Film===
The first cinematic version in English may have been the 1913 [[silent film]] directed by [[Phillips Smalley]].

[[Martin Hellberg]]'s 1964 East German film ''[[Viel Lärm um nichts]]'' was based on the Shakespeare play. In 1973 a [[Much Ado About Nothing (1973 film)|Soviet film adaptation]] was directed by [[Samson Samsonov]] which starred [[Galina Jovovich]] and [[Konstantin Raikin]].

The first sound version in English released to cinemas was the highly acclaimed [[Much Ado About Nothing (1993 film)|1993 film]] by [[Kenneth Branagh]]. It starred Branagh as Benedick, Branagh's then-wife [[Emma Thompson]] as Beatrice, [[Denzel Washington]] as Don Pedro, [[Keanu Reeves]] as Don John, [[Richard Briers]] as Leonato, [[Michael Keaton]] as Dogberry, [[Robert Sean Leonard]] as Claudio, [[Imelda Staunton]] as Margaret, and [[Kate Beckinsale]] in her film debut as Hero.

The 2001 [[Hindi]] film ''[[Dil Chahta Hai]]'' is a loose adaptation of the play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ramesh|first=Randeep|title=A matter of caste as Bollywood embraces the Bard|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jul/29/books.filmnews|accessdate=5 April 2011|newspaper=Guardian|date=29 July 2006|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, [[Joss Whedon]] completed filming of [[Much Ado About Nothing (2012 film)|an adaptation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Much Ado About Nothing|url=http://muchadothemovie.com|accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; released in June 2013. The cast includes [[Amy Acker]] as Beatrice, [[Alexis Denisof]] as Benedick, [[Nathan Fillion]] as Dogberry, [[Clark Gregg]] as Leonato, [[Reed Diamond]] as Don Pedro, [[Fran Kranz]] as Claudio, [[Jillian Morgese]] as Hero, [[Sean Maher]] as Don John, [[Spencer Treat Clark]] as Borachio, [[Riki Lindhome]] as Conrade, [[Ashley Johnson (actress)|Ashley Johnson]] as Margaret, [[Tom Lenk]] as Verges, and [[Romy Rosemont]] as the sexton. Whedon's adaptation is a contemporary revision with an Italian-mafia theme.

In 2012 a filmed version of the live 2011 performance at The Globe was released to cinemas and on DVD. The same year, a filmed version of the 2011 performance at Wyndham's Theatre was made available for download or streaming on the Digital Theatre website.

In 2015, a modern movie version of this play was created by Owen Drake entitled ''Messina High'', starring Faye Reagan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1720161/|title=Messina High|date=17 August 2015|publisher=|via=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Television and web series ===
There have been several screen adaptations of ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' and almost all of them have been made for television. An adaptation is the 1973 New York Shakespeare Festival production by [[Joseph Papp]], shot on [[videotape]] and released on VHS and DVD, that presents more of the text than [[Kenneth Branagh]]'s version. It is directed by A. J. Antoon. The [[The Public Theater|Papp production]] stars [[Sam Waterston]], Kathleen Widdoes, and Barnard Hughes.

The [[BBC Television Shakespeare#Much Ado About Nothing|1984 BBC Television version]] stars [[Lee Montague]] as Leonato, [[Cherie Lunghi]] as Beatrice, [[Katharine Levy]] as Hero, [[Jon Finch]] as Don Pedro, [[Robert Lindsay (actor)|Robert Lindsay]] as Benedick, [[Robert Reynolds (actor)|Robert Reynolds]] as Claudio, Gordon Whiting as Antonio and [[Vernon Dobtcheff]] as Don John. An earlier BBC television version with &lt;!-- Neither had a DBE or knighthood at this point. --&gt;[[Maggie Smith]] and [[Robert Stephens]], adapted from [[Franco Zeffirelli]]'s stage production for the &lt;!-- Did not acquire the Royal prefix until 1988 &amp; then still at the Old Vic. --&gt;[[Royal National Theatre|National Theatre Company]]'s London stage production, was broadcast in February 1967.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/articles/YYKTPCrSpLz6bxXgNtPhj8/dame-again-early-lost-maggie-smith-appearance-painstakingly-restored|title=Dame Again. Early 'lost' Maggie Smith appearance painstakingly restored|publisher=BBC|date=September 2016|accessdate=30 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 the [[BBC]] adapted the story by setting it in the modern-day studios of Wessex Tonight, a fictional regional news programme, as part of the ''[[ShakespeaRe-Told]]'' season, with [[Damian Lewis]], [[Sarah Parish]], and [[Billie Piper]].

The 2014 YouTube [[web series]] ''Nothing Much to Do'' is a modern retelling of the play, set in New Zealand.

=== Literature ===
In 2016, [[Lily Anderson]] released a young adult novel called ''The Only Thing Worse Than Me Is You'', a modernized adaptation of ''Much Ado About Nothing'' whose main characters, Trixie Watson and Ben West, attend a "school for geniuses".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/lily-anderson/the-only-thing-worse-than-me-is-you/|title=The Only Thing Worse Than Me Is You|last=|first=|date=16 March 2016|website=Kirkus Reviews|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=23 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, a [[Young adult fiction|YA]] adaptation was released by author Mckelle George called ''Speak Easy, Speak Love'', where the events of the play take place in the 1920s, focused around a failing speakeasy.

In 2018, author Molly Booth released a summer [[Young adult fiction|YA]] novel adaptation called ''Nothing Happened'', where Claudio and Hero are a homosexual couple, Claudia and Hana.

==See also==
* [[Margaret (moon)]], a moon of Uranus, named after the character from ''Much Ado About Nothing''

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Much Ado About Nothing (Shakespeare)|Much Ado About Nothing}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category}}
* {{librivox book | title=Much Ado About Nothing | author=William Shakespeare}}
* {{Gutenberg book|no=1519}}
* [http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/ado Annotated text] with line numbers, search engine, and scene summaries
* [http://shakespeare.mit.edu/much_ado/ Text of the play] at MIT
* [http://www.bl.uk/works/much-ado-about-nothing ''Much Ado About Nothing''] at the British Library
* [http://webenglishteacher.com/muchado.html Lesson plans for teaching ''Much Ado About Nothing''] at Web English Teacher
* ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20120709163313/https://www.stratfordfestival.ca/education/activities/muchado/06_animation/index.html Much Ado About Nothing]'' A modern re-telling in [[Flash Comics|flash comic]] format provided by the [[Stratford Shakespeare Festival]] of Canada
* {{Cite NIE|wstitle=Hero (Shakespeare)|display=Hero. The quiet daughter of Leonato and cousin of the gay Beatrice . . . |year=1905 |short=x}}

{{Much Ado About Nothing|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Shakespeare}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1599 plays]]
[[Category:Shakespearean comedies]]
[[Category:English Renaissance plays]]
[[Category:Plays set in Sicily]]
[[Category:British plays adapted into films]]</text>
      <sha1>5l3hxit13glzgb86718vqjufoptpi7j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
