<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Tuscany</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>319100</id>
    <revision>
      <id>948408237</id>
      <parentid>921197256</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-31T21:55:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wikirictor</username>
        <id>18855734</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Apennine, Proto-Villanovan and Villanovan culture */ internal link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="15484" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}
{{main|Tuscany}}
'''Tuscany''' is named after its pre-[[Roman Empire|Roman]] inhabitants, the [[Etruscans]]. It was ruled by Rome for many centuries. In the [[Middle Ages]], it saw many invasions, but in the [[Renaissance]] period it helped lead Europe back to civilization. Later, it settled down as a [[grand duchy]]. It was conquered by [[Napoleonic France]] in the late 18th century and became part of the Italian Republic in the 19th century.

=== Apennine, Proto-Villanovan and Villanovan culture ===
{{Main|Apennine culture|Proto-Villanovan culture|Villanovan culture}}
[[File:Ossuari biconici villanoviani da necropoli di casal di lanza (vulci), IX-VIII sec ac. 01.JPG|thumb|upright=1.1|Cinerary urns of the [[Villanovan culture]]]]

The pre-Etruscan history of the area in the middle and late [[Bronze Age|Bronze]] parallels that of the [[Archaic period in Greece|archaic]] [[Ancient Greece|Greeks]].{{sfn|Barker|Rasmussen|2000|p=5}} The Tuscan area was inhabited by peoples of the so-called [[Apennine culture]] in the [[second millennium BC]] (roughly 1400–1150 BC) who had trading relationships with the [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] and [[Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaean]] civilizations in the [[Aegean Sea]],{{sfn|Barker|Rasmussen|2000|p=5}} and, at the end of the Bronze Age, by peoples of the so-called of the [[Proto-Villanovan culture]] (c. 1100-900 BC) part of the central European [[Urnfield culture]] system. Following this, at the beginning of the [[Iron Age]], the [[Villanovan culture]] (c. 900–700 BC), regarded as the oldest phase of [[Etruscan civilization]],&lt;ref name=Neri&gt;{{cite book|title =Gli etruschi tra VIII e VII secolo a.C. nel territorio di Castelfranco Emilia (MO) |author =Diana Neri |authorlink = |editor = |chapter-url = |via = |publisher =All'Insegna del Giglio |location =Firenze |year =2012 |language = it|volume = |work = |edition = |chapter =1.1 Il periodo villanoviano nell’Emilia occidentale |chapterurl = |p =9 |isbn =978-8878145337 |lccn = |doi = |oclc = |id = |ref = |quote =Il termine “Villanoviano” è entrato nella letteratura archeologica quando, a metà dell ’800, il conte Gozzadini mise in luce le prime tombe ad incinerazione nella sua proprietà di Villanova di Castenaso, in località Caselle (BO). La cultura villanoviana coincide con il periodo più antico della civiltà etrusca, in particolare durante i secoli IX e VIII a.C. e i termini di Villanoviano I, II e III, utilizzati dagli archeologi per scandire le fasi evolutive, costituiscono partizioni convenzionali della prima età del Ferro|accessdate = |archivedate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bartolonivillanoviana&gt;{{cite book|title =La cultura villanoviana. All'inizio della storia etrusca |author = Gilda Bartoloni|authorlink = |editor = |url = |via = |publisher = Carocci editore|location = Roma|year = 2012|language = it|volume = |work = |edition = |chapter = |chapterurl = |p = |pp = |isbn = |lccn = |doi = |oclc = |id = |ref = |quote = |accessdate = |archivedate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; saw Tuscany, and the rest of Etruria, taken over by [[chiefdom]]s.{{sfn|Barker|Rasmussen|2000|p=5}} [[City-state]]s developed in the late Villanovan (paralleling Greece and the Aegean) before "[[Orientalizing period|Orientalization]]" occurred.&lt;ref name=Smith2014&gt;{{cite book |last1=Smith |first1=Christopher |author-link1= Christopher Smith (academic)|year=2014 |title= The Etruscans|series= A Very Short Introduction|language=English |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press |issn=2399-7168 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etruscan period ==
{{main|Etruscan civilization}}
The [[Etruscan civilization|Etruscans]] were the first major civilization in this region; large enough to lay down a transport infrastructure, implement agriculture and mining, and produce vivid art.&lt;ref name="Jones_2"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|2005|p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Etruscans lived in [[Etruria]] well into prehistory. The civilization grew to fill the area between the [[Arno River]] and [[Tiber River]] from the 10th century, reaching their peak during the 7th century BC and 6th century BC, finally succumbing to the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] by the first century.&lt;ref name="Barker_1"&gt;{{Harvnb|Barker|2000|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout their existence, they lost territory to [[Magna Graecia]], [[Carthage]] and [[Gaul]].&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt; Despite being seen as distinct in its manners and customs by contemporary Greeks,&lt;ref name="Barker_4"&gt;{{Harvnb|Barker|2000|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; the cultures of [[Ancient Greeks|Greece]], and later Rome, influenced the civilisation to a great extent. One reason for its eventual demise&lt;ref name="Barker_1" /&gt; was this increasing absorption by surrounding cultures, including the adoption of the Etruscan upper class by the Romans.&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt;

== Roman period ==
Soon after absorbing Etruria, Rome established the cities of [[Lucca]], [[Pisa]], [[Siena]], and [[Florence]], endowed the area with new technologies and development, and ensured peace.&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt; These developments included extensions of existing roads, introduction of aqueducts and sewers, and the construction of many buildings, both public and private.&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt; The Roman civilization in the West collapsed in the fifth century and the region was left to the [[Goths]], and others. In the sixth century, the [[Longobards]] arrived and designated [[Lucca]] the capital of their [[Duchy of Tuscia]].&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt;

==Middle Ages==
{{see also|March of Tuscany}}
After the fall of the [[Western Roman Empire]] the region went under the [[Ostrogothic Kingdom|Ostrogoth]] and [[Byzantine]] dominations, before the [[Lombards|Lombard]] conquest in 569. Tuscany was made a Duchy, its seat in [[Lucca]]. After the destruction of the Lombard kingdom by [[Charlemagne]], it became a county first, and then a march. In the 11th century the marquisate went to the Attoni family from [[Canossa]], who also held [[Modena]], [[Reggio Emilia]] and [[Mantua]]. [[Matilda of Canossa]] was their most famous member. 

In this period Tuscany acquired many castles, abbeys and monasteries, while the main towns started again to grow demographically, turning themselves into [[medieval commune|communes]] mostly independent from the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. Lucca was in fact the first commune in Italy; the other most important ones were [[Arezzo]], [[Republic of Florence|Florence]], [[Republic of Siena|Siena]] and [[History of Pisa|Pisa]], often struggling between each other. The south of current Tuscany (roughly identifiable with the modern [[province of Grosseto]]) was instead a feudal dominion of the [[Aldobrandeschi]] family. 

[[Pilgrim]]s travelling along the [[Via Francigena]] between Rome and France brought wealth and development during the Middle Ages.&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt; The food and shelter required by these travellers fuelled the growth of communities around churches and taverns.&lt;ref name="Jones_2" /&gt; 

In the 11th century Pisa became the most powerful of them, building a trade (as well as colonial) empire in the [[Mediterranean]] and playing a key role in the [[Crusades]]. Banking, soon turned into an international activity with branches in Flanders, France and England, was instead the main resource of Florence, Siena and Lucca. The latter was also an important center for silk production. 

Pisa began to decline in the 13th/14th centuries after its defeat by [[Genoa]] at the [[Battle of Meloria]]. After its conquest of Arezzo and Pisa, by the early 15th century Florence had gained a prominent role in Tuscany, as well as in Italy, and was also the cultural capital of the region.&lt;ref name="Jones_3"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|2005|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its only remaining rival in Tuscany was Siena.

== Renaissance period ==
Though "Tuscany" remained a linguistic, cultural and geographic conception, rather than a political reality, in the 15th century, Florence extended dominion in Tuscany through the annexion of Arezzo in 1384, the purchase of Pisa in 1405 and the suppression of a local resistance there (1406). Livorno was bought in 1421 and become the harbour of Florence.

In the leading city of Florence, the republic was from 1434 onward dominated by the increasingly monarchical Medici family. Initially, under [[Cosimo de' Medici|Cosimo]], [[Piero di Cosimo de' Medici|Piero the Gouty]], [[Lorenzo de' Medici|Lorenzo]] and [[Piero di Lorenzo de' Medici|Piero the Unfortunate]], the forms of the republic were retained and the Medici ruled without a title, usually without even a formal office. These rulers presided over the [[Florentine Renaissance]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.florentine-society.ru/Medici_Chapel_Mysteries.htm Peter Barenboim, Sergey Shiyan, ''Michelangelo: Mysteries of Medici Chapel'', SLOVO, Moscow, 2006]. {{ISBN|5-85050-825-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There was a return to the republic from 1494 to 1512, when first [[Girolamo Savonarola]] then [[Piero Soderini]] oversaw the state. Cardinal Giovanni de' Medici retook the city with Spanish forces in 1512, before going to Rome to become [[Pope Leo X]]. Florence was dominated by a series of papal proxies until 1527 when the citizens declared the republic again, only to have it taken from them again in 1530 after a siege by an Imperial and Spanish army. At this point [[Pope Clement VII]] and [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]] appointed Alessandro de' Medici as the first formally hereditary ruler.

The Sienese commune was not incorporated into Tuscany until 1555, and during the 15th century Siena enjoyed a cultural '[[Sienese Renaissance]]' with its own more conservative character. Lucca remained an independent Republic until 1847 when it became part of [[Grand Duchy of Tuscany]] by the will of its people. [[Piombino]] was another minor independent state, under both Spanish and Tuscan influence.

== Grand Duchy of Tuscany ==
{{main|Grand Duchy of Tuscany}}

=== Later Medici ===
For most of the 16th century the Medici ruled Florence and Tuscany quite successfully, expanding the state's territory greatly by acquiring Siena. The Medici were patrons of science and the arts which flowered for much of their reign. Tuscany became a more cohesive and unified state during these years, rather than simply the dominion of a dominating city, Florence. 

As time went on, Tuscany was transformed in a number of ways, not always positively. Most importantly, the economy underwent a fundamental change in character. The [[wool]] industry was decimated during these later years, though the silk industry was, to some extent, able to replace it. Nonetheless, industry, which had shaped and sustained Florence since the Middle Ages, began to decline throughout the 17th century. Investment in business became less lucrative and there was some “re-[[feudal]]ization” of the Tuscan state with many [[Patrician (post-Roman Europe)|patrician]]s investing in land instead of industry. Tuscany is generally agreed to have declined greatly by the early 18th century under a series of inept grand dukes. 

The Medici dukes were as follows. 

*[[Alessandro de' Medici, Duke of Florence|Alessandro]] 1530–1537 – Titled Duke of Florence.
*[[Cosimo I de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Cosimo I]] 1537–1574 – From 1569 he and his successors titled Grand Duke of Tuscany.
*[[Francesco I de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Francesco I]] 1574–1587 – Son of Cosimo I.
*[[Ferdinando I de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Ferdinando I]] 1587–1609 – Son of Cosimo I.
*[[Cosimo II de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Cosimo II]] 1609–1621 – Son of Ferdinando I.
*[[Ferdinando II de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Ferdinando II]] 1621–1670 – Son of Cosimo II.
*[[Cosimo III de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Cosimo III]] 1670–1723 – Son of Ferdinando II.
*[[Gian Gastone de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Gian Gastone]] 1723–1737 – Son of Cosimo III. When Gian Gastone died without heirs, the grand duchy was inherited by the House of [[Lorraine (province)|Lorraine]].

=== House of Habsburg-Lorraine ===
After the Medici [[dynasty]] died out, there was a take-over by Habsburg-Lorraine rulers with extensive Austrian domains.

Known in Italy as Pietro Leopoldino, Leopold I was the only progressive reformer to rule Tuscany. He abolished the last vestiges of [[serfdom]], encouraged trade and industry, and reformed the bureaucracy. During his long reign Tuscany became one of the most prosperous states in Italy. On 30 November 1786, he promulgated a penal reform making Tuscany the first sovereign state to abolish the death penalty. In this time period Tuscany was also known as a "Guild". 

*[[Francis I, Holy Roman Emperor|Francis of Lorraine]] 1737–1765 – Married [[Maria Theresa of Austria|Maria Theresa]], [[Archduchess]] of [[Austria]]. When he was elected [[Holy Roman Emperor]] in 1747 he passed the Grand Duchy of [[Tuscany]] to his son Leopold.
*[[Leopold I of Lorraine]] 1765–1790 – Leopold also became [[Holy Roman Emperor]] (1790–1792) upon the death of his brother Joseph II (1780–1790).
*[[Ferdinand III, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Ferdinand III]] 1790–1801

=== House of Bourbon-Parma ===
Ferdinand III was deposed by [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon Bonaparte]] in 1801 so that Tuscany could be given to the [[House of Bourbon|Bourbon]] [[Dukes of Parma]] as compensation for the loss of their duchy. During this brief period, the Grand Duchy of Tuscany was known as the [[Kingdom of Etruria]]. 

* [[Louis of Etruria|Louis]] 1801–1803
* [[Charles II, Duke of Parma|Charles Louis]] 1803–1807

Tuscany/Etruria was annexed by Napoleonic France in 1807.

=== House of Bonaparte ===
In 1809 Napoleon gave his sister Elisa the honorary title of Grand Duchess of Tuscany. 

* [[Elisa Bonaparte]] 1809–1814, Grand Duchess of Tuscany

=== House of Habsburg-Lorraine ===
In 1814, after Napoleon's downfall, Ferdinand III was restored as grand duke. However, in 1815, the [[Congress of Vienna]] separated the [[Duchy of Lucca]] from Tuscany to give to the Bourbons of Parma in compensation for other losses. (Lucca would be reintegrated into Tuscany in 1847.)

* [[Ferdinand III, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Ferdinand III]] 1814–1824 – Restored as grand duke.
* [[Leopold II, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Leopold II]] 1824–1848
* republic 1848–1849 – part of the [[Revolutions of 1848]].
* [[Leopold II, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Leopold II]] 1849–1859 – Restored as grand duke.
* [[Ferdinand IV, Grand Duke of Tuscany|Ferdinand IV]] 1859–1860

== Italian Republic ==
In 1860 Tuscany became part of modern [[Italian Republic|Italy]]. Florence replaced Turin as Italy's capital in 1865, hosting the country's first parliament, and was superseded by Rome six years later, in 1871.

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
* Strathern, Paul (2003), ''The Medici: The Godfathers of the Renaissance'' ({{ISBN|1-844-13098-3}}). Covers Florence and Tuscany under Medici.

== See also ==
*[[Tuscany]]
*[[Grand Duchy of Tuscany]]
*[[Kingdom of Etruria]]
*[[Medici Family]]
*[[House of Habsburg-Lorraine]]
*[[Rulers of Tuscany]]
*[[Line of succession to the Tuscan Throne]]
*[[Grand Princes of Tuscany]]
*[[Grand Princesses of Tuscany]]
*[[History of Florence]]
*[[History of Pisa]]
*[[History of Lucca]]
*[[Siena#History|History of Siena]]
*[[List of State Archives of Italy#Tuscany|List of Italian State Archives in Tuscany]]

{{Tuscany}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Tuscany}}
[[Category:History of Tuscany| ]]
[[Category:House of Medici]]

[[gl:Toscana#Historia]]</text>
      <sha1>l2ofq11fh2jfjqve4ar2qvc4ete11ma</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
