<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Maya codices</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1480879</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960840057</id>
      <parentid>960839970</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-05T05:34:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>205121</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Dresden Codex */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="28413" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Manuscript  written by the pre-Columbian Maya civilization in Maya hieroglyphic script}}
[[File:Dresden Codex p09.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Page 9 of the Dresden Codex (from the 1880 [[Ernst Förstemann|Förstemann]] edition)]]

[[File:Láminas 8 y 9 del Códice de Dresden.jpg|thumb|300px|plates 10 and 11 of the Dresden Maya Codex. Drawing by Lacambalam, 2001]]

'''Maya codices''' (singular ''[[codex]]'') are folding [[book]]s written by the [[Pre-Columbian era|pre-Columbian]] [[Maya civilization]] in [[Maya hieroglyphics|Maya hieroglyphic script]] on Mesoamerican [[Amate|bark paper]]. The folding books are the products of professional scribes working under the patronage of deities such as the [[Tonsured Maize God]] and the [[Howler Monkey Gods]]. Most of the codices were destroyed by conquistadors and Catholic priests in the 16th century. The codices have been named for the cities where they eventually settled. The [[Dresden codex]] is generally considered the most important of the few that survive.

The paper was made from the inner bark of certain trees, the main being the wild fig tree or ''[[amate]]'' (''[[Ficus insipida|Ficus glabrata]]''). This sort of paper was generally known by the word ''[[amatl|āmatl]]'' {{IPA-nah|ˈaːmat͡ɬ|}} in [[Nahuatl]], and by the word ''huun'' in [[Mayan Languages|Mayan]]. The Maya developed their ''huun''-paper around the 5th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Burns |first1=Marna |title=The Complete Book of Handcrafted Paper |date=2004 |publisher=Dover Publications |isbn=9780486435442 |page=199}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is roughly the same time that the codex became predominant over the scroll in the Roman world. Maya paper was more durable and a better writing surface than [[papyrus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wiedemann |first1=Hans G. |last2=Brzezinka |first2=Klaus-Werner |last3=Witke |first3=Klaus |last4=Lamprecht |first4=Ingolf  |lastauthoramp=yes|title=Thermal and Raman-spectroscopic analysis of Maya Blue carrying artefacts, especially fragment IV of the Codex Huamantla |journal=Thermochimica Acta |date=May 2007 |volume=456 |issue=1 |pages=56–63 |doi=10.1016/j.tca.2007.02.002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Our knowledge of ancient Maya thought must represent only a tiny fraction of the whole picture, for of the thousands of books in which the full extent of their learning and ritual was recorded, only four have survived to modern times (as though all that posterity knew of ourselves were to be based upon three prayer books and ''[[Pilgrim's Progress]]'').|Michael D. Coe&lt;ref&gt;Coe, Michael D. ''The Maya'', London: Thames and Hudson, 4th ed., 1987, p. 161&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Background ==
There were many books in existence at the time of the [[Spanish conquest of Yucatán]] in the 16th century; most were destroyed by the Catholic [[priests]].&lt;ref name="Foster"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Foster |first1=Lynn V. |title=Handbook to Life in the Ancient Maya World |url=https://archive.org/details/handbooktolifean00fost |url-access=limited |date=2002 |publisher=Facts On File |location=New York |isbn=978-0816041480 |page=[https://archive.org/details/handbooktolifean00fost/page/n311 297]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many in [[Yucatán (state)|Yucatán]] were ordered destroyed by [[Diego de Landa|Bishop Diego de Landa]] in July 1562.&lt;ref&gt;Diego de Landa) William Gates, translator, (1937) 1978. ''Yucatan Before and After the Conquest''. An English translation of Landa's ''Relación'' [https://web.archive.org/web/20170323233025/https://www.globalgreyebooks.com/books/yucatan-before-and-after-the-conquest.pdf Retrieved 22 Mar 2017]&lt;/ref&gt; In his conviction of the superiority and absolute truth of Christianity, De Landa wrote: &lt;blockquote&gt;We found a large number of books in these characters and, as they contained nothing in which were not to be seen as superstition and lies of the devil, we burned them all, which they regretted to an amazing degree, and which caused them much affliction.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Such codices were the primary written records of Maya civilization, together with the many [[inscription]]s on stone [[monument]]s and [[stela]]e that survived. Their range of subject matter in all likelihood embraced more topics than those recorded in stone and buildings, and was more like what is found on painted ceramics (the so-called 'ceramic codex'). Alonso de Zorita wrote that in 1540 he saw numerous such books in the [[Guatemala]]n highlands that "recorded their history for more than eight hundred years back, and that were interpreted for me by very ancient Indians".&lt;ref&gt;Zorita 1963, 271–272&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dominican order|Dominican]] friar [[Bartolomé de las Casas]] lamented when he found out that such books were destroyed: "These books were seen by our clergy, and even I saw part of those that were burned by the monks, apparently because they thought [they] might harm the Indians in matters concerning religion, since at that time they were at the beginning of their conversion." The last codices destroyed were those of [[Nojpetén]], Guatemala in 1697, the last city conquered in the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.authenticmaya.com/maya_writing.htm Maya writing] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070613162647/http://www.authenticmaya.com/maya_writing.htm |date=2007-06-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; With their destruction, access to the history of the Maya and opportunity for insight into some key areas of Maya life was greatly diminished.

There are only three codices whose authenticity is beyond doubt. These are:

* The '''[[Dresden Codex]]''' also known as the ''Codex Dresdensis'' (74 pages, {{convert|3.56|m|ft|abbr=off|disp=sqbr}});&lt;ref name="WDL"&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.wdl.org/pt/item/11621/ |title = O Códice de Dresden |website = [[World Digital Library]] |date = 1200–1250 |accessdate = 2013-08-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''[[Madrid Codex (Maya)|Madrid Codex]]''', also known as the ''Tro-Cortesianus Codex'' (112 pages, {{convert|6.82|m|ft|abbr=off|disp=sqbr}});
* The '''[[Paris Codex]]''', also known as the ''Peresianus Codex'' (22 pages, {{convert|1.45|m|ft|abbr=off|disp=sqbr}}).

A fourth codex that remained controversial until 2015 has been authenticated. Recent research, which includes a study that used everything from X-rays to UV imaging and microscopic analysis, points to its authenticity.

* The '''[[Grolier Codex]]''', also known as the ''Sáenz Codex'' (10 pages).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.brown.edu/articles/2016/09/mayacodex|title=13th century Maya codex, long shrouded in controversy, proves genuine|website=News from Brown|publisher=Brown University|access-date=2016-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Smithsonian 2016"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Blakemore |first1=Erin |title=New Analysis Shows Disputed Maya "Grolier Codex" Is the Real Deal |url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/maya-codex-once-thought-be-sketchy-real-thing-180960466/ |website=Smithsonian |accessdate=2018-11-09 |date=15 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dresden Codex==
{{Main|Dresden Codex}}

The Dresden Codex (''Codex Dresdensis'') is held in the [[Sächsische Landesbibliothek]] (SLUB), the state library in [[Dresden]], Germany. It is the most elaborate of the codices, and also a highly important specimen of [[Maya art]]. Many sections are ritualistic (including so-called 'almanacs'), others are of an [[astrological]] nature ([[eclipse]]s, the [[Transits of Venus|Venus cycles]]). The codex is written on a long sheet of paper that is 'screen-folded' to make a book of 39 leaves, written on both sides. It was probably written between the twelfth and fourteenth centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Ruggles|first=Clive L. N.|title=Ancient Astronomy: An Encyclopedia of Cosmologies and Myth|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Q9YYqiXm-lkC|year=2005|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-85109-477-6|page=134}}&lt;/ref&gt; Somehow it made its way to Europe and was bought by the royal library of the court of Saxony in Dresden in 1739. The only exact replica, including the ''huun'', made by a German artist is displayed at the ''Museo Nacional de Arqueología'' in [[Guatemala]] City, since October 2007.

Exactly how the Dresden Codex ended up in Europe is not clear.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Vail|first=Gabrielle|date=2015|title=Astronomy in the Dresden Codex|journal=Handbook of Archaeastronomy and Ethnoastronomy|volume=|pages=695–708|doi=10.1007/978-1-4614-6141-8_65|isbn=978-1-4614-6140-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It arrived sometime in the late 18th{{nbsp}}century, potentially from the first or second generation of Spanish conquistadores.  Even though the last date entry in the book is from several centuries before its relocation, the book was likely used and added to until just before the conquerors took it. 

About 65 per cent of the pages in the Dresden Codex contain richly illustrated astronomical tables. These tables focus on eclipses, equinoxes and solstices, the sidereal cycle of Mars, and the synodic cycles of Mars and Venus. These observations allowed the Mayans to plan the calendar year, agriculture, and religious ceremonies around the stars.  In the text, Mars is represented by a long nosed deer, and Venus is represented by a star. 

Pages 51–58 are eclipse tables. These tables accurately predicted solar eclipses for 33{{nbsp}}years in the 8th{{nbsp}}century, though the predictions of lunar eclipses were far less successful. Icons of serpents devouring the sun symbolize eclipses throughout the book. The glyphs show roughly 40 times in the text, making eclipses a major focus of the Dresden Codex. 

The first 52 pages of the Dresden Codex are about divination. The Mayan astronomers would use the codex for day keeping, but also determining the cause of sickness and other misfortunes. 

Though a wide variety of gods and goddesses appear in the Dresden Codex, the Moon Goddess is the only neutral figure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Barnhart|first=Edwin|date=Fall 2005|title=The First Twenty-Three Pages of the Dresden Codex: The Divination Pages|url=https://www.mayaexploration.org/pdf/DresdenCodex1-23.pdf|volume=|pages=1–145|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first 23 pages of the book, she is mentioned far more than any other god. 

Between 1880 and 1900, Dresden librarian [[Ernst Förstemann]] succeeded in deciphering the [[Maya numerals]] and the [[Maya calendar]] and realized that the codex is an [[ephemeris]].&lt;ref&gt;Ernst Förstemann, ''Commentary on the Maya Manuscript in the Royal  Public Library of Dresden'', Peabody Museum of American Archaeology and Ethnology, Harvard University Vol. IV, No. 2, Cambridge Mass. 1902&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent studies have decoded these astronomical almanacs, which include records of the cycles of the Sun and Moon, including eclipse tables, and all of the naked-eye planets.&lt;ref&gt;John Eric Sidney Thompson, ''A commentary on the Dresden Codex: A Maya Hieroglyphic Book'', Memoirs of the American Philosophical Society, 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; The "Serpent Series", pp.&amp;nbsp;61–69, is an [[ephemeris]] of these phenomena that uses a base date of 1.18.1.8.0.16 in the prior era (5,482,096 days).&lt;ref&gt;Beyer, Hermann 1933 Emendations of the 'Serpent Numbers' of the Dresden Maya Codex. Anthropos (St. Gabriel Mödling bei Wien) 28: pp. 1–7. 1943 The Long Count Position of the Serpent Number Dates. Proc. 27th Int. Cong. Of Amer., Mexico, 1939 (Mexico) I: pp. 401–405.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grofe, Michael John 2007 The Serpent Series: Precession in the Maya Dresden Codex&lt;/ref&gt;

== Madrid Codex ==
{{Main|Madrid Codex (Maya)}}
[[File:Madrid Codex 6.JPG|thumb|right|Rain-bringing snakes, Madrid Codex]]
The Madrid Codex was discovered in Spain in the 1860s; it was divided into two parts of differing sizes that were found in different locations.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p127"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; The Codex receives its alternate name of the Tro-Cortesianus Codex after the two parts that were separately discovered.&lt;ref name="FAMSI"&gt;FAMSI.&lt;/ref&gt; Ownership of the Troano Codex passed to the [[National Archaeological Museum of Spain|Museo Arqueológico Nacional]] ("National Archaeological Museum") in 1888.&lt;ref name="Noguez&amp;c09p20"&gt;Noguez et al. 2009, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The Museo Arqueológico Nacional acquired the Cortesianus Codex from a book-collector in 1872, who claimed to have recently purchased the codex in [[Extremadura]].&lt;ref&gt;Noguez et al. 2009, pp. 20–21.&lt;/ref&gt; Extremadura is the province from which [[Francisco de Montejo]] and many of his [[conquistador]]s came,&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p127"/&gt; as did [[Hernán Cortés]], the conqueror of Mexico.&lt;ref name="Noguez&amp;c09p21"&gt;Noguez et al. 2009, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; It is therefore possible that one of these conquistadors brought the codex back to Spain;&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p127"/&gt; the director of the Museo Arqueológico Nacional named the Cortesianus Codex after Hernán Cortés, supposing that he himself had brought the codex back.&lt;ref name="Noguez&amp;c09p21"/&gt;

The Madrid Codex is the longest of the surviving Maya codices.&lt;ref name="Noguez&amp;c09p20"/&gt; The content of the Madrid Codex mainly consists of almanacs and horoscopes that were used to help [[Maya priesthood|Maya priests]] in the performance of their ceremonies and divinatory rituals. The codex also contains astronomical tables, although fewer than the other two generally accepted surviving Maya codices.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p127"/&gt; A close analysis of glyphic elements suggests that a number of scribes were involved in its production, perhaps as many as eight or nine, who produced consecutive sections of the manuscript; the scribes were likely to have been members of the priesthood.&lt;ref&gt;Ciudad et al. 1999, pp. 877, 879.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars, such as [[Michael Coe]] and Justin Kerr,&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1999, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; have suggested that the Madrid Codex dates to after the [[Spanish conquest of Yucatán|Spanish conquest]] but the evidence overwhelmingly favours a pre-conquest date for the document. It is likely that the codex was produced in [[Yucatán (state)|Yucatán]].&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p127"/&gt; [[J. Eric S. Thompson|J.&amp;nbsp;Eric Thompson]] was of the opinion that the Madrid Codex came from western Yucatán and dated to between 1250 and 1450 AD. Other scholars have expressed a differing opinion, noting that the codex is similar in style to murals found at [[Chichen Itza]], [[Mayapan]] and sites on the east coast such as Santa Rita, [[Tancah]] and [[Tulum]].&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p129"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; Two paper fragments incorporated into the front and last pages of the codex contain Spanish writing, which led Thompson to suggest that a Spanish priest acquired the document at [[Nojpetén|Tayasal]] in Petén.&lt;ref&gt;Coe 1999, p. 200. Ciudad et al. 1999, p. 880.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Paris Codex==
{{Main|Paris Codex}}
[[File:Paris Codex, pages 23-24.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Paris Codex]]
The Paris Codex (also or formerly the Codex Peresianus) contains prophecies for tuns and katuns (see [[Maya Calendar]]), as well as a Maya zodiac, and is thus, in both respects, akin to the Books of [[Chilam Balam]]. The codex first appeared in 1832 as an acquisition of France's ''Bibliothèque Impériale'' (later the [[Bibliothèque Nationale]], or National Library) in [[Paris]]. Three years later the first reproduction drawing of it was prepared for [[Lord Kingsborough]], by his [[Lombardy|Lombardian]] artist [[Agostino Aglio]]. The original drawing is now lost, but a copy survives among some of Kingsborough's unpublished [[galley proof|proof sheet]]s, held in collection at the [[Newberry Library]], [[Chicago]].&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/paris.html "The Paris Codex"], in Marhenke (2003), {{page needed|date=September 2012}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although occasionally referred to over the next quarter-century, its permanent rediscovery is attributed to the French orientalist [[Léon de Rosny]], who in 1859 recovered the codex from a basket of old papers sequestered in a chimney corner at the [[Bibliothèque Nationale]] where it had lain discarded and apparently forgotten.&lt;ref&gt;Coe (1992, p. 101), Sharer &amp; Traxler (2006, p. 127)&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, it is in very poor condition. It was found wrapped in a paper with the word ''Pérez'' written on it, possibly a reference to the Jose Pérez who had published two brief descriptions of the then-anonymous codex in 1859.&lt;ref name="Stuart 1992, p.20"&gt;Stuart (1992, p. 20)&lt;/ref&gt; De Rosny initially gave it the name ''Codex Peresianus'' ("Codex Pérez") after its identifying wrapper, but in due course the codex would be more generally known as the Paris Codex.&lt;ref name="Stuart 1992, p.20"/&gt; De Rosny published a facsimile edition of the codex in 1864.&lt;ref&gt;Coe (1992, p. 101)&lt;/ref&gt; It remains in the possession of the [[Bibliothèque Nationale]].

==Grolier Codex==
{{Main|Grolier Codex}}
[[File:Grolier Codex, page 6.jpg|thumb|right|Page 6 of the ''Grolier Codex'', depicting a death god with captive]]
While the three codices above were known to scholars since the 19th century, the Grolier Codex only surfaced in the 1970s. The codex, found in a cave and bought from a Mexican collector that donated it to the Mexican government in 1971,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/grolier.html|title=FAMSI – Maya Codices – The Grolier Codex|website=www.famsi.org|access-date=2019-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; is really a fragment of 10 pages. As of 2016 it is in Mexico City's Museo Nacional de Antropología,&lt;ref name="Smithsonian 2016" /&gt; not on display. Each page shows a hero or god, facing to the left. At the top of each page is a number, and down the left of each page is what appears to be a list of dates. The pages are much less detailed than in the other codices, and hardly provide any information that is not already in the Dresden Codex. Although its authenticity was initially disputed, various tests conducted in the early 21st century supported its authenticity and Mexico's [[Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia|National Institute of Anthropology and History]] judged it to be an authentic Pre-Columbian codex in 2018.&lt;ref name="Smithsonian 2016" /&gt;&lt;ref name=INAH&gt;{{cite press release|last=Boletín N° 299|year=2018|title=INAH ratifica al Códice Maya de México, antes llamado Grolier, como el manuscrito auténtico más antiguo de América|url=http://www.inah.gob.mx/attachments/article/7497/Boleti%CC%81n%20299.pdf|publisher=INAH|location=Mexico|access-date=2018-09-22|language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been dated to between 1021 and 1154 CE.&lt;ref name="Bonello"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Bonello |first1=Deborah |title=Mexican historians prove authenticity of looted ancient Mayan text |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2018/08/31/mexican-historians-prove-authenticity-looted-ancient-mayan-text/ |accessdate=8 February 2019 |work=The Telegraph |date=31 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other Maya codices ==
Given the rarity and importance of these books, rumors of finding new ones often develop interest. [[Archaeology|Archaeological]] excavations of Maya sites have turned up a number of rectangular lumps of plaster and paint flakes, most commonly in elite tombs. These lumps are the remains of codices where all the organic material has rotted away. A few of the more coherent of these lumps have been preserved, with the slim hope that some technique to be developed by future generations of archaeologists may be able to recover some information from these remains of ancient pages. The oldest Maya codices known have been found by archaeologists as mortuary offerings with burials in excavations in [[Uaxactun]], [[Guaytán]] in San Agustín Acasaguastlán, and Nebaj in [[Quiché Department|El Quiché]], [[Guatemala]], at [[Altun Ha]] in [[Belize]] and at [[Copán]] in [[Honduras]]. The six examples of Maya books discovered in excavations date to the Early Classic (Uaxactún and Altun Ha), Late Classic (Nebaj, Copán), and Early Postclassic (Guaytán) periods. Unfortunately, all of them have degraded into unopenable masses or collections of very small flakes and bits of the original texts. Thus it may never be possible to read them.&lt;ref&gt;Whiting 1998: 207–208&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forgeries==
Since the start of the 20th century, [[forgery|forgeries]] of varying quality have been produced. Two elaborate early 20th-century forged codices were in the collection of [[William Randolph Hearst]]. Although fake codices have seldom fooled serious scholars, the [[Grolier Codex]] may be an exception. Its paper seems to be ancient, and the influential Mayanist [[Michael D. Coe]] believed the artifact to be genuine, followed in this by Stephen Houston and Karl Taube (all three scholars stemming from Yale), but other eminent Mayanists such as [[J.E.S. Thompson]],&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 1975: 1–9; 1976: 64–75&lt;/ref&gt; [[Claude Baudez]],&lt;ref&gt;Baudez 2002: 70–79, 98–102&lt;/ref&gt; and Susan Milbrath&lt;ref&gt;Milbrath 2002: 50–83&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that its pictures and glyphs are falsifications. They pointed out a long series of inconsistencies and errors in the alleged codex, and drew attention to its art historical improbability and its uselessness for astrological and divinatory purposes.&lt;ref&gt;For a succinct account, see Kelker &amp; Bruhns 2010: 95–104&lt;/ref&gt; Although their arguments were never effectively countered, no scholarly unanimity has been reached. In September 2016 Coe and other researchers published findings supporting its authenticity,&lt;ref name="newitz ars technica"&gt;Annalee Newitz (12 September 2016). "[https://arstechnica.com/science/2016/09/confirmed-mysterious-ancient-maya-book-grolier-codex-is-genuine/ Confirmed: Mysterious ancient Maya book, Grolier Codex, is genuine: 900 year-old astronomy guide is oldest known book written in the Americas]." ''[http://arstechnica.co.uk/ Ars Technica]''. Accessed 12 September 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; but in an extensive rejoinder (August 2017), Bruce Love &lt;ref&gt;Love 2017{{page?|date=May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that the artefact's authenticity had not been established.

==See also==
*[[Aztec codices]]
*[[Mesoamerican Long Count calendar]]
*[[Mesoamerican literature]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|indent=}}&lt;!--BEGIN biblio format. If indent param. is used,  Pls use a colon (:) instead of asterisk (*) for bullet markers in the references list --&gt;
* {{cite journal |author=Baudez, Claude  |date=2002 |title=Venus y el Códice Grolier |journal=Arqueología Mexicana | volume=10 |issue=55 |pages=70–79, 98–102}}
* {{cite journal |author=Ciudad Ruiz, Andrés |author2=Alfonso Lacadena |date=1999 |title=El Códice Tro-Cortesiano de Madrid en el contexto de la tradición escrita Maya |trans-title=The Tro-Cortesianus Codex of Madrid in the context of the Maya writing tradition |journal=Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala, 1998 |editor=[[Juan Pedro Laporte|J.P. Laporte]] and H.L. Escobedo |pages=876–888 |publisher=Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |url=http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/67.98%20-%20Andres%20y%20Alfonso.pdf |accessdate=2012-07-23 |language=es |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110914100729/http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/67.98%20-%20Andres%20y%20Alfonso.pdf |archivedate=2011-09-14 }}
* {{cite book |author=Coe, Michael D. |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |date=1992 |title=Breaking the Maya Code |location=London |publisher=[[Thames &amp; Hudson]] |isbn=978-0-500-05061-3 |oclc=26605966 |url=https://archive.org/details/breakingmayacode00coem_0 }}
* {{cite book |author=Coe, Michael D.   |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |date=1999 |title=The Maya |edition=6th, fully revised and expanded |series=Ancient peoples and places series|location=London and New York |publisher=[[Thames &amp; Hudson]] |isbn=978-0-500-28066-9 |oclc=59432778}}
* {{cite web |author=FAMSI   |title=Maya Hieroglyphic Writing – The Ancient Maya Codices: The Madrid Codex |url=http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/madrid.html |accessdate=2012-07-24 |publisher=FAMSI (Foundation for the Advancement of Mesoamerican Studies)}}
* {{cite book |author=Kelker, Nancy L.   |author2=Karen O. Bruhns |date=2010 |title=Faking Ancient Mesoamerica |location=[[Walnut Creek, California]] |publisher=[[Left Coast Press]] |isbn=978-1-59874-150-6}}
* {{cite journal |author=Love, Bruce |title=Authenticity of the Grolier Codex remains in doubt |date=August 2017 |journal=Mexicon |volume=39 |issue=4 |pages=88–95}}
* {{cite web |author=Marhenke, Randa   |date=2003 |title=The Ancient Maya Codices |url=http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/marhenke.html |work=Maya Hieroglyphic Writing |publisher=Mesoweb |oclc=53231537 |accessdate=2008-08-16}}
* {{cite journal |author=Milbrath, Susan  |date=2002 |title=New Questions Concerning the Authenticity of the Grolier Codex |journal=Latin American Indian Literatures Journal |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=50–83}}
* {{cite book |author=Miller, Mary Ellen |authorlink=Mary Miller (art historian) |date=1999 |title=Maya Art and Architecture |location=London and New York |publisher=[[Thames &amp; Hudson]] |isbn=978-0-500-20327-9 |oclc=41659173 |url=https://archive.org/details/mayaartarchitect00mill }}
* {{cite journal |author=Noguez, Xavier   |author2=Manuel Hermann Lejarazu |author3=Merideth Paxton |author4= Henrique Vela  |title=Códices Mayas |trans-title=Maya codices |journal=Arqueología Mexicana: Códices Prehispánicos y Coloniales Tempranos – Catálogo |volume=Special Edition |issue=31 |publisher=Editorial Raíces |date=August 2009 |pages=10–23|language=es}}
* {{cite book |author=Sharer, Robert J. |authorlink=Robert Sharer |author2=Loa P. Traxler |date=2006 |title=The Ancient Maya |edition=6th (fully revised) |location=Stanford, CA |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]] |isbn=978-0-8047-4816-2 |oclc=28067148 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/ancientmaya0006shar }}
* {{cite book |author=Stuart, George E. |date=1992 |chapter=Quest for Decipherment:A Historical and Biographical Survey of Maya Hieroglyphic Decipherment |title=New Theories on the Ancient Maya |series=University Museum Monograph series, no. 77 |editor1=Elin C. Danien |editor2=[[Robert Sharer|Robert J. Sharer]] |location=Philadelphia |publisher=[[University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology|University Museum, University of Pennsylvania]] |pages=[https://archive.org/details/newtheoriesonanc0000unse/page/n20 1]–64 |isbn=978-0-924171-13-0 |oclc=25510312 |url=https://archive.org/details/newtheoriesonanc0000unse |url-access=limited }}
* {{cite journal |author=Thompson, J.E.S.  |date=1975 |title=The Codex Grolier |journal=Contributions of the University of California |volume=27 |issue=1 |pages=1–9}}
* {{cite journal |author=Thompson, J.E.S.  |date=1976 |title=The Grolier Codex |journal=The Book Collector |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=64–75}}
* {{cite book|author=Whiting, Thomas A. L.  |title=Maya|date=1998|chapter=The Maya Codices|publisher=Rizzoli|location=New York City|isbn=978-0847821297|editor1=Peter Schmidt |editor2=Mercedes de la Garza |editor3=Enrique Nalda }}
{{Refend}}&lt;!-- END biblio format style --&gt;

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.mathcs.duq.edu/~tobin/maya/ The Construction of the Codex In Classic- and Postclassic-Period Maya Civilization] Maya Codex and Paper Making
* [http://www.mayadiscovery.com/ing/history/codices.htm Maya Codices]
* [http://www.famsi.org/research/graz/dresdensis/thumbs_0.html Complete Dresden codex as JPG],
* [http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/dresden.html Complete Dresden codex as PDF]
* [http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/madrid.html Complete Madrid Codex as PDF]
* [http://www.famsi.org/mayawriting/codices/pdf/paris_love.pdf Complete Paris Codex as PDF (Moderate size PDF)]
* [http://www.mayavase.com/grol/grolier.html Complete Grolier Codex as JPG]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070613162647/http://www.authenticmaya.com/maya_writing.htm Codex and Maya Writing]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070606210812/http://www.authenticmaya.com/maya_astronomy.htm The Maya Codex and the Maya Astronomy]
* [http://mathdl.maa.org/convergence/1/?pa=content&amp;sa=viewDocument&amp;nodeId=1459 Dresden Codex and the Mayan Calendar]
* [http://jqjacobs.net/archaeology/maya_astronomy.html The Dresden Codex Lunar Series and Sidereal Astronomy]

{{Maya}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maya Codices}}
[[Category:Maya civilization|Codex]]
[[Category:Maya script]]
[[Category:Manuscripts]]
[[Category:Astrological texts]]
[[Category:Maya codices]]
[[Category:Book burnings]]</text>
      <sha1>3fduj3s9hhth3q7myoggjfx9dik4xyp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
