<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Crisis of the Third Century</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47942</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962301389</id>
      <parentid>962068162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-13T07:36:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]] (prndis)) #IABot (v2.0.1) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="46617" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|period when the Roman Empire nearly collapsed due to multiple major simultaneous crises, beginning with the assassination of Severus Alexander, during which there were ≥26 claimants to the throne}}
{{Expand German|Reichskrise des 3. Jahrhunderts|date=November 2015}}
{{more footnotes|date=November 2011}}
[[Image:Map of Ancient Rome 271 AD.svg|thumb|400px|The divided Empire in 271]]

The '''Crisis of the Third Century''', also known as '''Military Anarchy''' or the '''Imperial Crisis''' (235–284 AD), was a period in which the [[Roman Empire]] nearly collapsed under the combined pressures of [[barbarian]] [[invasion]]s and [[Human migration|migration]]s into the Roman territory, [[civil war]]s, [[bagaudae|peasant rebellions]], [[political instability]] (with multiple [[Roman usurper|usurpers]] competing for power), Roman reliance on (and growing influence of) barbarian mercenaries known as [[foederati]] and commanders nominally working for Rome (but increasingly independent), [[Plague of Cyprian|plague]], [[debasement]] of [[Roman currency|currency]], and [[economic collapse|economic depression]].

The crisis began with the [[assassination]] of Emperor [[Severus Alexander]] by his own troops in 235. This initiated a 50-year period during which there were at least 26 claimants to the title of emperor, mostly prominent [[Roman army]] [[general]]s, who assumed imperial power over all or part of the Empire. The same number of men became accepted by the [[Roman Senate]] as emperor during this period and so became legitimate emperors.

By 268, the empire had split into three competing states: the [[Gallic Empire]] (including the [[Roman province]]s of [[Gaul]], [[Roman Britain|Britannia]] and, briefly, [[Hispania]]); the [[Palmyrene Empire]] (including the eastern provinces of [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria Palaestina]] and [[Egypt (Roman province)|Aegyptus]]); and, between them, the Italian-centered independent Roman Empire proper. Later, [[Aurelian]] (270–275) reunited the empire. The crisis ended with the ascension of [[Diocletian]] and his implementation of reforms in 284.

The crisis resulted in such profound changes in the empire's institutions, society, economic life, and [[religion in Ancient Rome|religion]] that it is increasingly seen by most historians as defining the transition between the [[periodization|historical periods]] of [[classical antiquity]] and [[Late Antiquity|late antiquity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last =Brown|first= Peter Robert Lamont|title = The World of Late Antiquity|location= London|year= 1971|page= 22|publisher = Thames and Hudson|isbn = 978-0500320228}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{more citations needed section|date=October 2015}}
{{Crisis of the Third Century}}
{{Campaignbox Crisis of the Third Century}}
{{further|Alemanni#Conflicts with the Roman Empire}}

After the Roman Empire had been stabilized, once again, after the turmoil of the [[Year of the Five Emperors]] (193) in the reign of [[Septimius Severus]], the later [[Severan dynasty]] lost more and more control.

The army required larger and larger bribes to remain loyal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Potter |first1=David Stone |title=The Roman Empire at Bay, AD 180–395 Routledge history of the ancient world |date=2004 |publisher=Psychology Press |isbn=978-0415100588 |pages=85, 167}}&lt;/ref&gt; Septimius Severus raised the pay of legionaries, and gave substantial ''[[donativum]]'' to the troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/miscellanea/numismatics/severus.html |title=Septimius Severus:Legionary Denarius |publisher=Penelope.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2019-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth W. Harl, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=5yPDL0EykeAC&amp;lpg=PA216&amp;ots=VcHE96FRuM&amp;dq=septimius%20severus%20legion%20pay&amp;pg=PA216#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Coinage in the Roman Economy, 300 B.C. to A.D. 700, Part 700]'', p.216&lt;/ref&gt; The large and ongoing increase in military expenditure caused problems for all of his successors.&lt;ref name="spek"&gt;[[R.J. van der Spek]], Lukas De Blois (2008), [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PDV8AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA272 ''An Introduction to the Ancient World'', page 272] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170730064823/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PDV8AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA272# |date=2017-07-30 }}, [[Routledge]]&lt;/ref&gt; His son [[Caracalla]] raised the annual pay and lavished many benefits on the army in accordance with the advice of his father to keep their loyalty,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Severans: the Changed Roman Empire|last=Grant|first=Michael|publisher=Psychology Press|year=1996|isbn=|location=|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ancient Rome|url=https://archive.org/details/ancientrome00duns|url-access=limited|last=Dunstan|first=William, E.|publisher=Lanham: Rowman and Littlefield|year=2011|isbn=978-0-7425-6832-7|location=|page=[https://archive.org/details/ancientrome00duns/page/n439 405]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Romans, from village to empire|last1=Boatwright|first1=Mary Taliaferro|last2=Gargola|first2=Daniel J|last3=Talbert|first3=Richard J. A.|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2004|isbn=978-0-19-511875-9|location=|page=[https://archive.org/details/romansfromvillag00boat_0/page/413 413]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/romansfromvillag00boat_0/page/413}}&lt;/ref&gt; and considered dividing the Empire into eastern and western sectors with his brother [[Geta (emperor)|Geta]] to reduce the conflict in their co-rule.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite book|title=How Rome Fell: death of a superpower|last=Goldsworthy|first=Adrian|publisher=New Haven: Yale University Press|year=2009|isbn=978-0-300-16426-8|location=|page=[https://archive.org/details/howromefelldeath0000gold/page/70 70]|url=https://archive.org/details/howromefelldeath0000gold/page/70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation of the Roman Empire became dire in 235. Many [[Roman legion]]s had been defeated during a previous campaign against [[Germanic peoples]] raiding across the borders, while the emperor [[Severus Alexander]] had been focused primarily on the dangers from the [[Sassanid Empire]]. Leading his troops personally, the emperor resorted to diplomacy and accepting tribute to pacify the [[Germanic chieftain]]s quickly, rather than military conquest. According to [[Herodian]] this cost Severus Alexander the respect of his troops, who may have felt that more severe punishment was required for the tribes that had intruded on Rome's territory.&lt;ref&gt;" Herodian says "in their opinion, Alexander showed no honourable intention to pursue the war and preferred a life of ease, when he should have marched out to punish the Germans for their previous insolence" (Herodian vi.7.10).&lt;/ref&gt; The troops assassinated Severus Alexander and proclaimed the new emperor to be [[Maximinus Thrax]], commander of one of the legions present.

Maximinus was the first of the [[barracks emperor]]s – rulers who were elevated by the troops without having any political experience, a supporting faction, distinguished ancestors, or a hereditary claim to the imperial throne. As their rule rested on military might and generalship, they operated as [[warlord]]s reliant on the army to maintain power. Maximinus continued the campaigns in [[Germania]] but struggled to exert his authority over the whole empire. The Senate was displeased at having to accept a peasant as Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Southern, Pat ''The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine'', Routledge, 2001, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; This precipitated the chaotic [[Year of the Six Emperors]] during which all of the original claimants were killed: in 238 a revolt broke out in Africa led by Gordian I and Gordian II,&lt;ref&gt;Southern, Pat ''The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine'', Routledge, 2001, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; which was soon supported by the [[Roman Senate]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Joannes Zonaras]], Compendium of History [https://web.archive.org/web/20080521191250/http://www.ancientsites.com/aw/Post/1049415 extract: ''Zonaras: Alexander Severus to Diocletian: 222–284''] 12:16&lt;/ref&gt; but this was quickly defeated with Gordian II killed and Gordian I committing suicide. The Senate, fearing Imperial wrath,&lt;ref&gt;Southern, Pat ''The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine'', Routledge, 2001, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; raised two of their own as co-Emperors, Pupienus and Balbinus with Gordian I's grandson Gordian III as ''Caesar''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roman-emperors.org/maxthrax.htm Meckler, Michael L., ''Maximinus Thrax (235–238 A.D.)'', ''De Imperatoribus Romanis''] (1997)&lt;/ref&gt; Maximinus marched on Rome but was assassinated by his [[Legio II Parthica]], and subsequently Pupienus and Balbinus were murdered by the [[Praetorian Guard]].

In the following years, numerous generals of the Roman army fought each other for control of the empire and neglected their duties of defending it from invasion. There were frequent raids across the [[Limes Germanicus|Rhine and Danube frontier]] by foreign tribes, including the [[Carpians]], [[Goths]], [[Vandals]], and [[Alamanni]], and attacks from [[Sassanids]] in the east. [[Climate change (general concept)|Climate changes]] and a [[sea level rise]] disrupted the agriculture of what is now the [[Low Countries]], forcing tribes residing in the region to migrate into Roman lands.&lt;ref&gt;Southern, Pat (2011-02-17). "Third Century Crisis of the Roman Empire". BBC History, 17 February 2011. Retrieved from http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ancient/romans/thirdcenturycrisis_article_01.shtml.{{dead link|date=July 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Further disruption arose in 251, when the [[Plague of Cyprian]] (possibly [[smallpox]]) broke out. This plague caused large-scale death, severely weakening the empire.&lt;ref name="Zosimus"&gt;{{cite book | title=The New History, Book 1 | publisher=Green and Chaplin | accessdate=2016-04-22 | last=Zosimus | authorlink=Zosimus | orig-year=translation originally printed | others=(scanned and published online by Roger Pearse) | url=http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/zosimus01_book1.htm | year=1814 | location=London | pages=16, 21, 31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LOjqWL-u9VMC&amp;pg=PA62#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=The power of plagues by Irwin W. Sherman |accessdate=2019-05-10|isbn=9781555816483 |last1=Sherman |first1=Irwin W. |year=2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The situation was worsened in 260 when the emperor [[Valerian (emperor)|Valerian]] was captured in battle by the Sassanids (he later died in captivity).

Throughout the period, numerous [[usurper]]s claimed the imperial throne. In the absence of a strong central authority, the empire broke into three competing states. The [[Roman province]]s of [[Gaul]], [[Roman Britain|Britain]], and [[Hispania]] broke off to form the [[Gallic Empire]] in 260. The eastern provinces of [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]], [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], and [[Aegyptus (Roman province)|Aegyptus]] also became independent as the [[Palmyrene Empire]] in 267. The remaining provinces, centered on Italy, stayed under a single ruler but now faced threats on every side.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

An invasion of Macedonia and Greece by [[Goths]], who had been displaced from their lands on the [[Black Sea]], was defeated by emperor [[Claudius II|Claudius II Gothicus]] at the [[Battle of Naissus]] in 268 or 269. Historians see this victory as the turning point of the crisis. In its aftermath, a series of tough, energetic barracks emperors were able to reassert central authority. Further victories by Claudius Gothicus drove back the [[Alamanni]] and recovered Hispania from the Gallic Empire. He died of the plague in 270 and was succeeded by [[Aurelian]], who had commanded the cavalry at Naissus. Aurelian reigned (270–275) through the worst of the crisis, gradually restoring the empire. He defeated the Vandals, [[Visigoths]], Palmyrene Empire, and finally the remainder of the Gallic Empire. By late 274, the Roman Empire had been reunited into a single entity. However, Aurelian was assassinated in 275, sparking a further series of competing emperors with short reigns. The situation didn't stabilize until [[Diocletian]], himself a barracks emperor, took power in 284.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

More than a century would pass before Rome again lost military ascendancy over its external enemies. However, dozens of formerly thriving cities, especially in the Western Empire, had been ruined. Their populations dead or dispersed, these cities could not be rebuilt, due to the economic breakdown caused by constant warfare. The economy had been ruined by the breakdown in trading networks and the debasement of the currency. Major cities and towns, including Rome itself, had not needed fortifications for many centuries, but now surrounded themselves with thick [[Defensive wall|walls]].{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

Fundamental problems with the empire still remained. The right of imperial succession had never been clearly defined, which was a factor in the continuous civil wars as competing factions in the military, Senate, and other parties put forward their favored candidate for emperor. The sheer size of the empire, which had been an issue since the late [[Roman Republic]] three centuries earlier, continued to make it difficult for a single ruler to effectively counter multiple threats at the same time. These continuing problems were addressed by the radical reforms of Diocletian, who broke the cycle of usurpation. He began by sharing his rule with a colleague, then formally established the [[Tetrarchy]] of four co-emperors in 293.&lt;ref&gt;Kolb, Frank (1987). Diocletian und die Erste Tetrarchie. Improvisation oder Experiment in der Organisation monarchischer Herrschaft?, Berlin: de Gruyter. {{ISBN|978-3-11-010934-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historians regard this as the end of the crisis period, which had lasted 58 years.  However the trend of civil war would continue after the abdication of Diocletian in the [[Civil wars of the Tetrarchy]] (306-324) until the rise of [[Constantine the Great]] as sole Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;MacMullen, Ramsay. Constantine. New York: Dial Press, 1969. {{ISBN|0-7099-4685-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The empire survived [[Fall of the Western Roman Empire|until 476 in the West]] and [[Decline of the Byzantine Empire|until 1453 in the East]].

== Causes ==

=== The problem of succession and civil war ===
From the beginning of the [[Principate]] there were no clear rules for the imperial succession, largely because the empire maintained the facade of a republic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.armstrong.edu/history-journal/history-journal-res-publica-restituta-republic-and-princeps-in-the-early-ro|title=Res Publica Restituta? Republic and Princeps in the Early Roman Empire – Armstrong Undergraduate Journal of History|website=www.armstrong.edu|language=en|access-date=2018-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early Principate, the process for becoming an emperor relied on a combination of proclamation by the Senate, popular approval, and acceptance by the army, in particular the [[Praetorian Guard]]. A family connection to a previous emperor was beneficial, but it did not determine the issue in the way a formal system of [[hereditary succession]] would. From the [[Julio-Claudian dynasty]] onwards was sometimes tension between the Senate's preferred choice and the army. As the Senatorial class declined in political influence and more generals were recruited from the provinces this tension increased. 

Whenever the succession appeared uncertain, there was an incentive for any general with support of a sizable army to attempt to seize power, sparking civil war. The most recent example of this prior to the Crisis was the [[Year of the Five Emperors]] which resulted in the victory of [[Septimius Severus]]. After the overthrow of the Severan dynasty, for the rest of the 3rd Century, Rome was ruled by a series of generals, coming into power through frequent civil wars which devastated the empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://oyc.yale.edu/history/hist-210/lecture-2|title=The Crisis of the Third Century and the Diocletianic Reforms|last=Freedman|first=Paul|date=Fall 2011|website=Yale University|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171208024717/http://oyc.yale.edu/history/hist-210/lecture-2#|archivedate=2017-12-08|url-status=live|accessdate=2018-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Natural disasters ===
The first and most immediately disastrous of the natural disasters that the Roman Empire faced during the Third Century was the plague. The [[Antonine Plague]] that preceded the Crisis of the Third Century sapped manpower from Roman armies and proved disastrous for the Roman economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sabbatani|first=S.|last2=Fiorino|first2=S.|date=December 2009|url=|title=The Antonine Plague and the decline of the Roman Empire|journal=Le Infezioni in Medicina: Rivista Periodica di Eziologia, Epidemiologia, Diagnostica, Clinica e Terapia delle Patologie Infettive|volume=17|issue=4|pages= 261–275 |issn=1124-9390|pmid=20046111}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 249 AD to 262 AD, the [[Plague of Cyprian]] devastated the Roman Empire so much so that some cities, such as the [[Alexandria|city of Alexandria]], experienced a 62% decline in population. These plagues greatly hindered the Roman Empire's ability to ward off barbarian invasions but also factored into problems such as [[famine]], with many farms becoming abandoned and unproductive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/11/solving-the-mystery-of-an-ancient-roman-plague/543528/ |title=Solving the Mystery of an Ancient Roman Plague|last=Harper |first=Kyle|date=2017-11-01|work=The Atlantic|access-date=2018-10-20|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180121010741/https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/11/solving-the-mystery-of-an-ancient-roman-plague/543528/#|archive-date=2018-01-21|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A second and longer-term natural disaster that took place during the Third Century was the increased variability of weather. Drier summers meant less [[agricultural productivity]] and more extreme weather events led to agricultural instability. This could also have contributed to the increased barbarian pressure on Roman borders, as they too would have experienced the detrimental effects of climate change and sought to push inward to more productive regions of the Mediterranean.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wnet/need-to-know/environment/was-the-roman-empire-a-victim-of-climate-change/6724/|title=Was the Roman Empire a victim of climate change? |work= Need to Know|publisher= PBS|language=en-US|access-date=|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20181020224030/http://www.pbs.org/wnet/need-to-know/environment/was-the-roman-empire-a-victim-of-climate-change/6724/#|archive-date=2018-10-20|url-status=live|first = John A.|last = Light|date = 26 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Foreign invasions ===
Barbarian invasions came in the wake of civil war, plague, and famine.  Distress caused in part by the changing climate led various barbarian tribes to push into Roman territory.  Other tribes coalesced into more formidable entities (notably the [[Alemanni|Alamanni]] and [[Franks]]), or were pushed out of their former territories by more dangerous peoples such as the [[Sarmatians]] (the [[Huns]] did not appear west of the Volga for another century).  Eventually, the frontiers were stabilized by the [[Illyrian emperors|Illyrian Emperors]]. However, barbarian migrations into the empire continued in greater and greater numbers. Though these migrants were initially  closely monitored and assimilated, later tribes eventually entered the Roman Empire ''en masse'' with their weapons, giving only token recognition of Roman authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Roman Empire|last=Nigel.|first=Rodgers|date=2006|publisher=Lorenz Books|others=Dodge, Hazel.|isbn=978-0754816027|location=London|oclc=62177842}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The defensive battles that Rome had to endure on the Danube since the 230s, however, paled in comparison to the threat the empire faced in the East. There, [[Sassanid Persia]] represented a far greater danger to Rome than the isolated attacks of [[Germanic tribe]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Josef Wiesehöfer: Das Reich der Sāsāniden, in Klaus Peter Johne, Udo Hartmann, Thomas Gerhardt, Die Zeit der Soldatenkaiser: Krise und Transformation des Römischen Reiches im 3. Jahrhundert n. Chr. (235–284) 2008, p. 531ff.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sassanids had in 224 and 226 overthrown the Parthian Arsacids, and the Persian King Ardashir I, who also wanted to prove his legitimacy through military successes, had already penetrated into Roman territory at the time of Severus Alexander, probably taking the strategically important cities of Nisibis and Carrhae.&lt;ref&gt;Erich Kettenhofen: Die Eroberung von Nisibis und Karrhai durch die Sāsāniden in der Zeit Kaiser Maximins, 235/236 AD. In: Iranica Antiqua 30 (1995), pp. 159–177&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic impact==
{{more citations needed section|date=August 2017}}
[[File:Diocletian bust.png|thumb|200px|Emperor [[Diocletian]]. With his rise to power in 284, the Crisis of the Third Century ended and gave rise to the [[Tetrarchy]]]]
Internally, the empire faced [[hyperinflation]] caused by years of coinage [[devaluation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/how-currency-debasement-contributed-to-fall-of-rome-2016-2|title=This infographic shows how currency debasement contributed to the fall of Rome|work=Business Insider|access-date=2017-10-20|language=en|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171011080246/http://www.businessinsider.com/how-currency-debasement-contributed-to-fall-of-rome-2016-2#|archive-date=2017-10-11|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; This had started earlier under the [[Severan dynasty|Severan emperors]] who enlarged the army by one quarter,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Financial crises and renewal of empires|last1=Flichy|first1=Thomas|publisher=Lulu.com|year=|isbn=9781291097337|location=|pages=|accessdate=}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}} and doubled the base pay of legionaries. As each of the short-lived emperors took power, they needed ways to raise money quickly to pay the military's "accession bonus" and the easiest way to do so was by inflating the coinage severely, a process made possible by debasing the coinage with bronze and copper.

This resulted in runaway rises in prices, and by the time Diocletian came to power, the old coinage of the Roman Empire had nearly collapsed. Some taxes were collected in kind and values often were notional, in [[bullion]] or [[bronze]] coinage. [[Real versus nominal value|Real values]] continued to be figured in gold coinage, but the silver coin, the denarius, used for 300 years, was gone (1 pound of gold = 40 gold [[aureus|aurei]] = 1,000 [[denarius|denarii]] = 4,000 [[sestertius|sestertii]]).{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}} This currency had almost no value by the end of the third century, and trade was carried out without retail coinage.

=== Breakdown of internal trade network ===
One of the most profound and lasting effects of the Crisis of the Third Century was the disruption of Rome's extensive internal trade network. Ever since the [[Pax Romana]], starting with [[Augustus]], the empire's economy had depended in large part on trade between Mediterranean ports and across the extensive road systems to the Empire's interior. Merchants could travel from one end of the empire to the other in relative safety within a few weeks, moving agricultural goods produced in the provinces to the cities, and manufactured goods produced by the great cities of the East to the more rural provinces.

Large estates produced cash crops for export and used the resulting revenues to import food and urban manufactured goods. This resulted in a great deal of economic interdependence among the empire's inhabitants. The historian Henry St. Lawrence Beaufort Moss describes the situation as it stood before the crisis:

{{quote |Along these roads passed an ever-increasing traffic, not only of troops and officials but of traders, merchandise and even tourists. An interchange of goods between the various provinces rapidly developed, which soon reached a scale unprecedented in the previous history and not repeated until a few centuries ago. Metals mined in the uplands of Western Europe, hides, fleeces, and livestock from the pastoral districts of Britain, Spain, and the shores of the Black Sea, wine and oil from Provence and Aquitaine, timber, pitch and wax from South Russia and northern Anatolia, [[dried fruit]]s from Syria, marble from the Aegean coasts, and – most important of all – grain from the wheat-growing districts of North Africa, Egypt, and the Danube Valley for the needs of the great cities; all these commodities, under the influence of a highly organized system of transport and marketing, moved freely from one corner of the Empire to the other.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/birthofthemiddle027632mbp |title=The Birth of the Middle Ages 395–814 |last=Henry St. Lawrence Beaufort Moss |date=1935 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=London |pages=[https://archive.org/details/birthofthemiddle027632mbp/page/n140 1]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

With the onset of the Crisis of the Third Century, however, this vast internal trade network broke down. The widespread civil unrest made it no longer safe for merchants to travel as they once had, and the financial crisis that struck made exchange very difficult with the debased currency. This produced profound changes that, in many ways, foreshadowed the very decentralized economic character of the coming [[Middle Ages]].

Large landowners, no longer able to successfully export their crops over long distances, began producing food for subsistence and local barter. Rather than import manufactured goods from the empire's great urban areas, they began to manufacture many goods locally, often on their own estates, thus beginning the self-sufficient "house economy" that would become commonplace in later centuries, reaching its final form in the [[manorialism]] of the Middle Ages. The common, free people of the Roman cities, meanwhile, began to move out into the countryside in search of food and better protection.

Made desperate by economic necessity, many of these former city dwellers, as well as many small farmers, were forced to give up hard-earned basic civil rights in order to receive protection from large land-holders. In doing so, they became a half-free class of Roman citizen known as ''[[Colonus (person)|coloni]]''. They were tied to the land, and in later Imperial law, their status was made hereditary. This provided an early model for [[serfdom]], the origins of medieval [[feudal society]] and of the medieval peasantry.

However, although the burdens on the population increased, especially the lower strata of the population, this can not be generalized to the whole empire, especially since the living conditions were not uniform. Although the structural integrity of the economy suffered from the military conflicts of that time and the inflationary episode of the 270s, it did not collapse, especially because of the complex regional differences. Recent research has shown that there were regions that prospered even further, such as Egypt, Africa and Hispania. But even for Asia Minor, which was directly affected by attacks, no general decline can be observed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Deleto paene imperio Romano: Transformationsprozesse des Römischen Reiches im 3. Jahrhundert und ihre Rezeption in der Neuzeit |last=Ruffing |first=Kai |date=2006 |publisher=Steiner |isbn=978-3-515-08941-8 |location=Stuttgart |page=223 |oclc=180946164}}&lt;/ref&gt; While commerce and the economy flourished in several regions, with several provinces not affected by hostilities, other provinces experienced some serious problems, as evidenced by personal [[hoards]] in the northwestern provinces of the empire. However, there can be no talk of a general economic crisis throughout the whole of Empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Rome and its Empire, AD 193–284 |last=Hekster, Olivier. |date=2008 |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |isbn=978-0-7486-2992-3 |location=Edinburgh |page=31 |oclc=271165910}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Increased localism ===
All the Barracks Emperors based their power on the military and on the soldiers of the field armies, not on the Praetorians in Rome. Thus, Rome lost its role as the political center of the empire during the third century, although it remained ideologically important. In order to legitimize and secure their rule, the emperors of the third century needed above all military successes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Johne |first1=Klaus-Peter |last2=Hartmann |first2=Udo |last3=Gerhardt |first3=Thomas |title=Die Zeit der Soldatenkaiser: Krise und Transformation des Römischen Reiches im 3. Jahrhundert n. Chr. (235–284) |date=2008 |publisher=Akademie Verlag |location=Rome |isbn=978-3050045290 |page=1026}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even the Roman cities began to change in character. The large cities of classical antiquity slowly gave way to the smaller, [[walled city|walled cities]] that became common in the Middle Ages. These changes were not restricted to the third century, but took place slowly over a long period, and were punctuated with many temporary reversals. In spite of extensive reforms by later emperors, however, the Roman trade network was never able to fully recover to what it had been during the [[Pax Romana]] (27 BC-AD 180). This economic decline was far more noticeable and important in the western part of the empire, which was also invaded by barbarian tribes several times during the century. Hence, the balance of power clearly shifted eastward during this period, as evidenced by the choice of Diocletian to rule from [[Nicomedia]] in [[Asia Minor]], putting his second in command, [[Maximian]], in [[Milan]]. This would have a considerable impact on the later development of the empire with a richer, more stable [[Eastern Roman Empire|eastern empire]] surviving the [[Fall of the Western Roman Empire|end of Roman rule in the west]].

While imperial revenues fell, imperial expenses rose sharply. More soldiers, greater proportions of cavalry, and the ruinous expense of walling in cities all added to the toll. Goods and services previously paid for by the government were now demanded in addition to monetary taxes. The steady exodus of both rich and poor from the cities and now-unprofitable professions forced [[Diocletian]] to use compulsion; most trades were made hereditary, and workers could not legally leave their jobs or travel elsewhere to seek better-paying ones.

The decline in commerce between the imperial provinces put them on a path toward increased self-sufficiency. Large landowners, who had become more self-sufficient, became less mindful of Rome's central authority, particularly in the Western Empire, and were downright hostile toward its tax collectors. The measure of wealth at this time began to have less to do with wielding urban civil authority and more to do with controlling large agricultural estates in rural regions since this guaranteed access to the only economic resource of real value — agricultural land and the crops it produced. The common people of the empire lost economic and political status to the land-holding nobility, and the commercial middle classes waned along with their trade-derived livelihoods. The Crisis of the Third Century thus marked the beginning of a long gradual process that would transform the ancient world of Classical antiquity into the medieval one of the [[Early Middle Ages]].

== Emperors ==
{{main|List of Roman emperors#Crisis of the Third Century (235–285)}}

Several emperors who rose to power through acclamation of their troops attempted to create stability by appointing their descendants as ''[[Caesar (title)|Caesar]]'', resulting in several brief dynasties. These generally failed to maintain any form of coherence beyond one generation, although there were exceptions.

=== Gordian dynasty ===
{{main|Gordian dynasty}}
{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Gordian I Musei Capitolini MC475.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Gordian I]]''' &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS ANTONIVS '''GORDIANVS''' SEMPRONIANVS AFRICANVS AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 159 AD, [[Phrygia]]?
|Proclaimed emperor, whilst Pro-consul in Africa, during a revolt against [[Maximinus I|Maximinus Thrax]]. Ruled jointly with his son [[Gordian II]], and in opposition to Maximinus. Technically a usurper, but retrospectively legitimized by the accession of [[Gordian III]]
|March 22, 238 AD – April 12, 238 AD
|April 238 AD &lt;br&gt; Committed suicide upon hearing of the death of [[Gordian II]]
|21 days
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:GordianusIIsest.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Gordian II]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS ANTONIVS '''GORDIANVS''' SEMPRONIANVS ROMANVS AFRICANVS AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 192 AD, ?
|Proclaimed emperor, alongside father [[Gordian I]], in opposition to [[Maximinus I|Maximinus]] by act of the Senate
|March 22, 238 AD – April 12, 238 AD
|April 238 AD &lt;br&gt; Killed during the [[Battle of Carthage (238)|Battle of Carthage]], fighting a pro-[[Maximinus I|Maximinus]] army
|21 days
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Pupienus Musei Capitolini MC477.jpg|100px]]
|[[Pupienus]] (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS CLODIVS '''PVPIENVS MAXIMVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 178 AD, ?
|Proclaimed joint emperor with [[Balbinus]] by the [[Roman Senate|Senate]] in opposition to [[Maximinus I|Maximinus]]; later co-emperor with Balbinus
|April 22, 238 AD – July 29, 238 AD
|July 29, 238 AD &lt;br&gt; Assassinated by the [[Praetorian Guard]]
|3 months and 7 days
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Balbinus Hermitage.jpg|100px]]
|[[Balbinus]] (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR DECIMVS CAELIVS CALVINVS '''BALBINVS''' PIVS AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|?
|Proclaimed joint emperor with [[Pupienus]] by the [[Roman Senate|Senate]] after death of [[Gordian I]] and [[Gordian II|II]], in opposition to [[Maximinus I|Maximinus]]; later co-emperor with Pupienus and [[Gordian III]]
|April 22, 238 AD – July 29, 238 AD
|July 29, 238 AD &lt;br&gt; Assassinated by [[Praetorian Guard]]
|3 months and 7 days
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Bust Gordianus III Louvre Ma1063.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Gordian III]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS ANTONIVS '''GORDIANVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|January 20, 225 AD, [[Rome]]
|Proclaimed emperor by supporters of [[Gordian I]] and [[Gordian II|II]], then by the [[Roman Senate|Senate]]; joint emperor with [[Pupienus]] and [[Balbinus]] until July 238 AD. Grandson of Gordian I
|April 22, 238 AD – February 11, 244 AD
|February 11, 244 AD &lt;br&gt; Unknown; possibly murdered on orders of [[Philip the Arab|Philip I]]
|5 years, 9 months and 20 days
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Bust of emperor Philippus Arabus - Hermitage Museum.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Philip the Arab]]''' (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS IVLIVS '''PHILIPPVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;''with'' '''[[Philippus II|Philip II]]'''
&lt;small&gt;MARCVS IVLIVS SEVERVS '''PHILLIPVS'''&lt;/small&gt; &lt;small&gt;AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 204 AD, [[Shahba]], [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]]
|[[Praetorian Prefect]] to Gordian III, took power after his death; made his son Philip II co-emperor in summer 247 AD
|February 244 AD – September/October 249 AD
|September/October 249 AD (aged 45)&lt;br&gt; Killed in the [[Battle of Verona (249)|Battle of Verona]] by Decius
|5 years
|}

=== Decian dynasty ===

{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Emperor Traianus Decius (Mary Harrsch).jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Trajan Decius]]''' &lt;br&gt;  &lt;small&gt;CAESAR GAIVS MESSIVS QVINTVS '''TRAIANVS DECIVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;''with'' '''[[Herennius Etruscus]]'''
|c. 201 AD, [[Budalia]], [[Pannonia Inferior]]
|Governor under [[Philip the Arab|Philip I]]; proclaimed emperor by Danubian legions then defeating &amp; killing Philip in the [[Battle of Verona (249)|Battle of Verona]]; made his son [[Herennius Etruscus]] co-emperor in early 251 AD
|September/ October 249 AD – June 251 AD
|June 251 AD &lt;br&gt; Both killed in the [[Battle of Abrittus]] fighting against the [[Goths]]
|2 years
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Sestertius Hostilian-s2771.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Hostilian]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR CAIVS VALENS '''HOSTILIANVS''' MESSIVS QVINTVS AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|[[Sirmium]]
|Son of [[Trajan Decius]], accepted as heir by the [[Roman Senate|Senate]]
|June 251 AD – late 251 AD
|September/October 251 AD &lt;br&gt; Natural causes ([[Plague of Cyprian|plague]])
|4–5 months
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Бюст_рим.jpg|center|frameless|128x128px]]
|'''[[Trebonianus Gallus]]''' (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR GAIVS VIBIVS '''TREBONIANVS GALLVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;''with'' '''[[Volusianus]]'''
&lt;small&gt;GAIVS VIBIVS '''VOLVSIANVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|206 AD, [[Roman Italy|Italia]]
|Governor of [[Moesia Superior]], proclaimed emperor by Danubian legions after Decius's death (and in opposition to Hostilian); made his son Volusianus co-emperor in late 251 AD.
|June 251 AD – August 253 AD
|August 253 AD (aged 47)&lt;br&gt; Assassinated by their own troops, in favor of [[Aemilian]]
|2 years
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Aemilian1.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Aemilian]]''' (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AEMILIVS '''AEMILIANVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 207 or 213 AD [[Africa Province|Africa]]
|Governor of [[Moesia Superior]], proclaimed emperor by Danubian legions after defeating the [[Goths]]; accepted as emperor after death of Gallus
|August 253 AD – October 253 AD
|September/October 253 AD (aged 40 or 46)&lt;br&gt; Assassinated by his own troops, in favor of Valerian
|2 months
|}

=== Valerian dynasty ===

{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Aureus Valerian-RIC 0034-transparent.png|100px]]
|'''[[Valerian (emperor)|Valerian]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR PVBLIVS LICINIVS '''VALERIANVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt;
|c. 195 AD
|Governor of [[Noricum]] and [[Raetia]], proclaimed emperor by Rhine legions after death of [[Trebonianus Gallus|Gallus]]; accepted as emperor after death of [[Aemilian]]
|October 253 AD – 260 AD
|After 260 AD &lt;br&gt; Captured in [[Battle of Edessa]] against [[Sassanid Empire|Persians]], died in captivity
|7 years
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Gallienus.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Gallienus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR PVBLIVS LICINIVS EGNATIVS '''GALLIENVS''' AVGVSTVS&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;''with'' '''[[Saloninus]]'''
|218 AD
|Son of [[Valerian (emperor)|Valerian]], made co-emperor in 253 AD; his son [[Saloninus]] is very briefly co-emperor in c. July 260 before assassination by [[Postumus]]
|October 253 AD – September 268 AD
|September 268 AD &lt;br&gt; Murdered at [[Aquileia]] by his own commanders
|15 years
|}

=== [[Gordian dynasty]] continued ? ===

{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Santa Giulia 4.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Claudius II]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS '''CLAVDIVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|May 10, 210 AD, [[Sirmium]]
|Victorious general at [[Battle of Naissus]], seized power after Gallienus's death According to [[Epitome de Caesaribus]]  He was a bastard son of [[Gordian II]]
|September 268 AD – January 270 AD
|January 270 AD (aged 60)&lt;br&gt; Natural causes ([[Plague of Cyprian|plague]])
|1 year, 4 months
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Aureus Quintillus (obverse).jpg|center|frameless|100x100px]]
|'''[[Quintillus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS CLAVDIVS '''QVINTILLVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|c.210 AD, [[Sirmium]]
|Brother of Claudius II, seized power after his death
|January 270 AD – September(?) 270 AD
|270 AD (aged around 60)&lt;br&gt; Unclear; possibly suicide or murder
|Unknown
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:AURELIANUS_RIC_V_15_(Rome)_and_182_(Siscia)-765588_(obverse).jpg|100x100px|center|frameless]]
|'''[[Aurelian]]''' (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR LVCIVS DOMITIVS '''AVRELIANVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|September 9, 214 AD/215 AD, [[Sirmium]]
|Proclaimed emperor by Danubian legions after Claudius II's death, in opposition to Quintillus
|September(?) 270 AD –  September 275 AD
|September 275 AD (aged 60–61)&lt;br&gt; Assassinated by [[Praetorian Guard]]
|5 years
|}

=== Tacitus ===

{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:EmpereurTacite.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Tacitus (emperor)|Tacitus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS CLAVDIVS '''TACITVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|c. 200, [[Terni|Interamna Nahars]], [[Roman Italy|Italia]]
|Elected by the Senate to replace Aurelian, after a short [[interregnum]]
|September 25, 275 AD – June 276 AD
|June 276 AD (aged 76)&lt;br&gt; Natural causes (possibly assassinated)
|9 months
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Aureus_Florianus_Ticinum_(obverse).jpg|center|frameless|100x100px]]
|'''[[Florianus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS ANNIVS '''FLORIANVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|?
|Brother of Tacitus, elected by the army in the west to replace him
|June 276 AD – September? 276 AD
|September? 276 AD (aged ?)&lt;br&gt; Assassinated by his own troops, in favor of Probus
|3 months
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Probus Musei Capitolini MC493.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Probus (emperor)|Probus]]''' (non-dynastic) &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS '''PROBVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|232 AD, [[Sirmium]]
|Governor of the eastern provinces, proclaimed emperor by Danubian legions in opposition to [[Marcus Annius Florianus|Florian]]
|September? 276 AD – September/ October 282 AD
|September/ October 282 AD (aged 50)&lt;br&gt; Assassinated by his own troops, in favor of [[Carus]]
|6 years
|}

=== Caran dynasty ===

{| class="wikitable" style="width:1200px;"
|-
! style="width:100px;"|Portrait
! style="width:200px;"|Name
! style="width:100px;"|Birth
! style="width:300px;"|Succession
! style="width:150px;"|Reign
! style="width:200px;"|Death
! style="width:150px;"|Time in office
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[File:Antoninianus of Carus.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Carus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS '''CARVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|c. 230 AD, [[Narbo]], [[Gallia Narbonensis]]
|[[Praetorian Prefect]] to [[Marcus Aurelius Probus|Probus]]; seized power either before or after Probus was murdered; made his son [[Carinus]] co-emperor in early 283 AD
|September/ October 282 AD – late July/ early August 283 AD
|Late July/early August 283 AD &lt;br&gt; Natural causes? (Possibly killed by lightning)
|10–11 months
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:NumerianusAntoninianus.jpg|100px]]
|'''[[Numerian]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS NVMERIVS '''NVMERIANVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|?
|Son of [[Carus]], succeeded him jointly with his brother [[Carinus]]
|Late July/early August 283 AD – 284 AD?
|284 AD &lt;br&gt; Unclear; possibly assassinated
|1 year
|-
| style="text-align:center;"|[[Image:Montemartini - Carino 1030439.JPG|100px]]
|'''[[Carinus]]''' &lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;CAESAR MARCVS AVRELIVS '''CARINVS''' AVGVSTVS &lt;/small&gt;
|?
|Son of [[Carus]], ruled shortly with him and then with his brother [[Numerian]]
|Early 283 AD – 285 AD
|285 AD &lt;br&gt; Died in battle against [[Diocletian]]?
|2 years
|}

==See also==
* [[Bagaudae]]
* [[Sengoku period]] – a similar period in Japanese history
* [[Warring States period]] and [[Three Kingdoms period]] – similar periods in Chinese history

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Allen|first=Larry|title=The Encyclopedia of Money|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediamone00alle|url-access=limited|year=2009|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|edition=2nd|place=[[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara, CA]]|pages=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediamone00alle/page/n364 346]–348|isbn=978-1598842517}}
* {{cite book|last=Davies|first=Glyn|title=A History of Money: From Ancient Times to the Present Day|year=1997|orig-year=1994|publisher=[[University of Wales Press]]|edition=Reprint|place=[[Cardiff|Cardiff, Wales]]|pages=95–99|isbn=978-0708313510}}
* Olivier Hekster, ''Rome and its Empire, AD 193–284'' (Edinburgh 2008) {{ISBN|978 0 7486 2303 7}}
* Klaus-Peter Johne (ed.), ''Die Zeit der Soldatenkaiser'' (Akademie Verlag, Berlin 2008).
* Alaric Watson, ''Aurelian and the Third Century'' (Taylor &amp; Francis, 2004) {{ISBN|0-415-30187-4}}
* John F. White, ''Restorer of the World: The Roman Emperor Aurelian'' (Spellmount, 2004) {{ISBN|1-86227-250-6}}
* H. St. L. B. Moss, [https://archive.org/details/birthofthemiddle027632mbp ''The Birth of the Middle Ages'']  (Clarendon Press, 1935, reprint Oxford University Press, January 2000) {{ISBN|0-19-500260-1}}
* [[Ferdinand Lot]], ''End of the Ancient World and the Beginnings of the Middle Ages'' (Harper Torchbooks Printing, New York, 1961.  First English printing by Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1931).

==Further reading==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050526035139/http://www.accla.org/actaaccla/kramer.html  Crisis of The Third Century], Hugh Kramer.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060819181741/http://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/firsteuro/imgs/map15.html Map], University of Calgary.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060717182740/http://isthmia.osu.edu/teg/50501/4.htm The Crisis of The Third Century], OSU.

{{Ancient Roman Wars}}
{{History of Europe}}
{{Financial crises}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Crisis of the Third Century| ]]
[[Category:3rd century in the Roman Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>700qkh5pi69aughn2mtit90tsqel0ek</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
