<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetics in learning and memory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35812169</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962383828</id>
      <parentid>961168045</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-13T18:46:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bernstein0275</username>
        <id>6952358</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Demethylation and Memory */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="46539" xml:space="preserve">While the cellular and molecular mechanisms of [[learning]] and [[memory]] have long been a central focus of [[neuroscience]], it is only in recent years that attention has turned to the epigenetic mechanisms behind the dynamic changes in [[gene transcription]] responsible for [[Encoding (memory)|memory formation]] and maintenance. [[Epigenetic gene regulation]] often involves the physical marking (chemical modification) of [[DNA]] or associated proteins to cause or allow long-lasting changes in gene activity. Epigenetic mechanisms such as [[DNA methylation]] and [[histone]] modifications ([[methylation]], [[acetylation]], and [[deacetylation]]) have been shown to play an important role in learning and memory.&lt;ref name="Rumbaugh"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Rumbaugh G, Miller CA | title = Alzheimer's Disease and Frontotemporal Dementia | chapter = Epigenetic changes in the brain: measuring global histone modifications | series = Methods in Molecular Biology | volume = 670 | pages = 263–74 | year = 2011 | pmid = 20967596 | pmc = 3235043 | doi = 10.1007/978-1-60761-744-0_18 | isbn = 978-1-60761-743-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==DNA Methylation==
[[DNA methylation]] involves the addition of a methyl group to a 5' [[cytosine]] residue. This usually occurs at cytosines that form part of a cytosine-guanine dinucleotide ([[CpG sites]]). Methylation can lead to activation or repression of [[gene transcription]] and is mediated through the activity of [[DNA methyltransferase]]s (DNMTs). [[DNMT3A]] and [[DNMT3B]] regulate ''de novo'' methylation of CpG sites, while [[DNMT1]] maintains established methylation patterns.&lt;ref name="bali"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bali P, Im HI, Kenny PJ | title = Methylation, memory and addiction | journal = Epigenetics | volume = 6 | issue = 6 | pages = 671–4 | date = June 2011 | pmid = 21586900 | pmc = 3142366 | doi = 10.4161/epi.6.6.15905 }}&lt;/ref&gt; S-adenosyl methionine acts as the methyl donor.&lt;ref name="lubin"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lubin FD | title = Epigenetic Mechanisms: Critical Contributors to Long-Term Memory Formation | journal = The Neuroscientist | volume = 71 | issue = 6 | pages = 616–632 | year = 2011 | pmid = 21460188 | doi = 10.1177/1073858410386967 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current hypothesis for how DNA methylation contributes to the storage of memories is that dynamic DNA methylation changes occur temporally to activate transcription of genes that encode for proteins whose role is to stabilize memory.

===DNMTs and Memory===
Miller and Sweatt demonstrated that rats trained in a contextual [[fear conditioning]] paradigm had elevated levels of [[mRNA]] for [[DNMT3a]] and [[DNMT3b]] in the [[hippocampus]].&lt;ref name="miller"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miller CA, Sweatt JD | title = Covalent modification of DNA regulates memory formation | journal = Neuron | volume = 53 | issue = 6 | pages = 857–69 | date = March 2007 | pmid = 17359920 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2007.02.022 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fear conditioning is an associative memory task where a context, like a room, is paired with an [[aversive stimulus]], like a foot shock; animals who have learned the association show higher levels of freezing behavior when exposed to the context even in the absence of the aversive stimulation. However, when rats were treated with the [[DNMT inhibitor]]s [[zebularine]] or [[5-aza-2′-deoxycytidine]] immediately after fear-conditioning, they demonstrated reduced learning (freezing behavior). When treated rats were re-trained 24 hours later, they performed as well as non-treated rats. Furthermore, it was shown that when these DNMT inhibitors were given 6 hours after training, and the rats were tested 24 hours later, the rats displayed normal fear memory, indicating that DNMTs are involved specifically in memory consolidation.&lt;ref name="miller"/&gt; These findings reveal the importance of dynamic changes in methylation status in memory formation.

Feng et al. created double conditional [[knock out mice|knock out]] (DKO) mice for the genes DNMT3a and DNMT1. These mice were shown to have significantly weakened [[long-term potentiation]] (LTP) and much more easily stimulated [[long-term depression]] (LTD) in the hippocampus. When tested in the [[Morris water navigation task]], which is used to study hippocampus-dependent [[spatial memory]], the DNMT3a/DNMT1 DKO mice took longer to find the platform than control mice. Single knock-out mice (SKO) for either DNMT3a or DNMT1 performed normally.&lt;ref name="feng"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Feng J, Zhou Y, Campbell SL, Le T, Li E, Sweatt JD, Silva AJ, Fan G | display-authors = 6 | title = Dnmt1 and Dnmt3a maintain DNA methylation and regulate synaptic function in adult forebrain neurons | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 13 | issue = 4 | pages = 423–30 | date = April 2010 | pmid = 20228804 | pmc = 3060772 | doi = 10.1038/nn.2514 }}&lt;/ref&gt; DKO mice were also unable to [[Memory consolidation|consolidate memory]] after fear-conditioning. Since SKO mice did not exhibit the same learning and memory defects as the DKO mice, it was concluded that DNMT3a and DNMT1 play redundant roles in regulating learning and memory.

When DNMTs are inhibited in the [[prefrontal cortex]], recall of existing memories is impaired, but not the formation of new ones. This indicates that DNA methylation may be circuit-specific when it comes to regulating the formation and maintenance of memories.&lt;ref name="SWEATT"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Day JJ, Sweatt JD | title = Epigenetic mechanisms in cognition | journal = Neuron | volume = 70 | issue = 5 | pages = 813–29 | date = June 2011 | pmid = 21658577 | pmc = 3118503 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2011.05.019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===DNA Methylation Targets===
The memory suppressor gene, [[protein phosphatase 1]] (''PP1''), was shown to have increased [[CpG island]] methylation after contextual-fear conditioning. This corresponded to decreased levels of PP1 mRNA in the hippocampus of the trained rats. When DNMTs were inhibited, increased methylation at the ''PP1'' gene was no longer observed.&lt;ref name="miller"/&gt; These data suggest that during memory consolidation in associative learning tasks, CpG methylation is used to inhibit the expression of ''PP1'', a gene that negatively inhibits memory formation.

===Demethylation and Memory===
While DNA methylation is necessary to inhibit genes involved in [[memory suppression]], [[DNA demethylation]] is important in activating genes whose expression is positively correlated with memory formation. Sweatt and Miller also showed that the gene ''[[reelin]]'', which is involved in long term potentiation induction, had a reduced methylation profile and increased reelin mRNA in fear-conditioned versus control rats. [[Brain-derived neurotrophic factor]] (''BDNF''), another important gene in neural plasticity, has also been shown to have reduced methylation and increased transcription in animals that have undergone learning.&lt;ref name="day"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Day JJ, Sweatt JD | title = DNA methylation and memory formation | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 13 | issue = 11 | pages = 1319–23 | date = November 2010 | pmid = 20975755 | pmc = 3130618 | doi = 10.1038/nn.2666 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While these studies have been linked to the [[hippocampus]], recent evidence has also shown increased demethylation of ''reelin'' and ''BDNF'' in the [[medial prefrontal cortex]] (mPFC), an area involved in cognition and emotion.&lt;ref name="sui"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sui L, Wang Y, Ju LH, Chen M | title = Epigenetic regulation of reelin and brain-derived neurotrophic factor genes in long-term potentiation in rat medial prefrontal cortex | journal = Neurobiology of Learning and Memory | volume = 97 | issue = 4 | pages = 425–40 | date = May 2012 | pmid = 22469747 | doi = 10.1016/j.nlm.2012.03.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mechanism behind this experience-dependent demethylation response was previously not fully understood, with some evidence showing that DNMTs may be involved in demethylation.&lt;ref name="day"/&gt; It was also suggested that members of the DNA damage repair [[GADD45]] family may contribute to this demethylation process.&lt;ref name="bali"/&gt;&lt;ref name="lubin"/&gt;  However, more recently, the pathways illustrated in the Figure below, titled "Demethylation of 5-Methylcytosine (5mC) in neuron DNA," especially the [[Tet enzymes|
TET]] dependent pathway, have been confirmed as pathways of DNA demethylation.&lt;ref name=Bayraktar&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bayraktar G, Kreutz MR | title = The Role of Activity-Dependent DNA Demethylation in the Adult Brain and in Neurological Disorders | journal = Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience | volume = 11 | issue =  | pages = 169 | date = 2018 | pmid = 29875631 | pmc = 5975432 | doi = 10.3389/fnmol.2018.00169 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  A role for GADD45 has also recently been indicated, since GADD45 physically interacts with [[thymine-DNA glycosylase]] (TDG) and GADD45 may promote the activity of TDG in its role(s) during conversion of 5mC to cytosine.&lt;ref name=Bayraktar /&gt;

===Methyl-Binding Domain Proteins (MBDs)===
Mice that have genetic disruptions for [[CpG binding protein 2]] (MeCP2) have been shown to have significant problems in [[hippocampus-dependent memory]] and have impaired hippocampal LTP.&lt;ref name="bali"/&gt;

===Methylation and Learning and Memory Disorders===
Changes in expression of genes associated with [[post-traumatic stress disorder]] (PTSD), which is characterized by an impaired extinction of traumatic memory, may be mediated by DNA methylation.&lt;ref name="lockett"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lockett GA, Wilkes F, Maleszka R | title = Brain plasticity, memory and neurological disorders: an epigenetic perspective | journal = NeuroReport | volume = 21 | issue = 14 | pages = 909–13 | date = October 2010 | pmid = 20717061 | doi = 10.1097/wnr.0b013e32833e9288 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[schizophrenic]]s, it has been shown that ''[[reelin]]'' is down-regulated through increased DNA methylation at [[Promoter (biology)|promoter]] regions in [[GABAergic]] interneurons. [[DNMT1]] has also been shown to be upregulated in these cells.&lt;ref name="lockett"/&gt;

==Histone methylation==
Methylation of [[histone]]s may either increase or decrease gene transcription depending on which histone is modified, the amino acid that is modified, and the number of methyl groups added.&lt;ref name="Berger"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Berger SL | title = The complex language of chromatin regulation during transcription | journal = Nature | volume = 447 | issue = 7143 | pages = 407–12 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17522673 | doi = 10.1038/nature05915 | bibcode = 2007Natur.447..407B }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of [[lysine methylation]], three types of modifications exist: monomethylated, dimethylated, or trimethylated lysines. The di- or trimethylation of [[histone H3]] at lysine 9 (H3K9) has been associated with transcriptionally silent regions, while the di- or trimethylation of histone H3 at lysine 4 (H3K4) is associated with transcriptionally active genes.&lt;ref name="Sims"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sims RJ, Nishioka K, Reinberg D | title = Histone lysine methylation: a signature for chromatin function | journal = Trends in Genetics | volume = 19 | issue = 11 | pages = 629–39 | date = November 2003 | pmid = 14585615 | doi = 10.1016/j.tig.2003.09.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Histone 3 Lysine 4 Trimethylation and Memory Formation===
The hippocampus is an important brain region in memory formation. H3K4 trimethylation is associated with active transcription. In contextual fear conditioning experiments in rats, it was found that levels of H3K4 trimethylation increases in the [[hippocampus]] after fear conditioning.&lt;ref name="Gupta"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gupta S, Kim SY, Artis S, Molfese DL, Schumacher A, Sweatt JD, Paylor RE, Lubin FD | display-authors = 6 | title = Histone methylation regulates memory formation | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 30 | issue = 10 | pages = 3589–99 | date = March 2010 | pmid = 20219993 | pmc = 2859898 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3732-09.2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In these experiments by Gupta et al., a connection was made between changes in histone methylation and active gene expression during the consolidation of associative memories.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt; In this same study, it was also found that these histone methylations were reversible, as the levels of trimethylation of H3K4 returned to basal levels after a period of 24 hours. This indicated that active demethylation was occurring following [[memory consolidation]]. To further explore the role of [[methyltransferase]]s in long-term memory formation, this study applied the same fear conditioning tests on rats deficient in [[MLL (gene)|Mll]], a H3K4-specific methyltransferase. The rats with a heterozygous mutant Mll+/- gene showed a significant reduction in their ability to form [[long-term memories]] compared to normal rats with an intact Mll gene. Therefore, H3K4 methyltransferases, such as Mll, must have an essential role in long-term memory formation in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt;

The change in methylation state of histones at the location of specific gene promoters, as opposed to just genome-wide, is also involved in memory formation.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt; [[Zif268]] and [[BDNF]] genes are critical for memory consolidation.&lt;ref name="Bramham"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bramham CR | title = Control of synaptic consolidation in the dentate gyrus: mechanisms, functions, and therapeutic implications | journal = Progress in Brain Research | volume = 163 | pages = 453–71 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17765733 | doi = 10.1016/s0079-6123(07)63025-8 | isbn = 9780444530158 }}&lt;/ref&gt; H3K4 trimethylation increases around both of the Zif268 and BDNF promoters following contextual fear conditioning, when these genes are transcriptionally active. This demonstrates that at the time of memory consolidation, the transcription of memory formation genes such as Zif268 and bdnf is regulated by histone methylation.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt;

===Histone 3 Lysine 9 Dimethylation and Memory Formation===
Histone H3 lysine 9 dimethylation is associated with [[transcriptional silencing]].&lt;ref name="Sims"/&gt; The [[G9a]]/[[G9a-like protein]] (GLP) complex is a methyltransferase specific for producing this modification.&lt;ref name="Vermeulen"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vermeulen M, Mulder KW, Denissov S, Pijnappel WW, van Schaik FM, Varier RA, Baltissen MP, Stunnenberg HG, Mann M, Timmers HT | display-authors = 6 | title = Selective anchoring of TFIID to nucleosomes by trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 4 | journal = Cell | volume = 131 | issue = 1 | pages = 58–69 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17884155 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2007.08.016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One study examined the role of G9a/GLP-mediated transcriptional silencing in the hippocampus and [[entorhinal cortex]] (EC) during memory consolidation. It was found that the inhibition of G9a/GLP in the EC, but not in the hippocampus, results in the enhancement of long-term memory formation.&lt;ref name="Agarwal"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gupta-Agarwal S, Franklin AV, Deramus T, Wheelock M, Davis RL, McMahon LL, Lubin FD | title = G9a/GLP histone lysine dimethyltransferase complex activity in the hippocampus and the entorhinal cortex is required for gene activation and silencing during memory consolidation | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 32 | issue = 16 | pages = 5440–53 | date = April 2012 | pmid = 22514307 | pmc = 3332335 | doi = 10.1523/jneurosci.0147-12.2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, G9a/GLP inhibition in the entorhinal cortex altered histone H3 lysine 9 dimethylation in the [[Cornu Ammonis area 1]] of the hippocampus, suggesting the importance of this complex in mediating connectivity between these two brain regions. Therefore, the G9a/GLP complex plays an important role in histone methylation and long term memory formation in the hippocampus and the EC.&lt;ref name="Agarwal"/&gt;

===Histone Methylation and Other Epigenetic Modifications===
Histone methylation marks are also correlated with other epigenetic modifications, such as [[Histone acetylation and deacetylation|histone deacetylation]] and DNA methylation, in the context of learning and memory. Reduced histone deacetylation is correlated with an increase in H3K9 dimethylation, a modification associated with transcriptional silencing.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt; Therefore, histone deacetylase inhibitors may be applied to increase histone acetylation and suppress H3K9 dimethylation, thereby increasing gene transcription. In the case of DNA methylation, it was found that increases in H3K4 trimethylation correlate with altered DNA methylation of [[CpG site]]s at the promoter of [[Zif268]], a gene involved in memory formation, after fear conditioning. Gupta et al. showed that DNA methylation at the Zif268 promoter increased after fear conditioning, correlating with an increase in Zif268 gene expression.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt; This finding was surprising, since it was previously thought that DNA methylation resulted in transcriptional silencing.&lt;ref name="Gupta"/&gt;

==Histone Acetylation==
[[Acetylation]] involves the replacement of a hydrogen with an [[acetyl group]]. In a biological context, acetylation is most often associated with the modification of proteins, specifically [[histone]]s. The acetylation reaction is most often catalyzed by enzymes that contain [[histone acetyltransferase]] (HAT) activity.

===Histone acetyltransferases (HATs)===
HATs are enzymes responsible for the acetylation of amino acids. HATs acetylate by converting the [[lysine]] side group of [[amino acid]]s with the addition of an acetyl group from an [[acetyl CoA]] molecule, creating [[lysine#biological roles|acetyl lysine]]. HAT enzymes are most often associated with histone proteins and work to regulate the interaction between histones and the DNA that is wrapped around them. HATs are not only restricted to the acetylation of histone but can also acetylate many other proteins implicated in the manipulation of gene expression like that of transcription factors and receptor proteins.

===Chromatin Remodeling===
Acetylation is one of the main mechanisms implicated in the process of [[chromatin remodeling]]. Chromatin remodeling affects the regulation of gene expression by altering the relationship between [[nucleosome]]s and DNA. Acetylation of histones removes positive charge, which reduces the level of interaction between the formerly positively charged histone and the negatively charged phosphate groups of the DNA wrapped around the nucleosome complex. This alteration in charges causes a relaxation of DNA from the nucleosome, this relaxed section is seen to have higher levels of gene expression than non acetylated regions.

===Acetylation as an epigenetic marker===
Patterns of histone acetylation have been useful as a source of epigenetic information due to their ability to reflect changes in transcription rates and the maintenance of gene expression patterns. This acetylation code can then be read and provide generous information for the study of inheritance patterns of epigenetic changes like that of learning, memory and disease states.

===Acetlylation as a mechanism for learning and memory===
The role of epigenetic mechanisms and chromatin remodeling has been implicated in both synaptic plasticity and neuronal gene expression. Studies with histone deactylase complex inhibitors like [[Suberoylanilide hydroxamic acid|SAHA]], [[toluene]], garcinol, [[trichostatin A]] and [[sodium butyrate]] have shown that acetylation is important for the synaptic plasticity of the brain; by inhibiting deactylase complexes total acetylation rates in the brain increased leading to increased rates of [[Transcription (genetics)|transcription]] and enhanced memory consolidation.&lt;ref name="Zhao"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhao Z, Fan L, Fortress AM, Boulware MI, Frick KM | title = Hippocampal histone acetylation regulates object recognition and the estradiol-induced enhancement of object recognition | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 32 | issue = 7 | pages = 2344–51 | date = February 2012 | pmid = 22396409 | pmc = 3401048 | doi = 10.1523/jneurosci.5819-11.2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Rivas"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Huerta-Rivas A, López-Rubalcava C, Sánchez-Serrano SL, Valdez-Tapia M, Lamas M, Cruz SL | title = Toluene impairs learning and memory, has antinociceptive effects, and modifies histone acetylation in the dentate gyrus of adolescent and adult rats | journal = Pharmacology, Biochemistry, and Behavior | volume = 102 | issue = 1 | pages = 48–57 | date = July 2012 | pmid = 22497993 | doi = 10.1016/j.pbb.2012.03.018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By using various learning assays like the [[Morris water maze test]] and fear conditioning assays in conjunction with acetlyation influencing drugs it was shown that acetylation patterns in the hippocampus are integral to memory association and learning behavior.&lt;ref name="Guan"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Guan JS, Haggarty SJ, Giacometti E, Dannenberg JH, Joseph N, Gao J, Nieland TJ, Zhou Y, Wang X, Mazitschek R, Bradner JE, DePinho RA, Jaenisch R, Tsai LH | display-authors = 6 | title = HDAC2 negatively regulates memory formation and synaptic plasticity | journal = Nature | volume = 459 | issue = 7243 | pages = 55–60 | date = May 2009 | pmid = 19424149 | pmc = 3498958 | doi = 10.1038/nature07925 | url = https://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/10590437/3498958.pdf?sequence=1 | bibcode = 2009Natur.459...55G }}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies with various [[HDAC inhibitor]]s and neural development have shown increased learning and memory, as a result of an increased acetylation state. Conversely studies conducted with HAT inhibitors yielded impairment of memory consolidation and an overall decrease in learning.&lt;ref name="Stafford"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Stafford JM, Raybuck JD, Ryabinin AE, Lattal KM | title = Increasing histone acetylation in the hippocampus-infralimbic network enhances fear extinction | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 72 | issue = 1 | pages = 25–33 | date = July 2012 | pmid = 22290116 | pmc = 3352991 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2011.12.012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===ERK/MAPK Cascade===
Studies have shown that the [[Extracellular signal-regulated kinases|ERK]]/[[MAPK]] cascade is important for the regulation of lysine acetylation in the [[insular cortex]] of the brain (A part of the brain implicated in the formation of [[taste]] memories). The activation of the ERK/MAPK cascade was seen in mice after the introduction of a new taste, the cascade was shown to be necessary for the memory of the taste to be formed. The proposed mechanism for how this cascade works is that MAPK regulates histone acetylation and subsequent chromatin remodeling by means of downstream effectors, such as the [[CREB binding protein]] (which has HAT activity).&lt;ref name="Bousiges"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bousiges O, Vasconcelos AP, Neidl R, Cosquer B, Herbeaux K, Panteleeva I, Loeffler JP, Cassel JC, Boutillier AL | display-authors = 6 | title = Spatial memory consolidation is associated with induction of several lysine-acetyltransferase (histone acetyltransferase) expression levels and H2B/H4 acetylation-dependent transcriptional events in the rat hippocampus | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 35 | issue = 13 | pages = 2521–37 | date = December 2010 | pmid = 20811339 | pmc = 3055563 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2010.117 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Swank"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Swank MW, Sweatt JD | title = Increased histone acetyltransferase and lysine acetyltransferase activity and biphasic activation of the ERK/RSK cascade in insular cortex during novel taste learning | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 21 | issue = 10 | pages = 3383–91 | date = May 2001 | pmid = 11331368 | pmc = 6762472 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.21-10-03383.2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Levenson"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Levenson JM, O'Riordan KJ, Brown KD, Trinh MA, Molfese DL, Sweatt JD | title = Regulation of histone acetylation during memory formation in the hippocampus | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 279 | issue = 39 | pages = 40545–59 | date = September 2004 | pmid = 15273246 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.m402229200 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; By observing the rates of acetylation in the insular cortex researchers were able to determine which patterns of acetylation were due to deacetylase or acetylase activity and which were a result of lysine acetyltransferase activity.&lt;ref name="Swank"/&gt;

===Long Term Potentiation===
[[Long term potentiation]] (LTP) is the enhancement of signal strength between neurons. LTP is the basis of [[synaptic plasticity]] and plays a pivotal role in memory formation. LTP is dependent on the activity of [[NMDA receptor]]s in the brain and it has been shown that [[NMDA]] activity influences acetylation. When NMDA receptors are activated they cause an influx of calcium into the cell which in turn activates various signal pathways that ultimately activate the [[ERK pathway]] which then modulates transcription factors like [[CREB]]. CREB then recruits a HAT to help create and stabilize the long term formation of memory, often through the self-perpetuation of acetylated histones. Studies done on Acetylation of histone H3 in the CA1 region of the hippocampus show that the activation of NMDA receptors increased the acetylation of H3 and conversely inhibition of the ERK pathway in the CA1 region resulted in a decrease in acetylation of H3.&lt;ref name="Levenson"/&gt; In summary:
* NMDA-R activation increases phosphorylation of ERK and Acetylation of Histone H3
* Memory requires proper NMDA-R function
* Memory conditioning increases phosphorylation of ERK and acetylation of Histone H3
* ERK is regulated by phosphorylation
* Histone H3 acetylation is regulated by ERK
* [[Histone H4]] is not regulated by ERK
* [[HDAC inhibitor]]s enhance LTP, this is dependent on rate of transcription
* HDAC inhibitors do not affect NMDA-R

==Histone Deacetylation==

===HDACs' Role in CREB: CBP-Dependent Transcriptional Activation===
[[image:HDACs' role.jpg|'''Figure 1''' HDAC inhibition enhances memory and synaptic plasticity through CREB:CBP. Figure adapted from Vecsey ''et al.'', (2007)&lt;ref name="Vecsey"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vecsey CG, Hawk JD, Lattal KM, Stein JM, Fabian SA, Attner MA, Cabrera SM, McDonough CB, Brindle PK, Abel T, Wood MA | display-authors = 6 | title = Histone deacetylase inhibitors enhance memory and synaptic plasticity via CREB:CBP-dependent transcriptional activation | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 27 | issue = 23 | pages = 6128–40 | date = June 2007 | pmid = 17553985 | pmc = 2925045 | doi = 10.1523/jneurosci.0296-07.2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; | thumb|top|500px]]
[[Histone deacetylase]]s (HDAC) remove acetyl groups (-COCH3) from histones altering [[chromatin structure]]s and decreasing accessibility of transcriptional factors to DNA, thereby reducing transcription of genes. HDACs have shown to play a role in learning and memory through their regulation in the [[CREB#Mechanism of action|CREB-CBP pathway]].

Studies conclude that HDAC inhibitors such as [[trichostatin A]] (TSA) increase histone acetylation and improve [[synaptic plasticity]] and [[long-term memory]] (Fig 1A). [[CREB]], a [[cAMP response element-binding protein]] and transcriptional activator, binds [[CREB-binding protein|CBP]] forming the CREB: CBP complex. This complex activates genes involved in synaptic formation and long-term memory.(Fig 1B) TSA treatments in the hippocampal CA1 region of mice increased acetylation levels and enhanced long-term potentiation (LTP), a mechanism involved in learning and memory (Fig 1B). However, TSA treatments in CBP mutants lacking [[P300-CBP coactivator family|KIX domains]] did not effect LTP in mice (Fig 1D). The KIX domain allows for interaction between CREB and CBP, so knocking out this region disrupts formation of the CREB: CBP complex. Knock outs of CREB produced similar results to those of mutant CBP mice (Fig 1C). Therefore, HDAC inhibition and CREB: CBP association are both necessary for memory development. TSA treatments showed increased expression levels of ''[[Nr4a1]]'' and ''Nra2'' genes while other CREB regulated genes were unaffected. HDAC inhibitors improve memory through activation of specific genes regulated by CREB: CBP complex.&lt;ref name="Vecsey"/&gt;

===HDAC2===
The role of individual HDACs in learning and memory is not well understood, but [[HDAC2]] has been shown to negatively regulate memory formation and synaptic plasticity.&lt;ref name="Guan"/&gt;

Overexpression (OE) of [[HDAC1]] and HDAC2 in mice resulted in decreased levels of acetylated lysines. After exposing these mice to context and tone-dependent fear conditioning experiments, HDAC1 OE mice did not change, but HDAC2 OE mice showed a decrease in freezing behavior, suggesting impairment in memory formation. On the other hand, mice with HDAC2 knockouts (KO) illustrated increased freezing levels compared to wild-type (WT) mice while HDAC1 displayed similar freezing behaviors to WTs.  In summary, Guan ''et al.''&lt;ref name="Guan"/&gt; have shown that:
* HDAC2, not HDAC1, regulates [[synaptogenesis]] and [[synaptic plasticity]]. HDAC2 overexpression decreases spine density in CA1 pyramidal neurons and [[dentate gyrus]] [[granule cell]]s but HDAC2 KO show an increase in spine density.
* Long term potentiation in CA1 neurons was not observed in HDAC2 OE mice but was easily induced in HDAC2 KO mice. LTP was not altered between HDAC1 KO and OE mice.
* HDAC2 suppresses neuronal gene expression. HDAC2 interacted more than HDAC1 with specific memory-forming promoters such as [[Bdnf]], [[Egr1]], [[c-Fos|Fos]], and [[GLUR1]].
* [[CoREST]], a co-repressor, associates with HDAC2 not HDAC1.
* [[Suberoylanilide hydroxamic acid|SAHA]], a HDAC inhibitor, increased freezing of HDAC2 OE mice in contextual fear and tone dependent experiments, but did not effect HDAC2 KO mice suggesting HDAC2 is major target of SAHA

===HDAC3===
[[HDAC3]] is also a negative regulator of long term potentiation formation. McQuown ''et al.''&lt;ref name="McQuown"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McQuown SC, Barrett RM, Matheos DP, Post RJ, Rogge GA, Alenghat T, Mullican SE, Jones S, Rusche JR, Lazar MA, Wood MA | display-authors = 6 | title = HDAC3 is a critical negative regulator of long-term memory formation | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 31 | issue = 2 | pages = 764–74 | date = January 2011 | pmid = 21228185 | pmc = 3160172 | doi = 10.1523/jneurosci.5052-10.2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; have shown that:
* KOs of HDAC3 in [[dorsal hippocampus]] resulted in enhanced memory during [[object location test]]s (OLM).
* [[RGFP136]], HDAC3 inhibitor, enhances LTP for object recognition and location
* RGFP136 enhances LTP through CBP-dependent mechanism
* HDAC3 deletions showed increased [[Nr4a2]] and [[c-Fos]] expression
* HDAC3 interacts with NCoR{{which|date=May 2012}} and [[HDAC4]] to perform its role in memory formation

===HDACs’ Role in CNS disorders===
Research has shown that HDACs and HATs play a crucial role in [[central nervous system]] (CNS) disorders such as [[Rett syndrome]].&lt;ref name="Kazantsev"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kazantsev AG, Thompson LM | title = Therapeutic application of histone deacetylase inhibitors for central nervous system disorders | journal = Nature Reviews. Drug Discovery | volume = 7 | issue = 10 | pages = 854–68 | date = October 2008 | pmid = 18827828 | doi = 10.1038/nrd2681 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Rubinstein-Tabyi syndrome]] causes mental retardation through possible mutations in [[CREB-binding protein]] and [[p300-CBP coactivator family|p300]]. However, enhancing expression of CREB-dependent genes or inhibition of HDAC activity partially restore LTP loss and ameliorate late LTP deficits. HDAC inhibitor like TSA may provide a possible therapy for Rubinstein-Tabyi syndrome.
Other memory-deficit disorders which may involve HDAC inhibitors as potential therapy are:
* [[Friedreich's ataxia]]
* [[Spinal muscular atrophy]]
* [[Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis]]
* [[Spinal and bulbar muscular atrophy]]
* [[Huntington's disease]]
* [[Spinocerebellar ataxia]]s
* [[Dentatorubropallidoluysian atrophy]]
* [[Alzheimer's disease]]
* [[Niemann-Pick disease, type C|Niemann Pick type C disease]]

==Roles of ROS and OGG1 in memory and learning==

[[File:Initiation of DNA demethylation at a CpG site.svg|thumb|400 px|Initiation of [[DNA demethylation]] at a [[CpG site]]. In adult somatic cells DNA methylation typically occurs in the context of CpG dinucleotides ([[CpG sites]]), forming [[5-methylcytosine]]-pG, or 5mCpG. Reactive oxygen species (ROS) may attack guanine at the dinucleotide site, forming [[8-oxo-2'-deoxyguanosine|8-hydroxy-2'-deoxyguanosine]] (8-OHdG), and resulting in a 5mCp-8-OHdG dinucleotide site.  The [[base excision repair]] enzyme [[oxoguanine glycosylase|OGG1]] targets 8-OHdG and binds to the lesion without immediate excision. OGG1, present at a 5mCp-8-OHdG site recruits [[Tet methylcytosine dioxygenase 1|TET1]] and TET1 oxidizes the 5mC adjacent to the 8-OHdG.  This initiates demethylation of 5mC.&lt;ref name=Zhou&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhou X, Zhuang Z, Wang W, He L, Wu H, Cao Y, Pan F, Zhao J, Hu Z, Sekhar C, Guo Z | display-authors = 6 | title = OGG1 is essential in oxidative stress induced DNA demethylation | journal = Cellular Signalling | volume = 28 | issue = 9 | pages = 1163–71 | date = September 2016 | pmid = 27251462 | doi = 10.1016/j.cellsig.2016.05.021 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

[[File:Demethylation of 5-methylcytosine.svg|thumb|400 px|Demethylation of [[5-Methylcytosine]] (5mC) in neuron DNA.  As reviewed in 2018,&lt;ref name="pmid29875631"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bayraktar G, Kreutz MR | title = The Role of Activity-Dependent DNA Demethylation in the Adult Brain and in Neurological Disorders | journal = Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience | volume = 11 | issue =  | pages = 169 | date = 2018 | pmid = 29875631 | pmc = 5975432 | doi = 10.3389/fnmol.2018.00169 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in brain neurons, 5mC is oxidized by the ten-eleven translocation (TET) family of dioxygenases ([[Tet methylcytosine dioxygenase 1|TET1]], [[Tet methylcytosine dioxygenase 2|TET2]], [[Tet methylcytosine dioxygenase 3|TET3]]) to generate [[5-hydroxymethylcytosine]] (5hmC).  In successive steps TET enzymes further hydroxylate 5hmC to generate 5-formylcytosine (5fC) and 5-carboxylcytosine (5caC).  [[Thymine-DNA glycosylase]] (TDG) recognizes the intermediate bases 5fC and 5caC and excises the [[glycosidic bond]] resulting in an apyrimidinic site ([[AP site]]).  In an alternative oxidative deamination pathway, 5hmC can be oxidatively deaminated by activity-induced cytidine deaminase/apolipoprotein B mRNA editing complex [[APOBEC3G|(AID/APOBEC)]] deaminases to form 5-hydroxymethyluracil (5hmU) or 5mC can be converted to [[thymine]] (Thy).  5hmU can be cleaved by TDG, single-strand-selective monofunctional uracil-DNA glycosylase 1 ([[SMUG1]]), Nei-Like DNA Glycosylase 1 ([[NEIL1]]), or methyl-CpG binding protein 4 ([[MBD4]]).  AP sites and T:G mismatches are then repaired by base excision repair (BER) enzymes to yield [[cytosine]] (Cyt).]]

[[File:Brain regions involved in memory formation.jpg|thumb|400 px|The identified areas of the human brain are involved in memory formation.]]

As reviewed by Massaad and Klann in 2011&lt;ref name="pmid20649473"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Massaad CA, Klann E | title = Reactive oxygen species in the regulation of synaptic plasticity and memory | journal = Antioxidants &amp; Redox Signaling | volume = 14 | issue = 10 | pages = 2013–54 | date = May 2011 | pmid = 20649473 | pmc = 3078504 | doi = 10.1089/ars.2010.3208 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and by Beckhauser et al. in 2016,&lt;ref name="pmid27625575"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beckhauser TF, Francis-Oliveira J, De Pasquale R | title = Reactive Oxygen Species: Physiological and Physiopathological Effects on Synaptic Plasticity | journal = Journal of Experimental Neuroscience | volume = 10 | issue = Suppl 1 | pages = 23–48 | date = 2016 | pmid = 27625575 | pmc = 5012454 | doi = 10.4137/JEN.S39887 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[reactive oxygen species]] (ROS) are required for normal learning and memory functions. 

One of the most frequent [[DNA oxidation]] products of ROS is [[8-oxo-2'-deoxyguanosine|8-hydroxy-2'-deoxyguanosine]] (8-OHdG).  Removal of oxidized bases in DNA usually occurs in a matter of minutes, with a half-life of 11 minutes for 8-OHdG.&lt;ref name="pmid11353081"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hamilton ML, Guo Z, Fuller CD, Van Remmen H, Ward WF, Austad SN, Troyer DA, Thompson I, Richardson A | display-authors = 6 | title = A reliable assessment of 8-oxo-2-deoxyguanosine levels in nuclear and mitochondrial DNA using the sodium iodide method to isolate DNA | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 29 | issue = 10 | pages = 2117–26 | date = May 2001 | pmid = 11353081 | pmc = 55450 | doi = 10.1093/nar/29.10.2117 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Steady-state levels of [[Endogeny (biology)|endogenous]] DNA damages represent the balance between formation and repair.  8-OHdGs are among the most frequent DNA damages present in the steady-state, with about 2,400 8-OHdG damaged nucleotides in the average mammalian cell.&lt;ref name="pmid21163908"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Swenberg JA, Lu K, Moeller BC, Gao L, Upton PB, Nakamura J, Starr TB | title = Endogenous versus exogenous DNA adducts: their role in carcinogenesis, epidemiology, and risk assessment | journal = Toxicological Sciences | volume = 120 Suppl 1 | issue =  | pages = S130-45 | date = March 2011 | pmid = 21163908 | pmc = 3043087 | doi = 10.1093/toxsci/kfq371 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The steady state 8-OHdG level in the brain is similar to that in other tissues.&lt;ref name="pmid15231648"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Russo MT, De Luca G, Degan P, Parlanti E, Dogliotti E, Barnes DE, Lindahl T, Yang H, Miller JH, Bignami M | display-authors = 6 | title = Accumulation of the oxidative base lesion 8-hydroxyguanine in DNA of tumor-prone mice defective in both the Myh and Ogg1 DNA glycosylases | journal = Cancer Research | volume = 64 | issue = 13 | pages = 4411–4 | date = July 2004 | pmid = 15231648 | doi = 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0355 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The occurrence of 8-OHdG in neurons appears to have a role in memory and learning.  The DNA glycosylase [[oxoguanine glycosylase]] (OGG1) is the primary enzyme responsible for the excision of 8-OHdG in [[base excision repair]].  However, OGG1, which targets and associates with 8-OHdG, also has a role in adaptive behavior, which implies a physiologically relevant role for 8-OHdG combined with OGG1 in cognition in the adult brain.&lt;ref name="pmid27512601"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Marshall P, Bredy TW | title = Cognitive neuroepigenetics: the next evolution in our understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying learning and memory? | journal = NPJ Science of Learning | volume = 1 | issue =  | pages = 16014 | date = 2016 | pmid = 27512601 | pmc = 4977095 | doi = 10.1038/npjscilearn.2016.14 | bibcode = 2016npjSL...116014M }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid26711335"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bjørge MD, Hildrestrand GA, Scheffler K, Suganthan R, Rolseth V, Kuśnierczyk A, Rowe AD, Vågbø CB, Vetlesen S, Eide L, Slupphaug G, Nakabeppu Y, Bredy TW, Klungland A, Bjørås M | display-authors = 6 | title = Synergistic Actions of Ogg1 and Mutyh DNA Glycosylases Modulate Anxiety-like Behavior in Mice | journal = Cell Reports | volume = 13 | issue = 12 | pages = 2671–8 | date = December 2015 | pmid = 26711335 | doi = 10.1016/j.celrep.2015.12.001 | url = https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/10852/55259/2/mmc2.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In particular, heterozygous OGG1+/- mice, with about half the protein level of OGG1, exhibit poorer learning performance in the Barnes maze compared to wild-type animals.&lt;ref name="pmid29101721"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hofer T, Duale N, Muusse M, Eide DM, Dahl H, Boix F, Andersen JM, Olsen AK, Myhre O | display-authors = 6 | title = Restoration of Cognitive Performance in Mice Carrying a Deficient Allele of 8-Oxoguanine DNA Glycosylase by X-ray Irradiation | journal = Neurotoxicity Research | volume = 33 | issue = 4 | pages = 824–836 | date = May 2018 | pmid = 29101721 | doi = 10.1007/s12640-017-9833-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In adult somatic cells, such as neurons, DNA methylation typically occurs in the context of CpG dinucleotides ([[CpG sites]]), forming [[5-methylcytosine]] (5mC).&lt;ref name=Zhou&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhou X, Zhuang Z, Wang W, He L, Wu H, Cao Y, Pan F, Zhao J, Hu Z, Sekhar C, Guo Z | display-authors = 6 | title = OGG1 is essential in oxidative stress induced DNA demethylation | journal = Cellular Signalling | volume = 28 | issue = 9 | pages = 1163–71 | date = September 2016 | pmid = 27251462 | doi = 10.1016/j.cellsig.2016.05.021 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus, a CpG site may be methylated to form 5mCpG.  The presence of 5mC at CpG sites in gene promoters is widely considered to be an epigenetic mark that acts to suppress transcription.&lt;ref name="pmid28208656"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Keifer J | title = Primetime for Learning Genes | journal = Genes | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 69 | date = February 2017 | pmid = 28208656 | pmc = 5333058 | doi = 10.3390/genes8020069 }}&lt;/ref&gt;    If the guanine at the 5mCpG site is attacked by ROS, leading to 8-OHdG formation, OGG1 binds to the 8-OHdG lesion without immediate excision of the 8-OHdG.  When OGG1 is present at a 5mCp-8-OHdG site, it recruits [[Tet methylcytosine dioxygenase 1|TET1]] to the 8-OHdG lesion and TET1 oxidizes the 5mC adjacent to 8-OHdG.  This causes the 5mC to enter the [[DNA demethylation]] pathway (see Figure titled "Initiation of DNA demethylation at a CpG site").&lt;ref name=Zhou /&gt;  This pathway is initiated by formation of [[5-hydroxymethylcytosine]], which may remain in the DNA, or there may be further oxidative reactions followed by base excision repair, to return the nucleoside at that position to cytosine (see Figure "Demethylation of 5-Methylcytosine (5mC) in neuron DNA"). 

The total number of [[CpG site]]s in the human genome is approximately 28 million and the average frequency of CpG sites in the genome is about 1 per hundred base pairs.&lt;ref name="pmid26932361"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lövkvist C, Dodd IB, Sneppen K, Haerter JO | title = DNA methylation in human epigenomes depends on local topology of CpG sites | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 44 | issue = 11 | pages = 5123–32 | date = June 2016 | pmid = 26932361 | pmc = 4914085 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkw124 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   An intense learning situation can be applied to rats, referred to as contextual [[fear conditioning]].&lt;ref name=KimJung&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kim JJ, Jung MW | title = Neural circuits and mechanisms involved in Pavlovian fear conditioning: a critical review | journal = Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews | volume = 30 | issue = 2 | pages = 188–202 | date = 2006 | pmid = 16120461 | pmc = 4342048 | doi = 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2005.06.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This can result in a life-long fearful memory after a single training event.&lt;ref name=KimJung /&gt;  While the [[long-term memory]] of this event appears to be first stored in the hippocampus, this storage is transient and does not remain in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name=KimJung /&gt;  Much of the long term storage of contextual fear conditioning memory appears to take place in the anterior cingulate cortex.&lt;ref name=Frankland&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Frankland PW, Bontempi B, Talton LE, Kaczmarek L, Silva AJ | s2cid = 15893863 | title = The involvement of the anterior cingulate cortex in remote contextual fear memory | journal = Science | volume = 304 | issue = 5672 | pages = 881–3 | date = May 2004 | pmid = 15131309 | doi = 10.1126/science.1094804 | bibcode = 2004Sci...304..881F }}&lt;/ref&gt;  (See the Figure showing identified areas of the human brain that are involved in memory formation and also this reference &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://qbi.uq.edu.au/brain-basics/memory/where-are-memories-stored) |title = The Brain - Queensland Brain Institute - University of Queensland}}&lt;/ref&gt;.)  When contextual fear conditioning is applied to a rat, more than 5,000 [[differentially methylated regions]] (DMRs) (of 500 nucleotides each) occur in the rat [[hippocampus]] neural genome both one hour and 24 hours after the conditioning in the hippocampus.&lt;ref name=DukeSweatt&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Duke CG, Kennedy AJ, Gavin CF, Day JJ, Sweatt JD | title = Experience-dependent epigenomic reorganization in the hippocampus | journal = Learning &amp; Memory | volume = 24 | issue = 7 | pages = 278–288 | date = July 2017 | pmid = 28620075 | pmc = 5473107 | doi = 10.1101/lm.045112.117 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This causes about 500 genes to be up-regulated (often due to hypomethylation of CpG sites) and about 1,000 genes to be down-regulated (often due to newly formed 5mC at CpG sites in a promoter region).  The pattern of induced and repressed genes within neurons appears to provide a molecular basis for forming this first transient memory of this training event in the hippocampus of the rat brain.&lt;ref name=DukeSweatt /&gt;  When similar contextual fear conditioning is applied to a mouse, one hour after contextual fear conditioning there were 675 demethylated genes and 613 hypermethylated genes in the hippocampus region of the mouse brain.&lt;ref name=Halder&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Halder R, Hennion M, Vidal RO, Shomroni O, Rahman RU, Rajput A, Centeno TP, van Bebber F, Capece V, Garcia Vizcaino JC, Schuetz AL, Burkhardt S, Benito E, Navarro Sala M, Javan SB, Haass C, Schmid B, Fischer A, Bonn S | display-authors = 6 | title = DNA methylation changes in plasticity genes accompany the formation and maintenance of memory | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 19 | issue = 1 | pages = 102–10 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26656643 | pmc = 4700510 | doi = 10.1038/nn.4194 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These changes were transient in the hippocampal neurons, and almost none were present after four weeks.  However, in mice subjected to conditional fear conditioning, after four weeks there were more than 1,000 differentially methylated genes and more than 1,000 differentially expressed genes in the anterior cingulate cortex,&lt;ref name=Halder /&gt; where long-term memories are stored in the mouse brain.&lt;ref name=Frankland /&gt;
{{clear}}
== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Epigenetics]]
[[Category:Learning]]
[[Category:Memory]]</text>
      <sha1>2ywv3lj09bgxf6wew4oz4n5bauwdapi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
