<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Red Balloon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1572108</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960828640</id>
      <parentid>960261262</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-05T03:45:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ser Amantio di Nicolao</username>
        <id>753665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */add category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="19618" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Red balloon (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|1956 film by Albert Lamorisse}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2016}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = The Red Balloon
| image          = Le ballon rouge (1956).png
| alt            = 
| caption        = French theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Albert Lamorisse]]
| producer       = Albert Lamorisse
| screenplay     = Albert Lamorisse
| starring       = Pascal Lamorisse
| music          = [[Maurice Le Roux]]
| cinematography = [[Edmond Séchan]]
| editing        = Pierre Gillette
| studio         = Films Montsouris
| distributor    = [[Ilya Lopert|Lopert Pictures]]
| released       = {{Film date|1956|5|3|[[1956 Cannes Film Festival|Cannes]]|1956|10|19|France|df=y}}
| runtime        = 35 minutes&lt;!--Theatrical runtime: 35:00--&gt;&lt;ref name=bbfc&gt;{{cite web | url=http://bbfc.co.uk/releases/red-balloon-film | title=''THE RED BALLOON'' (U) | work=[[British Board of Film Classification]] | date=15 October 1956 | accessdate=25 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country        = France
| language       = French
}}

'''''The Red Balloon''''' ({{lang-fr|Le ballon rouge}}) is a 1956 French [[Fantasy film|fantasy]] [[comedy-drama]] [[featurette]] written, produced, and directed by [[Albert Lamorisse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|id=0048980|title=The Red Balloon}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The thirty-five-minute&lt;ref name=bbfc/&gt; short, which follows the adventures of a young boy who one day finds a sentient, mute, red balloon, was filmed in the [[Ménilmontant]] neighbourhood of [[Paris]].

Lamorisse used his children as actors in the film. His son, Pascal, plays himself in the main role, and his daughter, Sabine, portrays a little girl.

The film won numerous awards, including an [[Academy Awards|Oscar]] for Lamorisse for writing the [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Original Screenplay]] in 1956 and the [[Short Film Palme d'Or|Palme d'Or for short films]] at the [[1956 Cannes Film Festival]]. It also became popular with children and educators. It is the only short film to win the [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay]].

==Plot==
The film follows Pascal (Pascal Lamorisse), a young boy who, on his way to school one morning, discovers a large helium-filled red balloon. As he plays with it, he realizes it has a mind and will of its own. It begins to follow him wherever he goes, never straying far from him, and at times floating outside his bedroom window, as his mother will not allow it in their apartment.

The balloon follows Pascal through the streets of Paris, and they draw a lot of attention and envy from other children as they wander the streets. At one point the balloon enters his classroom, causing an uproar from his classmates. The noise alerts the principal, who locks Pascal up in his office. Later, after being set free, Pascal and the balloon encounter a little girl (Sabine Lamorisse) with a blue balloon that also seems to have a mind of its own, just like his.

One Sunday, the balloon is told to stay home while Pascal and his mother go to church. However, it follows them through the open window and into the church, and they are led out by a scolding [[beadle]].

As Pascal and the balloon wander around the neighborhood, a gang of older boys, who are envious of the balloon, steal it while Pascal is inside a bakery; however, he manages to retrieve it. Following a chase through narrow alleyways, the boys finally catch up to them. They hold Pascal back as they bring it down with sling shots before one of the boys finishes it off by stomping on it.

The film ends as all the other balloons in Paris come to Pascal's aid and take him on a [[cluster balloon]] ride over the city.

==Themes==
As the film was filmed in [[Paris]] after World War II, its mise-en-scène is quite dark and grey and therefore gives a depressing quality to the setting and mood.  In contrast, the balloon's bright colour acts as a symbol of hope and light within the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Koresky|first=Michael|title=The Red Balloon|url=https://www.criterion.com/current/posts/655-the-red-balloon|website=The Criterion Collection|date=28 April 2008|accessdate=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cluster balloon ride in the closing scene could also be said to represent a religious or spiritual analogy. For example, when the balloon is destroyed, its "spirit" lives on as it is transferred to all the other balloons in the city, which is said to be a metaphor for Christ.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://alisashortfilm.wordpress.com/2011/02/28/the-red-balloon-1956/|last=Hathaway|first=Alisa|title=The Red Balloon (1956)|date=28 February 2011|work=Notes on Short Film|access-date=2018-09-22|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Themes of self-realisation and loneliness are also present in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.criterion.com/current/posts/778-the-red-balloon-written-on-the-wind|last=Selznick|first=Brian|title=''The Red Balloon'': Written on the Wind|website=The Criterion Collection|date=19 November 2008|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The theme of innocence is persistent and is one of the main focuses of the film. Through a child's gaze, a cynical world is transformed into an almost magical one, highlighting the power of the innocence and imagination of children.&lt;ref name="Kennicott"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/11/22/AR2007112201315.html|title='Red Balloon' and 'White Mane': Childhood Colored by Adult Cynicism|last=Kennicott|first=Philip|work=Washington Post|date=23 November 2007|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, authors such as Myles P. Breen have identified the film as having thematic/stylistic qualities that are reflective of the poetic medium. This perspective is rationalised by Breen through quoting film theorist Christian Metz, who states, “in a poem there is no story line, and nothing intrudes between the author and the reader”. The film, therefore, is categorised by Breen as being a filmic poem, partially due to its loose, non-narrative structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Breen|first=Myles P.|date=1978|title=The Rhetoric of the Short Film|journal=Journal of the University Film Association|volume=30|issue=3|pages=3–13|jstor=20687433}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==

The film serves as a color record of the [[Belleville, Paris|Belleville]] area of Paris, which had fallen into decay by the 1960s, prompting the Parisian government to demolish it as a slum-clearance effort. Part of the site was built up with housing projects; the remainder was left as wasteland for 20 years. Some of what is seen in the film no longer exists: one of the bakeries, the school, the famous shaped staircase situated just beyond the equally famous café "Au Repos de la Montagne", the steep steps of the passage Julien Lacroix where Pascal finds the balloon, and the empty lot where all the battles take place. Instead stands the [[Parc de Belleville]]. The apartment where Pascal lives with his mother, located at 15, rue du Transvaal, the church, known as the [[Église Notre-Dame-de-la-Croix de Ménilmontant]], and the bus stop Pyrénées-Ménilmontant, located at the intersection of rue des Pyrénées and rue de Ménilmontant, still stand.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.furoremagazine.com/exemples/|last=Schreuders|first=Piet|title=Het Parijs van Le Ballon Rouge|date=8 February 2012|work=Furore|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery mode="packed" caption="" heights="140"&gt;
Pascal%27s_apartment_in_the_Red_Balloon_(15_rue_du_Transvaal,_75020_Paris).jpg|The building hosting Pascal's apartment (15 rue du Transvaal)
Rue_des_Envierges_and_rue_du_Transvaal_(Paris,_20th_arrondissement).jpg|This view is seen in the movie. The photo is taken from the side of the building hosting the bakery (intersection of rue des Envierges and rue du Transvaal)
Parc_de_Belleville_(Paris,_20th_arrondissement).jpg|[[Parc de Belleville]]
Parc_de_Belleville_(stairs).jpg|Stairs in the [[Parc de Belleville]]
P1010045 Paris XX Église Notre-Dame-de-la-Croix de Ménilmontant reductwk.JPG|[[Église Notre-Dame-de-la-Croix de Ménilmontant]] in [[Ménilmontant]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

Albert Lamorrise was a former auditor at the [[Institut des hautes études cinématographiques]] (IDHEC), and the crew that he used for the making of the film was entirely composed of IDHEC graduates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tessonneau|first=Rémy|last2=Ferguson|first2=Charles|date=1957|title=The French Institute Of Cinema (IDHEC)|journal=Journal of the University Film Producers Association|volume=10|issue=1|pages=4–6|jstor=20686478}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The main role is played by Albert Lamorrisse's son, Pascal. French singer [[Renaud]] and his brother play the twin brothers who appear at the end of the movie, wearing red coats. They got the role through their uncle [[Edmond Séchan]], who was the [[director of photography]] for the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.leparisien.fr/culture-loisirs/dans-son-clip-renaud-a-4-ans-16-04-2016-5719563.php|title=Dans son clip, Renaud à... 4 ans !|author=E. M.|date=16 April 2016|work=Le Parisien|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==
The film premiered and opened nationwide in France on 19 October 1956; it was released in the United Kingdom on 23 December 1956 (as the supporting film to the 1956 Royal Performance Film ''[[The Battle of the River Plate (film)|The Battle of the River Plate]]'', which ensured it a [[Wide release|wide distribution]]) and in the United States on 11 March 1957.

It has been featured in many festivals over the years, including the Wisconsin International Children's Film Festival; the Los Angeles Outfest Gay and Lesbian Film Festival; the [[Wisconsin Film Festival]]; and others.

The film, in its American [[television]] premiere, was introduced by then-actor [[Ronald Reagan]] as an episode of the [[CBS]] [[anthology series]] ''[[General Electric Theater]]'' on 2 April 1961.&lt;ref&gt;{{Allmovie title|id=40656|title=The Red Balloon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the 1960s, 1970s, 1980s and early 1990s, the film was popular in elementary classrooms throughout the United States and Canada. A four-minute clip is on the rotating list of programming on [[Classic Arts Showcase]].

===Reception===
Since its first release in 1956, the film has generally received overwhelmingly favorable reviews from critics. The film critic for ''[[the New York Times]]'', [[Bosley Crowther]], hailed the simple tale and praised director Lamorisse, writing:  "Yet with the sensitive cooperation of his own beguiling son and with the gray-blue atmosphere of an old Paris quarter as the background for the shiny balloon, he has got here a tender, humorous drama of the ingenuousness of a child and, indeed, a poignant symbolization of dreams and the cruelty of those who puncture them."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9D07E7DC1639E33BBC4A52DFB566838C649EDE|last=Crowther|first=Bosley|title=Screen: Documentary and Fantasy; 'Lost Continent,' 'Red Balloon' on Bill|work=New York Times|date=12 March 1957|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the film was re-released in the United States in late 2006 by [[Janus Films]], ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' magazine film critic [[Owen Gleiberman]] praised its direction and simple story line that reminded him of his youth, and wrote: "More than any other children's film, ''The Red Balloon'' turns me into a kid again whenever I see it...[to] see ''The Red Balloon'' is to laugh, and cry, at the impossible joy of being a child again."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20162166,00.html|last=Gliebermann|first=Owen|title=The Red Balloon|work=EW.com|date=21 November 2007|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Film critic Brian Gibson wrote: "So far, this seems a post-Occupation France happy to forget the blood and death of [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler's]] war a decade earlier. But soon people’s occasional, playful efforts to grab the floating, carefree balloon become grasping and destructive. In a gorgeous sequence, light streaming down alleys as children's shoes clack and clatter on the cobblestones, the balloon bouncing between the walls, Pascal is hunted down for his floating pet. Its ballooning sense of hope and freedom is deflated by a fierce, squabbling mass. Then, fortunately, it floats off, with the breeze of magic-realism, into a feeling of escape and peace, ''The Red Balloon'' taking hold of Pascal, lifting him out of this rigid, petty, earthbound life."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://archive.is/20130205160335/http://www.vueweekly.com/article.php?id=7536|last=Gibson|first=Brian|title=What childhood films are these?|work=archive.is|date=5 February 2007|access-date=9 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a review in ''[[The Washington Post]],'' critic Philip Kennicott had a cynical view: "[The film takes] place in a world of lies. Innocent lies? Not necessarily. ''The Red Balloon'' may be the most seamless fusion of [[capitalism]] and [[Christianity]] ever put on film. A young boy invests in a red balloon the love of which places him on the outside of society. The balloon is hunted down and killed on a barren hilltop–-think [[Calvary]]–-by a mob of cruel boys. The ending, a bizarre emotional sucker punch, is straight out of the [[New Testament]]. Thus is investment rewarded-–with Christian [[Transcendence (philosophy)|transcendence]] or, at least, an old-fashioned [[Assumption of Mary|Assumption]]. This might be sweet. Or it might be a very cynical reduction of the primary impulse to religious faith."&lt;ref name="Kennicott"/&gt;

The review aggregator [[Rotten Tomatoes]] reported that 95% of critics gave the film a positive review, based on twenty reviews. The critical consensus reads: "''The Red Balloon'' invests the simplest of narratives with spectacular visual inventiveness, making for a singularly wondrous portrait of innocence."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/red_balloon/ ''The Red Balloon''] at [[Rotten Tomatoes]]. Accessed July 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accolades===
* [[Prix Louis Delluc]]: Prix Louis Delluc; Albert Lamorisse, 1956.&lt;ref&gt;(The A to Z of French Cinema, P.xxx) 1956: December: Albert Lamorisse's Le Ballon rouge wins the Prix Louis-Delluc Accessed February 12, 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cannes Film Festival]]: ''Palme d'Or du court métrage''/[[Golden Palm]]; Best Short Film, Albert Lamorisse, 1956.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cineressources.net/archives/recherche_s/index.php|title=Recherche spécifique - Archives|website=www.cineressources.net|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[British Academy of Film and Television Arts]]: BAFTA Award; Special Award, France, 1957.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://awards.bafta.org/keyword-search?keywords=the+red+balloon|title=BAFTA Awards Search {{!}} BAFTA Awards|website=awards.bafta.org|language=en|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Academy Awards]]: Oscar; [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Writing, Best Original Screenplay]], Albert Lamorisse, 1957.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nationalboardofreview.org/award-years/1957/|title=1957 Archives - National Board of Review|website=National Board of Review|language=en-US|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[National Board of Review]]: [[National Board of Review Awards 1957|Top Foreign Films]], 1957.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.filmaffinity.com/en/awards.php?award_id=nyfcc&amp;year=1957|title=FilmAffinity|website=FilmAffinity|language=en|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In 1960, Lamorisse released a second film, ''[[Stowaway in the Sky]]'', which also starred Pascal and was a [[spiritual successor]] to ''The Red Balloon''.

A stage adaptation by Anthony Clark was performed at the [[Royal National Theatre]] in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;''The Red Balloon'', Anthony Clark. London: Oberon Books ,2000, {{ISBN|978-1-84002-079-3}}. Accessed February 12, 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

Zlatko Grcic and Bob Godfrey's animated short, ''Dream Doll'', is something of an animated reinterpretation of ''The Red Balloon'', focusing on an adult man whose "red balloon" is actually an inflatable nude woman.

[[Don Hertzfeld]]'s 1997 short film ''[[Billy's Balloon]]'', which also showed at Cannes, is a parody of ''The Red Balloon''.

The music video for "Son of Sam" by [[Elliott Smith]], from his 2000 album [[Figure 8 (album)|Figure 8]], is a direct homage to ''The Red Balloon''.

[[Hou Hsiao-hsien]]'s 2007 film ''[[Flight of the Red Balloon]]'' is a direct homage to the film.

A boy with a bright red balloon is featured in the epilogue of [[Damien Chazelle]]'s 2016 musical film ''[[La La Land (film)|La La Land]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2016/12/13/la_la_land_s_many_references_to_classic_movies_from_singin_in_the_rain_to.html|title=La La Land’s Many References to Classic Movies: A Guide|last=Harris|first=Aisha|date=2016-12-13|work=Slate|access-date=2018-09-22|language=en-US|issn=1091-2339}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Merchandise==
===Home media===
The film was first released on VHS by [[Embassy Home Entertainment]] in 1984. A [[laserdisc]] of it was later released by [[The Criterion Collection]] in 1986, and was produced by Criterion, Janus Films, and Voyager Press. Included in it was Lamorisse's award-winning short ''[[White Mane]]'' (1953). A DVD version became available in 2008, and a [[Blu-ray]] version was released in the United Kingdom on January 18, 2010; it has now been confirmed as region-free.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.janusfilms.com/redandwhite/|title=The Red Balloon &amp; White Mane|website=www.janusfilms.com|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Red Balloon / The White Mane Blu-ray|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/The-Red-Balloon-Blu-ray-Review/6245/|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Book===
A tie-in book was first published by [[Doubleday Books]], (now [[Penguin Random House]]), in 1957, using black and white and color stills from the film, with added prose. It was highly acclaimed and went on to win 'A New York Times Best Illustrated Children's Book of the Year.' Albert Lamorisse was credited as its sole author.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/97392/the-red-balloon-by-albert-lamorisse/9781101935217/|title=The Red Balloon by Albert Lamorisse|website=PenguinRandomhouse.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soundtrack===
A soundtrack, featuring music adapted from the film by Lamorisse, was released on the [[Nonesuch Records]] label.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{IMDb title|0048980|The Red Balloon}}
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|red_balloon|The Red Balloon}}
* {{tcmdb title|344209|The Red Balloon}}
* [http://www.janusfilms.com/redandwhite/ ''The Red Balloon''] at [[Janus Films]] (official web site)
* [http://www.dvdbeaver.com/film2/dvdreviews36/the_red_balloon.htm ''The Red Balloon''] information site and DVD/Blue-ray review at DVD Beaver (includes images)
* [http://www.cinefeed.com/index.php/2006/10/22/44-le-ballon-rouge-premiers-souvenirs-cine  ''Le Ballon rouge''] at ''Cinefeed'' {{in lang|fr}}

{{Short Film Palme d'Or Winners}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Red Balloon, The}}
[[Category:French films]]
[[Category:French-language films]]
[[Category:1950s comedy-drama films]]
[[Category:1950s fantasy films]]
[[Category:French comedy-drama films]]
[[Category:French fantasy films]]
[[Category:French short films]]
[[Category:Balloons (entertainment)]]
[[Category:1950s children's fantasy films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Albert Lamorisse]]
[[Category:Films shot in Paris]]
[[Category:Films whose writer won the Best Original Screenplay Academy Award]]
[[Category:Louis Delluc Prize winners]]
[[Category:Short Film Palme d'Or winners]]
[[Category:1956 comedy films]]
[[Category:1956 drama films]]</text>
      <sha1>n3bp7hob9tsmiy3766ta4zf8bpkiqge</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
