<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hollywood and Vine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>255650</id>
    <revision>
      <id>950988283</id>
      <parentid>950988084</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-14T22:17:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Philip Cross</username>
        <id>124152</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Redevelopment and urbanization */ ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11923" xml:space="preserve">{{Update|part=[[#Redevelopment_and_urbanization|Redevelopment and urbanization]], which mentions buildings completed ten years ago as under construction or planned.|date=September 2019}}
{{other uses}}
{{Infobox road junction
| country       = USA
| state         = CA
| name          = Hollywood and Vine
| image         = File:Hollywood and Vine.png
| image_caption = The famous Hollywood and Vine street signs have appeared in thousands of tourist and professional photographs
| maint         = [[Los Angeles County Department of Public Works|City of Los Angeles Department of Public Works]]
| location      = [[Intersection]]
| coord         = {{Coord|34.101598|N|118.326657|W|region:US-CA|display=inline,title}}
| roads         = [[Hollywood Boulevard]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Vine Street]]
| type          = [[Intersection (road)|Intersection]]
| const         =
| opened        = 1887 (as Prospect and Weyse)&lt;br/&gt;1910 (as Hollywood and Vine)
| height        =
| other_names   = Prospect and Weyse Avenues (1887–1910)
|mapframe-zoom=16
}}
[[File:Hollywood and Vine Sign, Hollywood, LA, CA, jjron 21.03.2012.jpg|thumb|The Hollywood and Vine intersection has become iconic]]
'''Hollywood and Vine''', the intersection of [[Hollywood Boulevard]] and [[Vine Street]] in [[Hollywood]], a district of [[Los Angeles]], became known in the 1920s for its concentration of radio and movie-related businesses. The [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] is centered on the intersection.

Few production facilities are still located in the immediate area.  One of the few remaining is the [[Capitol Records Building|Capitol Records Tower]] to the north of the intersection.

The [[Hollywood/Vine (LACMTA station)|namesake subway station]] for the [[LACMTA Red Line|Metro Red Line]] is located directly below the intersection, but the entrance/exit to the station is located one block east at Hollywood and Argyle Avenue. The intersection is located in [[ZIP code]] 90028.

==History==
[[File:Hollywood&amp;Vine-1907.jpg|right|thumb|The intersection of Hollywood and Vine (looking north) in 1907 showed only farmland]]
The area was a [[lemon]] grove until 1903, when [[Daeida Wilcox Beveridge|Daeida Beveridge]] allowed one corner of the dirt intersection on her property to be used for the building of the Hollywood Memorial Church for the local German Methodist population.

The historical marker plaque placed at the site by The Broadway-Hollywood Department Store and the Board of Supervisors of the County of Los Angeles reads:

{{quote|Hollywood was given its name by pioneers Mr. and Mrs. Horace H. Wilcox. They subdivided their ranch in 1887 and called two dirt cross-roads Prospect Avenue and Weyse Avenue. Prospect Avenue, the main artery, was renamed Hollywood Boulevard and Weyse Avenue became Vine Street. This was the origin of "Hollywood and Vine."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earthsignals.com/Collins/0015/0010_1.jpg|title=Image of historical marker plaque|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The streets were renamed in 1910, when the town of Hollywood was annexed by the City of [[Los Angeles]].

Beginning in the 1920s, during the [[Golden Age of Hollywood]], the area began to see an influx of money and influence as movie and music businesses began to move to the district, turning the local farms and orchards into movie [[backlot]]s. Hollywood and Vine was the second busiest intersection in the area, after [[Wilshire Boulevard]] and [[Western Avenue (Los Angeles)|Western Avenue]].&lt;ref name=Pool&gt;Pool, Bob. "[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-thenandnow4-2008may04,0,2431816.story Turning the corner at Hollywood and Vine]" ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'',
May 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1930s, radio programs such as [[KFWB]] and the [[CBS]] ''[[Lux Radio Theater]]'' spoke of "broadcasting live from Hollywood and Vine," and newspaper columnists [[Hedda Hopper]] and [[Jimmie Fidler]] regularly touted the intersection's mystique.&lt;ref name=Pool /&gt;

In 1958, the intersection became the central point of the newly installed [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]. Later [[Neil Armstrong]], [[Buzz Aldrin]] and [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]], the astronauts of the first lunar landing mission [[Apollo 11]], were awarded television stars for coverage of the mission, and given the places of honor at the exact corners of Hollywood and Vine.

By the 1960s, however, many studios and broadcasters had moved onto more upscale areas, and the area fell into disrepair and disrepute, with many abandoned stores and offices, and the streets themselves, claimed by [[squatting|squatters]] and [[begging|panhandlers]]. It took several decades for redevelopment to take hold, and visitors looking for Hollywood dreams were often taken aback by the area's contrast with shinier tourist meccas.

The Hollywood/Vine subway station opened in 1999, and led to more sustained and serious redevelopment in the area. On May 29, 2003, Hollywood and Vine was named "Bob Hope Square" to commemorate [[Bob Hope|Hope]]'s 100th birthday.

In [[urban folklore]], many of the local buildings are considered to be part of "Haunted Hollywood", home to the ghosts of celebrities (and less stellar residents) of Hollywood's legendary past. The intersection has been mentioned or alluded to in dozens of songs, films, video games, music videos and other popular media, often as a symbol of Hollywood's lure as a destination for dreamers, or for its decadence and disappointments.&lt;ref name=Pool /&gt;

===Historic buildings===
[[File:Taft Bldg.png|thumb|125px|left|The Taft Building is where many of [[Charlie Chaplin]]'s films were conceived and written.]]
[[File:20161005 Broadway Hollywood Building from Hollywood and Vine (2).jpg|thumb|left|The [[Broadway Hollywood Building]] at the southwest corner]]
The first "high-rise" building at Hollywood and Vine was the 12-story [[Taft Building (Los Angeles)|Taft Building]], built in 1923 on the southeast corner on the site of the old Memorial Church. It was built for A.Z. Taft Jr. by architects [[Walker &amp; Eisen]], in the [[Neo-Renaissance|Renaissance Revival]] style. "In Hollywood's golden age, all the studios had offices there," said Hollywood Chamber of Commerce President Leron Gubler,&lt;ref name=Pool /&gt; including [[Charlie Chaplin]] and [[Will Rogers]]. From 1935 to 1945, it was home to the [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] offices.
[[File:CapitolRecords.jpg|thumb|[[Capitol Records Building]] viewed from the intersection, 1997]]
On the northwest corner, the [[Laemmle Building]] was built in the [[International style (architecture)|International Style]] in 1932 by architect [[Richard Neutra]] for [[Carl Laemmle]], head of [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]]. Unfortunately, the original drawing depicting the design that Neutra intended was not built because of the [[Wall Street Crash of 1929|1929 stock market crash]]. It was significantly altered from 1940, and retained few of its original features. The building was gutted by fire in April 2008, and razed in October 2008. To the west of the Laemmle Building is another landmark International Style building, by Neutra's friend and rival [[Rudolph Schindler (architect)|Rudolf Schindler]]. The building was originally known for Sardi's Diner, and is now home to the Cave Theater.

To the north of the Laemmle Building is a Spanish Colonial style building housing the [[Avalon Hollywood]], opened on January 24, 1927, as the Hollywood Playhouse and designed by the architectural firm of [[H. L. Gogerty]] and [[Carl Jules Weyl]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historicla.com/hollywood/block10.html#anchor412339|title=Historic L.A.|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The building's name has changed many times over the 20th century, but was known as the Hollywood Palace for many years before its most recent renaming.
[[File:Hollywood, Ca.-The Equitable Building of Hollywood-1930.jpg|thumb|250px|Equitable Building of Hollywood]]
On the northeast corner of Hollywood and Vine is the [[Equitable Building (Hollywood)|Equitable Building]], a Gothic Deco commercial tower built in 1929 on the northeast corner, designed by Aleck Curlett. Next to it is the [[Art Deco]] movie house, the [[Pantages Theatre (Hollywood)|Pantages Theatre]], built in 1930 by B. Marcus Priteca—the first of its kind in the United States. The [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] ceremonies were held at the Pantages from 1949 to 1959.

On the southwest corner, the B.H. Dyas building was built in 1927 by architect Frederick Rice Dorn. The B.H Dyas Specialty Emporium was a victim of the depression. From 1931 to 1982 it housed [[The Broadway (Department Stores)|The Broadway-Hollywood]] [[department store]]. The sign is a historical landmark and remains. In 2007, the [[Broadway Hollywood Building]] underwent extensive reconstruction and has opened as a luxury class apartment building. The building has an art deco style annex just to the west of it built in the 1930s. (1943). In 1927, while researching ''The Skyscraper'' for DeMille Studios, [[Ayn Rand]] visited the building and, while waiting for her contact to arrive, went to the nearby Hollywood Branch Library, where she was reunited with Frank O'Connor, whom she had lost track of 6 months earlier when DeMille's ''The King of Kings'' finished shooting; Rand and O'Connor then began dating, were married in 1929 until his death in 1979.

Just to the south on Vine was the fabled [[Hollywood Plaza Hotel]], built in 1924 and home to [[silent film]] star [[Clara Bow]]'s "It Cafe". Across the street, the Hollywood [[Brown Derby]] restaurant, the second in the chain, opened in 1929 in a Spanish Colonial Revival building designed for [[Cecil B. DeMille]]; it was demolished in 1994, leaving only a part of the Derby facade, which itself was threatened with demolition as of April 2006. Farther south on Vine were the original [[Famous Players-Lasky|Lasky]]-[[Paramount Pictures|Paramount Studios]], later [[NBC]]'s West coast studios; and [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC's]] first West coast studios.

== Redevelopment and urbanization ==
[[File:20161005 Hollywood and Vine historical marker.jpg|thumb|left|At the base of the [[Broadway Hollywood Building]] is a historical designation plaque for the Hollywood and Vine intersection]]
A number of high-profile projects are attempting to restore the lost luster of the area. As of May 2007, major renovations announced by the Los Angeles city council, began construction on the intersection, developments expected to cost upwards of $600-million. The new projects call for a 305-room [[W Hotels|W Hotel]] tower with 143 adjoining condominiums. Also part of the plan for the southeast corner of the intersection, 375 luxury apartments, restaurants, a nightclub, stores and a spa, as well as retail renovations of the Pantages Theater, similar to the [[Hollywood and Highland]] Center a mile down the Boulevard. Expected completion date is November 2009.

Two other large projects are Palisades Development Group's $50-million conversion of the former Equitable office building to condominiums and Kor Group's $70-million conversion of the former Broadway department store, also into condos.

==Basque Nightclub fire==
On April 30, 2008, a large fire destroyed the Basque Nightclub at Hollywood and Vine. It required the calling of 23 fire engines.&lt;ref name=Pool /&gt; This destroyed the historic Laemmle building.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Hollywood and Vine}}
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
* [http://www.hollywoodbid.org Hollywood Entertainment District]
* [http://www.seeing-stars.com/Streets/HollywoodBlvdMyth&amp;Reality.shtml Hollywood Boulevard - myth &amp; reality]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050404050109/http://www.historicla.com/hollywood/block08.html Historic Resources Group - Historic LA Project]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hollywood And Vine}}
[[Category:Hollywood history and culture]]
[[Category:Hollywood]]
[[Category:Hollywood Boulevard]]</text>
      <sha1>55cc997jsa6obulabomjrq6fjbg5l33</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
