<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chrisann Brennan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45092623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>954659932</id>
      <parentid>954635960</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-03T16:30:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.33.175.176</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 954635960 by [[Special:Contributions/2003:F1:ABD3:5700:C4DB:DF99:9A4F:A203|2003:F1:ABD3:5700:C4DB:DF99:9A4F:A203]] ([[User talk:2003:F1:ABD3:5700:C4DB:DF99:9A4F:A203|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="22996" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Short description|American biographer}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{BLP primary sources|date=September 2017}}
{{Overly detailed|date=November 2015}}
}}

{{Infobox writer &lt;!--For more information, see [[:Template:Infobox Writer/doc]].--&gt;
| name         = Chrisann Brennan
| image        = 
| image_size   = 
| alt          = 
| caption      = 
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1954|9|29}}
| birth_place  = [[Dayton, Ohio]], U.S.
| death_place  = 
| occupation   = Painter
| nationality  = American
| notableworks = ''[[The Bite in the Apple]]'' (memoir)
| partner      = [[Steve Jobs]]
| children     = [[Lisa Brennan-Jobs]]
| website      = 
| portaldisp   = &lt;!-- "on", "yes", "true", etc; or omit --&gt;
}}

'''Chrisann Brennan''' (born September 29, 1954)&lt;ref name=bite&gt;{{cite book |last=Brennan |first=Chrisann |date= |title=[[The Bite in the Apple|THE BITE IN THE APPLE:A Memoir of My Life with Steve Jobs]] |url= |location= |publisher=St. Martin's Griffin |page=ebook |isbn= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an American painter&lt;ref name="menlo"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://inmenlo.com/2013/04/08/artist-chrisann-brennan-describes-her-art-as-light-encoded-paintings/
|title=Artist Chrisann Brennan describes her art as "light encoded paintings"|accessdate=January 19, 2015|last=Gulker|first=Linda|date=April 8, 2013|publisher=InMenlo}}&lt;/ref&gt; and writer. She is the author of ''[[The Bite in the Apple]]'',&lt;ref name="pens"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mercurynews.com/business/ci_24414122/steve-jobs-ex-describes-coping-mercurial-apple-genius|title=Steve Jobs' ex describes coping with the mercurial Apple genius|accessdate=January 17, 2015|last=Nakaso|first=Dan|date=October 29, 2013|publisher=San Jose Mercury}}&lt;/ref&gt; an autobiography about her relationship with [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] co-founder [[Steve Jobs]]. They had one child, [[Lisa Brennan-Jobs]]. 

==Early life==
Brennan was born in [[Dayton, Ohio]], in 1954, one of four daughters of James Richard Brennan and Virginia Lavern Rickey. Chrisann was named after the flower [[chrysanthemum]].&lt;ref name=bite/&gt; Brennan notes in her memoir that she is "[[dyslexia|dyslexic]], which has had the effect of making me differently wired, creative, and a voracious problem solver— bright, but more than slightly clueless to convention."&lt;ref name="bite" /&gt;

Her father worked for [[Sylvania (brand)|Sylvania]] and the family lived in a number of places including [[Colorado Springs]] and [[Nebraska]]. They eventually settled in [[Sunnyvale, California]]. Her parents divorced after their move to [[Buffalo, New York]]. Brennan attended [[Homestead High School (Cupertino, California)|Homestead High School]] in [[Cupertino, California]], where she met [[Steve Jobs]] during the early months of 1972.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

==Relationship with Steve Jobs==
Brennan and Jobs's relationship began in 1972 while they were students in high school together.&lt;ref name=bite/&gt;&lt;ref name="JobsBio1"&gt;{{cite book|last=Isaacson|first=Walter | authorlink =Walter Isaacson|title=[[Steve Jobs (book)|Steve Jobs]]|year=2011|isbn= |page=ebook|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Brennan remained involved with Jobs while he was at [[Reed College]].&lt;ref name="JobsBio1"/&gt; Brennan (who was now a senior at Homestead High School) did not have plans to attend college, and was supportive of Jobs when he told her he planned to drop out of Reed. He continued to attend by auditing classes, but Brennan stopped visiting him. Jobs later asked her to come and live with him in a house he rented near the Reed campus, but she refused. He had started seeing other women, and she was interested in someone she met in her art class. Brennan speculates that the house was Jobs' attempt to make their relationship monogamous again.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

In mid-1973, Jobs moved back to the [[San Francisco Bay Area]]. Brennan states by this point that their "relationship was complicated. I couldn't break the connection and I couldn't commit. Steve couldn't either." Jobs hitchhiked and worked around the West Coast and Brennan would occasionally join him. At the same time, Brennan notes, "little by little, Steve and I separated. But we were never able to fully let go. We never talked about breaking up or going our separate ways and we didn't have that conversation where one person says it's over." They continued to grow apart, but Jobs would still seek her out, and visit her. They remained involved with each other while continuing to see other people.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

By early 1974, Jobs was living what Brennan describes as a "simple life" in a [[Los Gatos, California|Los Gatos]] cabin, working at [[Atari]], and saving money for [[Hippie trail|his impending trip]] to [[India]]. Brennan visited him twice at the cabin. Brennan's memories of this cabin consist of Jobs reading ''[[Be Here Now (book)|Be Here Now]]'' (and giving her a copy), listening to [[South Indian culture#Music|South Indian]] music, and using a Japanese meditation pillow. Brennan felt that he was more distant and negative towards her. Brennan states in her memoir that she met with Jobs right before he left for India and that he tried to give her $100 that he had earned at Atari. She initially refused to accept it but eventually accepted the money.&lt;ref name="bite2"&gt;"The morning of the day Steve left for India he came to my house to say good-bye and to give me a $ 100 bill. He had made a bit of money at Atari and he just wanted to give me this gift. I hadn't seen him in a while and was standing with my new boyfriend at the entrance to the apartment when Steve walked up. Steve touched my forehead to indicate that I was his, which I found outrageous. When I objected to the money, Steve demanded I not play the game of rejecting it. Steve was nothing if not ceremonial in his passages and this money was about him, not me, so I took it and thanked him." In {{cite book |last=Brennan |first=Chrisann |date= |title=[[The Bite in the Apple|THE BITE IN THE APPLE:A Memoir of My Life with Steve Jobs]] |url= |location= |publisher=St. Martin's Griffin |page=ebook |isbn= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Brennan graduated from high school Jobs invited her to come and see him at the [[Robert Friedland#Early life and education|All One Farm]], a [[History of the hippie movement#New Communalism|commune]] in [[Oregon]]. While she did not spend much time with Jobs (who was recovering from an illness), Brennan was deeply influenced by the experience of meeting and working with the people that she met there.&lt;ref name="bite" /&gt;

In early 1975, Brennan became involved with a [[Zen]] Buddhist community in Los Altos, where she accidentally bumped into Jobs (whom she had not seen since the All One Farm). It was through this community that they would both meet and work with the Zen master [[Kōbun Chino Otogawa|Kobun]]. Jobs and Brennan began to spend more time together, although she noted that his behavior with her was more aloof than in the past. Brennan notes their lives were on different paths as she was deeply involved in her art program at [[Foothill College]] where she studied under Gordon Holler&lt;ref name="menlo"/&gt; while Jobs was working with "[[Kōbun Chino Otogawa|Kobun]] and [[Steve Wozniak|Woz]]."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt; She also fell in love with Greg Calhoun (Jobs' former Reed classmate) who had come to visit from the All One Farm.&lt;ref name="JobsBio1"/&gt; Brennan moved to the All One Farm and lived for a while with Calhoun in a renovated chicken coop. They eventually moved back to the Bay Area to earn money for [[Hippie trail|a trek to India]]. Jobs helped them find a home to rent, though he was opposed to their traveling together to India. After Brennan and Calhoun had earned enough money to go, Jobs drove them to the airport and gave them advice about how to survive in India. Brennan traveled for a year through India with Calhoun, though their relationship ended by the time she returned to the United States.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;&lt;ref name="JobsBio1"/&gt;

==Apple (1977)==
After her return from India, Brennan visited Jobs, whom she now considered just a friend, at his parents' home, where he was still living. It was during this period that Jobs and Brennan fell in love again, as Brennan noted changes in him that she attributes to [[Kōbun Chino Otogawa]], whom she was also still following. It was also at this time that Jobs displayed a prototype [[Apple I|Apple computer]] for Brennan and his parents in their living room. Brennan notes a shift in this time period, where the two main influences on Jobs were [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] and Kobun. By the early 1977, she and Jobs would spend time together at her home at [[Hidden Villa|Duveneck Ranch in Los Altos]], which served as a hostel and environmental education center. Brennan also worked there as a teacher for inner city children who came to learn about the farm.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

As Jobs and Apple became more successful, his relationship with Brennan grew more complex. In 1977 Brennan, [[Daniel Kottke]], and Jobs moved into a house near the Apple office in [[Cupertino, California|Cupertino]]. Brennan notes that Jobs wanted the three of them to live together because, "Steve told me that he didn't want to get a house with just the two of us because it felt insufficient to him. Steve wanted his buddy Daniel to live with him because he believed it would break up the intensity of what wasn't working between us. Our relationship was running hot and cold. We were completely crazy about each other and utterly bored in turns. I had suggested to Steve that we separate, but he told me that he just couldn't bring himself to say good-bye." In addition, Jobs initially suggested that all three of them each have separate rooms. They were still involved with each other, but even then Brennan states that in her memory of the time, "I recalled how awful he was becoming and how I was starting to flounder."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt; When she moved into the house, she had initially planned to commit to becoming an artist. However, she also needed to find work and eventually took a position at Apple in the Shipping Department (where she was part of a team that tested, assembled, and shipped [[Apple II]]s with Mark Johnson and Bob Martinengo whom she enjoyed working with).&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;&lt;ref name="standingphoto"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/pictures-of-apples-first-employees-2013-12|title=These Pictures Of Apple's First Employees Are Absolutely Wonderful
|accessdate=January 19, 2015|last=Edwards|first=Jim|date=December 26, 2013|publisher=Business Insider
}}&lt;/ref&gt; She also took art classes at nearby [[De Anza College]].&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

Brennan's relationship with Jobs was deteriorating as his position with Apple grew and she began to consider ending the relationship. In October 1977, Brennan was approached by Apple employee #5, [[Rod Holt]], who asked her to take "a paid apprenticeship designing blueprints for the Apples." Both Holt and Jobs felt that it would be a good position for her, given her artistic abilities. Brennan's decision, however, was overshadowed by the fact that she realized she was pregnant and that Jobs was the father. It took her a few days to tell Jobs, whose face, according to Brennan "turned ugly" at the news.  According to Brennan, at the beginning of her third trimester, Jobs said to her: "I never wanted to ask that you get an abortion. I just didn't want to do that."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt; He also refused to discuss the pregnancy with her.&lt;ref name="JobsBio1"/&gt; Brennan, herself, felt confused about what to do. She was estranged from her mother and afraid to discuss the matter with her father. She also did not feel comfortable with the idea of having an abortion. She chose instead to discuss the matter with Kobun, who encouraged her to have and keep the baby as he would lend his support. Meanwhile, Holt was waiting for her decision on the internship. Brennan states that Jobs continued to encourage her to take the internship, stating that she could "be pregnant and work at Apple, you can take the job. I don't get what the problem is." Brennan however notes that she "felt so ashamed: the thought of my growing belly in the professional environment at Apple, with the child being his, while he was unpredictable, in turn being punishing and sentimentally ridiculous. I could not have endured it." Brennan thus turned down the internship and decided to leave Apple. She states that Jobs told her "If you give up this baby for adoption, you will be sorry" and "I am never going to help you."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

==Lisa Brennan-Jobs==
Now alone, Brennan was on welfare and cleaning houses to earn money. She would sometimes ask Jobs for money but he always refused. Brennan hid her pregnancy for as long as she could, living in a variety of homes, and continuing her work with Zen meditation. At the same time, according to Brennan, Jobs "started to seed people with the notion that I slept around and he was infertile, which meant that this could not be his child." A few weeks before she was due, Brennan was invited to have her baby at the All One Farm in Oregon and Brennan accepted the offer.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

At the age of 23, Brennan gave birth to her daughter, [[Lisa Brennan-Jobs|Lisa Brennan]], on May 17, 1978.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/oct/15/steve-jobs-chrisann-brennan-memoir-apple|title=Steve Jobs' ex-girlfriend pens memoir on life with 'vicious' Apple founder|accessdate=January 17, 2015|last=Metz|first=Rachel
|date=October 15, 2013|publisher=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jobs initially did not come for the birth. He eventually did so after he was contacted by [[Robert Friedland]], their mutual friend and owner of the All One Farm. While distant, Jobs worked with her on a name for the baby. Brennan suggested the name "Lisa" and notes that Jobs was very attached to the name "Lisa" while he "was also publicly denying paternity." She would discover later that Jobs was preparing to unveil a new kind of computer that he wanted to give a female name. She states that she never gave him permission to use the baby's name for a computer and he hid the plans from her. Jobs also worked with his team to come up with the phrase, "Local Integrated Software Architecture" as an alternative explanation for the [[Apple Lisa]]&lt;ref name="Bullock"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.minyanville.com/special-features/articles/lisa-brennan-jobs-business-icons-rich/8/31/2010/id/29768|archiveurl= |title= The Kids of Business Icons: Lisa Brennan-Jobs |last=Bullock |first= Diane |date=August 31, 2010|archivedate= |work=[[Minyanville]] |pages=|accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (decades later, however, Jobs admitted to his biographer [[Walter Isaacson]] that "obviously, it was named for my daughter"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Isaacson|first=Walter|authorlink=Walter Isaacson|title=[[Steve Jobs (book)|Steve Jobs]]|year=2011|isbn=1-4516-4853-7|page=[https://archive.org/details/stevejobs00isaa/page/93 93]|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

Brennan did explore adoption both before and after Lisa's birth but ultimately decided to become a single parent. Once, while staying with friends in the Bay Area, Jobs stopped by to see her. Brennan states that they went for a walk when Jobs said to her, "I am really sorry. I'll be back, this thing with Apple will be over when I'm about thirty. I am really, really sorry." Around the same time, she met with Kobun who distanced himself from her and did not fulfill his promise to help her once the baby was born.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

Brennan would come under intense criticism from Jobs, who claimed that "she doesn't want money, she just wants me." According to Brennan, Apple's [[Michael Scott (Apple)|Mike Scott]] wanted Jobs to give her money, while other Apple executives "advised him to ignore me or fight if I tried to go after a paternity settlement." Brennan also notes that later, after Jobs was forced out of Apple, "he apologized many times over for this behavior. He said that he never took responsibility when he should have and that he was sorry."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt; By this time, Jobs had developed a strong relationship with Lisa, who wanted her name changed{{clarify|date=November 2016}} and Jobs agreed. So he had her name on her birth certificate changed from Lisa Brennan to Lisa Brennan-Jobs.&lt;ref name="bitecert"&gt;"Fast-forward six years when Lisa was nine, after she and her father had grown to know and love each other … It was in that window of time that Steve and Lisa decided to get her birth certificate straightened out. At nine, Lisa went from Lisa Brennan to Lisa Brennan-Jobs. Steve told me that he could hardly believe that she wanted to take his name. Very plainly relieved and honest, he said, 'I am just so happy that she does' … William Fenwick of Fenwick &amp; West was the lawyer Steve used to fact-check and change the birth certificate." In {{cite book |last=Brennan |first=Chrisann |date= |title=[[The Bite in the Apple|THE BITE IN THE APPLE:A Memoir of My Life with Steve Jobs]] |url= |location= |publisher=St. Martin's Griffin |page=ebook |isbn= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Lisa was a baby and Jobs continued to deny paternity, a [[DNA paternity testing|DNA paternity test]] was given that established him as Lisa's father. He was required to give Brennan $385 a month and return the money she had received from welfare. Jobs gave her $500 a month at the time when Apple went public, and Jobs became a millionaire. Brennan worked as a waitress in [[Palo Alto, California|Palo Alto]]. Later, Brennan agreed to give an interview with [[Michael Moritz]] for ''[[Time (magazine)|Time Magazine]].'' It would be for its 1982 [[Time Person of the Year]] special (released on January 3, 1983). She decided to be honest about her relationship with Jobs. The ''Time'' magazine issue had a lifelong impact on Brennan. Rather than give Jobs the "Person of the Year" award, ''Time'' offered the award of "Machine of the Year: The Computer Moves In."&lt;ref&gt;''Machine of the Year: The Computer Moves in.'' [[Time (magazine)|Time Magazine]]'', January 3, 1983&lt;/ref&gt; In the issue, Jobs questioned the reliability of the paternity test (which stated that the "probability of paternity for Jobs, Steven... is 94.1%").&lt;ref name="machineofthe year1"&gt;Cocks Jay. Reported by Michael Moritz. "[http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,953633,00.html The Updated Book of Jobs]" in ''Machine of the Year: The Computer Moves in.'' [[Time (magazine)|Time Magazine]]'', January 3, 1983:27.&lt;/ref&gt; Jobs responded by arguing that "28% of the male population of the United States could be the father."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;&lt;ref name="machineofthe year1"/&gt; ''Time'' also noted that "the baby girl and the machine on which Apple has placed so much hope for the future share the same name: Lisa."&lt;ref name="machineofthe year1"/&gt; After this issue, Brennan "didn't pay much attention to Steve's career again."&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;''

Over the years, however, Brennan and Jobs developed a working relationship to co-parent Lisa, particularly after he was forced out of Apple. Brennan credits the change in him to the influence of his newly found biological sister, [[Mona Simpson]], who worked to repair the relationship between Lisa and Jobs.&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

According to ''[[Fortune (magazine)|Fortune]]'', Brennan wrote a letter to Jobs in 2005, and another in 2009, in which she said she would abandon writing her memoirs if Jobs would supply her with financial compensation of US$28 million for the suffering she went through as a single mother.&lt;ref name=Fortune2015-08-06&gt;{{cite news|url = http://fortune.com/2015/08/06/steve-jobs-apple-girlfriend/|title = When Steve Jobs' ex-girlfriend asked him to pay $25 million for his "dishonorable behavior"|publisher = [[Fortune Magazine]]|date = August 5, 2015|author = Peter Elkind|accessdate = November 1, 2015|quote = In his estate, Jobs left their daughter a multi-million-dollar inheritance, which Lisa has used to help support her, according to Brennan.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Painter==
During the late 1980s, Brennan decided to finish her formal education and began to study at the [[California College of the Arts|California College of Arts and Crafts]] (where she was able to transfer her units from [[Foothill College]]).&lt;ref name="menlo"/&gt; She asked Jobs to pay her tuition. He agreed to this request and according to Brennan was quite happy to do so, as part of his developing relationship with Lisa. In 1989, she transferred to the [[San Francisco Art Institute]].&lt;ref name="bite"/&gt;

Brennan has lived in [[Monterey, California]] while working as a professional painter.&lt;ref name="bite" /&gt; She describes her art as "light encoded paintings" and works mostly on commission for either private or corporate parties.&lt;ref name="menlo"/&gt; She has also created murals for the [[Ronald McDonald House Charities|Ronald McDonald House]], [[LAC+USC Medical Center|Los Angeles County Hospital]], [[Massachusetts General Hospital|Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.paloaltoonline.com/weekly/morgue/listings/1997_Aug_15.SPOT15.html
|title=Spotlight: Chrisann Brennan: The painting on the wall|accessdate=January 25, 2015|last=Traugott|first=Elisabeth|date=August 15, 1997|magazine=[[Palo Alto Weekly]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lucile Packard Children's Hospital|Packard Children's Hospital]]. Brennan stated that painting is "a language for me. Letters are form, and paintings are documents for information. When I mix those two, I'm happy. It gets me out of the normal way, which is what I want to do."&lt;ref name="menlo"/&gt;

==Works==
* Brennan, Chrisann. ''[[The Bite in the Apple]].'' New York: St. Martin's Press, 2013.
* Brennan, Chrisann. "[https://web.archive.org/web/20120425233149/http://india.nydailynews.com/article/3ea39bee2a29179c3406250afd01c526/the-steve-jobs-nobody-knew Jobs at 17: Nerd, Poet, Romantic]." [[Rolling Stone Magazine]], October 27, 2011:42. (Scroll down the page)

==Portrayals==
She was portrayed by ''[[Road to Avonlea]]'' 's [[Gema Zamprogna]] in ''[[Pirates of Silicon Valley]]'' and by [[Katherine Waterston]] in ''[[Steve Jobs (film)|Steve Jobs]]''.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Apple celeb}}
{{Steve Jobs}}
{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brennan, Chrisann}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1954 births]]
[[Category:American women painters]]
[[Category:Artists from the San Francisco Bay Area]]
[[Category:Culture of the Pacific Northwest]]
[[Category:Apple Inc. employees]]
[[Category:Steve Jobs]]
[[Category:American women essayists]]
[[Category:American essayists]]
[[Category:People from Sunnyvale, California]]
[[Category:American Zen Buddhists]]
[[Category:Foothill College alumni]]
[[Category:California College of the Arts alumni]]
[[Category:San Francisco Art Institute alumni]]
[[Category:20th-century American women artists]]
[[Category:People with dyslexia]]
[[Category:21st-century American women artists]]</text>
      <sha1>mfjofznxkshj26xsw0s5gmwi6f9t188</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
