<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Irish involvement in the Spanish Civil War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5830557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941100263</id>
      <parentid>941100194</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T16:19:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>73.193.60.39</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Legacy */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9457" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2014}}
[[File:Memorial to Limerick International Brigade.jpg|thumb|Memorial to [[Limerick]] men who fought in the [[International Brigades]], erected outside Limerick City Hall in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thejournal.ie/limerick-spanish-civil-war-1669851-Sep2014/ "Memorial to honour six Limerick men who fought in the Spanish Civil War"], 14 Sept 2014, [[TheJournal.ie]]: (Retrieved 24 April 2016)&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The [[Spanish Civil War]] lasted from July 17, 1936 to April 1, 1939. While both sides in the Spanish Civil War attracted participants from [[Ireland]], the majority sided with the [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|Nationalist faction]].

==Support for the Nationalists==
Feeling in Ireland in the 1930s ran overwhelmingly against the [[Second Spanish Republic]] due to the opposition by the [[Catholic Church]].

Following [[Spanish coup of July 1936|the July coup]] by the generals in Spain a wave of atrocities swept the country on both sides; in Republican Spain the [[Red Terror (Spain)|Red Terror]] was, in part, directed [[Martyrs of the Spanish Civil War|against the Church there]]. Ireland was awash with atrocity stories, leading to proposals to form a crusade to protect the Church and fight against the left-wing Republic. In fact, these atrocities against the Catholic Church -including, convents and schools and student residences- had already begun back in 1931, soon after the inauguration of the 2nd Republic. (See "Quema de conventos 1931").

''In Ireland the issue was presented in stark contrasts. Intermediate shades received little toleration. The Catholic church, arguably coming to the height of its conservatism, portrayed the war as a struggle between Christ and anti-Christ. Religion was under attack. Christian civilisation was mortally imperilled by the poison of communism. Innumerable sermons dinned home the dubious tenet that whatever opposed the onrush of communism was good. A joint pastoral of the Irish bishops firmly supported Franco.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=They Have Fooled You Again: Michael O'Flanagan (1876-1942) Priest, Republican, Social Critic|last=Carroll|first=Denis|publisher=Columba Press|year=2016|isbn=978-1782183006|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Encouraged by the Church hierarchy, [[Eoin O'Duffy]], leader of the fascist [[National Corporate Party|NCP]], started to recruit a brigade of Irish volunteers to fight in Spain in defence of the church. By late 1936 some 7,000 men had volunteered, of whom about 700 were selected, and in November 1936 these sailed to Spain, where they became the ''XV Bandera'' (battalion) of the [[Spanish Foreign Legion]], or "[[Irish Brigade (Spanish Civil War)|Irish Brigade]]".

However, the Brigade became something of a political football: Franco was at first keen to have it, as a way of cementing control over the ''[[Requetes]]'', the catholic monarchist militia of [[Navarre]], but once this was achieved the brigades presence was at odds with the Nationalists emphasis on "Spanishness". On the other hand, O'Duffy's purpose for the Brigade was not so much to support Spain as to enhance his own reputation in Ireland, and restore his political fortunes there.

Militarily the Brigade achieved little; in its first action, near [[Ciempozuelos]] in February 1937, the Brigade was involved in a [[friendly fire]] incident with a [[Falangist]] unit while advancing to the front. Four brigaders and 13 Falangists were killed in the exchange of fire.&lt;ref&gt;Othen p117&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after, at Titulcia in March 1937 the Brigade refused to advance after taking casualties and was withdrawn.&lt;ref&gt;Othen p119&lt;/ref&gt; Later, months of inactivity in a quiet sector sapped morale and saw an erosion of discipline; the unit was finally sent home in July 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Othen p160&lt;/ref&gt;

==Support for the Spanish Republic==
Support for the [[Second Spanish Republic|Spanish Republic]] was organized through various left wing organizations, though it was limited by the actions in Spain against the Catholic Church. [[Harry Midgley]], the leader of the [[Northern Ireland Labour Party|NILP]], spoke out against Franco, but lost support amongst his constituents and in 1938 his seat in the Northern Ireland parliament because of this.&lt;ref&gt;Bardon, Jonathan, A History of Ulster, 199&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1936 a decision was made in Paris by the Third [[Communist International]] to form an [[International Brigade]] of volunteers to fight with the Republicans.
Recruiting in Ireland was organised by the [[Communist Party of Ireland]]: Chief organizers of this effort were [[Sean Murray (politician)|Sean Murray]], [[Peadar O'Donnell]], and [[Frank Ryan (Irish republican)|Frank Ryan]].
In all 320 Irish men served with the International Brigades, a quarter of whom were killed in action.  
Some were involved with underground unions, some were opposed to O'Duffy's [[Blueshirts]] and [[Greenshirts (National Corporate Party)|Greenshirts]] in Ireland, while others believed that fascism threatened Ireland.  
One of those was [[Michael O'Riordan]], the future head of the Communist Party of Ireland.
O'Riordan took part in all the battles of the 15th International Brigade in support of the [[Spanish Republican Army]], including the [[Battle of the Ebro]], at which he was wounded.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1519535/Michael-ORiordan.html   Michael-O'Riordan],  [[Daily Telegraph]] (London) 27 May 2006. Retrieved 24 April 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1936 Frank Ryan travelled to Spain with about 80 men to fight in the [[International Brigades]] on the Republican side. Ryan's men are sometimes referred to as the "[[Connolly Column]]".&lt;ref&gt;O'Riordan p55&lt;/ref&gt;
As part of the [[XV International Brigade]] the Connollys fought in the battles of 
[[Battle of Jarama|Jarama]], [[Battle of Brunete|Brunete]] and [[Battle of Belchite (1937)|Belchite]] in 1937, and at [[Battle of Teruel|Teruel]], [[Battle of Gandesa|Gandesa]] and [[Battle of the Ebro|the Ebro]] in 1938.

Ryan himself rose to the rank of Brigadier, was seriously wounded in March 1937 at Jarama, and was captured in March 1938 on the Ebro. He was tried and sentenced to death, though this was later commuted to thirty years hard labour in January 1940.

As part of an international agreement, the Spanish republican government called upon the International Brigades to withdraw in 1938.&lt;ref&gt;O'Riordan p134&lt;/ref&gt; The Connollys returned to Ireland, where many were treated as pariahs for their efforts.&lt;ref name=McGarry&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/tv/whodoyouthinkyouare/social_fionnula2.html “Irish Involvement in the Spanish Civil War 1936-39”] rte.ie. Retrieved 24 April 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the death of [[Michael O'Riordan]] in Dublin on 18 May 2006, [[Bob Doyle (activist)|Bob Doyle]] was the last Irishman alive to have fought for the International Brigade until his death on 23 January 2009. Paddy Cochrane (Born 11 March 1913 in Dublin),&lt;ref name=BAND1&gt;{{cite book|title=The Real Band Of Brothers – First hand accounts from the last British survivors of the Spanish Civil War|last=Arthur|first=Max|publisher=Collins|date=2009|isbn=9780007295098|work=Section 8 – Paddy Cochrane, Page 271, reference to Cochrane's place and date of birth}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20091028150204/http://geocities.com/irelandscw/part-CochraneEtc.htm Paddy Cochrane at the Ireland and the Spanish Civil War site]&lt;/ref&gt; who served as a medic, died on 31 March 2011 aged 98, the last Irish non-combatant.

==Legacy==
[[Fearghal McGarry]], writing for [[RTÉ]], has noted:&lt;br /&gt;
"The Spanish Civil War is now remembered in Ireland as a conflict between democracy and fascism rather than Christianity and communism. As a result, the veterans of the International Brigades have gradually come to be regarded as heroes, while the Irish Brigade's crusaders have been forgotten or are reviled as supporters of fascism. Such are the vagaries of history."&lt;ref name=McGarry/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Connolly Column]]
* [[Foreign involvement in the Spanish Civil War]]
* [[Ireland–Spain relations]]
* [[Irish Brigade (Spanish Civil War)]]
* [[Irish Christian Front]] - raised money for the Nationalists - attempted to get the Irish government to officially recognise Franco's regime
* [[Irish Socialist Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War]]
* ''[[Politics (poem)|Politics]]'', a poem by [[W. B. Yeats]]

==Publications==
*McGarry, Fearghal, Irish Politics and the Spanish Civil War, Cork: Cork University Press, 1999. ''{{ISBN|1-85918-239-9}}''
*Stradling, Robert, The Irish and the Spanish Civil War 1936-1939. Crusades in Conflict, Manchester: Manchester University Press, ''{{ISBN|0-7190-5153-3}}''

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* O'Riordan, Michael. ''Connolly Column: The story of the Irishmen who fought for the Spanish Republic 1936–1939''. Dublin: New Books, 1979. ISBN (none)
* Othen, Christopher. ''Franco's International Brigades'', London: Reportage Press, 2008, {{ISBN|978-0-9558302-6-6}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091028112140/http://irelandscw.com/ Ireland and the Spanish Civil War]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091028150411/http://irelandscw.com/ibvol-CollectedED.htm Eugene Downing - Irish veteran of SCW]

{{Spanish Civil War}}

[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Military history of Ireland|Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:History of the Republic of Ireland|Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Ireland–Spain military relations]]</text>
      <sha1>66f6ab0k5wzmrqxcprtbel29h4hozl3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
