<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Eye of Horus</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2750998</id>
    <revision>
      <id>927852900</id>
      <parentid>927851185</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-25T05:08:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>A. Parrot</username>
        <id>839494</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Semi-protected edit request on 25 November 2019 */ Reply</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="28962" xml:space="preserve">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProject Ancient Egypt|class=start|importance=high|religion=yes|religion-importance=top}}

== Horus parentage ==
Issue:  Hathor as mother of Horus.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.180.8.112|68.180.8.112]] ([[User talk:68.180.8.112|talk]]) 18:25, 11 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:According to the Horus article, Hathor was his wife and Isis was his mother. Were there multiple traditions, perhaps? --[[User:Abou Ben Adhem|benadhem]] ([[User talk:Abou Ben Adhem|talk]]) 02:54, 3 February 2009 (UTC)

== I find this statement perplexing: ==
'''yet on the numeration side denoted a decimal system where round off was set to the first 6-terms.'''
Perhaps it can initially be stated that the symbol also had numerical/mathematical uses, and move an expanded (more intelligible) version of the above referenced statement to the section on the numerical use.

== Fractions and the Pyramid Texts ==
It would be really good if the quoted texts could be given accurate citations by the original poster or anyone else who knows where those passages may be found.

[[User:Kay Dekker|Kay Dekker]] 22:41, 25 October 2006 (UTC)
==Consistent spelling==
Can someone please sort our "Wadjet" vs "Wedjat"? I have seen other spellings as well.
--[[User:Hugh7|Hugh7]] 23:16, 1 October 2007 (UTC)
To mix things up, it's also sometimes spelt Udjat.

Truth is, translating a pictoral language to phonetic is difficult at best.  Look at the two main spellings for the capitol of China, Peking and Beijing.  And that is with authentic people still speaking the language today.  Add in the difficulties of a language several thousand years dead....  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/65.169.195.238|65.169.195.238]] ([[User talk:65.169.195.238|talk]]) 13:35, 3 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*Agreed, but this article needs to pick a spelling and stick with it, and save the other spellings for a parenthetical "also spelled as" note. [[Special:Contributions/68.156.95.34|68.156.95.34]] ([[User talk:68.156.95.34|talk]]) 07:08, 21 June 2015 (UTC)

== External links ==

Why does it say "Horus is beastin" in the external links? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/71.202.193.43|71.202.193.43]] ([[User talk:71.202.193.43|talk]]) 08:18, 5 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== See also ==
*Pemmerening, Tanja, "Altagyptische Holmasse Metrologish neu Interpretiert" and relevant phramaceutical and medical knowledge, an abstract,  Phillips-Universtat, Marburg, 8-11-2004, taken from "Die Altagyptschen Hohlmass" in studien zur Altagyptischen Kulture, Beiheft, 10, Hamburg, Buske-Verlag, 2005
I don't know where you found this fragment of a quote, but its absolutely crappy citing. The author should at least have taken the effort to spell it correctly. I can find 10 errors in that without doing background research (and that's without counting the many misrepresentations of the German special characters)

Alright, so I did the background research:
*http://www.aegyptologie-altorientalistik.uni-mainz.de/313.php
*http://www.buske.de/product_info.php?products_id=2601
Not really hard to find. [[UTFG]], for[[cthulhu]]&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;ssake.

I'll put the following in the article.
*Pommerening, Tanja, ''Die altägyptischen Hohlmaße'' (''Studien zur Altägyptischen Kultur'', Beiheft 10), Hamburg, Helmut Buske Verlag, 2005

What I'm leaving out is stuff that seems irrelevant, redundant or just plain wrong to me. However I have no idea about the source itself. I'm just repairing a bad quote. Maybe someone should cross-check the content and its relevance. --[[User:BjKa|BjKa]] 09:03, 20 June 2007 (UTC)

== In arithmetic ==

In this section someone has linked the fractions of the eye to various senses and so on - such as smell - also there are quotes which seem to have nothing to do with the ideas presented.  I would like to know where this comes from - and unless someone can cite a reference then I will delete it.[[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] 09:15, 9 August 2007 (UTC)

== the very first comment is correct in a sense (Eye of Ra discussion)==

The Eye of Ra (The Story of Sekhmet's Fury)
Ra was angry when he heard this, and he was more angry still at the evil deeds which men were doing in disobedience to his laws. So he called together the gods whom he had made - Shu and Tefnut and Geb and Nut - and he also summoned Nun. Soon the gods gathered about Ra in his Secret Place, and the goddesses also. But mankind knew nothing of what was happening, and continued to jeer at Ra and to break his commandments. Then Ra spoke to Nun before the assembled gods: "Eldest of the gods, you who made me; and you gods whom I have made: look upon mankind who came into being at a glance of my Eye. See how men plot against me; hear what they say of me; tell me what I should do to them. For I will not destroy mankind until I have heard what you advise."

hen Nun said: "My son Ra, the god greater than he who made him and mightier than those whom he has created, turn your mighty Eye upon them and send destruction upon them in the form of your daughter, the goddess Sekhmet."

one person can not have 2 mothers and 2 fathers so there for there is a missleading statement RA or THE EYE OF RA (the right eye) was placed on the book of the dead (look it up) due to RA'S destructive nature. HORUS or THE EYE OF HORUS (the left eye) was placed on the book of the living because horus was the god of birth rebirth (movie trivia as well). IF you noticed the eye of ra and the eye of horus are placed in 2 different paterns but yet still have the same shape because the mathmatical fractions of 10. Now the eye of ra aka horus make the right side of the eyes, the left R is the eye of Thoth (its polar oppisite) makes a R there also the eye of Thoth was considered the moon and the eye of ra the solar eye.

not to mention:
the eye of horus : udjat : mother - Isis : father - Osiris
the eye of ra : wedjat : mother - Nun : father - one of the other gods (all in all its the same guy)

the funny thing is that in school the most common one used is the eye of horus but we are told in some pictures that the eye of ra is the eye of horus.

places:
www.phoenixphamily.com/displayarticle303.html
www.themystica.com/mystica/articles/e/eye_of_horus.html
http://www.touregypt.net/featurestories/eyeofhorusandre.htm (&lt;----- a really good one that explains it all)
and some others but i can find them at the moment  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/12.96.54.132|12.96.54.132]] ([[User talk:12.96.54.132|talk]]) 21:01, 14 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


Daisy is pretty much the beez kneez Isn't this sentence --'''The Eye of [[Horus]]''' (originally, '''The Eye of [[Ra]]''') is... -- should be --'''The Eye of [[Horus]]''' (mistakenly known as, '''The Eye of [[Ra]]''') is... -- As far as I know the original is Eye of Horus then many people for various popularity reasons know as Eye of Ra. What do you think? —[[User:Jack in the box|Jack in the box]] 00:37, 25 September 2005 (UTC)

No, it was originally the Eye of Ra for a few centuries, then when Horus and Ra started to amalgamate, becoming Ra-Herakhty (literally meaning "Ra '''who is''' Horus, of the two horizons"), so Horus, as the stronger identity, became the owner of the symbol. Technically, you could say that it is the Eye of Ra-Herakhty, but it was always referred to as Eye of Horus as this was easier to write (and much less long winded than "the Eye of Ra who is Horus of the two horizons"). [[User:-Ril-|&lt;nowiki&gt;~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] ( [[User:-Ril-/BarBoy|!]] | [[User:-Ril-/Temple Bar|?]] | [[User:-Ril-/Nissa|*]] ) 19:50, 3 October 2005 (UTC)

Well, thank you for the info. I didn't know that way. Maybe you should add a few more lines on that paragraph. — [[User:Jack in the box|Jack in the box]] 21:10, 3 October 2005 (UTC)

I would dispute that the eye of Horus was originally the eye of Ra as stated above and in the article - anyone got any evidence for this?  I think they both refer to the sun but I don't recognise the idea that one preceded the other historically - unless someone can substantiate I want to delete this.[[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] 09:09, 9 August 2007 (UTC)

:In my experience, It is my understanding that It came to be known as the Eye of Ra when Ra threw out his eye (Sekhmet), upon mortals who plotted agaist him and she killed them until her vengence filled the earth, and Ra stopped her by trickery, mixing beer and red ochere, to appear to be blood, causing her to drink and become asleep. lol, what you remember from high school. Source: http://www.thekeep.org/~kunoichi/kunoichi/themestream/hathor.html [[User:Sephiroth storm|Sephiroth storm]] 02:50, 7 October 2007 (UTC)

merged by: [[User:Sephiroth storm|Sephiroth storm]] ([[User talk:Sephiroth storm|talk]]) 04:17, 2 July 2008 (UTC)

== I think the eye of Horus symbolises the brain stem. ==

Thats what I have read on some prophecy site. Doesn't mean this detail cannot be taken seriously.
--[[User:N33|N33]] ([[User talk:N33|talk]]) 21:08, 18 January 2008 (UTC)

I think it symbolizes comic strip fumigation; this interpretation is self-evident from the shape.
:Excuse me, but what the hell do you mean by that? :p--[[User:N33|N33]] ([[User talk:N33|talk]]) 06:57, 27 March 2008 (UTC)

I believe what he may be referring to is the symbol's correlation to the glands and inner parts of the human brain as they appear when vivisected in certain ways. http://beforeitsnews.com/mediadrop/uploads/2013/38/d39eedb8fb82baf38d3e00a5df7469db651fc742.jpg
It's a long shot, though. It's probably coincidence. Hieroglyphics look like a lot of things. Then again, the Egyptians were ahead of their times when it came to understanding the human body, so it's possible...just not likely.[[Special:Contributions/98.210.88.228|98.210.88.228]] ([[User talk:98.210.88.228|talk]]) 04:22, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

== Correlations in Other Languages to the Eye of Horus ==

Being that humans traveled around on this big globe, I noticed that in Japanese, "hora" means "look" and then immediately thought of the eye of horus.  I could be stretching it, though I think this would make an interesting addition to the discussion.
[[http://linear.mv.com/cgi-bin/j-e/dosearch?sDict=on&amp;H=PS&amp;L=E&amp;T=look&amp;WC=none&amp;FG=r&amp;BG=b&amp;S=26]]
If anyone has further language correlations (other than arguments regarding Ra vs. Horus), I would love to see them displayed on here!  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.26.58.18|24.26.58.18]] ([[User talk:24.26.58.18|talk]]) 23:29, 12 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Direction of the eye ==

in this article it says that the eye of horus is depicted as the right eye, and that the mirror or left eye is something to do with the moon, but i notice that all but one of the pictures on this page are showing the left eye and not the right.... so i would like to know which way it is supposed to go, and if anyone replys to this could they please include a picture or link to a picture of which way is correct for horus, thanks [[Image: FireFlames.jpg|25px]]&lt;span style="color:purple"&gt;'''[[User:Admiralsith|Any Spelling Mistakes are due to my]] [[Dyslexia]] [[User:Admiralsith|,A.S.]]''' &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk: admiralsith|(Comms)]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 17:50, 14 November 2008 (UTC)
*after leaving this comment i have read this site [http://www.netconstructions.com/horus/eye.html] and would like to direct anyone who wishes to correct this article to it. [[Image: FireFlames.jpg|25px]]&lt;span style="color:purple"&gt;'''[[User:Admiralsith|The Illuminati are coming ,A.S.]]''' &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk: admiralsith|(Comms)]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 18:04, 14 November 2008 (UTC)

This anomaly has not yet been explained or resolved. &lt;span style="color:purple"&gt;'''[[User:Centrepull|The Illuminati have evidently got lost on the way]]''' &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk: Centrepull|(Comms)]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; [[User:Centrepull|Centrepull]] ([[User talk:Centrepull|talk]]) 11:32, 12 September 2010 (UTC)

This is a very good question.  Even the Egyptians themselves seem to either be confused or not to care as you can find examples both ways.  Horus (the ancient sky god version) had two eyes, the right being the sun and the left the moon.  The eye that is injured and healed by Thoth and so on is usually taken to be the left/moon because the phasic nature of the moon can indicate decline (injury) and revival.  The Eye of Ra is always the sun (obviously).  The Eye of Horus is also seen as a kind of vital force (hence Wadjet the 'green one' as green was the colour of freshness and health) and the food offerings are identified with it.  The Eye of Horus is said to 'shine like ra' which makes it like the sun also - so I suppose the answer to left or right has to be based on which function is being addressed.  BTW the website you direct to is no more accurate than the article.[[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] ([[User talk:Apepch7|talk]]) 15:05, 12 September 2010 (UTC)

== Eye of Horus and the senses ==

The article suggests an identification of the fraction portions of the Eye and the five senses but does not give a citation.  Does anyone know where this comes from - its position in the text seems to imply it is from one the mathematical papyri Ebers maybe. [[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] ([[User talk:Apepch7|talk]]) 16:58, 18 June 2009 (UTC)

I still can't find any link between the fractions of the eye and the five senses - also the quotes from the Pyramid Texts don't seem relevant to the assertions of the article in that they don't relate to the senses either but are just quotes from the Reversion of Offerings.  Unless someone knows better I'm going to delete.[[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] ([[User talk:Apepch7|talk]]) 17:30, 28 March 2010 (UTC)

Any progress on this? I did not find any references either. The concept of five senses is so firmly linked to Aristoteles that it seems unlikely to me that they actually showed up in the Middle Kingdom. Hieroglyphs for the senses also do not show any resemblance to fractions of the eye of horus. To be proven or deleted...  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/201.52.148.107|201.52.148.107]] ([[User talk:201.52.148.107|talk]]) 23:46, 19 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I have looked but have been unable to find the source for these ideas.  I suspect it is someone's speculative ideas - not without merit possibly but certainly not proven.  Maybe this section should go?[[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] ([[User talk:Apepch7|talk]]) 08:58, 20 September 2010 (UTC)

Removed the part identifying parts of eye with senses, I have looked for a reference material to support this idea but found none except other websites which repeat this article.  So I think it is someone's speculative idea and not genuinely AE. [[User:Apepch7|Apepch7]] ([[User talk:Apepch7|talk]]) 10:52, 26 September 2010 (UTC)

== Eye of Horus fractions references ==

The [[MathWorld]] entry [http://mathworld.wolfram.com/EyeofHorusFraction.html Eye of Horus Fracttion] has some references which might be of use here. [[User:Paradoctor|Paradoctor]] ([[User talk:Paradoctor|talk]]) 15:45, 15 November 2009 (UTC)

== Hobby? ==

The text says "The eye symbol represents the marking around the eye of the Eurasian Hobby falcon". Isn't it instead a Lanner (Falco biarmicus)? (And rather obviously so!) The lanner is a common resident breeding bird of north Africa including all of Egypt (the hobby is only seen in Egypt on migration between breeding areas north of the of the Mediterranean and wintering areas south of Sahara) and also has the light brownish crown shown on many (most?) images of Horus (often striped - and might be mistaken for an eyebrow by a non-ornithologist) while the crown of the hobby is black. Also note the thinner moustachial stripe (the stripe that goes downward from the eye), the large "rounded" white cheek and the almost unspotted underside (on adult birds - and it is adults that are depicted as juveniles have blue skin around the eye) of the lanner which agrees with images of Horus. It should also be noted that the lanner is one of the species most frequently used for falconry (which the smaller hobby never is) and thus have a long relationship to man (according to http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falconry it might go back to 2000 BC in Mesopotamia). I doubt the Egyptians even were aware of the existance of a species like the hobby (but they must on the other hand have been &lt;u&gt;very&lt;/u&gt; familiar with the lanner).

Horus: &lt;br&gt;
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horus&lt;br&gt;
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Horus.jpg&lt;br&gt;
http://ascendingpassage.com/Merneptah-Horus.jpg&lt;br&gt;
http://images.imagestate.com/Watermark/1277610.jpg (falcon)&lt;br&gt;
http://www.globalegyptianmuseum.org/large.aspx?img=images/NMI/1091+14a.jpg (falcon)&lt;br&gt;
http://www.flickr.com/photos/peterjr1961/sets/72157602881797225/detail/?page=46 (falcons)&lt;br&gt;
http://www.flickr.com/photos/peterjr1961/5865629728/ (falcon)&lt;br&gt;

Lanner: &lt;br&gt;
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanner_Falcon&lt;br&gt;
http://ibc.lynxeds.com/files/imagecache/photo_940/pictures/IMG_1383_0.JPG&lt;br&gt;
http://www.flickr.com/photos/grantbrummett/4137248680/sizes/z/in/photostream/&lt;br&gt;

Hobby:&lt;br&gt;
http://www.kolkatabirds.com/eurasianhobby8cf.jpg&lt;br&gt;
http://www.leonardo-pharmacy.com/fileadmin/bilder/voegel/baumfalke.jpg&lt;br&gt;  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.254.200.12|83.254.200.12]] ([[User talk:83.254.200.12|talk]]) 12:37, 4 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Fringe theories/Noticeboard ==

There is a discussion on the mathematics/fraction section currently at the [[Wikipedia:Fringe theories/Noticeboard]].--[[User:Salix alba|Salix]] ([[User talk:Salix alba|talk]]): 21:27, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
:Archived here [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Fringe_theories/Noticeboard/Archive_33#Eye_of_Horus_numbers] [[User:Aarghdvaark|Aarghdvaark]] ([[User talk:Aarghdvaark|talk]]) 08:50, 27 May 2013 (UTC)

==Mathematics - Jim Ritter, Unsourced Claims==

&lt;blockquote&gt;Studies from the 1970s to this day in Egyptian mathematics have clearly shown this theory was fallacious and Jim Ritter definitely showed it to be false in 2003.[16]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

There is no reference included or explanation given how the widely accepted interpretation of the eye of horus as representing mathematical fractions, is wrong. Only a reference to the book "Under One Sky: Astronomy and Mathematics in the ancient Near East," is given. His book is also not on Amazon.

&lt;blockquote&gt;" Jim Ritter (2002) has conclusively shown that these are ‘capacity system submultiples’, which originated in hieratic texts, not hieroglyphic ones, and appear to have had non-religious meanings originally. "

Ritter shows conclusively that in their origin, and their written form, and their everyday use, the capacity system submultiples have nothing to do with the Eye of Horus.

" Ritter distinguishes this “strong” thesis from a “weak” version, in which, many centuries after their invention, the hieratic capacity system submultiples were imported into the hieroglyphic script and that some scribe or scribes wrote about them as if they could be combined into the wedjat hieroglyph.  This weak version has more evidence for it, but as Ritter points out (2002: 311), this “does not automatically mean that ‘the Egyptians’ thought like that; for example, those Egyptians whose task it was to engrave hieroglyphic inscriptions on temple walls. "&lt;ref&gt;http://glossographia.wordpress.com/2013/07/05/the-mystical-eye-of-horus-capacity-system-submultiples/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

I don't see where John Ritter anywhere disproves the Horus Eye Fractions.[[User:MrSativa|MrSativa]] ([[User talk:MrSativa|talk]]) 06:31, 24 January 2014 (UTC)

:This issue could definitely be explained better, but I don't feel comfortable making the attempt unless I can see Ritter's full argument. If I can obtain that book, I will see what he says and rework the "Mathematics" section accordingly. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 19:08, 28 January 2014 (UTC)

{{reflist-talk}}

== Unicode ==

Eye of Horus seems to be at U+13080, but is called "Egyptian Hieroglyph D010." If that really is it, this should be mentioned in the article. But I can't find a source other than the Unicode spec. Also it's not in any of the fonts I checked. [[User:Kendall-K1|Kendall-K1]] ([[User talk:Kendall-K1|talk]]) 22:12, 12 April 2015 (UTC)

:The Eye of Horus is called D10 on [[Gardiner's sign list]], and the [[Egyptian Hieroglyphs (Unicode block)|Unicode hieroglyph list]] is based on Gardiner's, so I don't think any other source should be needed to establish that they're the same. I added those details to the article. Thanks for pointing it out. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 00:52, 13 April 2015 (UTC)

::I wasn't 100% sure it was the same glyph but that seems pretty definitive. Thanks. I added the unicode glyph. [[User:Kendall-K1|Kendall-K1]] ([[User talk:Kendall-K1|talk]]) 01:26, 13 April 2015 (UTC)

== Use in Pharmacology ==

The Rx symbol is derived from the Eye of Horus --

http://www.history.com/news/ask-history/where-did-the-rx-symbol-come-from

[[Special:Contributions/24.51.217.118|24.51.217.118]] ([[User talk:24.51.217.118|talk]]) 14:48, 13 November 2015 (UTC)

== Too many images ==

We've got too many images. Per [[WP:IG]] we should get rid of a few. [[User:Kendall-K1|Kendall-K1]] ([[User talk:Kendall-K1|talk]]) 17:31, 1 November 2018 (UTC)

:Good point. And several weren't very high-quality or relevant. So I removed severa; let me know if you think any of those I removed should be kept. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 03:48, 3 November 2018 (UTC)
::Much better. Thank you. [[User:Kendall-K1|Kendall-K1]] ([[User talk:Kendall-K1|talk]]) 04:30, 3 November 2018 (UTC)

== The Eye of Horus "as a plant" ==

I've removed the "As a plant" section, added by [[User:Jnbagnol]] back in December. It's based on a paper by Stephen Berlant, who has scholarly but not Egyptological qualifications, arguing for the widespread use of entheogens in ancient Egypt. Berlant himself has advanced related claims in other Wikipedia articles on ancient Egypt, and they've always seemed like [[WP:UNDUE|undue weight]] to me. See [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Ancient Egypt/Archive 7#Westcar Papyrus]] and [[User talk:Doug Weller/Archive 20#User:Berlant and Westcar Papyrus]] for some of the background. This is the text I cut:

&lt;blockquote&gt;"In Egyptian society, the eye of Horus was also a plant, which they included in elixirs and cakes. This plant was believed to have the ability to confer immortality onto people. One myth includes gods living upon plant life growing near a lake in Sekhet-hetep. The plants by this great lake was believed to be baked into the 'bread of eternity'. (Berlant, S. (2005). The entheomycological origin of Egyptian crowns and the esoteric underpinnings of Egyptian religion. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 102(2), 275–288.)"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Berlant's paper is available [https://www.academia.edu/9293937/The_entheomycological_origin_of_Egyptian_crowns_and_the_esoteric_underpinnings_of_Egyptian_religion here]; the relevant page is 286. Its source for the claim that the Eye of Horus was a plant is Budge's ''Gods of the Egyptians'', pages 164–165 (available [http://www.etana.org/sites/default/files/coretexts/20625.pdf here]), and Berlant seems to be misinterpreting it. Budge says:

&lt;blockquote&gt;"The gods nourished themselves with celestial food which was supplied to them by the Eye of Horus, that is to say, they supported their existence on the rays of light which fell from the sun which lit up heaven, and they became beings whose bodies were wholly of light. According to one myth the gods themselves lived upon a 'wood, or plant of life', (Pepi I., line 430) which seems to have grown near the great lake in Sekhet-hetep, round which they were wont to sit but this idea belongs to the group of views which held that the beatified dead lived in a beautiful, fertile region, where white wheat and red barley grew luxuriantly to a great height, and where canals were numerous and full of water, and where material enjoyments of every kind could be found. In other places we read of 'bread of eternity', and 'beer of eternity', i.e., bread and beer which was supposed never to grow stale or to become spoiled, and we also have mention of a heavenly fig-tree, and a heavenly vine, the fruit of which is eaten by the beatified. The bread upon which the blessed fed themselves was that bread which the Eye of Horus shed upon the branches of the olive-tree…"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In short, the Eye of Horus supplied the gods with many types of food and drink, including bread. That is consistent with the use of the Eye to represent the offerings, especially food, that the Egyptians gave to the gods or, even more generally, to represent "plenitude of life force" (as [[Jan Assmann]] put it). I can't track down the original text that Budge refers to when discussing the "plant of life"—"Pepi I" presumably refers to the [[Pyramid Texts]] of [[Pepi I]], but "line 430" doesn't match the traditional system of organizing the Pyramid Texts, which was established four years after Budge's book was published. In any case, Budge's text does not indicate that the gods made their bread from the plant of life, and the gods' bread probably isn't even mentioned in the Pyramid Texts spell that mentions the plant. Berlant is conflating two ideas that, as far as I can tell, come from separate sources and making up his own ideas about how they fit together. I don't blame Jnbagnol for this, as journal papers are generally assumed to be reliable sources, although I know nothing about the reliability of the ''Journal of Ethnopharmacology''. Berlant is another story. This discovery makes it even less surprising that his ideas have no traction in the Egyptological community. They shouldn't have any traction on Wikipedia, either. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 17:14, 24 March 2019 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 10 April 2019 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Eye of Horus|answered=yes}}
Johns Hopkins Archaeological Museum. http://archaeologicalmuseum.jhu.edu/the-collection/object-stories/ancient-egyptian-amulets/wedjat-eyes/. Accessed 28 Feb. 2019. [[User:Juniata Ryan|Juniata Ryan]] ([[User talk:Juniata Ryan|talk]]) 13:49, 10 April 2019 (UTC)
:Have added to external links. – '''''[[User:Þjarkur|Þjarkur]]''''' [[User talk:Þjarkur|(talk)]] 14:55, 10 April 2019 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 25 November 2019 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Eye of Horus|answered=yes}}
This has a lot of pictures of the eye of Ra as well as the eye of Horus and this is causing a lot of readers to get confused of which one is correct.  The eye of Horus is the left eye and the rest of the pictures should be removed or flipped. This is a huge error and needs to be corrected. It is embarrassing to see this error on Wikipedia. [[User:Zmorganx1|Zmorganx1]] ([[User talk:Zmorganx1|talk]]) 02:56, 25 November 2019 (UTC)

:{{Not done}}. It's not clear what pictures you're referring to; please be more precise.  Please also provide [[WP:RS|reliable source(s)]] for this information. &amp;ndash;[[User:Deacon Vorbis|Deacon Vorbis]]&amp;nbsp;([[User Talk:Deacon Vorbis|carbon]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull;&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Deacon Vorbis|videos]]) 04:49, 25 November 2019 (UTC)

::{{ping|Zmorganx1}} The problem is that the distinction between right and left eyes doesn't seem to have been consistently upheld. Both right and left eyes, with the distinctive markings below the eye that indicate it is more than an ordinary human eye, were used in amulets. In '[[The Contendings of Horus and Seth]]", the single best-known Egyptian text describing the myth of the struggle between those two gods, Set tears out ''both'' of Horus' eyes. Although I don't know whether any sources say so, I suspect the strict pattern of lunar/left and solar/right is something of an oversimplification. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 05:08, 25 November 2019 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hfuz72vofz1wwxfwuqvoloyi1dz4fev</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
