<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49033</id>
    <revision>
      <id>960548315</id>
      <parentid>959505669</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-03T15:18:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ich</username>
        <id>43393</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Alter: doi. Add: bibcode, pages, year, title, doi, pmc, page, volume, journal, pmid, issue, author pars. 1-1. Removed URL that duplicated unique identifier. Removed parameters. Formatted [[WP:ENDASH|dashes]]. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this tool]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | via #UCB_Gadget</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="122540" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Epigenetic (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|study of heritable DNA and histone modifications that affect the expression of a gene without a change in its nucleotide sequence.}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2019}}
[[File:Epigenetic mechanisms.png|thumb|right|449px|Epigenetic mechanisms]]

In [[biology]], '''epigenetics''' is the study of [[heritable]] [[phenotype]] changes that do not involve alterations in the [[DNA sequence]].&lt;ref name="Epigenetics 2009 review"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dupont C, Armant DR, Brenner CA | title = Epigenetics: definition, mechanisms and clinical perspective | journal = Seminars in Reproductive Medicine | volume = 27 | issue = 5 | pages = 351–7 | date = September 2009 | pmid = 19711245 | pmc = 2791696 | doi = 10.1055/s-0029-1237423 | quote = In the original sense of this definition, epigenetics referred to all molecular pathways modulating the expression of a genotype into a particular phenotype. Over the following years, with the rapid growth of genetics, the meaning of the word has gradually narrowed. Epigenetics has been defined and today is generally accepted as 'the study of changes in gene function that are mitotically and/or meiotically heritable and that do not entail a change in DNA sequence.' }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] prefix ''[[wikt:epi-|epi-]]'' ({{wikt-lang|grc|ἐπι-}} "over, outside of, around") in ''epigenetics'' implies features that are "on top of" or "in addition to" the traditional [[Genetics|genetic]] basis for [[Heredity|inheritance]].&lt;ref name = science&gt;{{cite news | title=Beware the pseudo gene genies |first = Adam|last = Rutherford| url= https://www.theguardian.com/science/2015/jul/19/epigenetics-dna--darwin-adam-rutherford | work=[[The Guardian]] | date=19 July 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Epigenetics most often involves changes that affect gene activity and [[gene expression|expression]], but the term can also be used to describe any heritable phenotypic change. Such effects on [[cell (biology)|cellular]] and [[physiology|physiological]] [[phenotypic trait]]s may result from external or [[environment (biophysical)|environmental]] factors, or be part of normal development. The standard definition of epigenetics requires these alterations to be heritable&lt;ref name="nature2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid19339683" /&gt; in the progeny of either cells or organisms.

The term also refers to the changes themselves: functionally relevant changes to the [[genome]] that do not involve a change in the [[nucleotide sequence]]. Examples of mechanisms that produce such changes are [[DNA methylation]] and [[histone|histone modification]], each of which alters how genes are expressed without altering the underlying [[DNA]] sequence. Gene expression can be controlled through the action of [[repressor protein]]s that attach to [[silencer (DNA)|silencer]] regions of the DNA. These epigenetic changes may last through [[cell division]]s for the duration of the cell's life, and may also last for multiple generations, even though they do not involve changes in the underlying DNA sequence of the organism;&lt;ref name="pmid17522671"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bird A | title = Perceptions of epigenetics | journal = Nature | volume = 447 | issue = 7143 | pages = 396–8 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17522671 | doi = 10.1038/nature05913 | bibcode = 2007Natur.447..396B }}&lt;/ref&gt; instead, non-genetic factors cause the organism's genes to behave (or "express themselves") differently.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=10140 |title =What genes remember | last = Hunter | first = Philip | name-list-format = vanc | magazine=Prospect Magazine | issue=146 | date=1 May 2008 | access-date=26 July 2012 | url-status=dead | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080501094940/http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=10140 | archive-date=1 May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One example of an epigenetic change in [[eukaryotic]] biology is the process of [[cellular differentiation]]. During [[morphogenesis]], [[totipotent]] [[stem cells]] become the various [[pluripotent]] [[cell line]]s of the [[embryo]], which in turn become fully differentiated cells. In other words, as a single fertilized [[egg cell]] – the [[zygote]] – continues to [[mitosis|divide]], the resulting daughter cells change into all the different cell types in an organism, including [[neuron]]s, [[Myocyte|muscle cells]], [[epithelium]], [[endothelium]] of [[blood vessel]]s, etc., by activating some genes while inhibiting the expression of others.&lt;ref name="pmid17522676"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Reik W | title = Stability and flexibility of epigenetic gene regulation in mammalian development | journal = Nature | volume = 447 | issue = 7143 | pages = 425–32 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17522676 | doi = 10.1038/nature05918 | bibcode = 2007Natur.447..425R }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, some phenomena not necessarily heritable have also been described as epigenetic. For example, the term "epigenetic" has been used to describe any modification of chromosomal regions, especially histone modifications, whether or not these changes are heritable or associated with a phenotype. The consensus definition now requires a trait to be heritable for it to be considered epigenetic.&lt;ref name="pmid19339683" /&gt;

==Definitions==
The term ''epigenetics'' in its contemporary usage emerged in the 1990s, but for some years has been used with somewhat variable meanings.&lt;ref name="Moore_2015"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-developing-genome-9780199922345?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;|title=The Developing Genome: An Introduction to Behavioral Epigenetics|last=Moore|first=David S.|date=2015|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0199922345|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt; A consensus definition of the concept of ''epigenetic trait'' as a "stably heritable phenotype resulting from changes in a chromosome without alterations in the DNA sequence" was formulated at a [[Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory|Cold Spring Harbor]] meeting in 2008,&lt;ref name="pmid19339683"/&gt; although alternate definitions that include non-heritable traits are still being used.&lt;ref name="NIH"/&gt;

The term ''epigenesis'' has a generic meaning of "extra growth", and has been used in English since the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;[[Oxford English Dictionary]]: "The word is used by W. Harvey, ''Exercitationes'' 1651, p. 148, and in the ''English Anatomical Exercitations'' 1653, p. 272. It is explained to mean ‘partium super-exorientium additamentum’, ‘the additament of parts budding one out of another’."&lt;/ref&gt;

===Waddington's canalisation, 1940s===

From the generic meaning, and the associated adjective ''epigenetic'', British [[embryologist]] [[C. H. Waddington]] invented the term ''epigenetics'' in 1942 as pertaining to ''[[epigenesis (biology)|epigenesis]]'', in parallel to [[Valentin Haecker]]'s 'phenogenetics' ({{lang|de|Phänogenetik}}).&lt;ref name=waddington&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Waddington CH | title=The epigenotype| journal=Endeavour | volume=1 | pages=18–20 |doi= 10.1093/ije/dyr184| year=1942 | issue=1| pmid=22186258|quote=For the purpose of a study of inheritance, the relation between phenotypes and genotypes [...] is, from a wider biological point of view, of crucial importance, since it is the kernel of the whole problem of development. Many geneticists have recognized this and attempted to discover the processes involved in the mechanism by which the genes of the genotype bring about phenotypic effects. The first step in such an enterprise is – or rather should be, since it is often omitted by those with an undue respect for the powers of reason – to describe what can be seen of the developmental processes. For enquiries of this kind, the word 'phenogenetics' was coined by Haecker [1918, {{lang|de|Phänogenetik}}]. The second and more important part of the task is to discover the causal mechanisms at work, and to relate them as far as possible to what experimental embryology has already revealed of the mechanics of development. We might use the name 'epigenetics' for such studies, thus emphasizing their relation to the concepts, so strongly favourable to the classical theory of epigenesis, which have been reached by the experimental embryologists. We certainly need to remember that between genotype and phenotype, and connecting them to each other, there lies a whole complex of developmental processes. It is convenient to have a name for this complex: 'epigenotype' seems suitable. }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Epigenesis'' in the context of the biology of that period referred to the [[cellular differentiation|differentiation]] of cells from their initial [[totipotent]] state during [[embryonic development]].&lt;ref&gt;See ''[[preformationism]]'' for historical background. ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'': "the theory that the germ is brought into existence (by successive accretions), and not merely developed, in the process of reproduction. [...] The opposite theory was formerly known as the 'theory of evolution'; to avoid the ambiguity of this name, it is now spoken of chiefly as the 'theory of preformation', sometimes as that of 'encasement' or 'emboîtement'."&lt;/ref&gt;

When Waddington coined the term, the physical nature of [[gene]]s and their role in heredity was not known. He used it instead as a conceptual model of how genetic components might interact with their surroundings to produce a [[phenotype]]; he used the phrase "epigenetic landscape" as a metaphor for [[morphogenesis|biological development]]. Waddington held that cell fates were established during development in a process he called [[canalisation (genetics)|canalisation]] much as a marble rolls down to the point of [[local optimum|lowest local elevation]].&lt;ref name="Waddington2014"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Waddington |first1=C. H. |title=The Epigenetics of Birds |date=2014 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-1-107-44047-0 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lqKTBQAAQBAJ }}{{page needed|date=January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Waddington suggested visualising increasing irreversibility of cell type differentiation as ridges rising between the valleys where the marbles (analogous to cells) are travelling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hall BK | title = In search of evolutionary developmental mechanisms: the 30-year gap between 1944 and 1974 | journal = Journal of Experimental Zoology Part B: Molecular and Developmental Evolution | volume = 302 | issue = 1 | pages = 5–18 | date = January 2004 | pmid = 14760651 | doi = 10.1002/jez.b.20002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent times, Waddington's notion of the epigenetic landscape has been rigorously formalized in the context of the [[system dynamics|systems dynamics]] state approach to the study of cell-fate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Alvarez-Buylla ER, Chaos A, Aldana M, Benítez M, Cortes-Poza Y, Espinosa-Soto C, Hartasánchez DA, Lotto RB, Malkin D, Escalera Santos GJ, Padilla-Longoria P | display-authors = 6 | title = Floral morphogenesis: stochastic explorations of a gene network epigenetic landscape | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 3 | issue = 11 | pages = e3626 | date = 3 November 2008 | pmid = 18978941 | pmc = 2572848 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0003626 | bibcode = 2008PLoSO...3.3626A | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sciencedirect.com"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rabajante JF, Babierra AL | title = Branching and oscillations in the epigenetic landscape of cell-fate determination | journal = Progress in Biophysics and Molecular Biology | volume = 117 | issue = 2–3 | pages = 240–249 | date = March 2015 | pmid = 25641423 | doi = 10.1016/j.pbiomolbio.2015.01.006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cell-fate determination is predicted to exhibit certain dynamics, such as attractor-convergence (the attractor can be an equilibrium point, limit cycle or [[strange attractor]]) or oscillatory.&lt;ref name="sciencedirect.com"/&gt;

===Contemporary===

[[Robin Holliday]] defined epigenetics as "the study of the mechanisms of temporal and spatial control of gene activity during the development of complex organisms".&lt;ref name="pmid2265224"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Holliday R | title = DNA methylation and epigenetic inheritance | journal = Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences | volume = 326 | issue = 1235 | pages = 329–38 | date = January 1990 | pmid = 1968668 | doi = 10.1098/rstb.1990.0015 | bibcode = 1990RSPTB.326..329H | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, in its broadest sense, ''epigenetic'' can be used to describe anything other than DNA sequence that influences the development of an organism.

More recent usage of the word in biology follows stricter definitions. It is, as defined by [[Arthur Riggs (geneticist)|Arthur Riggs]] and colleagues, "the study of [[mitosis|mitotically]] and/or [[meiosis|meiotically]] heritable changes in gene function that cannot be explained by changes in DNA sequence".&lt;ref name="isbn0-87969-490-4"&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Riggs AD, Martienssen RA, Russo VE | title=Epigenetic mechanisms of gene regulation | publisher=Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press | location=Plainview, NY | year=1996 | pages=1–4| isbn=978-0-87969-490-6 | oclc=| doi=}}{{page needed|date=August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term has also been used, however, to describe processes which have not been demonstrated to be heritable, such as some forms of histone modification; there are therefore attempts to redefine "epigenetics" in broader terms that would avoid the constraints of requiring [[heritability]]. For example, [[Adrian Peter Bird|Adrian Bird]] defined epigenetics as "the structural adaptation of chromosomal regions so as to register, signal or perpetuate altered activity states".&lt;ref name="pmid17522671" /&gt; This definition would be inclusive of transient modifications associated with [[DNA repair]] or [[cell-cycle]] phases as well as stable changes maintained across multiple cell generations, but exclude others such as templating of membrane architecture and [[prions]] unless they impinge on chromosome function. Such redefinitions however are not universally accepted and are still subject to debate.&lt;ref name="nature2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ledford H | title = Language: Disputed definitions | journal = Nature | volume = 455 | issue = 7216 | pages = 1023–8 | date = October 2008 | pmid = 18948925 | doi = 10.1038/4551023a | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Institutes of Health|NIH]] "Roadmap Epigenomics Project", ongoing as of 2016, uses the following definition: "For purposes of this program, epigenetics refers to both heritable changes in gene activity and [[gene expression|expression]] (in the progeny of cells or of individuals) and also stable, long-term alterations in the transcriptional potential of a cell that are not necessarily heritable."&lt;ref name="NIH"&gt;{{cite web |work=NIH Roadmap Epigenomics Project |url=http://www.roadmapepigenomics.org/overview |title=Overview}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, a consensus definition of the epigenetic trait, a "stably heritable phenotype resulting from changes in a chromosome without alterations in the DNA sequence", was made at a [[Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory|Cold Spring Harbor]] meeting.&lt;ref name="pmid19339683"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Berger SL, Kouzarides T, Shiekhattar R, Shilatifard A | title = An operational definition of epigenetics | journal = Genes &amp; Development | volume = 23 | issue = 7 | pages = 781–3 | date = April 2009 | pmid = 19339683 | pmc = 3959995 | doi = 10.1101/gad.1787609 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The similarity of the word to "genetics" has generated many parallel usages. The "[[epigenome]]" is a parallel to the word "[[genome]]", referring to the overall epigenetic state of a cell, and [[epigenomics]] refers to global analyses of epigenetic changes across the entire genome.&lt;ref name="NIH"/&gt; The phrase "[[genetic code]]" has also been adapted – the "[[epigenetic code]]" has been used to describe the set of epigenetic features that create different phenotypes in different cells from the same underlying DNA sequence. Taken to its extreme, the "epigenetic code" could represent the total state of the cell, with the position of each molecule accounted for in an ''epigenomic map'', a diagrammatic representation of the gene expression, DNA methylation and histone modification status of a particular genomic region. More typically, the term is used in reference to systematic efforts to measure specific, relevant forms of epigenetic information such as the [[histone code hypothesis|histone code]] or [[DNA methylation]] patterns.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

===Developmental psychology===

In a sense somewhat unrelated to its use in biological disciplines, the term "epigenetic" has also been used in [[developmental psychology]] to describe psychological development as the result of an ongoing, bi-directional interchange between heredity and the environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gottlieb G | year=1991 | title=Epigenetic systems view of human development | url=| journal=Developmental Psychology | volume=27 | issue=1| pages=33–34 | doi=10.1037/0012-1649.27.1.33}}&lt;/ref&gt; Interactive ideas of development have been discussed in various forms and under various names throughout the 19th and 20th centuries. An early version was proposed, among the founding statements in [[embryology]], by [[Karl Ernst von Baer]] and popularized by [[Ernst Haeckel]]. A radical epigenetic view (physiological epigenesis) was developed by [[Paul Wintrebert]]. Another variation, probabilistic epigenesis, was presented by [[Gilbert Gottlieb]] in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert Gottlieb. [http://chd.ucsd.edu/_files/winter2009/Gottlieb.probabilistic.pdf Probabilistic epigenesis], Developmental Science 10:1 (2007), 1–11&lt;/ref&gt; This view encompasses all of the possible developing factors on an organism and how they not only influence the organism and each other but how the organism also influences its own development.

The developmental psychologist [[Erik Erikson]] wrote of an ''epigenetic principle'' in his 1968 book [[Erik Erikson#Bibliography|''Identity: Youth and Crisis'']], encompassing the notion that we develop through an unfolding of our personality in predetermined stages, and that our environment and surrounding culture influence how we progress through these stages. This biological unfolding in relation to our socio-cultural settings is done in [[Erikson's stages of psychosocial development|stages of psychosocial development]], where "progress through each stage is in part determined by our success, or lack of success, in all the previous stages."&lt;ref name=Boeree1997&gt;Boeree, C. George, (1997/2006), [http://www.social-psychology.de/do/pt_erikson.pdf ''Personality Theories, Erik Erikson'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Erikson|first=Erik|title=Identity: Youth and Crisis|url=https://archive.org/details/identityyouthcri00erikrich|url-access=registration|year=1968|publisher=W.W. Norton and Company |location=Chapter 3|page=[https://archive.org/details/identityyouthcri00erikrich/page/92 92]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bio-medicine.org/biology-definition/Epigenetics|title=Epigenetics|publisher= Bio-Medicine.org|access-date=21 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although empirical studies have yielded discrepant results, epigenetic modifications are thought to be a biological mechanism for [[transgenerational trauma]].

==Molecular basis==
[[File:Nucleosome 1KX5 2.png|thumb|DNA associates with histone proteins to form chromatin.]]

Epigenetic changes modify the activation of certain genes, but not the genetic code sequence of DNA. The microstructure (not code) of DNA itself or the associated [[chromatin]] proteins may be modified, causing activation or silencing. This mechanism enables differentiated cells in a multicellular organism to express only the genes that are necessary for their own activity. Epigenetic changes are preserved when [[Cell division|cells divide]]. Most epigenetic changes only occur within the course of one individual organism's lifetime; however, these epigenetic changes can be transmitted to the organism's offspring through a process called [[transgenerational epigenetic inheritance]]. Moreover, if gene inactivation occurs in a sperm or egg cell that results in fertilization, this epigenetic modification may also be transferred to the next generation.&lt;ref name="pmid17320501"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chandler VL | title = Paramutation: from maize to mice | journal = Cell | volume = 128 | issue = 4 | pages = 641–5 | date = February 2007 | pmid = 17320501 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2007.02.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific epigenetic processes include [[paramutation]], [[bookmarking]], [[Imprinting (genetics)|imprinting]], [[gene silencing]], [[X-inactivation|X chromosome inactivation]], [[position effect]], [[DNA methylation reprogramming]], [[transvection (genetics)|transvection]], [[maternal effect]]s, the progress of [[carcinogenesis]], many effects of [[teratogen]]s, regulation of [[histone]] modifications and [[heterochromatin]], and technical limitations affecting [[parthenogenesis]] and [[cloning]].

=== DNA damage ===
DNA damage can also cause epigenetic changes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kovalchuk O, Baulch JE | title = Epigenetic changes and nontargeted radiation effects--is there a link? | journal = Environmental and Molecular Mutagenesis | volume = 49 | issue = 1 | pages = 16–25 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 18172877 | doi = 10.1002/em.20361 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ilnytskyy Y, Kovalchuk O | title = Non-targeted radiation effects-an epigenetic connection | journal = Mutation Research | volume = 714 | issue = 1–2 | pages = 113–25 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 21784089 | doi = 10.1016/j.mrfmmm.2011.06.014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Friedl AA, Mazurek B, Seiler DM | title = Radiation-induced alterations in histone modification patterns and their potential impact on short-term radiation effects | journal = Frontiers in Oncology | volume = 2 | issue =  | pages = 117 | year = 2012 | pmid = 23050241 | pmc = 3445916 | doi = 10.3389/fonc.2012.00117 }}&lt;/ref&gt; DNA damage is very frequent, occurring on average about 60,000 times a day per cell of the human body (see [[DNA damage (naturally occurring)]]). These damages are largely repaired, but at the site of a DNA repair, epigenetic changes can remain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cuozzo C, Porcellini A, Angrisano T, Morano A, Lee B, Di Pardo A, Messina S, Iuliano R, Fusco A, Santillo MR, Muller MT, Chiariotti L, Gottesman ME, Avvedimento EV | display-authors = 6 | title = DNA damage, homology-directed repair, and DNA methylation | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 3 | issue = 7 | pages = e110 | date = July 2007 | pmid = 17616978 | pmc = 1913100 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.0030110 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, a double strand break in DNA can initiate unprogrammed epigenetic [[gene silencing]] both by causing [[DNA methylation]] as well as by promoting silencing types of histone modifications (chromatin remodeling - see next section).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = O'Hagan HM, Mohammad HP, Baylin SB | title = Double strand breaks can initiate gene silencing and SIRT1-dependent onset of DNA methylation in an exogenous promoter CpG island | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 4 | issue = 8 | pages = e1000155 | date = August 2008 | pmid = 18704159 | pmc = 2491723 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.1000155 | editor1-last = Lee | editor1-first = Jeannie T }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the enzyme [[Poly ADP ribose polymerase|Parp1 (poly(ADP)-ribose polymerase)]] and its product poly(ADP)-ribose (PAR) accumulate at sites of DNA damage as part of a repair process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Malanga M, Althaus FR | title = The role of poly(ADP-ribose) in the DNA damage signaling network | journal = Biochemistry and Cell Biology | volume = 83 | issue = 3 | pages = 354–64 | date = June 2005 | pmid = 15959561 | doi = 10.1139/o05-038 | url = https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/5838/1/RPViewDoc.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; This accumulation, in turn, directs recruitment and activation of the chromatin remodeling protein ALC1 that can cause [[nucleosome]] remodeling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gottschalk AJ, Timinszky G, Kong SE, Jin J, Cai Y, Swanson SK, Washburn MP, Florens L, Ladurner AG, Conaway JW, Conaway RC | display-authors = 6 | title = Poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation directs recruitment and activation of an ATP-dependent chromatin remodeler | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 106 | issue = 33 | pages = 13770–4 | date = August 2009 | pmid = 19666485 | pmc = 2722505 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0906920106 | bibcode = 2009PNAS..10613770G }}&lt;/ref&gt; Nucleosome remodeling has been found to cause, for instance, epigenetic silencing of DNA repair gene MLH1.&lt;ref name="isbn0-87969-490-4"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lin JC, Jeong S, Liang G, Takai D, Fatemi M, Tsai YC, Egger G, Gal-Yam EN, Jones PA | display-authors = 6 | title = Role of nucleosomal occupancy in the epigenetic silencing of the MLH1 CpG island | journal = Cancer Cell | volume = 12 | issue = 5 | pages = 432–44 | date = November 2007 | pmid = 17996647 | pmc = 4657456 | doi = 10.1016/j.ccr.2007.10.014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; DNA damaging chemicals, such as [[benzene]], [[hydroquinone]], [[styrene]], [[carbon tetrachloride]] and [[trichloroethylene]], cause considerable hypomethylation of DNA, some through the activation of oxidative stress pathways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tabish AM, Poels K, Hoet P, Godderis L | title = Epigenetic factors in cancer risk: effect of chemical carcinogens on global DNA methylation pattern in human TK6 cells | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 7 | issue = 4 | pages = e34674 | year = 2012 | pmid = 22509344 | pmc = 3324488 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0034674 | editor1-last = Chiariotti | bibcode = 2012PLoSO...734674T | editor1-first = Lorenzo }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Foods are known to alter the epigenetics of rats on different diets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Burdge GC, Hoile SP, Uller T, Thomas NA, Gluckman PD, Hanson MA, Lillycrop KA | title = Progressive, transgenerational changes in offspring phenotype and epigenotype following nutritional transition | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 6 | issue = 11 | pages = e28282 | year = 2011 | pmid = 22140567 | pmc = 3227644 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0028282 | editor1-last = Imhof | bibcode = 2011PLoSO...628282B | editor1-first = Axel }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some food components epigenetically increase the levels of DNA repair enzymes such as [[O-6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase|MGMT]] and [[MLH1]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fang M, Chen D, Yang CS | title = Dietary polyphenols may affect DNA methylation | journal = The Journal of Nutrition | volume = 137 | issue = 1 Suppl | pages = 223S–228S | date = January 2007 | pmid = 17182830 | doi = 10.1093/jn/137.1.223S | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[p53]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Olaharski AJ, Rine J, Marshall BL, Babiarz J, Zhang L, Verdin E, Smith MT | title = The flavoring agent dihydrocoumarin reverses epigenetic silencing and inhibits sirtuin deacetylases | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 1 | issue = 6 | pages = e77 | date = December 2005 | pmid = 16362078 | pmc = 1315280 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.0010077 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kikuno N, Shiina H, Urakami S, Kawamoto K, Hirata H, Tanaka Y, Majid S, Igawa M, Dahiya R | display-authors = 6 | title = Genistein mediated histone acetylation and demethylation activates tumor suppressor genes in prostate cancer cells | journal = International Journal of Cancer | volume = 123 | issue = 3 | pages = 552–60 | date = August 2008 | pmid = 18431742 | doi = 10.1002/ijc.23590 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other food components can reduce DNA damage, such as soy [[isoflavones]]. In one study, markers for [[oxidative stress]], such as modified nucleotides that can result from DNA damage, were decreased by a 3-week diet supplemented with soy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Djuric Z, Chen G, Doerge DR, Heilbrun LK, Kucuk O | title = Effect of soy isoflavone supplementation on markers of oxidative stress in men and women | journal = Cancer Letters | volume = 172 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–6 | date = October 2001 | pmid = 11595123 | doi = 10.1016/S0304-3835(01)00627-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A decrease in oxidative DNA damage was also observed 2 h after consumption of [[anthocyanin]]-rich [[bilberry]] (''[[Vaccinium myrtillus|Vaccinium myrtillius]]'' L.) [[pomace]] extract.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kropat C, Mueller D, Boettler U, Zimmermann K, Heiss EH, Dirsch VM, Rogoll D, Melcher R, Richling E, Marko D | display-authors = 6 | title = Modulation of Nrf2-dependent gene transcription by bilberry anthocyanins in vivo | journal = Molecular Nutrition &amp; Food Research | volume = 57 | issue = 3 | pages = 545–50 | date = March 2013 | pmid = 23349102 | doi = 10.1002/mnfr.201200504 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, [[Ultraviolet|UV radiation]] is a common source of [[DNA damage (naturally occurring)|DNA damage]], as both [[Pyrimidine dimer|cyclobutane-pyrimidine dimers]] and 6-4 photoproducts (and their Dewar valance isomers) are created by UV radiation. Since cyclobutane-pyrimidine dimers and 6-4 photoproducts are the two most abundant mutagenic and cytotoxic DNA lesions, there are a host of [[DNA repair]] pathways enacted to confront these UV-induced lesions: excision repair, mutagenic repair, recombinational repair, [[Cell cycle checkpoint|cell-cycle checkpoints]], and [[apoptosis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Sinha|first1=Rajeshwar P.|last2=Häder|first2=Donat P.|date=April 2002|title=UV-induced DNA damage and repair: a review|journal=Photochemical &amp; Photobiological Sciences|volume=1|issue=4|pages=225–236|doi=10.1039/b201230h|issn=1474-905X|pmid=12661961}}&lt;/ref&gt; These repair pathways can be more generally referred to using broad categories for DNA repair, such as direct reversal mechanisms, excision repair mechanisms, and post-replication repair mechanisms.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cooper|first=Geoffrey M.|date=2000|title=DNA Repair|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK9900/|journal=The Cell: A Molecular Approach. 2nd Edition|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Techniques used to study epigenetics ===
Epigenetic research uses a wide range of [[molecular biology|molecular biological]] techniques to further understanding of epigenetic phenomena, which can be broadly placed into the following categories: DNA methylation analysis, DNA/protein interaction analysis, and chromatin accessibility and confirmation assays.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Epigenetics Analysis {{!}} LSR {{!}} Bio-Rad|url=https://www.bio-rad.com/en-us/applications-technologies/epigenetics-analysis?ID=LUSNNRCZF|website=www.bio-rad.com|access-date=2020-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within these categories are techniques such as [[chromatin immunoprecipitation]] (together with its large-scale variants [[ChIP-on-chip]] and [[ChIP-Seq]]), [[fluorescent in situ hybridization]], methylation-sensitive [[restriction enzymes]], DNA adenine methyltransferase identification ([[DamID]]), high resolution melt analysis (HRM), and [[bisulfite sequencing]].&lt;ref name="verma"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Verma M, Rogers S, Divi RL, Schully SD, Nelson S, Joseph Su L, Ross SA, Pilch S, Winn DM, Khoury MJ | display-authors = 6 | title = Epigenetic research in cancer epidemiology: trends, opportunities, and challenges | journal = Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention | volume = 23 | issue = 2 | pages = 223–33 | date = February 2014 | pmid = 24326628 | pmc = 3925982 | doi = 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-13-0573 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the use of [[bioinformatics]] methods has a role in [[computational epigenetics]].&lt;ref name=verma/&gt;

==Mechanisms==
Several types of epigenetic inheritance systems may play a role in what has become known as cell memory,&lt;ref name="jablonka92"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Jablonka E, Lamb MJ, Lachmann M | title=Evidence, mechanisms and models for the inheritance of acquired characteristics | journal=[[J. Theor. Biol.]] |date=September 1992 | volume=158 | issue=2 | pages=245–68 | doi=10.1016/S0022-5193(05)80722-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; note however that not all of these are universally accepted to be examples of epigenetics.

===Covalent modifications===
[[File:Histone tails and their function in chromatin formation.svg|thumb|Histone tails and their function in chromatin formation]]

[[Covalent]] modifications of either DNA (e.g. [[cytosine]] methylation and hydroxymethylation) or of histone proteins (e.g. [[lysine]] acetylation, lysine and [[arginine]] methylation, [[serine]] and [[threonine]] [[phosphorylation]], and lysine [[ubiquitination]] and [[sumoylation]]) play central roles in many types of epigenetic inheritance. Therefore, the word "epigenetics" is sometimes used as a synonym for these processes. However, this can be misleading. Chromatin remodeling is not always inherited, and not all epigenetic inheritance involves chromatin remodeling.&lt;ref name="pmid17407749"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ptashne M | title = On the use of the word 'epigenetic' | journal = Current Biology | volume = 17 | issue = 7 | pages = R233-6 | date = April 2007 | pmid = 17407749 | doi = 10.1016/j.cub.2007.02.030 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, a further lysine modification appeared in the scientific literature linking epigenetics modification to cell metabolism, i.e. Lactylation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang D, Tang Z, Huang H, Zhou G, Cui C, Weng Y, Liu W, Kim S, Lee S, Perez-Neut M, Ding J, Czyz D, Hu R, Ye Z, He M, Zheng YG, Shuman HA, Dai L, Ren B, Roeder RG, Becker L, Zhao Y | display-authors = 6 | title = Metabolic regulation of gene expression by histone lactylation | journal = Nature | volume = 574 | issue = 7779 | pages = 575–580 | date = October 2019 | pmid = 31645732 | pmc = 6818755 | doi = 10.1038/s41586-019-1678-1 | bibcode = 2019Natur.574..575Z }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because the [[phenotype]] of a cell or individual is affected by which of its genes are transcribed, heritable [[Transcription (genetics)|transcription states]] can give rise to epigenetic effects. There are several layers of regulation of [[gene expression]]. One way that genes are regulated is through the remodeling of chromatin. Chromatin is the complex of DNA and the [[histone]] proteins with which it associates. If the way that DNA is wrapped around the histones changes, gene expression can change as well. Chromatin remodeling is accomplished through two main mechanisms:
# The first way is [[post translational modification]] of the [[amino acid]]s that make up histone proteins. Histone proteins are made up of long chains of amino acids. If the amino acids that are in the chain are changed, the shape of the histone might be modified. DNA is not completely unwound during [[DNA replication|replication]]. It is possible, then, that the modified histones may be carried into each new copy of the DNA. Once there, these histones may act as templates, initiating the surrounding new histones to be shaped in the new manner. By altering the shape of the histones around them, these modified histones would ensure that a lineage-specific transcription program is maintained after cell division.
# The second way is the addition of methyl groups to the DNA, mostly at [[CpG site]]s, to convert [[cytosine]] to [[5-methylcytosine]]. 5-Methylcytosine performs much like a regular cytosine, pairing with a [[guanine]] in double-stranded DNA. However, some areas of the genome are methylated more heavily than others, and highly methylated areas tend to be less transcriptionally active, through a mechanism not fully understood. Methylation of cytosines can also persist from the germ line of one of the parents into the zygote, marking the chromosome as being inherited from one parent or the other ([[genetic imprinting]]).

Mechanisms of heritability of histone state are not well understood; however, much is known about the mechanism of heritability of DNA methylation state during cell division and [[Cellular differentiation|differentiation]]. Heritability of methylation state depends on certain enzymes (such as [[DNA methyltransferase|DNMT1]]) that have a higher affinity for 5-methylcytosine than for cytosine. If this enzyme reaches a "hemimethylated" portion of DNA (where 5-methylcytosine is in only one of the two DNA strands) the enzyme will methylate the other half.

Although histone modifications occur throughout the entire sequence, the unstructured N-termini of histones (called histone tails) are particularly highly modified. These modifications include [[acetylation]], [[methylation]], [[ubiquitylation]], [[phosphorylation]], [[sumoylation]], ribosylation and [[citrullination]]. Acetylation is the most highly studied of these modifications. For example, acetylation of the K14 and K9 lysines of the tail of [[histone H3]] by histone acetyltransferase enzymes (HATs) is known to regulate transcription in accordance with complementary histone deacetylases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Berndsen|first1=Christopher E.|last2=Denu|first2=John M.|date=2009|title=Catalysis and Substrate Selection by Histone/Protein Lysine Acetyltransferases|journal=Current Opinion in Structural Biology|volume=18|issue=6|pages=682–689|doi=10.1016/j.sbi.2008.11.004|issn=0959-440X|pmc=2723715|pmid=19056256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One mode of thinking is that this tendency of acetylation to be associated with "active" transcription is biophysical in nature. Because it normally has a positively charged [[nitrogen]] at its end, lysine can bind the negatively charged phosphates of the DNA backbone. The acetylation event converts the positively charged amine group on the side chain into a neutral [[Peptide bond|amide linkage]]. This removes the positive charge, thus loosening the DNA from the histone. When this occurs, complexes like [[SWI/SNF]] and other transcriptional factors can bind to the DNA and allow transcription to occur. This is the "cis" model of the epigenetic function. In other words, changes to the histone tails have a direct effect on the DNA itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Billie Wilson|title=Developmental Genetics|publisher=ED - Tech Press (Reprinted 2020)|year=2018|isbn=978-1-83947-266-4|location=United Kingdom|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another model of epigenetic function is the "trans" model. In this model, changes to the histone tails act indirectly on the DNA. For example, lysine acetylation may create a binding site for chromatin-modifying enzymes (or transcription machinery as well). This chromatin remodeler can then cause changes to the state of the chromatin. Indeed, a bromodomain – a protein domain that specifically binds acetyl-lysine – is found in many enzymes that help activate transcription, including the [[SWI/SNF]] complex. It may be that acetylation acts in this and the previous way to aid in transcriptional activation.

The idea that modifications act as docking modules for related factors is borne out by [[histone methylation]] as well. Methylation of lysine 9 of histone H3 has long been associated with constitutively transcriptionally silent chromatin (constitutive [[heterochromatin]]). It has been determined that a [[chromodomain]] (a domain that specifically binds methyl-lysine) in the transcriptionally repressive protein [[Heterochromatin Protein 1|HP1]] recruits HP1 to K9 methylated regions. One example that seems to refute this biophysical model for methylation is that tri-methylation of histone H3 at lysine 4 is strongly associated with (and required for full) transcriptional activation. Tri-methylation, in this case, would introduce a fixed positive charge on the tail.

It has been shown that the histone lysine methyltransferase (KMT) is responsible for this methylation activity in the pattern of histones H3 and [[Histone H4|H4]]. This enzyme utilizes a catalytically active site called the SET domain (Suppressor of variegation, Enhancer of zeste, Trithorax). The SET domain is a 130-amino acid sequence involved in modulating gene activities. This domain has been demonstrated to bind to the histone tail and causes the methylation of the histone.&lt;ref name="pmid9487389"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jenuwein T, Laible G, Dorn R, Reuter G | title = SET domain proteins modulate chromatin domains in eu- and heterochromatin | journal = Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences | volume = 54 | issue = 1 | pages = 80–93 | date = January 1998 | pmid = 9487389 | doi = 10.1007/s000180050127 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Differing histone modifications are likely to function in differing ways; acetylation at one position is likely to function differently from acetylation at another position. Also, multiple modifications may occur at the same time, and these modifications may work together to change the behavior of the [[nucleosome]]. The idea that multiple dynamic modifications regulate gene transcription in a systematic and reproducible way is called the [[histone code]], although the idea that histone state can be read linearly as a digital information carrier has been largely debunked. One of the best-understood systems that orchestrate chromatin-based silencing is the [[SIR protein]] based silencing of the yeast hidden mating-type loci HML and HMR.

DNA methylation frequently occurs in repeated sequences, and helps to suppress the expression and mobility of '[[transposable elements]]':&lt;ref name="slotkin2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Slotkin RK, Martienssen R | title = Transposable elements and the epigenetic regulation of the genome | journal = Nature Reviews. Genetics | volume = 8 | issue = 4 | pages = 272–85 | date = April 2007 | pmid = 17363976 | doi = 10.1038/nrg2072 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because [[5-methylcytosine]] can be spontaneously [[Deamination|deaminated]] (replacing nitrogen by oxygen) to [[thymidine]], CpG sites are frequently mutated and become rare in the genome, except at [[CpG islands]] where they remain unmethylated. Epigenetic changes of this type thus have the potential to direct increased frequencies of permanent genetic mutation. [[DNA methylation]] patterns are known to be established and modified in response to environmental factors by a complex interplay of at least three independent [[DNA methyltransferase]]s, [[DNMT1]], [[DNMT3a]], and [[DNMT3B]], the loss of any of which is lethal in mice.&lt;ref name="li92"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Li E, Bestor TH, Jaenisch R | title = Targeted mutation of the DNA methyltransferase gene results in embryonic lethality | journal = Cell | volume = 69 | issue = 6 | pages = 915–26 | date = June 1992 | pmid = 1606615 | doi = 10.1016/0092-8674(92)90611-F }}&lt;/ref&gt; DNMT1 is the most abundant methyltransferase in [[somatic cell]]s,&lt;ref name="robertson99"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Robertson KD, Uzvolgyi E, Liang G, Talmadge C, Sumegi J, Gonzales FA, Jones PA | title = The human DNA methyltransferases (DNMTs) 1, 3a and 3b: coordinate mRNA expression in normal tissues and overexpression in tumors | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 27 | issue = 11 | pages = 2291–8 | date = June 1999 | pmid = 10325416 | pmc = 148793 | doi = 10.1093/nar/27.11.2291 }}&lt;/ref&gt; localizes to replication foci,&lt;ref name="leonhardt92"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Leonhardt H, Page AW, Weier HU, Bestor TH | title = A targeting sequence directs DNA methyltransferase to sites of DNA replication in mammalian nuclei | journal = Cell | volume = 71 | issue = 5 | pages = 865–73 | date = November 1992 | pmid = 1423634 | doi = 10.1016/0092-8674(92)90561-P | url = https://epub.ub.uni-muenchen.de/5003/1/003.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; has a 10–40-fold preference for hemimethylated DNA and interacts with the [[proliferating cell nuclear antigen]] (PCNA).&lt;ref name="chuang97"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chuang LS, Ian HI, Koh TW, Ng HH, Xu G, Li BF | title = Human DNA-(cytosine-5) methyltransferase-PCNA complex as a target for p21WAF1 | journal = Science | volume = 277 | issue = 5334 | pages = 1996–2000 | date = September 1997 | pmid = 9302295 | doi = 10.1126/science.277.5334.1996 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

By preferentially modifying hemimethylated DNA, DNMT1 transfers patterns of methylation to a newly synthesized strand after [[DNA replication]], and therefore is often referred to as the ‘maintenance' methyltransferase.&lt;ref name="robertson00"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Robertson KD, Wolffe AP | title = DNA methylation in health and disease | journal = Nature Reviews. Genetics | volume = 1 | issue = 1 | pages = 11–9 | date = October 2000 | pmid = 11262868 | doi = 10.1038/35049533 }}&lt;/ref&gt; DNMT1 is essential for proper embryonic development, imprinting and X-inactivation.&lt;ref name="li92" /&gt;&lt;ref name="li93"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Li E, Beard C, Jaenisch R | title = Role for DNA methylation in genomic imprinting | journal = Nature | volume = 366 | issue = 6453 | pages = 362–5 | date = November 1993 | pmid = 8247133 | doi = 10.1038/366362a0 | bibcode = 1993Natur.366..362L }}&lt;/ref&gt; To emphasize the difference of this molecular mechanism of inheritance from the canonical Watson-Crick base-pairing mechanism of transmission of genetic information, the term 'Epigenetic templating' was introduced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Viens A, Mechold U, Brouillard F, Gilbert C, Leclerc P, Ogryzko V | title = Analysis of human histone H2AZ deposition in vivo argues against its direct role in epigenetic templating mechanisms | journal = Molecular and Cellular Biology | volume = 26 | issue = 14 | pages = 5325–35 | date = July 2006 | pmid = 16809769 | pmc = 1592707 | doi = 10.1128/MCB.00584-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in addition to the maintenance and transmission of methylated DNA states, the same principle could work in the maintenance and transmission of histone modifications and even cytoplasmic ([[Structural inheritance|structural]]) heritable states.&lt;ref name="pmid18419815"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ogryzko VV | title = Erwin Schroedinger, Francis Crick and epigenetic stability | journal = Biology Direct | volume = 3 | issue =  | pages = 15 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 18419815 | pmc = 2413215 | doi = 10.1186/1745-6150-3-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Histones H3 and H4 can also be manipulated through demethylation using histone lysine demethylase (KDM). This recently identified enzyme has a catalytically active site called the Jumonji domain (JmjC). The demethylation occurs when JmjC utilizes multiple cofactors to hydroxylate the methyl group, thereby removing it. JmjC is capable of demethylating mono-, di-, and tri-methylated substrates.&lt;ref name="pmid19234061"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nottke A, Colaiácovo MP, Shi Y | title = Developmental roles of the histone lysine demethylases | journal = Development | volume = 136 | issue = 6 | pages = 879–89 | date = March 2009 | pmid = 19234061 | pmc = 2692332 | doi = 10.1242/dev.020966 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chromosomal regions can adopt stable and heritable alternative states resulting in bistable gene expression without changes to the DNA sequence. Epigenetic control is often associated with alternative [[covalent modification]]s of histones.&lt;ref name="Rosenfeld_2009"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rosenfeld JA, Wang Z, Schones DE, Zhao K, DeSalle R, Zhang MQ | title = Determination of enriched histone modifications in non-genic portions of the human genome | journal = BMC Genomics | volume = 10 | issue =  | pages = 143 | date = March 2009 | pmid = 19335899 | pmc = 2667539 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2164-10-143 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The stability and heritability of states of larger chromosomal regions are suggested to involve positive feedback where modified [[nucleosome]]s recruit enzymes that similarly modify nearby nucleosomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sneppen K, Micheelsen MA, Dodd IB | title = Ultrasensitive gene regulation by positive feedback loops in nucleosome modification | journal = Molecular Systems Biology | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 182 | date = 15 April 2008 | pmid = 18414483 | pmc = 2387233 | doi = 10.1038/msb.2008.21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A simplified stochastic model for this type of epigenetics is found here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cmol.nbi.dk/models/epigen/Epigen.html |title=Epigenetic cell memory |publisher=Cmol.nbi.dk |access-date=26 July 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110930093915/http://cmol.nbi.dk/models/epigen/Epigen.html |archive-date=30 September 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid17512413"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dodd IB, Micheelsen MA, Sneppen K, Thon G | title = Theoretical analysis of epigenetic cell memory by nucleosome modification | journal = Cell | volume = 129 | issue = 4 | pages = 813–22 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17512413 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2007.02.053 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been suggested that chromatin-based transcriptional regulation could be mediated by the effect of small RNAs. [[Small interfering RNA]]s can modulate transcriptional gene expression via epigenetic modulation of targeted [[Promoter (biology)|promoters]].&lt;ref name="Morris"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Morris KL | title=RNA and the Regulation of Gene Expression: A Hidden Layer of Complexity | chapter=Epigenetic Regulation of Gene Expression | publisher=Caister Academic Press | location=Norfolk, England | year=2008 | pages=| isbn=978-1-904455-25-7 }}{{page needed|date=August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===RNA transcripts===
Sometimes a gene, after being turned on, transcribes a product that (directly or indirectly) maintains the activity of that gene. For example, [[Hnf4]] and [[MyoD]] enhance the transcription of many liver-specific and muscle-specific genes, respectively, including their own, through the [[transcription factor]] activity of the [[proteins]] they encode. RNA signalling includes differential recruitment of a hierarchy of generic chromatin modifying complexes and DNA methyltransferases to specific loci by RNAs during differentiation and development.&lt;ref name="pmid19154003"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mattick JS, Amaral PP, Dinger ME, Mercer TR, Mehler MF | title = RNA regulation of epigenetic processes | journal = BioEssays | volume = 31 | issue = 1 | pages = 51–9 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 19154003 | doi = 10.1002/bies.080099 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other epigenetic changes are mediated by the production of [[alternative splicing|different splice forms]] of [[RNA]], or by formation of double-stranded RNA ([[RNAi]]). Descendants of the cell in which the gene was turned on will inherit this activity, even if the original stimulus for gene-activation is no longer present. These genes are often turned on or off by [[signal transduction]], although in some systems where [[syncytia]] or [[gap junction]]s are important, RNA may spread directly to other cells or nuclei by [[diffusion]]. A large amount of RNA and protein is contributed to the [[zygote]] by the mother during [[oogenesis]] or via [[nurse cell]]s, resulting in [[maternal effect]] phenotypes. A smaller quantity of sperm RNA is transmitted from the father, but there is recent evidence that this epigenetic information can lead to visible changes in several generations of offspring.&lt;ref name="choi06"&gt;{{cite web|last=Choi |first=Charles Q. |title=RNA can be hereditary molecule |website=The Scientist |url=http://www.the-scientist.com/news/display/23494/ |date=25 May 2006 |url-status=dead |archive-date=8 February 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070208182915/http://www.the-scientist.com/news/display/23494/  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===MicroRNAs===
[[MicroRNA]]s (miRNAs) are members of [[non-coding RNA]]s that range in size from 17 to 25 nucleotides. miRNAs regulate a large variety of biological functions in plants and animals.&lt;ref name=Wang&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wang Z, Yao H, Lin S, Zhu X, Shen Z, Lu G, Poon WS, Xie D, Lin MC, Kung HF | display-authors = 6 | title = Transcriptional and epigenetic regulation of human microRNAs | journal = Cancer Letters | volume = 331 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–10 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23246373 | doi = 10.1016/j.canlet.2012.12.006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; So far, in 2013, about 2000 miRNAs have been discovered in humans and these can be found online in a miRNA database.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mirbase.org/cgi-bin/browse.pl Browse miRBase by species&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Each miRNA expressed in a cell may target about 100 to 200 messenger RNAs(mRNAs) that it downregulates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lim LP, Lau NC, Garrett-Engele P, Grimson A, Schelter JM, Castle J, Bartel DP, Linsley PS, Johnson JM | display-authors = 6 | title = Microarray analysis shows that some microRNAs downregulate large numbers of target mRNAs | journal = Nature | volume = 433 | issue = 7027 | pages = 769–73 | date = February 2005 | pmid = 15685193 | doi = 10.1038/nature03315 | bibcode = 2005Natur.433..769L }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the downregulation of mRNAs occurs by causing the decay of the targeted mRNA, while some downregulation occurs at the level of translation into protein.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lee D, Shin C | title = MicroRNA-target interactions: new insights from genome-wide approaches | journal = Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences | volume = 1271 | issue = 1 | pages = 118–28 | date = October 2012 | pmid = 23050973 | pmc = 3499661 | doi = 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06745.x | bibcode = 2012NYASA1271..118L }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It appears that about 60% of human protein coding genes are regulated by miRNAs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Friedman RC, Farh KK, Burge CB, Bartel DP | title = Most mammalian mRNAs are conserved targets of microRNAs | journal = Genome Research | volume = 19 | issue = 1 | pages = 92–105 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 18955434 | pmc = 2612969 | doi = 10.1101/gr.082701.108 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many miRNAs are epigenetically regulated. About 50% of miRNA genes are associated with [[CpG island]]s,&lt;ref name=Wang /&gt; that may be repressed by epigenetic methylation. Transcription from methylated CpG islands is strongly and heritably repressed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Goll MG, Bestor TH | s2cid = 32123961 | title = Eukaryotic cytosine methyltransferases | journal = Annual Review of Biochemistry | volume = 74 | issue =  | pages = 481–514 | year = 2005 | pmid = 15952895 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.biochem.74.010904.153721 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other miRNAs are epigenetically regulated by either histone modifications or by combined DNA methylation and histone modification.&lt;ref name=Wang /&gt;

===mRNA===
In 2011, it was demonstrated that the [[methylation]] of [[messenger RNA|mRNA]] plays a critical role in human [[energy balance (biology)|energy homeostasis]]. The obesity-associated [[FTO gene]] is shown to be able to [[demethylate]] [[N6-methyladenosine]] in RNA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jia G, Fu Y, Zhao X, Dai Q, Zheng G, Yang Y, Yi C, Lindahl T, Pan T, Yang YG, He C | display-authors = 6 | title = N6-methyladenosine in nuclear RNA is a major substrate of the obesity-associated FTO | journal = Nature Chemical Biology | volume = 7 | issue = 12 | pages = 885–7 | date = October 2011 | pmid = 22002720 | pmc = 3218240 | doi = 10.1038/nchembio.687 | author9 = Tao Pan | author10 = Yun-Gui Yang | author11 = Chuan He | first8 = Tomas | last8 = Lindahl }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.physorg.com/news/2011-10-links-common-rna-modification-obesity.html |title=New research links common RNA modification to obesity |publisher=Physorg.com |access-date=26 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===sRNAs===
[[Bacterial small RNA|sRNAs]] are small (50–250 nucleotides), highly structured, non-coding RNA fragments found in bacteria. They control gene expression including [[virulence]] genes in pathogens and are viewed as new targets in the fight against drug-resistant bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Howden BP, Beaume M, Harrison PF, Hernandez D, Schrenzel J, Seemann T, Francois P, Stinear TP | display-authors = 6 | title = Analysis of the small RNA transcriptional response in multidrug-resistant Staphylococcus aureus after antimicrobial exposure | journal = Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy | volume = 57 | issue = 8 | pages = 3864–74 | date = August 2013 | pmid = 23733475 | pmc = 3719707 | doi = 10.1128/AAC.00263-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They play an important role in many biological processes, binding to mRNA and protein targets in prokaryotes. Their phylogenetic analyses, for example through sRNA–mRNA target interactions or protein [[Hfq binding sRNA|binding properties]], are used to build comprehensive databases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ccb.bmi.ac.cn/srnatarbase/ sRNATarBase 2.0 A comprehensive database of bacterial SRNA targets verified by experiments] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130926215123/http://ccb.bmi.ac.cn/srnatarbase/ |date=26 September 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; sRNA-[[gene map]]s based on their targets in microbial genomes are also constructed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://srnamap.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/ Genomics maps for small non-coding RNA's and their targets in microbial genomes]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prions===
{{details|Fungal prions}}
[[Prion]]s are [[Infection|infectious]] forms of [[protein]]s. In general, proteins fold into discrete units that perform distinct cellular functions, but some proteins are also capable of forming an infectious conformational state known as a prion. Although often viewed in the context of [[Transmissible spongiform encephalopathy|infectious disease]], prions are more loosely defined by their ability to catalytically convert other native state versions of the same protein to an infectious conformational state. It is in this latter sense that they can be viewed as epigenetic agents capable of inducing a phenotypic change without a modification of the genome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Epigenetic inheritance and prions|vauthors=Yool A, Edmunds WJ | journal=Journal of Evolutionary Biology | year=1998 | pages=241–42 | volume=11 | doi=10.1007/s000360050085 | issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fungal prion]]s are considered by some to be epigenetic because the infectious phenotype caused by the prion can be inherited without modification of the genome. [[PSI (prion)|PSI+]] and URE3, discovered in [[Saccharomyces cerevisiae|yeast]] in 1965 and 1971, are the two best studied of this type of prion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=[PSI], a cytoplasmic suppressor of super-suppression in yeast | vauthors = Cox BS| journal=Heredity | volume=20 | pages=505–21 | year=1965 | doi=10.1038/hdy.1965.65 | issue=4| doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid5573734"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lacroute F | title = Non-Mendelian mutation allowing ureidosuccinic acid uptake in yeast | journal = Journal of Bacteriology | volume = 106 | issue = 2 | pages = 519–22 | date = May 1971 | pmid = 5573734 | pmc = 285125 | doi =  10.1128/JB.106.2.519-522.1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prions can have a phenotypic effect through the sequestration of protein in aggregates, thereby reducing that protein's activity. In PSI+ cells, the loss of the Sup35 protein (which is involved in termination of translation) causes ribosomes to have a higher rate of read-through of stop [[codon]]s, an effect that results in suppression of [[nonsense mutation]]s in other genes.&lt;ref name="pmid225301"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Liebman SW, Sherman F | title = Extrachromosomal psi+ determinant suppresses nonsense mutations in yeast | journal = Journal of Bacteriology | volume = 139 | issue = 3 | pages = 1068–71 | date = September 1979 | pmid = 225301 | pmc = 218059 | doi =  10.1128/JB.139.3.1068-1071.1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ability of Sup35 to form prions may be a conserved trait. It could confer an adaptive advantage by giving cells the ability to [[Evolutionary capacitance|switch into a PSI+ state]] and express dormant genetic features normally terminated by stop codon mutations.&lt;ref name="pmid11028992"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = True HL, Lindquist SL | title = A yeast prion provides a mechanism for genetic variation and phenotypic diversity | journal = Nature | volume = 407 | issue = 6803 | pages = 477–83 | date = September 2000 | pmid = 11028992 | doi = 10.1038/35035005 | bibcode = 2000Natur.407..477T }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid15931169"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Shorter J, Lindquist S | title = Prions as adaptive conduits of memory and inheritance | journal = Nature Reviews. Genetics | volume = 6 | issue = 6 | pages = 435–50 | date = June 2005 | pmid = 15931169 | doi = 10.1038/nrg1616 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Giacomelli MG, Hancock AS, Masel J | title = The conversion of 3' UTRs into coding regions | journal = Molecular Biology and Evolution | volume = 24 | issue = 2 | pages = 457–64 | date = February 2007 | pmid = 17099057 | pmc = 1808353 | doi = 10.1093/molbev/msl172 | author3link = Joanna Masel }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lancaster AK, Bardill JP, True HL, Masel J | title = The spontaneous appearance rate of the yeast prion [PSI+] and its implications for the evolution of the evolvability properties of the [PSI+] system | journal = Genetics | volume = 184 | issue = 2 | pages = 393–400 | date = February 2010 | pmid = 19917766 | pmc = 2828720 | doi = 10.1534/genetics.109.110213 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Structural inheritance===
{{details|Structural inheritance}}
In [[ciliate]]s such as ''[[Tetrahymena]]'' and ''[[Paramecium]]'', genetically identical cells show heritable differences in the patterns of ciliary rows on their cell surface. Experimentally altered patterns can be transmitted to daughter cells. It seems existing structures act as templates for new structures. The mechanisms of such inheritance are unclear, but reasons exist to assume that multicellular organisms also use existing cell structures to assemble new ones.&lt;ref name="pmid1804215"&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1007/978-1-4615-6823-0_11 |pmid=1804215 |chapter=Concepts of Organization the Leverage of Ciliate Protozoa |title=A Conceptual History of Modern Embryology |series=Developmental Biology |volume=7 |pages=229–258 |year=1991 |last1=Sapp |first1=Jan |isbn=978-1-4615-6825-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="isbn0-19-515619-6"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors=Sapp J | title=Genesis: the evolution of biology | publisher=Oxford University Press | location=Oxford | year=2003 | pages= | isbn=978-0-19-515619-5 | url-access=registration | url=https://archive.org/details/genesisevolution00sapp }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="isbn0-262-65063-0"&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Gray RD, Oyama S, Griffiths PE | title=Cycles of Contingency: Developmental Systems and Evolution (Life and Mind: Philosophical Issues in Biology and Psychology) | publisher=The MIT Press | location=Cambridge, Massachusetts | year=2003 | pages=| isbn=978-0-262-65063-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nucleosome positioning===
Eukaryotic genomes have numerous [[nucleosomes]]. Nucleosome position is not random, and determine the accessibility of DNA to regulatory proteins. Promoters active in different tissues have been shown to have different nucleosome positioning features.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Serizay|first1=Jacques|last2=Dong|first2=Yan|last3=Janes|first3=Jurgen|last4=Chesney|first4=Michael A.|last5=Cerrato|first5=Chiara|last6=Ahringer|first6=Julie|date=2020-02-20|title=Tissue-specific profiling reveals distinctive regulatory architectures for ubiquitous, germline and somatic genes|url=https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.02.20.958579v1|journal=bioRxiv|language=en|pages=2020.02.20.958579|doi=10.1101/2020.02.20.958579|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; This determines differences in gene expression and cell differentiation. It has been shown that at least some nucleosomes are retained in sperm cells (where most but not all histones are replaced by [[protamines]]). Thus nucleosome positioning is to some degree inheritable. Recent studies have uncovered connections between nucleosome positioning and other epigenetic factors, such as DNA methylation and hydroxymethylation.&lt;ref name=Teif_2014&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Teif VB, Beshnova DA, Vainshtein Y, Marth C, Mallm JP, Höfer T, Rippe K | title = Nucleosome repositioning links DNA (de)methylation and differential CTCF binding during stem cell development | journal = Genome Research | volume = 24 | issue = 8 | pages = 1285–95 | date = August 2014 | pmid = 24812327 | pmc = 4120082 | doi = 10.1101/gr.164418.113 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Functions and consequences==

===Development===
Developmental epigenetics can be divided into predetermined and probabilistic epigenesis. Predetermined epigenesis is a unidirectional movement from structural development in DNA to the functional maturation of the protein. "Predetermined" here means that development is scripted and predictable. Probabilistic epigenesis on the other hand is a bidirectional structure-function development with experiences and external molding development.&lt;ref name=Griesemer_2005&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Griesemer J, Haber MH, Yamashita G, Gannett L | title=Critical Notice: Cycles of Contingency – Developmental Systems and Evolution | journal=Biology &amp; Philosophy |date=March 2005 | volume=20 | issue =2–3 | pages=517–44 | doi=10.1007/s10539-004-0836-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Somatic epigenetic inheritance, particularly through DNA and histone covalent modifications and [[nucleosome]] repositioning, is very important in the development of multicellular eukaryotic organisms.&lt;ref name="Teif_2014"/&gt; The genome sequence is static (with some notable exceptions), but cells differentiate into many different types, which perform different functions, and respond differently to the environment and intercellular signaling. Thus, as individuals develop, [[morphogen]]s activate or silence genes in an epigenetically heritable fashion, giving cells a memory. In mammals, most cells terminally differentiate, with only [[stem cells]] retaining the ability to differentiate into several cell types ("totipotency" and "multipotency"). In [[mammal]]s, some stem cells continue producing newly differentiated cells throughout life, such as in [[Epigenetic Regulation of Neurogenesis|neurogenesis]], but mammals are not able to respond to loss of some tissues, for example, the inability to regenerate limbs, which some other animals are capable of. Epigenetic modifications regulate the transition from neural stem cells to glial progenitor cells (for example, differentiation into oligodendrocytes is regulated by the deacetylation and methylation of histones.&lt;ref&gt;Chapter: "Nervous System Development" in "Epigenetics," by Benedikt Hallgrimsson and Brian Hall&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike animals, plant cells do not terminally differentiate, remaining totipotent with the ability to give rise to a new individual plant. While plants do utilize many of the same epigenetic mechanisms as animals, such as [[chromatin remodeling]], it has been hypothesized that some kinds of plant cells do not use or require "cellular memories", resetting their gene expression patterns using positional information from the environment and surrounding cells to determine their fate.&lt;ref name="pmid17194589"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Costa S, Shaw P | title = 'Open minded' cells: how cells can change fate | journal = Trends in Cell Biology | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = 101–6 | date = March 2007 | pmid = 17194589 | doi = 10.1016/j.tcb.2006.12.005 | url = http://cromatina.icb.ufmg.br/biomol/seminarios/outros/grupo_open.pdf | url-status = dead | quote = This might suggest that plant cells do not use or require a cellular memory mechanism and just respond to positional information. However, it has been shown that plants do use cellular memory mechanisms mediated by PcG proteins in several processes, ... (p. 104) | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131215042638/http://cromatina.icb.ufmg.br/biomol/seminarios/outros/grupo_open.pdf | df = dmy-all | archive-date = 15 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Epigenetic changes can occur in response to environmental exposure – for example, maternal dietary supplementation with [[genistein]] (250&amp;nbsp;mg/kg) have epigenetic changes affecting expression of the [[agouti gene]], which affects their fur color, weight, and propensity to develop cancer.&lt;ref name="pmid12163699"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cooney CA, Dave AA, Wolff GL | title = Maternal methyl supplements in mice affect epigenetic variation and DNA methylation of offspring | journal = The Journal of Nutrition | volume = 132 | issue = 8 Suppl | pages = 2393S–2400S | date = August 2002 | pmid = 12163699 | doi = 10.1093/jn/132.8.2393S | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="waterland"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Waterland RA, Jirtle RL | title = Transposable elements: targets for early nutritional effects on epigenetic gene regulation | journal = Molecular and Cellular Biology | volume = 23 | issue = 15 | pages = 5293–300 | date = August 2003 | pmid = 12861015 | pmc = 165709 | doi = 10.1128/MCB.23.15.5293-5300.2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dolinoy DC | title = The agouti mouse model: an epigenetic biosensor for nutritional and environmental alterations on the fetal epigenome | journal = Nutrition Reviews | volume = 66 | issue = Suppl 1 | pages = S7-11 | date = August 2008 | pmid = 18673496 | pmc = 2822875 | doi = 10.1111/j.1753-4887.2008.00056.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Controversial results from one study suggested that traumatic experiences might produce an epigenetic signal that is capable of being passed to future generations. Mice were trained, using foot shocks, to fear a cherry blossom odor. The investigators reported that the mouse offspring had an increased aversion to this specific odor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=fearful-memories-passed-down&amp;print=true Fearful Memories Passed Down to Mouse Descendants: Genetic imprint from traumatic experiences carries through at least two generations], By Ewen Callaway and Nature magazine | Sunday, 1 December 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://medicalxpress.com/news/2013-12-mice-sons-grandsons-dangers-sperm.html#ajTabs Mice can 'warn' sons, grandsons of dangers via sperm], by Mariette Le Roux, 12/1/13.&lt;/ref&gt; They suggested epigenetic changes that increase gene expression, rather than in DNA itself, in a gene, M71, that governs the functioning of an odor receptor in the nose that responds specifically to this cherry blossom smell. There were physical changes that correlated with olfactory (smell) function in the brains of the trained mice and their descendants. Several criticisms were reported, including the study's low statistical power as evidence of some irregularity such as bias in reporting results.&lt;ref&gt;G. Francis, "Too Much Success for Recent Groundbreaking Epigenetic Experiments" http://www.genetics.org/content/198/2/449.abstract&lt;/ref&gt; Due to limits of sample size, there is a probability that an effect will not be demonstrated to within statistical significance even if it exists. The criticism suggested that the probability that all the experiments reported would show positive results if an identical protocol was followed, assuming the claimed effects exist, is merely 0.4%. The authors also did not indicate which mice were siblings, and treated all of the mice as statistically independent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dias BG, Ressler KJ | title = Parental olfactory experience influences behavior and neural structure in subsequent generations | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 17 | issue = 1 | pages = 89–96 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 24292232 | pmc = 3923835 | doi = 10.1038/nn.3594 }} (see comment by Gonzalo Otazu)&lt;/ref&gt; The original researchers pointed out negative results in the paper's appendix that the criticism omitted in its calculations, and undertook to track which mice were siblings in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.the-scientist.com/?articles.view/articleNo/41239/title/Epigenetics-Paper-Raises-Questions/ | title=Epigenetics Paper Raises Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transgenerational===
{{main|Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance}}
&lt;!--Note that the first sentence of this section clashes with the first sentence of the article defining 'epigenetics', by which epigenetics is necessarily heritable. This may arise from confusing the molecular marks sometimes associated with epigenetic variation (e.g. DNA methylation) with epigenetic phenotypic variation itself.--&gt;
Epigenetic mechanisms were a necessary part of the evolutionary origin of [[cell differentiation]].&lt;ref name="isbn0-19-854968-7"&gt;{{cite book | author = Hoekstra RF | title = Evolution: an introduction | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | year = 2000 | page = 285 | isbn = 978-0-19-854968-0  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although epigenetics in multicellular organisms is generally thought to be a mechanism involved in differentiation, with epigenetic patterns "reset" when organisms reproduce, there have been some observations of transgenerational epigenetic inheritance (e.g., the phenomenon of [[paramutation]] observed in [[maize]]). Although most of these multigenerational epigenetic traits are gradually lost over several generations, the possibility remains that multigenerational epigenetics could be another aspect to evolution and adaptation.
As mentioned above, some define epigenetics as heritable. The chromatin landscape is recognized to be pivotal in composing the epigenome, and as such there are a variety of known mechanisms projected to allow for this chromatin landscape to be passed on. Among these mechanisms are models of histone recycling after replication, positive-feedback loops, long-range gene interactions, and networks of trans-acting factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Margueron|first1=Raphaël|last2=Reinberg|first2=Danny|date=April 2010|title=Chromatin structure and the inheritance of epigenetic information|journal=Nature Reviews Genetics|language=en|volume=11|issue=4|pages=285–296|doi=10.1038/nrg2752|pmid=20300089|pmc=3760772|issn=1471-0064}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A sequestered germ line or [[Weismann barrier]] is specific to animals, and epigenetic inheritance is more common in plants and microbes. [[Eva Jablonka]], [[Marion J. Lamb]] and Étienne Danchin have argued that these effects may require enhancements to the standard conceptual framework of the [[modern synthesis (20th century)|modern synthesis]] and have called for an [[extended evolutionary synthesis]].&lt;ref name="isbn0-262-10107-6"&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Lamb MJ, Jablonka E | title=Evolution in four dimensions: genetic, epigenetic, behavioral, and symbolic variation in the history of life | journal=Journal of Clinical Investigation | publisher=MIT Press | location=Cambridge, Massachusetts | year=2005 | volume=115 | issue=11 | page=2961 | isbn=978-0-262-10107-3 | oclc=| doi= 10.1172/JCI27017| pmc=1265888 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also [[Denis Noble]] ''The Music of Life'' see esp pp. 93–98 and p. 48 where he cites Jablonka &amp; Lamb {{cite journal |url=https://www.nature.com/articles/435565a |authorlink=Massimo Pigliucci |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]|doi=10.1038/435565a |title=Expanding evolution |year=2005 |last1=Pigliucci |first1=Massimo |volume=435 |issue=7042 |pages=565–566 |bibcode=2005Natur.435..565P }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Danchin É, Charmantier A, Champagne FA, Mesoudi A, Pujol B, Blanchet S | title = Beyond DNA: integrating inclusive inheritance into an extended theory of evolution | journal = Nature Reviews. Genetics | volume = 12 | issue = 7 | pages = 475–86 | date = June 2011 | pmid = 21681209 | doi = 10.1038/nrg3028 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other evolutionary biologists, such as [[John Maynard Smith]], have incorporated epigenetic inheritance into [[population genetics]] models&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Maynard Smith J | title = Models of a dual inheritance system | journal = Journal of Theoretical Biology | volume = 143 | issue = 1 | pages = 41–53 | date = March 1990 | pmid = 2359317 | doi = 10.1016/S0022-5193(05)80287-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or are openly skeptical of the extended evolutionary synthesis ([[Michael Lynch (geneticist)|Michael Lynch]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lynch M | title = The frailty of adaptive hypotheses for the origins of organismal complexity | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 104 | issue = Suppl 1 | pages = 8597–604 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17494740 | pmc = 1876435 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0702207104 | bibcode = 2007PNAS..104.8597L }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thomas Dickins]] and [[Qazi Rahman]] state that epigenetic mechanisms such as DNA methylation and histone modification are genetically inherited under the control of [[natural selection]] and therefore fit under the earlier "[[Modern synthesis (20th century)|modern synthesis]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dickins TE, Rahman Q | title = The extended evolutionary synthesis and the role of soft inheritance in evolution | journal = Proceedings. Biological Sciences | volume = 279 | issue = 1740 | pages = 2913–21 | date = August 2012 | pmid = 22593110 | pmc = 3385474 | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2012.0273 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two important ways in which epigenetic inheritance can be different from traditional genetic inheritance, with important consequences for evolution, are that rates of epimutation can be much faster than rates of mutation&lt;ref name=rando_and_verstrepen&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rando OJ, Verstrepen KJ | title = Timescales of genetic and epigenetic inheritance | journal = Cell | volume = 128 | issue = 4 | pages = 655–68 | date = February 2007 | pmid = 17320504 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2007.01.023 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the epimutations are more easily reversible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lancaster AK, Masel J | title = The evolution of reversible switches in the presence of irreversible mimics | journal = Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution | volume = 63 | issue = 9 | pages = 2350–62 | date = September 2009 | pmid = 19486147 | pmc = 2770902 | doi = 10.1111/j.1558-5646.2009.00729.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; In plants, heritable DNA methylation mutations are 100,000 times more likely to occur compared to DNA mutations.&lt;ref name=van_der_Graaf_et_al&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = van der Graaf A, Wardenaar R, Neumann DA, Taudt A, Shaw RG, Jansen RC, Schmitz RJ, Colomé-Tatché M, Johannes F | display-authors = 6 | title = Rate, spectrum, and evolutionary dynamics of spontaneous epimutations | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 112 | issue = 21 | pages = 6676–81 | date = May 2015 | pmid = 25964364 | pmc = 4450394 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1424254112 | bibcode = 2015PNAS..112.6676V }}&lt;/ref&gt; An epigenetically inherited element such as the [[PSI (prion)|PSI+]] system can act as a "stop-gap", good enough for short-term adaptation that allows the lineage to survive for long enough for mutation and/or recombination to [[genetic assimilation|genetically assimilate]] the adaptive phenotypic change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Griswold CK, Masel J | title = Complex adaptations can drive the evolution of the capacitor [PSI], even with realistic rates of yeast sex | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 5 | issue = 6 | pages = e1000517 | date = June 2009 | pmid = 19521499 | pmc = 2686163 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.1000517 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The existence of this possibility increases the [[evolvability]] of a species.

More than 100&amp;nbsp;cases of [[transgenerational epigenetic inheritance]] phenomena have been reported in a wide range of organisms, including prokaryotes, plants, and animals.&lt;ref name="Jablonka09"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jablonka E, Raz G | title = Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance: prevalence, mechanisms, and implications for the study of heredity and evolution | journal = The Quarterly Review of Biology | volume = 84 | issue = 2 | pages = 131–76 | date = June 2009 | pmid = 19606595 | doi = 10.1086/598822 | url = http://compgen.unc.edu/wiki/images/d/df/JablonkaQtrRevBio2009.pdf | citeseerx = 10.1.1.617.6333 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, [[Nymphalis antiopa|mourning cloak butterflies]] will change color through hormone changes in response to experimentation of varying temperatures.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, Hazel (2008). Do Butterflies Bite?: Fascinating Answers to Questions about Butterflies and Moths (Animals Q&amp;A). Rutgers University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, experiments performed on mice and rats have concluded that metabolic and environmental changes for the organisms can yield generational effects, such as induced pre-diabetic mice whose F1 and F2 generations showed similar methylation patterns to the original pre-diabetic father.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Horsthemke|first=Bernhard|date=2018-07-30|title=A critical view on transgenerational epigenetic inheritance in humans|journal=Nature Communications|language=en|volume=9|issue=1|pages=2973|doi=10.1038/s41467-018-05445-5|pmid=30061690|pmc=6065375|bibcode=2018NatCo...9.2973H|issn=2041-1723}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The filamentous fungus ''Neurospora crassa'' is a prominent model system for understanding the control and function of cytosine methylation. In this organism, DNA methylation is associated with relics of a genome defense system called RIP (repeat-induced point mutation) and silences gene expression by inhibiting transcription elongation.&lt;ref name="pmid19092133"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lewis ZA, Honda S, Khlafallah TK, Jeffress JK, Freitag M, Mohn F, Schübeler D, Selker EU | display-authors = 6 | title = Relics of repeat-induced point mutation direct heterochromatin formation in Neurospora crassa | journal = Genome Research | volume = 19 | issue = 3 | pages = 427–37 | date = March 2009 | pmid = 19092133 | pmc = 2661801 | doi = 10.1101/gr.086231.108 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[yeast]] [[prion]] PSI is generated by a conformational change of a translation termination factor, which is then inherited by daughter cells. This can provide a survival advantage under adverse conditions. This is an example of epigenetic regulation enabling unicellular organisms to respond rapidly to environmental stress. Prions can be viewed as epigenetic agents capable of inducing a phenotypic change without modification of the genome.&lt;ref name=JorgTost&gt;{{cite book | first = Jorg | last = Tost | name-list-format = vanc | title=Epigenetics | publisher=Caister Academic Press | location=Norfolk, England | year=2008 | pages=| isbn=978-1-904455-23-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Direct detection of epigenetic marks in microorganisms is possible with [[single molecule real time sequencing]], in which polymerase sensitivity allows for measuring methylation and other modifications as a DNA molecule is being sequenced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schadt EE, Banerjee O, Fang G, Feng Z, Wong WH, Zhang X, Kislyuk A, Clark TA, Luong K, Keren-Paz A, Chess A, Kumar V, Chen-Plotkin A, Sondheimer N, Korlach J, Kasarskis A | display-authors = 6 | title = Modeling kinetic rate variation in third generation DNA sequencing data to detect putative modifications to DNA bases | journal = Genome Research | volume = 23 | issue = 1 | pages = 129–41 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 23093720 | pmc = 3530673 | doi = 10.1101/gr.136739.111 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several projects have demonstrated the ability to collect genome-wide epigenetic data in bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Davis BM, Chao MC, Waldor MK | title = Entering the era of bacterial epigenomics with single molecule real time DNA sequencing | journal = Current Opinion in Microbiology | volume = 16 | issue = 2 | pages = 192–8 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23434113 | pmc = 3646917 | doi = 10.1016/j.mib.2013.01.011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lluch-Senar M, Luong K, Lloréns-Rico V, Delgado J, Fang G, Spittle K, Clark TA, Schadt E, Turner SW, Korlach J, Serrano L | display-authors = 6 | title = Comprehensive methylome characterization of Mycoplasma genitalium and Mycoplasma pneumoniae at single-base resolution | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 9 | issue = 1 | pages = e1003191 | year = 2013 | pmid = 23300489 | pmc = 3536716 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.1003191 | editor1-last = Richardson | editor1-first = Paul M }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Murray IA, Clark TA, Morgan RD, Boitano M, Anton BP, Luong K, Fomenkov A, Turner SW, Korlach J, Roberts RJ | display-authors = 6 | title = The methylomes of six bacteria | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 40 | issue = 22 | pages = 11450–62 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 23034806 | pmc = 3526280 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gks891 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fang G, Munera D, Friedman DI, Mandlik A, Chao MC, Banerjee O, Feng Z, Losic B, Mahajan MC, Jabado OJ, Deikus G, Clark TA, Luong K, Murray IA, Davis BM, Keren-Paz A, Chess A, Roberts RJ, Korlach J, Turner SW, Kumar V, Waldor MK, Schadt EE | display-authors = 6 | title = Genome-wide mapping of methylated adenine residues in pathogenic Escherichia coli using single-molecule real-time sequencing | journal = Nature Biotechnology | volume = 30 | issue = 12 | pages = 1232–9 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 23138224 | pmc = 3879109 | doi = 10.1038/nbt.2432 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Epigenetics in bacteria ==
[[File:Escherichia coli flagella TEM.png|thumb|150px|''Escherichia coli'' bacteria]]
While epigenetics is of fundamental importance in [[eukaryote]]s, especially [[Multicellular organism|metazoans]], it plays a different role in bacteria. Most importantly, eukaryotes use epigenetic mechanisms primarily to regulate gene expression which bacteria rarely do. However, bacteria make widespread use of postreplicative DNA methylation for the epigenetic control of DNA-protein interactions. Bacteria also use DNA [[adenine]] methylation (rather than DNA [[cytosine]] methylation) as an epigenetic signal. DNA adenine methylation is important in bacteria virulence in organisms such as ''[[Escherichia coli]]'', ''[[Salmonella]], [[Vibrio]], [[Yersinia]], [[Haemophilus]]'', and ''[[Brucella]]''. In ''[[Alphaproteobacteria]]'', methylation of adenine regulates the cell cycle and couples gene transcription to DNA replication. In ''[[Gammaproteobacteria]]'', adenine methylation provides signals for DNA replication, chromosome segregation, mismatch repair, packaging of bacteriophage, transposase activity and regulation of gene expression.&lt;ref name="JorgTost" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Casadesus"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Casadesús J, Low D | title = Epigenetic gene regulation in the bacterial world | journal = Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews | volume = 70 | issue = 3 | pages = 830–56 | date = September 2006 | pmid = 16959970 | pmc = 1594586 | doi = 10.1128/MMBR.00016-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There exists a genetic switch controlling ''[[Streptococcus pneumoniae]]'' (the pneumococcus) that allows the bacterium to randomly change its characteristics into six alternative states that could pave the way to improved vaccines. Each form is randomly generated by a phase variable methylation system. The ability of the pneumococcus to cause deadly infections is different in each of these six states. Similar systems exist in other bacterial genera.&lt;ref name="MansoOggioni2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Manso AS, Chai MH, Atack JM, Furi L, De Ste Croix M, Haigh R, Trappetti C, Ogunniyi AD, Shewell LK, Boitano M, Clark TA, Korlach J, Blades M, Mirkes E, Gorban AN, Paton JC, Jennings MP, Oggioni MR | display-authors = 6 | title = A random six-phase switch regulates pneumococcal virulence via global epigenetic changes | journal = Nature Communications | volume = 5 | issue =  | pages = 5055 | date = September 2014 | pmid = 25268848 | pmc = 4190663 | doi = 10.1038/ncomms6055 | bibcode = 2014NatCo...5.5055M }}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Firmicutes]]'' such as ''[[Clostridioides difficile (bacteria)|Clostridioides difficile]],'' adenine methylation regulates [[Spore|sporulation]], [[biofilm]] formation and host-adaptation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Oliveira PH, Ribis JW, Garrett EM, Trzilova D, Kim A, Sekulovic O, Mead EA, Pak T, Zhu S, Deikus G, Touchon M, Lewis-Sandari M, Beckford C, Zeitouni NE, Altman DR, Webster E, Oussenko I, Bunyavanich S, Aggarwal AK, Bashir A, Patel G, Wallach F, Hamula C, Huprikar S, Schadt EE, Sebra R, van Bakel H, Kasarskis A, Tamayo R, Shen A, Fang G | display-authors = 6 | title = Epigenomic characterization of Clostridioides difficile finds a conserved DNA methyltransferase that mediates sporulation and pathogenesis | journal = Nature Microbiology | volume = 5 | issue = 1 | pages = 166–180 | date = January 2020 | pmid = 31768029 | pmc = 6925328 | doi = 10.1038/s41564-019-0613-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Highly conserved DNA methyltransferases of the m4C, m5C, and m6A types have been reported,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Oliveira|first1=Pedro H.|last2=Fang|first2=Gang|date=2020-05-13|title=Conserved DNA Methyltransferases: A Window into Fundamental Mechanisms of Epigenetic Regulation in Bacteria|url=https://www.cell.com/trends/microbiology/fulltext/S0966-842X(20)30100-1|journal=Trends in Microbiology|language=en|doi=10.1016/j.tim.2020.04.007|pmid=32417228}}&lt;/ref&gt; which appear as promising targets for the development of novel epigenetic inhibitors to fight bacterial virulence, antibiotic resistance, among other biomedical applications.

==Medicine==
Epigenetics has many and varied potential medical applications.&lt;ref name="pmid21447282"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chahwan R, Wontakal SN, Roa S | title = The multidimensional nature of epigenetic information and its role in disease | journal = Discovery Medicine | volume = 11 | issue = 58 | pages = 233–43 | date = March 2011 | pmid = 21447282 | doi =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the National Institutes of Health announced that $190 million had been earmarked for epigenetics research over the next five years. In announcing the funding, government officials noted that epigenetics has the potential to explain mechanisms of aging, human development, and the origins of cancer, heart disease, mental illness, as well as several other conditions. Some investigators, like [[Randy Jirtle]], Ph.D., of Duke University Medical Center, think epigenetics may ultimately turn out to have a greater role in disease than genetics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Laura |last=Beil |title=Medicine's New Epicenter? Epigenetics: New field of epigenetics may hold the secret to flipping cancer's "off" switch. |date=Winter 2008 |publisher=CURE (Cancer Updates, Research and Education) |url=http://www.curetoday.com/index.cfm/fuseaction/article.show/id/2/article_id/949 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090529011629/http://www.curetoday.com/index.cfm/fuseaction/article.show/id/2/article_id/949 |archive-date=29 May 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twins===
Direct comparisons of identical twins constitute an optimal model for interrogating environmental epigenetics. In the case of humans with different environmental exposures, monozygotic (identical) twins were epigenetically indistinguishable during their early years, while older twins had remarkable differences in the overall content and genomic distribution of 5-methylcytosine DNA and histone acetylation.&lt;ref name="Moore_2015"/&gt; The twin pairs who had spent less of their lifetime together and/or had greater differences in their medical histories were those who showed the largest differences in their levels of 5-methylcytosine DNA and acetylation of histones H3 and H4.&lt;ref name="pmid16009939" /&gt;

Dizygotic (fraternal) and monozygotic (identical) twins show evidence of epigenetic influence in humans.&lt;ref name="pmid16009939"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fraga MF, Ballestar E, Paz MF, Ropero S, Setien F, Ballestar ML, Heine-Suñer D, Cigudosa JC, Urioste M, Benitez J, Boix-Chornet M, Sanchez-Aguilera A, Ling C, Carlsson E, Poulsen P, Vaag A, Stephan Z, Spector TD, Wu YZ, Plass C, Esteller M | display-authors = 6 | title = Epigenetic differences arise during the lifetime of monozygotic twins | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 102 | issue = 30 | pages = 10604–9 | date = July 2005 | pmid = 16009939 | pmc = 1174919 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0500398102 | bibcode = 2005PNAS..10210604F }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid19151718"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kaminsky ZA, Tang T, Wang SC, Ptak C, Oh GH, Wong AH, Feldcamp LA, Virtanen C, Halfvarson J, Tysk C, McRae AF, Visscher PM, Montgomery GW, Gottesman II, Martin NG, Petronis A | display-authors = 6 | title = DNA methylation profiles in monozygotic and dizygotic twins | journal = Nature Genetics | volume = 41 | issue = 2 | pages = 240–5 | date = February 2009 | pmid = 19151718 | doi = 10.1038/ng.286 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Claim: Identical Twins Have Identical DNA|newspaper=New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/11/health/11real.html| first=Anahad | last=O'Connor | date=11 March 2008 | access-date=2 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; DNA sequence differences that would be abundant in a singleton-based study do not interfere with the analysis. Environmental differences can produce long-term epigenetic effects, and different developmental monozygotic twin subtypes may be different with respect to their susceptibility to be discordant from an epigenetic point of view.&lt;ref name="pmid19653134"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ballestar E | title = Epigenetics lessons from twins: prospects for autoimmune disease | journal = Clinical Reviews in Allergy &amp; Immunology | volume = 39 | issue = 1 | pages = 30–41 | date = August 2010 | pmid = 19653134 | doi = 10.1007/s12016-009-8168-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A high-throughput study, which denotes technology that looks at extensive genetic markers, focused on epigenetic differences between monozygotic twins to compare global and locus-specific changes in DNA methylation and histone modifications in a sample of 40 monozygotic twin pairs.&lt;ref name="pmid16009939" /&gt; In this case, only healthy twin pairs were studied, but a wide range of ages was represented, between 3 and 74 years. One of the major conclusions from this study was that there is an age-dependent accumulation of epigenetic differences between the two siblings of twin pairs. This accumulation suggests the existence of epigenetic "drift". Epigenetic drift is the term given to epigenetic modifications as they occur as a direct function with age. While age is a known risk factor for many diseases, age-related methylation has been found to occur differentially at specific sites along the genome. Over time, this can result in measurable differences between biological and chronological age. Epigenetic changes have been found to be reflective of lifestyle and may act as functional biomarkers of disease before clinical threshold is reached.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wallace RG, Twomey LC, Custaud MA, Moyna N, Cummins PM, Mangone M, Murphy RP | title = Potential Diagnostic and Prognostic Biomarkers of Epigenetic Drift within the Cardiovascular Compartment | journal = BioMed Research International | volume = 2016 | issue =  | pages = 2465763 | year = 2016 | pmid = 26942189 | pmc = 4749768 | doi = 10.1155/2016/2465763 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A more recent study, where 114 monozygotic twins and 80 dizygotic twins were analyzed for the DNA methylation status of around 6000 unique genomic regions, concluded that epigenetic similarity at the time of blastocyst splitting may also contribute to phenotypic similarities in monozygotic co-twins. This supports the notion that microenvironment at early stages of embryonic development can be quite important for the establishment of epigenetic marks.&lt;ref name="pmid19151718"/&gt; Congenital genetic disease is well understood and it is clear that epigenetics can play a role, for example, in the case of [[Angelman syndrome]] and [[Prader-Willi syndrome]]. These are normal genetic diseases caused by gene deletions or inactivation of the genes but are unusually common because individuals are essentially [[hemizygous]] because of [[genomic imprinting]], and therefore a single gene knock out is sufficient to cause the disease, where most cases would require both copies to be knocked out.&lt;ref&gt;{{OMIM|105830}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genomic imprinting===
{{further|Genomic imprinting}}

Some human disorders are associated with [[genomic imprinting]], a phenomenon in mammals where the father and mother contribute different epigenetic patterns for specific genomic loci in their [[germ cells]].&lt;ref name="pmid17121465"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wood AJ, Oakey RJ | title = Genomic imprinting in mammals: emerging themes and established theories | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 2 | issue = 11 | pages = e147 | date = November 2006 | pmid = 17121465 | pmc = 1657038 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.0020147 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The best-known case of imprinting in human disorders is that of [[Angelman syndrome]] and [[Prader-Willi syndrome]] – both can be produced by the same genetic mutation, [[chromosome 15q partial deletion]], and the particular syndrome that will develop depends on whether the mutation is inherited from the child's mother or from their father.&lt;ref name="pmid2564739"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Knoll JH, Nicholls RD, Magenis RE, Graham JM, Lalande M, Latt SA | title = Angelman and Prader-Willi syndromes share a common chromosome 15 deletion but differ in parental origin of the deletion | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics | volume = 32 | issue = 2 | pages = 285–90 | date = February 1989 | pmid = 2564739 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.1320320235 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is due to the presence of genomic imprinting in the region. [[Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome]] is also associated with genomic imprinting, often caused by abnormalities in maternal genomic imprinting of a region on chromosome 11.

[[Rett syndrome]] is underlain by mutations in the [[MECP2]] gene despite no large-scale changes in expression of MeCP2 being found in microarray analyses. [[BDNF]] is downregulated in the MECP2 mutant resulting in Rett syndrome.

In the [[Överkalix study]], paternal (but not maternal) grandsons&lt;ref name="paternal-grandson"&gt;A person's paternal grandson is the son of a son of that person; a maternal grandson is the son of a daughter.&lt;/ref&gt; of Swedish men who were exposed during preadolescence to famine in the 19th century were less likely to die of cardiovascular disease. If food was plentiful, then [[diabetes]] mortality in the grandchildren increased, suggesting that this was a transgenerational epigenetic inheritance.&lt;ref name="pmid16391557"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pembrey ME, Bygren LO, Kaati G, Edvinsson S, Northstone K, Sjöström M, Golding J | title = Sex-specific, male-line transgenerational responses in humans | journal = European Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 14 | issue = 2 | pages = 159–66 | date = February 2006 | pmid = 16391557 | doi = 10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201538 | doi-access = free }} [[Robert Winston]] refers to this study in a [http://www.dundee.ac.uk/externalrelations/events/lectures.html lecture] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070523074254/http://www.dundee.ac.uk/externalrelations/events/lectures.html|date=23 May 2007}}; see also discussion at [[Leeds University]], here [https://web.archive.org/web/20061003060251/http://www.fbs.leeds.ac.uk/staff/pm/epigenetics.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; The opposite effect was observed for females – the paternal (but not maternal) granddaughters of women who experienced famine while in the womb (and therefore while their eggs were being formed) lived shorter lives on average.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/transcripts/3413_genes.html |title=NOVA &amp;#124; Transcripts &amp;#124; Ghost in Your Genes |publisher=PBS |date=16 October 2007 |access-date=26 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cancer===
{{details|Cancer epigenetics}}
&lt;!--This section is being merged to [[cancer epigenetics]]. If you are planning new edits, please consider whether you could add or improve there--&gt;
A variety of epigenetic mechanisms can be perturbed in different types of cancer. Epigenetic alterations of DNA repair genes or cell cycle control genes are very frequent in sporadic (non-germ line) cancers, being significantly more common than germ line (familial) [[mutation]]s in these sporadic cancers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wood LD, Parsons DW, Jones S, Lin J, Sjöblom T, Leary RJ, Shen D, Boca SM, Barber T, Ptak J, Silliman N, Szabo S, Dezso Z, Ustyanksky V, Nikolskaya T, Nikolsky Y, Karchin R, Wilson PA, Kaminker JS, Zhang Z, Croshaw R, Willis J, Dawson D, Shipitsin M, Willson JK, Sukumar S, Polyak K, Park BH, Pethiyagoda CL, Pant PV, Ballinger DG, Sparks AB, Hartigan J, Smith DR, Suh E, Papadopoulos N, Buckhaults P, Markowitz SD, Parmigiani G, Kinzler KW, Velculescu VE, Vogelstein B | display-authors = 6 | title = The genomic landscapes of human breast and colorectal cancers | journal = Science | volume = 318 | issue = 5853 | pages = 1108–13 | date = November 2007 | pmid = 17932254 | doi = 10.1126/science.1145720 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.218.5477 | bibcode = 2007Sci...318.1108W }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jasperson KW, Tuohy TM, Neklason DW, Burt RW | title = Hereditary and familial colon cancer | journal = Gastroenterology | volume = 138 | issue = 6 | pages = 2044–58 | date = June 2010 | pmid = 20420945 | pmc = 3057468 | doi = 10.1053/j.gastro.2010.01.054 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Epigenetic alterations are important in cellular transformation to cancer, and their manipulation holds great promise for cancer prevention, detection, and therapy.&lt;ref name="Novak"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Novak K | title = Epigenetics changes in cancer cells | journal = MedGenMed | volume = 6 | issue = 4 | pages = 17 | date = December 2004 | pmid = 15775844 | pmc = 1480584 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid22735547"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Banno K, Kisu I, Yanokura M, Tsuji K, Masuda K, Ueki A, Kobayashi Y, Yamagami W, Nomura H, Tominaga E, Susumu N, Aoki D | display-authors = 6 | title = Epimutation and cancer: a new carcinogenic mechanism of Lynch syndrome (Review) | journal = International Journal of Oncology | volume = 41 | issue = 3 | pages = 793–7 | date = September 2012 | pmid = 22735547 | pmc = 3582986 | doi = 10.3892/ijo.2012.1528 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several medications which have epigenetic impact are used in several of these diseases. These aspects of epigenetics are addressed in [[cancer epigenetics]].

=== Aging ===
The aging [[phenotype]]—marked by functional decline of tissues and organs—is owed in large part to a changing epigenetic landscape. Specifically, changes in the methylation state of DNA has the consequence of perpetuating the aging phenotype, along with [[histone]] modifications, [[chromatin]] remodeling, and [[non-coding RNA]] misregulation. After research began revealing the substantial role epigenetics plays in creating the aging phenotype and promoting age-associated disease, a host of scientists globally have devoted themselves to finding potential interventions to the aging process that capitalize on these epigenetic markers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Cakouros|first1=Dimitrios|last2=Gronthos|first2=Stan|date=2019|title=Epigenetic Regulation of Bone Marrow Stem Cell Aging: Revealing Epigenetic Signatures associated with Hematopoietic and Mesenchymal Stem Cell Aging|journal=Aging and Disease|volume=10|issue=1|pages=174–189|doi=10.14336/ad.2017.1213|pmid=30705777|pmc=6345334|issn=2152-5250}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, reduced methylation of DNA with age also functions simultaneously with higher variability in methylation sites—a finding that is particularly well visualized by looking at the epigenomes of monozygotic twins.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Jones|first1=Meaghan J.|last2=Goodman|first2=Sarah J.|last3=Kobor|first3=Michael S.|date=December 2015|title=DNA methylation and healthy human aging|journal=Aging Cell|volume=14|issue=6|pages=924–932|doi=10.1111/acel.12349|issn=1474-9718|pmc=4693469|pmid=25913071}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diabetic wound healing===
Epigenetic modifications have given insight into the understanding of the pathophysiology of different disease conditions. Though, they are strongly associated with cancer, their role in other pathological conditions are of equal importance. It appears that the hyperglycaemic environment could imprint such changes at the genomic level, that macrophages are primed towards a pro-inflammatory state and could fail to exhibit any phenotypic alteration towards the pro-healing type. This phenomenon of altered Macrophage Polarization is mostly associated with all the diabetic complications in a clinical set-up. As of 2018, several reports reveal the relevance of different epigenetic modifications with respect to diabetic complications. Sooner or later, with the advancements in biomedical tools, the detection of such biomarkers as prognostic and diagnostic tools in patients could possibly emerge out as alternative approaches. It is noteworthy to mention here that the use of epigenetic modifications as therapeutic targets warrant extensive preclinical as well as clinical evaluation prior to use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Basu Mallik |first1=Sanchari |last2=Jayashree |first2=B.S. |last3=Shenoy |first3=Rekha R. |title=Epigenetic modulation of macrophage polarization- perspectives in diabetic wounds |journal=Journal of Diabetes and Its Complications |date=May 2018 |volume=32 |issue=5 |pages=524–530 |doi=10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2018.01.015 |pmid=29530315 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Examples of drugs altering gene expression from epigenetic events===

{{See also|Epigenetic Priming|label 1=Epigenetic Priming}}

The use of beta-lactam antibiotics can alter glutamate receptor activity and the action of cyclosporine on multiple transcription factors. Additionally, lithium can impact autophagy of aberrant proteins, and opioid drugs via chronic use can increase the expression of genes associated with addictive phenotypes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Anderson |first1=Stephen J. |last2=Feye |first2=Kristina M. |last3=Schmidt-McCormack |first3=Garrett R. |last4=Malovic |first4=Emir |last5=Mlynarczyk |first5=Gregory S. A. |last6=Izbicki |first6=Patricia |last7=Arnold |first7=Larissa F. |last8=Jefferson |first8=Matthew A. |last9=de la Rosa |first9=Bierlein M. |last10=Wehrman |first10=Rita F. |last11=Luna |first11=K. C. |last12=Hu |first12=Hilary Z. |last13=Kondru |first13=Naveen C. |last14=Kleinhenz |first14=Michael D. |last15=Smith |first15=Joe S. |last16=Manne |first16=Sireesha |last17=Putra |first17=Marson R. |last18=Choudhary |first18=Shivani |last19=Massey |first19=Nyzil |last20=Luo |first20=Diou |last21=Berg |first21=Carrie A. |last22=Acharya |first22=Sreemoyee |last23=Sharma |first23=Shaunik |last24=Kanuri |first24=Sri Harsha |last25=Lange |first25=Jennifer K. |last26=Carlson |first26=Steve A. |title=Off-Target drug effects resulting in altered gene expression events with epigenetic and 'Quasi-Epigenetic' origins |journal=Pharmacological Research |date=1 May 2016 |volume=107 |pages=229–233 |doi=10.1016/j.phrs.2016.03.028 |pmid=27025785 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Psychology and psychiatry ==

===Early life stress===
In a groundbreaking 2003 report, Caspi and colleagues demonstrated that in a robust cohort of over one-thousand subjects assessed multiple times from preschool to adulthood, subjects who carried one or two copies of the short allele of the serotonin transporter promoter polymorphism exhibited higher rates of adult depression and suicidality when exposed to childhood maltreatment when compared to long allele homozygotes with equal early life stress exposure.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Caspi A, Sugden K, Moffitt TE, Taylor A, Craig IW, Harrington H, McClay J, Mill J, Martin J, Braithwaite A, Poulton R | display-authors = 6 | title = Influence of life stress on depression: moderation by a polymorphism in the 5-HTT gene | journal = Science | volume = 301 | issue = 5631 | pages = 386–9 | date = July 2003 | pmid = 12869766 | doi = 10.1126/science.1083968 | bibcode = 2003Sci...301..386C }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parental nutrition, in utero exposure to stress, male-induced maternal effects such as the attraction of differential mate quality, and maternal as well as paternal age, and offspring gender could all possibly influence whether a germline epimutation is ultimately expressed in offspring and the degree to which intergenerational inheritance remains stable throughout posterity.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-809324-5.02862-5 |chapter=Persistence of Early-Life Stress on the Epigenome: Nonhuman Primate Observations☆ |title=Reference Module in Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Psychology |year=2017 |last1=Coplan |first1=J. |last2=Chanatry |first2=S.T. |last3=Rosenblum |first3=L.A. |isbn=9780128093245 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Addiction===
[[Addiction]] is a disorder of the brain's [[reward system]] which arises through [[transcriptional]] and neuroepigenetic mechanisms and occurs over time from chronically high levels of exposure to an addictive stimulus (e.g., morphine, cocaine, sexual intercourse, gambling, etc.).&lt;ref name="Nestler"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Robison AJ, Nestler EJ | title = Transcriptional and epigenetic mechanisms of addiction | journal = Nature Reviews. Neuroscience | volume = 12 | issue = 11 | pages = 623–37 | date = October 2011 | pmid = 21989194 | pmc = 3272277 | doi = 10.1038/nrn3111 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cellular basis"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nestler EJ | title = Cellular basis of memory for addiction | journal = Dialogues in Clinical Neuroscience | volume = 15 | issue = 4 | pages = 431–43 | date = December 2013 | pmid = 24459410 | pmc = 3898681 | doi =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="What the ΔFosB?"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ruffle JK | title = Molecular neurobiology of addiction: what's all the (Δ)FosB about? | journal = The American Journal of Drug and Alcohol Abuse | volume = 40 | issue = 6 | pages = 428–37 | date = November 2014 | pmid = 25083822 | doi = 10.3109/00952990.2014.933840 | quote = Conclusions&lt;br /&gt;ΔFosB is an essential transcription factor implicated in the molecular and behavioral pathways of addiction following repeated drug exposure. The formation of ΔFosB in multiple brain regions, and the molecular pathway leading to the formation of AP-1 complexes is well understood. The establishment of a functional purpose for ΔFosB has allowed further determination as to some of the key aspects of its molecular cascades, involving effectors such as GluR2 (87,88), Cdk5 (93) and NFkB (100). Moreover, many of these molecular changes identified are now directly linked to the structural, physiological and behavioral changes observed following chronic drug exposure (60,95,97,102). New frontiers of research investigating the molecular roles of ΔFosB have been opened by epigenetic studies, and recent advances have illustrated the role of ΔFosB acting on DNA and histones, truly as a ‘‘molecular switch’’ (34). As a consequence of our improved understanding of ΔFosB in addiction, it is possible to evaluate the addictive potential of current medications (119), as well as use it as a biomarker for assessing the efficacy of therapeutic interventions (121,122,124). Some of these proposed interventions have limitations (125) or are in their infancy (75). However, it is hoped that some of these preliminary findings may lead to innovative treatments, which are much needed in addiction. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="G9a reverses ΔFosB plasticity"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Biliński P, Wojtyła A, Kapka-Skrzypczak L, Chwedorowicz R, Cyranka M, Studziński T | title = Epigenetic regulation in drug addiction | journal = Annals of Agricultural and Environmental Medicine | volume = 19 | issue = 3 | pages = 491–6 | year = 2012 | pmid = 23020045 | doi =  | quote = For these reasons, ΔFosB is considered a primary and causative transcription factor in creating new neural connections in the reward centre, prefrontal cortex, and other regions of the limbic system. This is reflected in the increased, stable and long-lasting level of sensitivity to cocaine and other drugs, and tendency to relapse even after long periods of abstinence. These newly constructed networks function very efficiently via new pathways as soon as drugs of abuse are further taken&amp;nbsp;... In this way, the induction of CDK5 gene expression occurs together with suppression of the G9A gene coding for dimethyltransferase acting on the histone H3. A feedback mechanism can be observed in the regulation of these 2 crucial factors that determine the adaptive epigenetic response to cocaine. This depends on ΔFosB inhibiting G9a gene expression, i.e. H3K9me2 synthesis which in turn inhibits transcription factors for ΔFosB. For this reason, the observed hyper-expression of G9a, which ensures high levels of the dimethylated form of histone H3, eliminates the neuronal structural and plasticity effects caused by cocaine by means of this feedback which blocks ΔFosB transcription }}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance of addictive [[phenotypes]] has been noted to occur in preclinical studies.&lt;ref name="pmid23920159"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vassoler FM, Sadri-Vakili G | title = Mechanisms of transgenerational inheritance of addictive-like behaviors | journal = Neuroscience | volume = 264 | issue =  | pages = 198–206 | date = April 2014 | pmid = 23920159 | pmc = 3872494 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.07.064 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid26572641"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yuan TF, Li A, Sun X, Ouyang H, Campos C, Rocha NB, Arias-Carrión O, Machado S, Hou G, So KF | display-authors = 6 | title = Transgenerational Inheritance of Paternal Neurobehavioral Phenotypes: Stress, Addiction, Ageing and Metabolism | journal = Molecular Neurobiology | volume = 53 | issue = 9 | pages = 6367–6376 | date = November 2016 | pmid = 26572641 | doi = 10.1007/s12035-015-9526-2 | hdl = 10400.22/7331 | hdl-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anxiety ===
Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance of anxiety-related phenotypes has been reported in a preclinical study using mice.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Short AK, Fennell KA, Perreau VM, Fox A, O'Bryan MK, Kim JH, Bredy TW, Pang TY, Hannan AJ | display-authors = 6 | title = Elevated paternal glucocorticoid exposure alters the small noncoding RNA profile in sperm and modifies anxiety and depressive phenotypes in the offspring | journal = Translational Psychiatry | volume = 6 | issue = 6 | pages = e837 | date = June 2016 | pmid = 27300263 | pmc = 4931607 | doi = 10.1038/tp.2016.109 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In this investigation, transmission of paternal stress-induced traits across generations involved small non-coding RNA signals transmitted via the male germline.

=== Depression ===
Epigenetic inheritance of depression-related phenotypes has also been reported in a preclinical study.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Inheritance of paternal stress-induced traits across generations involved small non-coding RNA signals transmitted via the paternal germline.

=== Fear conditioning ===
Studies on mice have shown that certain conditional fears can be inherited from either parent. In one example, mice were conditioned to fear a strong scent, [[acetophenone]], by accompanying the smell with an electric shock. Consequently, the mice learned to fear the scent of acetophenone alone. It was discovered that this fear could be passed down to the mice offspring. Despite the offspring never experiencing the electric shock themselves the mice still displayed a fear of the acetophenone scent, because they inherited the fear epigenetically by site-specific DNA methylation. These epigenetic changes lasted up to two generations without reintroducing the shock.&lt;ref name="Szyf2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Szyf M | title = Lamarck revisited: epigenetic inheritance of ancestral odor fear conditioning | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 17 | issue = 1 | pages = 2–4 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 24369368 | doi = 10.1038/nn.3603 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
The two forms of heritable information, namely genetic and epigenetic, are collectively denoted as dual inheritance. Members of the APOBEC/AID family of [[cytosine deaminase]]s may concurrently influence genetic and epigenetic inheritance using similar molecular mechanisms, and may be a point of crosstalk between these conceptually compartmentalized processes.&lt;ref name="pmid20800313"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chahwan R, Wontakal SN, Roa S | title = Crosstalk between genetic and epigenetic information through cytosine deamination | journal = Trends in Genetics | volume = 26 | issue = 10 | pages = 443–8 | date = October 2010 | pmid = 20800313 | doi = 10.1016/j.tig.2010.07.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fluoroquinolone]] antibiotics induce epigenetic changes in [[mammalian]] cells through iron [[chelation]]. This leads to epigenetic effects through inhibition of α-ketoglutarate-dependent [[dioxygenases]] that require [[iron]] as a co-factor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Badal S, Her YF, Maher LJ | title = Nonantibiotic Effects of Fluoroquinolones in Mammalian Cells | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 290 | issue = 36 | pages = 22287–97 | date = September 2015 | pmid = 26205818 | pmc = 4571980 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M115.671222 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various pharmacological agents are applied for the production of induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSC) or maintain the embryonic stem cell (ESC) phenotypic via epigenetic approach. Adult stem cells like bone marrow stem cells have also shown a potential to differentiate into cardiac competent cells when treated with G9a histone methyltransferase inhibitor BIX01294.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mezentseva NV, Yang J, Kaur K, Iaffaldano G, Rémond MC, Eisenberg CA, Eisenberg LM | title = The histone methyltransferase inhibitor BIX01294 enhances the cardiac potential of bone marrow cells | journal = Stem Cells and Development | volume = 22 | issue = 4 | pages = 654–67 | date = February 2013 | pmid = 22994322 | pmc = 3564468 | doi = 10.1089/scd.2012.0181 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yang J, Kaur K, Ong LL, Eisenberg CA, Eisenberg LM | title = Inhibition of G9a Histone Methyltransferase Converts Bone Marrow Mesenchymal Stem Cells to Cardiac Competent Progenitors | journal = Stem Cells International | volume = 2015 | pages = 270428 | date = 2015 | pmid = 26089912 | pmc = 4454756 | doi = 10.1155/2015/270428 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pseudoscience==
Due to epigenetics being in the early stages of development as a science and the [[sensationalism]] surrounding it in the public media, [[David Gorski]] and geneticist [[Adam Rutherford]] advised caution against proliferation of false and [[Pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] conclusions by [[new age]] authors who make unfounded suggestions that a person's genes and health can be manipulated by [[brainwashing|mind control]]. Misuse of the scientific term by [[quackery|quack authors]] has produced misinformation among the general public.&lt;ref name =science/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.sciencebasedmedicine.org/epigenetics-it-doesnt-mean-what-quacks-think-it-means/ |title=Epigenetics: It doesn't mean what quacks think it means |website=[[Science-Based Medicine]] |first=David |last=Gorski |author-link=David Gorski |date=February 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2015/jul/19/epigenetics-dna--darwin-adam-rutherford |title=Beware the pseudo gene genies |first=Adam |last=Rutherford |newspaper=The Observer |date=July 19, 2015 |quote=Epigenetics is a real and important part of biology, but due to predictable quackery, it is threatening to become the new quantum.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Biology|Medicine|Pharmacy and Pharmacology}}
{{Div col}}
* [[Baldwin effect]]
* [[Behavioral epigenetics]]
* [[Biological effects of radiation on the epigenome]]
* [[Computational epigenetics]]
* [[Contribution of epigenetic modifications to evolution]]
* [[Epigenesis (biology)]]
* [[Epigenetics in forensic science]]
* [[Epigenetic therapy]]
* [[Epigenetics of neurodegenerative diseases]]
* [[Lamarckism]]
* [[Nutriepigenomics]]
* [[Position-effect variegation]]
* [[Preformationism]]
* [[Somatic epitype]]
* [[Synthetic genetic array]]
* [[Transcriptional memory]]
{{div col end}}
{{clear}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Haque FN, Gottesman II, Wong AH | title = Not really identical: epigenetic differences in monozygotic twins and implications for twin studies in psychiatry | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics. Part C, Seminars in Medical Genetics | volume = 151C | issue = 2 | pages = 136–41 | date = May 2009 | pmid = 19378334 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.c.30206 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons}}
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
* {{Cite web|url=https://learn.genetics.utah.edu/content/epigenetics/inheritance/|title=Epigenetics &amp; Inheritance|website=learn.genetics.utah.edu|access-date=17 April 2019}}
* [http://www.epigenome.org/ The Human Epigenome Project (HEP)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100503172418/http://www.epigenome-noe.net/index.php The Epigenome Network of Excellence (NoE)]
* [http://www.epigenomes.ca/ Canadian Epigenetics, Environment and Health Research Consortium (CEEHRC)]
* [http://www.epigenome.eu/ The Epigenome Network of Excellence (NoE) – public international site]
* [http://discovermagazine.com/2006/nov/cover "DNA Is Not Destiny"] – ''Discover'' magazine cover story
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/sn/tvradio/programmes/horizon/ghostgenes.shtml "The Ghost In Your Genes"], ''Horizon'' (2005), BBC
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080509124439/http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/press/2002/November/epigenetics.htm Epigenetics article] at Hopkins Medicine
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110721032750/http://genome.wellcome.ac.uk/doc_WTX036556.html Towards a global map of epigenetic variation ]

{{Genetics}}
{{MolBioGeneExp}}
{{genarch}}
{{Biology_nav}}
{{Molecular Biology}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Epigenetics| ]]
[[Category:Genetic mapping]]
[[Category:Lamarckism]]</text>
      <sha1>18q6yxbjkumljdp6q7ou47mye65mrnr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
