<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Background of the Spanish Civil War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24125782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962001135</id>
      <parentid>961985955</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-11T15:05:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Paul2520</username>
        <id>19295592</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>unified footnote formats; added {{short description}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="52997" xml:space="preserve">{{good article}}
{{short description|historical context leading to the Spanish Civil War}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
The '''background of the Spanish Civil War''' dates back to the end of the 19th century, when the owners of large estates, called ''[[latifundia|latifundios]]'', held most of the power in a land-based oligarchy. The landowners' power was unsuccessfully challenged by the industrial and merchant sectors. In 1868 [[Glorious Revolution (Spain)|popular uprisings]] led to the overthrow of Queen [[Queen Isabella II of Spain|Isabella II]] of the [[House of Bourbon]]. In 1873 Isabella's replacement, King [[Amadeo I of Spain|Amadeo I]] of the [[House of Savoy]], abdicated due to increasing political pressure, and the short-lived [[First Spanish Republic]] was proclaimed. After the [[Spain under the Restoration|restoration of the Bourbons]] in December 1874, [[Carlists]] and [[anarchists]] emerged in opposition to the monarchy. [[Alejandro Lerroux]] helped bring [[republicanism]] to the fore in [[Catalonia]], where poverty was particularly acute. Growing resentment of conscription and of the military culminated in the [[Tragic Week (Catalonia)|Tragic Week]] in [[Barcelona]] in 1909. After the [[First World War]], the working class, the industrial class, and the military united in hopes of removing the corrupt central government, but were unsuccessful. Fears of communism grew. A military [[coup d'état|coup]] brought [[Miguel Primo de Rivera]] to power in 1923, and he ran Spain as a military dictatorship. Support for his regime gradually faded, and he resigned in January 1930. There was little support for the monarchy in the major cities, and [[King Alfonso XIII]] abdicated; the [[Second Spanish Republic]] was formed, whose power would remain until the culmination of the [[Spanish Civil War]]. Monarchists would continue to oppose the Republic.

The revolutionary committee headed by [[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora]] became the provisional government, with [[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora|Zamora]] as the President and Head of State.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006. p. 23"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; The Republic had broad support from all segments of society; elections in June 1931 returned a large majority of Republicans and Socialists. With the onset of the [[Great Depression]], the government attempted to assist rural Spain by instituting an [[eight-hour day]] and giving tenure to farm workers. Land reform and working conditions remained important issues throughout the lifetime of the Republic. [[Fascism]] remained a reactive threat, helped by controversial reforms to the military. In December a new reformist, liberal, and democratic [[Spanish Constitution of 1931|constitution]] was declared. The [[Spanish Constitution of 1931|constitution]] secularised the government, and this, coupled with their slowness to respond to a wave of anti-clerical violence prompted committed Catholics to become disillusioned with the incumbent [[coalition government]].&lt;ref&gt; Beevor (2006). pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1931 [[Manuel Azaña]] became Prime Minister of a minority government. The Right won the [[Spanish general election, 1933|elections of 1933]] following an unsuccessful uprising by General [[José Sanjurjo]] in August 1932, who would later lead the coup that started the civil war.

Events in the period following November 1933, called the "two black years", seemed to make a civil war more likely. [[Alejandro Lerroux]] of the [[Radical Republican Party]] (RRP) formed a government with the support of [[Spanish Confederation of Autonomous Right-wing Groups|CEDA]] and rolled back all major changes made under the previous administration, he also granted amnesty to General [[José Sanjurjo]], who had attempted an unsuccessful [[coup d'etat|coup]] in 1932. Some monarchists moved to the Fascist [[Falange Española]] to help achieve their aims. In response, the socialist party ([[PSOE]]) became more extreme, setting up a revolutionary committee and training the socialist youth in secret.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2009). pp. 31–32&lt;/ref&gt; Open violence occurred in the streets of Spanish cities and militancy continued to increase right up until the start of the civil war, reflecting a movement towards radical upheaval rather than peaceful democratic means as a solution to Spain's problems. In the last months of 1934, two government collapses brought members of the [[Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right]] (CEDA) into the government, making it more right-wing. Farm workers' wages were halved, and the military was purged of republican members and reformed. A [[Popular Front]] alliance was organised, which won the [[Spanish general election, 1936|1936 elections]]. Azaña led a weak minority government, but soon replaced Zamora as president in April. Prime Minister Casares failed to heed warnings of a military conspiracy involving several generals, who decided that the government had to be replaced if the dissolution of Spain was to be prevented. They organised a [[Spanish coup of July 1936|military coup in July]], which started the Spanish Civil War.

==Constitutional monarchy==

===19th century===
The 19th century was a turbulent time for Spain.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006 8"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Those in favour of reforming Spain's government vied for political power with conservatives, who tried to prevent reforms from taking place. Some [[liberalism|liberal]]s, in a tradition that had started with the [[Spanish Constitution of 1812]], sought to limit the power of the [[monarchy of Spain]] and to establish a liberal state.&lt;ref name="Fraser38"&gt;Fraser (1979). pp. 38–39.&lt;/ref&gt; The reforms of 1812 did not last after King [[Ferdinand VII]] dissolved the Constitution and ended a [[Trienio Liberal|short-lived liberal government]] with [[Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis|French royalist military assistance]].&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Twelve successful coups were carried out between 1814 and 1874.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006 8"/&gt; There were several attempts to realign the political system to match social reality.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Until the 1850s, the economy of Spain was primarily based on agriculture. There was little development of a [[bourgeois]] industrial or commercial class. The land-based [[oligarchy]] remained powerful; a small number of people held large estates (called ''[[latifundia]]'') as well as all the important government positions. The landowners' power was challenged by the industrial and merchant sectors, largely unsuccessfully.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Amadeo I, rey de España.jpg|thumb|upright|King [[Amadeo I of Spain]]]]
In 1868 popular uprisings led to the overthrow of Queen [[Queen Isabella II of Spain|Isabella II]] of the [[House of Bourbon]]. Two distinct factors led to the uprisings: a series of urban riots, and a liberal movement within the middle classes and the military (led by General [[Joan Prim]]),&lt;ref name="thomas13"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; who were concerned about the ultra-conservatism of the monarchy.&lt;ref name="preston21"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1873 Isabella's replacement, King [[Amadeo I of Spain|Amadeo I]] of the [[House of Savoy]], [[abdication|abdicated]] due to increasing political pressure, and the [[First Spanish Republic]] was proclaimed.&lt;ref name="thomas13"/&gt;&lt;ref name="preston21"/&gt; However, the intellectuals behind the Republic were powerless to prevent a descent into chaos.&lt;ref name="thomas13"/&gt; Uprisings were crushed by the military. The old monarchy returned with the [[Spain under the Restoration|restoration of the Bourbons]] in December 1874,&lt;ref name="preston22"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; as reform was deemed less important than peace and stability.&lt;ref name="preston22"/&gt; Despite the introduction of [[universal male suffrage]] in 1890, elections were controlled by local political bosses (''[[caciques]]'').&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006 8"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most traditionalist sectors of the [[Politics of Spain|political sphere]] systematically tried to prevent liberal reforms and to sustain the [[patrilineal]] monarchy. The [[Carlists]] – supporters of [[Infante Carlos, Count of Molina|Infante Carlos]] and his descendants – fought to promote Spanish tradition and [[Catholicism]] against the liberalism of successive Spanish governments.&lt;ref name="Fraser38"/&gt; The Carlists attempted to restore the historic liberties and broad regional autonomy granted to the [[Basque Country (historical territory)|Basque Country]] and [[Catalonia]] by their ''[[fuero]]s'' (regional charters). At times they allied with nationalists (separate from the [[National Faction (Spanish Civil War)|National Faction]] during the civil war itself), including during the [[Carlist Wars]].&lt;ref name="Fraser38"/&gt;

Periodically, [[anarchism]] became popular among the working class, and was far stronger in Spain than anywhere else in Europe at the time.&lt;ref name="Fraser38"/&gt; Anarchists were easily defeated in clashes with government forces.&lt;ref name="preston24"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===
[[File:Angiolillo-assassinato.jpg|thumb|right|[[Michele Angiolillo]] kills [[Antonio Cánovas del Castillo|Cánovas]] in a health resort in 1897]]
In 1897 an Italian anarchist assassinated Prime Minister [[Antonio Cánovas del Castillo]], motivated by a growing number of arrests and the use of torture by the government. The loss of [[Cuba]], Spain's last valuable colony, in the [[Spanish–American War]] of 1898 hit exports from [[Catalonia]] hardest; there were acts of terrorism and actions by ''[[agents provocateurs]]'' in Barcelona.&lt;ref name="preston24"/&gt; In the first two decades of the 20th century, the industrial working class grew in number. There was a growing discontent in the Basque country and Catalonia, where much of Spain's industry was based. They believed that the government favoured [[agrarianism]] and therefore failed to represent their interests.&lt;ref name="preston25"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; The average illiteracy rate was 64%, with considerable regional variation. Poverty in some areas was great and mass emigration to the New World occurred in the first decade of the century.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

Spain's [[socialist]] party, the [[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party]] ({{lang-es|Partido Socialista Obrero Español}}, PSOE) and its associated [[trade union]], the ''[[Unión General de Trabajadores]]'' (UGT), gained support. The UGT grew from 8,000 members in 1908 to 200,000 in 1920. Branch offices (''[[Casa del pueblo|Casas del pueblo]]'') of the unions were established in major cities.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; The UGT was constantly fearful of losing ground to the anarchists. It was respected for its discipline during strikes. However, it was [[centrism|centrist]] and anti-Catalan, with only 10,000 members in Barcelona as late as 1936.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The PSOE and the UGT were based on a simple form of [[Marxism]], one that assumed an inevitable revolution, and were [[isolationist]] in character.&lt;ref name="preston25"/&gt; When the UGT moved their headquarters from Barcelona to [[Madrid]] in 1899, many industrial workers in Catalonia were no longer able to access it.&lt;ref name="preston25"/&gt; Some elements of the PSOE recognised the need for cooperation with republican parties.

In 1912 the [[Reformist Party (Spain)|Reformist Party]] was founded, which attracted intellectuals. Figures like its leader, [[Alejandro Lerroux]], helped attract wide support from the working class. His advocacy of [[anti-clericalism]] made him a successful [[demagogue]] in Barcelona. He argued that the [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic Church]] was inseparable from the system of oppression the people were under. It was around this time that [[republicanism]] came to the fore.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

The military was keen to avoid the break-up of the state and was increasingly inward-looking following the loss of Cuba. Regional [[nationalism]], perceived as [[separatism]], was frowned upon. In 1905 the army attacked the headquarters of two satirical magazines in Catalonia believed to be undermining the government. To appease the military, the government outlawed negative comments about the military or Spain itself in the Spanish press. Resentment of the military and of [[conscription]] grew with the disastrous [[Rif War (1909)|Rif War]] of 1909 in [[Spanish Morocco]].&lt;ref name="beevor13"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Lerroux's support of the army's aims lost him support.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Events culminated in the [[Tragic Week (Catalonia)|Tragic Week]] ({{lang-es|Semana Trágica}}) in Barcelona in 1909, when working class groups rioted against the call-up of reservists.&lt;ref name="thomas15"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; 48 churches and similar institutions were burned in anti-clerical attacks.&lt;ref name="thomas15"/&gt; The riot was finally ended by the military; 1,725 members of such groups were put on trial, with five people sentenced to death.&lt;ref name="preston29"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;  These events led to the establishment of the National Confederation of Labour ({{lang-es|Confederación Nacional del Trabajo}}, CNT), an anarchist-controlled trade union committed to [[anarcho-syndicalism]].&lt;ref name="preston29"/&gt; It had over a million members by 1923.&lt;ref name="thomas16"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-09414, Primo de Rivera.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Prime Minister [[Miguel Primo de Rivera]]]]
Increasing exports during the [[First World War]] led to a boom in industry and declining living standards in the industrial areas, particularly Catalonia and the Basque country.&lt;ref name="preston30"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; There was high inflation.&lt;ref name="beevor13"/&gt; The industrial sector resented its subjugation by the agrarian central government. Along with concerns about antiquated promotion systems and political corruption, the war in Morocco had caused divisions in the military.&lt;ref name="preston30"/&gt; [[Regenerationism]] became popular, and the working class, industrial class, and the military were united in their hope of removing the corrupt central government. However, these hopes were defeated in 1917 and 1918 when the various political parties representing these groups were either appeased or suppressed by the central government, one by one. The industrialists eventually backed the government as a way to restore order.&lt;ref name="preston32"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 32–33.&lt;/ref&gt; After the formation of the [[Communist International]] in 1919, there was a growing fear of [[communism]] within Spain and growing repression on the part of the government through military means. The PSOE split, with the more [[left-wing]] members founding the [[Communist Party of Spain|Communist Party]] in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="preston34"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt; The Restoration government failed to cope with an increasing number of strikes amongst the industrial workers in the north and the agricultural workers in the south.&lt;ref name="preston34"/&gt;

[[Miguel Primo de Rivera]] came to power in a military coup in 1923 and ran Spain as a military dictatorship.&lt;ref name="thomas16"/&gt; He handed monopolistic control of trade union power to the UGT, and introduced a sweeping programme of public works.&lt;ref name="preston34"/&gt; These public works were extremely wasteful, including [[hydroelectricity|hydroelectric]] dams and highways causing the deficit to double between 1925 and 1929. [[Spain|Spain's]] financial situation was made far worse by the pegging of the [[Spanish peseta|peseta]] to the [[gold standard]] and by 1931 the [[Spanish peseta|peseta]] had lost nearly half its value.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006. p. 20"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The UGT was brought into the government to set up industrial arbitration boards, though this move was opposed by some in the group and was seen as opportunism by anarchist leaders.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; He also attempted to defend the agrarian–industrial monarchist coalition formed during the war.&lt;ref name="preston34"/&gt; No significant reform to the political system (and in particular the monarchy) was instituted.&lt;ref name="preston34"/&gt; This made forming a new government difficult, as existing problems had not been rectified. Gradually, his support faded because his personal approach to political life ensured he was personally held accountable for the government's failings,&lt;ref name="preston34"/&gt; and due to an increasing frustration over his interference in economic matters he did not understand.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006. p. 20"/&gt; [[José Calvo Sotelo]], his finance minister, was one person to withdraw support,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; and de Rivera resigned in January 1930.&lt;ref name="preston36"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; There was little support for a return to the pre-1923 system, and the monarchy had lost credibility by backing the military government.&lt;ref name="preston36"/&gt; [[Dámaso Berenguer]] was ordered by the king to form a replacement government, but his [[dictablanda]] dictatorship failed to provide a viable alternative.&lt;ref name="preston37"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; The choice of Berenguer annoyed another important general, [[José Sanjurjo]], who believed himself to be a better choice.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; In the municipal elections of 12 April 1931, little support was shown for pro-monarchy parties in the major cities, and large numbers of people gathered in the streets of Madrid. [[King Alfonso XIII]] abdicated to prevent a "fratricidal civil war".&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). pp. 18–19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;His statement included the sentence "I am determined to have nothing to do with setting one of my countrymen against another in a fratricidal civil war." from Thomas (1961). pp. 18–19.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Second Spanish Republic]] was formed.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006. p. 20"/&gt;&lt;ref name="preston37"/&gt;

==Second Republic==
[[File:Niceto Alcalá Zamora, presidente de la II República Española.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora]] in 1931]]
The Second Republic was a source of hope to the poorest in Spanish society and a threat to the richest, but had broad support from all segments of society.&lt;ref name="preston38"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 38–39.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora]] was the first prime minister of the Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; The wealthier landowners and the middle class accepted the Republic because of the lack of any suitable alternative.&lt;ref name="preston38"/&gt; Elections to a constituent [[Cortes Generales|Cortes]] in June 1931 returned a large majority of Republicans and Socialists, with the PSOE gaining 116 seats and Lerroux's Radical Party 94.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Lerroux became foreign minister.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt; The government was controlled by a Republican–Socialist coalition, whose members had differing objectives. Some more conservative members believed that the removal of the monarchy was enough by itself, but the Socialists and leftist Republicans demanded much wider reforms.&lt;ref name="preston38"/&gt;

The state's financial position was poor. Supporters of the dictatorship attempted to block progress on reforming the economy.&lt;ref name="preston41"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt; The redistribution of wealth supported by the new government seemed a threat to the richest, in light of the recent [[Wall Street Crash]] and the onset of the [[Great Depression]].&lt;ref name="preston41"/&gt; The government attempted to tackle the dire poverty in rural areas by instituting an eight-hour day and giving the security of tenure to farm workers.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="beevor22"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Landlords complained. The effectiveness of the reforms was dependent on the skill of the local governance, which was often badly lacking.&lt;ref name="preston43"/&gt; Changes to the military were needed and education reform was another problem facing the Republic. The relationship between central government and the Basque and Catalan regions also needed to be decided.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

Effective opposition was led by three groups. The first group included Catholic movements such as the [[Asociación Católica de Propagandistas]],&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;See also: [[:es:Asociación Católica de Propagandistas]] {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; who had influence over the judiciary and the press.&lt;ref name="preston43"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Rural landowners were told to think of the Republic as godless and communist.&lt;ref name="preston44"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; The second group consisted of organisations that had supported the monarchy, such as the [[Renovación Española]] and Carlists, who wished to see the new republic overthrown in a violent uprising.&lt;ref name="preston44"/&gt; The third group were [[Fascist]] organisations, among them supporters of the dictator's son, [[José Antonio Primo de Rivera]]. Primo de Rivera was the most significant leader of fascism in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; The press often editorialised about a foreign [[Jewish]]–[[Masonic]]–[[Bolshevik]] plot.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the CNT willing to cooperate with the Republic were forced out, and it continued to oppose the government.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; The deeply unpopular [[Civil Guard (Spain)|Civil Guard]] ({{lang-es|Guardia Civil}}), founded in 1844, was charged with putting down revolts and was perceived as ruthless. Violence, including at [[Castilblanco]] in December 1931, was usual.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). pp. 48–49.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 May 1931 rumours that a taxi driver was supposedly killed by monarchists sparked a wave of anti-clerical violence throughout south west urban Spain beginning. An angry crowd assaulted and burned [[ABC (newspaper)|ABC newspaper]]. The government's reluctance to declare martial law in response and a comment attributed to [[Manuel Azaña|Azaña]] that he would "rather all the churches in Spain be burnt than a single Republican harmed" prompted many Catholics to believe that the Republic was trying to prosecute Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006) p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Next day the Jesuit Church in the Calle de La Flor was also burned. Several other churches and convents were burned throughout the day. Over the next days some hundred churches were burned all over Spain. The government blamed the monarchists for sparking the riots and closed the [[ABC (newspaper)|ABC newspaper]] and [[El Debate]].&lt;ref name="Thomas Chapter 5"&gt;Thomas (2013). Chapter 5&lt;/ref&gt;

Parties in opposition to Alcalá-Zamora's provisional government gained the support of the church and the military.&lt;ref name="preston46"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt; The head of the church in Spain, Cardinal [[Pedro Segura]], was particularly vocal in his disapproval.&lt;ref name="preston46"/&gt; Until the 20th century, the Catholic Church had proved an essential part of Spain's character, although it had internal problems.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; Segura was expelled from Spain in June 1931.&lt;ref name="Beevor 2006. p. 23"/&gt; This prompted an outcry from the Catholic right, who cited oppression.&lt;ref name="preston46"/&gt; The military were opposed to reorganisation, including an increase in regional autonomy granted by the central government, and reforms to improve efficiency were seen as a direct attack. Officers were retired and a thousand had their promotions reviewed, including [[Francisco Franco]], who served as director of the General Military Academy in [[Zaragoza]], which was closed by Manuel Azaña.&lt;ref name="beevor22"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitution of 1931===

In October 1931 The conservative Catholic Republican prime-minister Alcalá-Zamora and the Interior Minister [[Miguel Maura]] resigned from the provisional government when the controversial articles 26 and 27 of the constitution, which strictly controlled Church property and prohibited religious orders from engaging in education were passed. During the debate held on October 13, a night that Alcalá-Zamora considered the saddest night of his life, Azaña declared that Spain had "ceased to be Catholic"; although to an extent his statement was accurate,&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;According to Thomas (1961). p. 31., it was estimated that around two-thirds of Spaniards were not practising Catholics.&lt;/ref&gt; it was a politically unwise thing to say.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961) p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Manuel Azaña became the new provisional Prime Minister. Desiring the job for himself, Lerroux became alienated, and his Radical Party switched to the opposition,&lt;ref name="thomas47"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; leaving Azaña dependent on the Socialists for support. The Socialists, who favoured reform, objected to the lack of progress. The reforms that were made alienated the land-holding right.&lt;ref name="preston545"&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions for labourers remained dreadful; the reforms had not been enforced.&lt;ref name="preston57"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; Rural landowners declared war on the government by refusing to plant crops.&lt;ref name="preston58"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, several agricultural strikes were harshly put down by the authorities.&lt;ref name="preston57"/&gt; Reforms, including the unsuccessful attempt to break up large holdings, failed to significantly improve the situation for rural workers.&lt;ref name="preston58"/&gt; By the end of 1931, King Alfonso, in exile, stopped attempting to prevent an armed insurrection of monarchists in Spain, and was tried and condemned to life imprisonment ''in absentia''.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Spanish Constitution of 1931|A new constitution]] was approved on 9 December 1931.&lt;ref name="preston53"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; The first draft, prepared by [[Ángel Ossorio y Gallardo]] and others, was rejected, and a much more daring text creating a "democratic republic of workers of every class" was promulgated.&lt;ref&gt;Lannon (1987). p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt; It contained much in the way of emotive language and included many controversial articles, some of which were aimed at curbing the Catholic Church.&lt;ref name="thomas46"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="beevor24"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution was reformist, liberal, and democratic in nature, and was welcomed by the Republican–Socialist coalition. It appalled landowners, industrialists, the organised church, and army officers.&lt;ref name="preston53"/&gt;At this point once the constituent assembly had fullfilled its mandate of approving a new constitution, it should have arranged for regular parliamentary elections and adjourned.&lt;ref name="Hayes"&gt;Hayes (1951). p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; However fearing the increasing popular opposition the Radical and Socialist majority postponed the regular elections, therefore prolonging their way in power for two more years. This way the provisional republican government of Manuel Azaña initiated numerous reforms to what in their view would "modernize" the country.&lt;ref name="Hayes"&gt;Hayes (1951). p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the provisional government believed it was necessary to break the control the church had over Spanish affairs, the new constitution removed any special rights held by the Catholic Church.&lt;ref name="preston53"/&gt; The constitution proclaimed religious freedom and a complete [[separation of Church and State]]. Catholic schools continued to operate, but outside the state system; in 1933 further legislation banned all monks and nuns from teaching.&lt;ref&gt;Vincent (2007). p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; The Republic regulated church use of property and investments,&lt;ref name="thomas46"/&gt; provided for recovery and controls on the use of property the church had obtained during past dictatorships, and banned the Vatican-controlled [[Society of Jesus]].&lt;ref name="preston53"/&gt;&lt;ref name="beevor24"/&gt; The controversial articles 26 and 27 of the constitution strictly controlled Church property and prohibited religious orders from engaging in education.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (2009). p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters of the church and even [[Jose Ortega y Gasset]], a liberal advocate of the separation of church and state, considered the articles overreaching.&lt;ref&gt;Paz (2001). p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Other articles legalising divorce and initiating agrarian reforms were equally controversial,&lt;ref name="preston53"/&gt; and on 13 October 1931, [[José María Gil-Robles y Quiñones|Gil Robles]], the leading spokesman of the parliamentary right, called for a Catholic Spain to make its stand against the Republic.&lt;ref name="preston54"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; Commentator [[Stanley Payne]] has argued that "the Republic as a democratic constitutional regime was doomed from the outset", because the far left considered any moderation of the anticlerical aspects of the constitution as totally unacceptable.&lt;ref name="payne 632"&gt;Payne (1973). p. 632.&lt;/ref&gt;

Restrictions on Christian iconography in schools and hospitals and the ringing of bells came into force in January 1932. State control of cemeteries was also imposed. Many ordinary Catholics began to see the government as an enemy because of the educational and religious reforms.&lt;ref name="thomas47"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 59–60.&lt;/ref&gt; Government actions were denounced as barbaric, unjust, and corrupt by the press.&lt;ref name="preston61"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1932 there was an unsuccessful uprising by General [[José Sanjurjo]], who had been particularly appalled by events in Castilblanco.&lt;ref name="thomas62"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; The aims of the insurrection were vague,&lt;ref name="thomas62"/&gt; and it quickly turned into a fiasco.&lt;ref name="thomas63"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the generals tried and sent to Spanish colonies were four men who would go on to distinguish themselves fighting against the Republic in the civil war: [[Francisco de Borbón y de la Torre]], [[Duke of Seville]], [[Martin Alonso]],&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;See also: [[:es:Pablo Martín Alonso]] {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ricardo Serrador Santés]], and [[Heli Rolando de Tella y Cantos]].&lt;ref name="thomas63"/&gt;

Azaña's government continued to ostracized the church. The Jesuits who were in charge of the best schools throughout the country were banned and had all their property confiscated. The army was reduced. Landowners were expropriated. Home rule was granted to Catalonia, with a local parliament and a president of its own.&lt;ref name="Hayes"&gt;Hayes (1951). p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;In November 1932, [[Miguel de Unamuno]], one of the most respected Spanish intellectuals, rector of the University of Salamanca, and himself a Republican, publicly raised his voice to protest. In a speech delivered on November 27 1932, at the Madrid Ateneo, he protested: "Even the Inquisition was limited by certain legal guarantees. But now we have something worse: a police force which is grounded only on a general sense of panic and on the invention of non-existent dangers to cover up this over-stepping of the law."&lt;ref&gt;Hayes (1951) p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; On June 1933 Pope Pius XI issued the encyclical [[Dilectissima Nobis]], "On Oppression of the Church of Spain", raising his voice against the persecution of the Catholic Church in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Hayes (1951) p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

The political left became fractured, whilst the right united.&lt;ref name="preston61"/&gt; The Socialist Party continued to support Azaña but headed further to the political left.&lt;ref name="thomas67"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Gil Robles set up a new party, the [[Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right]] ({{lang-es|Confederatión Espanola de Derechas Autónomas}}, CEDA) to contest the 1933 election, and tacitly embraced Fascism. The right won an overwhelming victory, with the CEDA and the Radicals together winning 219 seats.&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 66. allocates 207 seats to the political right.&lt;/ref&gt; They had spent far more on their election campaign than the Socialists, who campaigned alone.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 63–65.&lt;/ref&gt; The roughly 3,000 members of the Communist Party were at this point not significant.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The "two black years"===
{{See also|Asturian miners' strike of 1934}}
Following the elections of November 1933, Spain entered a period called the "two black years" ({{lang-es|bienio negro}})&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; by the left. The CEDA had won a plurality of seats, but not enough to form a majority. President [[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora]] declined to invite the leader of the most voted party,Gil Robles, to form a government, and instead invited the [[Radical Republican Party]]'s [[Alejandro Lerroux]] to do so.&lt;ref name="preston67"/&gt; Immediately after the election, the Socialists alleged [[electoral fraud]]; they had, according to the PSOE, needed twice as many votes as their opponents to win each seat. They identified the lack of unity in the left as another reason for their defeat.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 66–67.&lt;/ref&gt; The Socialist opposition began to propagate a revolutionary ideal.&lt;ref name="preston67"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; Stanley Payne asserts that the left demanded the cancelation of the elections not because the elections were fraudulent but because in its view those that had won the elections did not share the republican ideals.&lt;ref name="Payne84"&gt;Preston (2012). p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;

The government, with the backing of CEDA, set about removing price controls, selling state favours and monopolies, and removing the land reforms—to the landowners' considerable advantage. This created growing malnourishment in the south of Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt; The agrarian reforms, still in force, went tacitly unenforced.&lt;ref name="thomas75"&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; Radicals became more aggressive and conservatives turned to paramilitary and vigilante actions. 

The first working class protest came from the anarchists on 8 December 1933, and was easily crushed by force in most of Spain; Zaragoza held out for four days before the [[Spanish Republican Army]], employing tanks, stopped the uprising.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; The Socialists stepped up their revolutionary rhetoric, hoping to force Zamora to call new elections.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; Carlists and [[Alfonsist monarchist]]s continued to prepare, with Carlists undergoing military drills in Navarre;&lt;ref name="thomas75"/&gt; they received the backing of Italian Prime Minister [[Benito Mussolini]]. Gil Robles struggled to control the RRP's youth wing, which copied Germany and Italy's youth movements. Monarchists turned to the Fascist [[Falange Española]], under the leadership of José Antonio Primo de Rivera, as a way to achieve their aims.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 69–70.&lt;/ref&gt; Open violence occurred in the streets of Spanish cities.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; Official statistics state that 330 people were assassinated in addition to 213 failed attempts, and 1,511 people wounded in political violence. Those figures also indicate a total of 113 general strikes were called and 160 religious buildings were destroyed, typically by arson.&lt;ref&gt;Brincat (2005). p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=queabc&gt;[http://www.abc.es/fotos-abc/20120510/quema-iglesias-durante-segunda-98412.html abc.es: "La quema de iglesias durante la Segunda República" 10 May 2012]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Lerroux resigned in April 1934, after President Zamora hesitated to sign an Amnesty Bill which let off the arrested members of the 1932 plot. He was replaced by [[Ricardo Samper]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; The Socialist Party ruptured over the question of whether or not to move towards [[Bolshevism]]. The youth wing, the [[Federation of Young Socialists]] ({{lang-es|Federación de Juventudes Socialistas}}), were particularly militant.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; The anarchists called a four-week strike in Zaragoza.&lt;ref name="preston72"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Gil Robles' CEDA continued to mimic the German [[Nazi Party]], staging a rally in March 1934, to shouts of "Jefe" ("Chief", after the Italian "Duce" used in support of Mussolini).&lt;ref name="thomas67"/&gt;&lt;ref name="preston72"/&gt; Gil Robles used an anti-strike law to successfully provoke and break up unions one at a time, and attempted to undermine the republican government of the [[Esquerra]] in Catalonia, who were attempting to continue the republic's reforms.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 73–74.&lt;/ref&gt; Efforts to remove local councils from socialist control prompted a general strike, which was brutally put down by Interior Minister [[Salazar Alonso]],&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;See also: [[:es:Rafael Salazar Alonso]] {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the arrest of four deputies and other significant breaches of articles 55 and 56 of the constitution.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; The Socialist Landworkers' Federation ({{lang-es|Federación Nacional da Trabajadores de la Tierra}}, FNTT), a trade union founded in 1930, was effectively prevented from operating until 1936.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 September, the CEDA announced it would no longer support the RRP's minority government. It was replaced by an RRP cabinet, again led by Lerroux, that included three members of the CEDA.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; After a year of intense pressure, CEDA, the party with more seats in the parliament, was finally successful in forcing the acceptance of three ministries. As a reaction, the Socialists (PSOE) and Communists triggered an insurrection that they had been preparing for nine months.&lt;ref&gt;Payne&amp;Palacios (2014) p.88&lt;/ref&gt; In Catalonia [[Lluís Companys]] (leader of the [[Republican Left of Catalonia]] and the [[President (government title)|President]] of the [[Generalitat of Catalonia]]) saw an opportunity in the [[general strike]] and declared [[Catalonia]] an independent state inside the federal republic of Spain;&lt;ref name="beevor30"&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; the Esquerra, however, refused to arm the populace, and the head of the military in Catalonia, [[Domingo Batet]],&lt;ref group="nb"&gt;See also: [[:es:Domingo Batet]] {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; charged with putting down the revolt, showed similar restraint. In response, [[Lluís Companys]] was arrested and Catalan autonomy was suspended.&lt;ref name="beevor30"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The 1934 strike was unsuccessful in most of Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; but in [[Asturias]] in northern [[Spain]], it developed into a bloody [[Revolution of 1934|revolutionary uprising]], trying to overthrow the legitimate democratic regime. Around 30,000 workers were called to arms in ten days.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; Armed with dynamite, rifles, carbines and light and heavy machine guns, the revolutionaries managed to take the whole province of Asturias committing numerous murders of policemen, clergymen and civilians and destroying religious buildings including churches, convents and part of the university at Oviedo. &lt;ref&gt;Orella Martínez|Mizerska-Wrotkowska, 2015&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Thomas (2001) pp=131-132&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Hayes (1951), p=96&lt;/ref&gt; In the occupied areas the rebels officially declared the proletarian revolution and abolished regular money.&lt;ref&gt;Payne (2004) p=55&lt;/ref&gt; 

The war minister, [[Diego Hidalgo y Durán|Diego Hidalgo]] wanted General Franco to lead the troops. However President Alcalá Zamora, aware of Franco's monarchist sympathies, opted to send General López Ochoa to Asturias to lead the government forces; hoping that his reputation as a loyal Republican would minimize the bloodshed.&lt;ref&gt;Payne &amp; Palacios (2014) p=90&lt;/ref&gt; Franco was put in informal command of the military effort against the revolt.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt;   

Government troops, some brought in from Spain's [[Army of Africa (Spain)|Army of Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; killed men, women and children and carried out summary executions after the main cities of Asturias were retaken.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt; About 1,000 workers were killed, with about 250 government soldiers left dead.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt; Atrocities were carried out by both sides.&lt;ref&gt;Payne (1973) pp. 637–638.&lt;/ref&gt;The failed rising in Asturias marked the effective end of the Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 79–80.&lt;/ref&gt; Months of retaliation and repression followed; torture was used on political prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). pp. 84–85.&lt;/ref&gt; Even moderate reformists within the CEDA became sidelined. The two generals in charge of the campaign, Franco and [[Manuel Goded Llopis]], were seen as heroes.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; Azaña was unsuccessfully made out to be a revolutionary criminal by his right-wing opponents.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; Gil Robles once again prompted a cabinet collapse, and five positions in Lerroux's new government were conceded to CEDA, including one awarded to Gil Robles himself. Farm workers' wages were halved, and the military was purged of republican members and reformed. Those loyal to Robles were promoted, and Franco was made Chief of Staff.&lt;ref name="preston81"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; Stanley Payne thinks that in the perspective of contemporary European history the repression of the 1934 revolution was relatively mild and that the key leaders of the rebellion were treated with leniency.&lt;ref&gt;Payne &amp; Palacios (2014) p.92&lt;/ref&gt; There were no mass killing after the fighting was over as was in the case of the suppression of the Paris Commune or the Russian 1905 revolution; all death sentences were commuted aside from two, army sergeant and deserter Diego Vásquez, who fought alongside the miners, and a worker known as "El Pichilatu" who had committed serial killings. Little effort was actually made to suppress the organisations that had carried out the insurrection, resulting in most being functional again by 1935. Support for fascism was minimal and did not increase, while civil liberties were restored in full by 1935, after which the revolutionaries had a generous opportunity to pursue power through electoral means.&lt;ref&gt;Payne (2006) pp.100-103&lt;/ref&gt;

With this rebellion against established political legitimate authority, the Socialists showed identical repudiation of representative institutional system that anarchists had practiced.&lt;ref&gt;Casanova (2010) p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; The Spanish historian [[Salvador de Madariaga]], an Azaña's supporter, and an exiled vocal opponent of Francisco Franco asserted that: "The uprising of 1934 is unforgivable. The argument that Mr Gil Robles tried to destroy the Constitution to establish fascism was, at once, hypocritical and false. With the rebellion of 1934, the Spanish left lost even the shadow of moral authority to condemn the rebellion of 1936" &lt;ref&gt;Madariaga - Spain (1964) p.416&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Orella Martínez &amp; Mizerska-Wrotkowska (2015)&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn |group=nb | In the original: “El alzamiento de 1934 es imperdonable. La decisión del presidente de la República de llamar al poder a la CEDA era inatacable y hasta debida desde hacía ya tiempo. El argumento de que el señor Gil Robles intentaba destruir la Constitución para instaurar el fascismo era, a la vez, hipócrita y falso. ….. Con la rebelión de 1934, la izquierda española perdió hasta la sombra de autoridad para condenar la rebelión de 1936." }}

In 1935 Azaña and Indalecio Prieto started to unify the left and to combat its extreme elements. They staged large, popular rallies of what would become the [[Popular Front]].&lt;ref name="preston81"/&gt; Lerroux's Radical government collapsed after two major scandals, including the [[Straperlo]] affair.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Zamora did not allow the CEDA to form a government, instead calling elections. The [[Spanish general election, 1936|elections of 1936]] were won by the Popular Front, with vastly smaller resources than the political right who followed [[Nazi propaganda]] techniques.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). pp. 82–83.&lt;/ref&gt; The right began to plan how to best overthrow the Republic, rather than taking control of it.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt;

The government was weak, and the influence of the revolutionary [[Largo Caballero]] prevented socialists from being part of the cabinet. The republicans were left to govern alone; Azaña led a minority government.&lt;ref name="Preston 2006. p. 84"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt; Pacification and reconciliation would have been a huge task.&lt;ref name="Preston 2006. p. 84"/&gt; Largo Caballero accepted support from the Communist Party (with a membership of around 10,000).&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; Acts of violence and reprisals increased.&lt;ref name="preston85"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; By early 1936, Azaña found that the left was using its influence to circumvent the Republic and the constitution; they were adamant about increasingly radical changes.&lt;ref&gt;Payne (1973). p. 643.&lt;/ref&gt; Parliament replaced Zamora with Azaña in April. Zamora's removal was made on specious grounds, using a constitutional technicality.&lt;ref&gt;Payne (1973). p. 642.&lt;/ref&gt; Azaña and Prieto hoped that by holding the positions of Prime Minister and President, they could push through enough reforms to pacify the left and deal with right-wing militancy.&lt;ref name="preston85"/&gt; However, Azaña was increasingly isolated from everyday politics; his replacement, [[Casares Quiroga]], was weak. Although the right also voted for Zamora's removal, this was a watershed event which inspired conservatives to give up on parliamentary politics.&lt;ref name="Preston1999"&gt;Preston (1999). pp. 17–23.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leon Trotsky]] wrote that Zamora had been Spain's "stable pole", and his removal was another step towards revolution.&lt;ref name="Trotsky"&gt;Trotsky (1936). pp. 125–126.&lt;/ref&gt; Largo Caballero held out for a collapse of the republican government, to be replaced with a socialist one as in France.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

CEDA turned its campaign chest over to army plotter [[Emilio Mola]].  Monarchist [[José Calvo Sotelo]] replaced CEDA's Gil Robles as the right's leading spokesman in parliament.&lt;ref name="Preston1999"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; The Falange expanded rapidly, and many members of the [[Juventudes de Acción Popular]] joined. They successfully created a sense of militancy on the streets to try to justify an authoritarian regime.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Prieto did his best to avoid revolution by promoting a series of public works and civil order reforms, including of parts of the military and civil guard. Largo Caballero took a different attitude, continuing to preach of an inevitable overthrow of society by the workers.&lt;ref name="preston90"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; Largo Caballero also disagreed with Prieto's idea of a new Republican–Socialist coalition.&lt;ref name="preston92"&gt;Preston (2006). p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; With Largo Caballero's acquiescence, communists alarmed the middle classes by quickly taking over the ranks of socialist organisations.&lt;ref name="preston90"/&gt; This alarmed the middle classes.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; The division of the Popular Front prevented the government from using its power to prevent right-wing militancy.&lt;ref name="preston92"/&gt; The CEDA came under attack from the Falange, and Prieto's attempts at moderate reform were attacked by the Socialist Youth. Sotelo continued to do his best to make conciliation impossible.&lt;ref name="preston92"/&gt;
Casares failed to heed Prieto's warnings of a military conspiracy involving several generals who disliked professional politicians and wanted to replace the government to prevent the dissolution of Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Preston (2006). p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Spanish coup of July 1936|military coup of July]] that started the [[Spanish Civil War]] was devised with Mola as director and Sanjurjo as a figurehead leader.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (2006). p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=nb|2}}

== Citations ==
{{reflist|20em}}

== See also ==
* [[Revisionism (Spain)]]

== Sources ==
=== Books ===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |title=The Battle for Spain: The Spanish Civil War 1936–1939 |first=Antony |last=Beevor |authorlink=Antony Beevor |location=London, UK |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |year=2006 |isbn=978-0-297-84832-5}}
* {{Cite book |last= Hayes |first=Carlton J.H. |authorlink=Carlton J. H. Hayes| date= 1951|title=The United States and Spain. An Interpretation |publisher=Sheed &amp; Ward; 1ST edition |asin=B0014JCVS0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last= Fraser |first= Ronald |title=Blood of Spain |publisher=[[Penguin Books|Allen Lane]] |location=London, UK |year=1979 |isbn=978-0-7126-6014-3}}
*{{cite book|last= Lannon |first= Frances |title=Privilege, Persecution, and Prophecy: The Catholic Church in Spain, 1875–1975 |location=Oxford, UK |publisher=Clarendon Press |year=1987|isbn=978-0-19-821923-1}}
*{{cite book |last=Payne| authorlink=  Stanley G. Payne |first=Stanley G. |url=http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne25.htm |title=A History of Spain and Portugal ''(Print Edition)'' |volume=2 |chapter=25: The Second Spanish Republic |publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|location=Madison, Wis, USA |year=1973|isbn=978-0-299-06280-4 |series=Library of Iberian Resources Online}}
*{{cite book |last1=Payne |first1=Stanley G |authorlink=  Stanley G. Payne |title=The collapse of the Spanish Republic, 1933-1936 : origins of the Civil War |date=2006 |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0300110654}}
* {{cite book |last= Payne |first= Stanley G.|authorlink=  Stanley G. Payne |url= http://www.cambridge.org/us/academic/subjects/history/twentieth-century-european-history/spanish-civil-war |title=The Spanish Civil War |year=2012 |isbn = 978-0-521-17470-1 | publisher = Cambridge University Press |ref = harv}}
* {{Cite book|first=Stanley G.|last=Payne|authorlink=Stanley G. Payne|first2=Jesús|last2=Palacios|author-link2=Jesús Palacios Tapias|title=Franco: A Personal and Political Biography|year=2018|ref = harv|publisher= [[University of Wisconsin Press]]|edition =4th|isbn= 978-0299302146}}
*{{cite book|last= Preston |first=Paul |authorlink=Paul Preston|title=The Spanish Civil War: Reaction, Revolution and Revenge |year=2006 |edition=3rd |publisher=[[HarperCollins]]|location=London, UK |isbn=978-0-00-723207-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith |first=Angel |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IFuxO9NO-voC&amp;dq |title=Historical Dictionary of Spain |publisher=Scarecrow Press|location=Lanham, Md, USA |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-8108-5849-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Thomas |first=Hugh |title=The Spanish Civil War |authorlink=Hugh Thomas (writer)|year=1961 |location=London, UK |publisher=Eyre and Spottiswoode |edition=1st|oclc=395987}}
*{{cite book |last1=Thomas |first1=Hugh| authorlink=Hugh Thomas (writer) |title=The Spanish Civil War |date=2013 |publisher=Penguin UK |isbn=978-0-7181-9293-8 |url=https://books.google.es/books?id=4c4F7KM9UE8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=hugh+thomas+spanish+civil+war+2013&amp;hl=pt-BR&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj1l7KEp_LpAhVE4YUKHWClBiwQ6AEIJzAA#v=onepage&amp;q=hugh%20thomas%20spanish%20civil%20war%202013&amp;f=false |language=en}}
*{{cite book|last=Vincent |first=Mary |title=Spain, 1833–2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, UK; New York |isbn=978-0-19-873159-7 |year=2007}}
{{refend}}

===Journals===
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book |last=Brincat |first=Leo |title=Documents: working papers, 2006 ordinary session (first part) |chapter=Need for international condemnation of the Franco regime |publisher=[[Council of Europe]] |type=Report |date=4 November 2005 |id=Document 10737 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=wKonXLgCTLQC |isbn=978-92-871-5932-8 }}
*{{cite journal|last=Paz|first= Jose Antonio Souto|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3736/is_200101/ai_n8951721/pg_2|title= Perspectives on religious freedom in Spain|work= [[Brigham Young University Law Review]]|location=Provo, Utah, USA|publisher=[[Brigham Young University]]|date=1 January 2001|oclc=94892517}}
*{{cite journal|last=Preston|first= Paul|url=http://www.historytoday.com/paul-preston/franco-and-aza%C3%B1|title=Franco and Azaña|journal=[[History Today]]|publisher=History Today Ltd.|volume=49|issue=5|date=May 1999|location=London, UK|oclc=95360332}}
*{{cite journal |last=Trotsky |first=Leon |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1936/04/spain01.htm |title=The Task in Spain |journal=New International |publisher=Marxists Internet Archive |volume=5 |issue=4 |year=1936 |location=New York, USA|accessdate=4 September 2011}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite book
|title=The Spanish labyrinth : an account of the social and political background of the Civil War
|first=Gerald
|last=Brenan
|location=Cambridge, United Kingdom
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|year=2014
|edition=2nd
|isbn=1107431751
|others=First published 1943.}}
{{Spanish Civil War}}

[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Causes of wars|Spanish Civil War]]</text>
      <sha1>qo72a5zs5k6b0utleyxgo1pif81wjmz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
