<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fascist symbolism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1125811</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962178648</id>
      <parentid>962173854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-12T15:05:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sus scrofa</username>
        <id>270506</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 962173854 by [[Special:Contributions/2A00:23C5:E000:6F01:106B:4EF8:E536:BEDD|2A00:23C5:E000:6F01:106B:4EF8:E536:BEDD]] ([[User talk:2A00:23C5:E000:6F01:106B:4EF8:E536:BEDD|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="19929" xml:space="preserve">{{Fascism sidebar}}
'''Fascist symbolism''' is the use of certain images and symbols which are designed to represent aspects of [[fascism]]. These include national symbols of historical importance, goals, and political policies.&lt;ref name="urlHate Symbols Database | ADL"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.adl.org/education-and-resources/resource-knowledge-base/hate-symbols?cat_id%5B151%5D=151 |title=Hate Symbols Database &amp;#124; ADL |format= |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The best-known is the [[swastika]] of [[Nazism]]

==Common symbols of fascist movements==
Organized fascist movements have [[militarist]]-appearing uniforms for their members; use historical national symbols as symbols of their movement; and use orchestrated rallies for [[propaganda]] purposes. Fascist movements are led by a "Leader" (e.g. ''[[Duce]]'', ''[[Führer]]'', ''[[Caudillo]]'') who is publicly idolized in propaganda as the nation's saviour. A number of fascist movements use a [[Roman salute|straight-armed salute]].

The use of symbols, graphics, and other artifacts created by fascist, [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] and [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] governments has been noted as a key aspect of their propaganda.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Heller |first=Steven |authorlink=Steven Heller (graphic design) |title=Iron Fists: Branding the 20th-Century Totalitarian State |url=https://archive.org/details/ironfistsbrandin0000hell |url-access=registration |year=2008 |publisher=[[Phaidon Press]] |location= |isbn=0-7148-4846-8 |page=[https://archive.org/details/ironfistsbrandin0000hell/page/n137 240] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most fascist movements adopted symbols of [[Ancient Rome|Ancient Roman]] or [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] origin, for example the German use of Roman standards during rallies and the Italian adoption of the ''[[fasces]]'' symbol. The Spanish [[Falange]] took its name from the Spanish word for the Greek [[phalanx]].

{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = horizontal
| image1    = Mussolini young.jpg
| width1    = 180
| caption1  = [[Benito Mussolini]] in uniform
| image2    = Гитлер и Мюллер.jpg
| width2    = 137
| caption2  = [[Adolf Hitler]] in uniform
}}

==Militarist uniforms with nationalist insignia==
Organized fascist movements typically use military-like uniforms with the symbol of their movement on them.

In Italy, the Italian Fascist movement in 1919 wore black military-like uniforms, and were nicknamed [[Blackshirts]]. In power, uniforms during the Fascist era extended to both the party and the military which typically bore ''fasces'' or an eagle clutching a fasces on their caps or on the left arm section of the uniform.

In Germany, the fascist Nazi movement was similar to the Italian Fascists in that they initially used a specifically colored uniform for their movement, the tan-brown colored uniform of the SA paramilitary group earned the group and the Nazis themselves the nickname of the Brownshirts. The Nazis used the swastika for their uniforms and copied the Italian Fascists' uniforms, with an eagle clutching a wreathed swastika instead of a fasces, and a Nazi flag arm sash on the left arm section of the uniform for party members.

Other fascist countries largely copied the symbolism of the Italian Fascists and German Nazis for their movements. Like them, their uniforms looked typically like military uniforms with Nationalist type insignia of the movement. The Spanish Falange adopted dark blue shirts for their party members, symbolizing Spanish workers, many of whom wore blue shirts. Berets were also used, representing their [[Carlist]] supporters. The Spanish [[Blue Division]] expeditionary volunteers sent to the Eastern Front of WWII in (relatively indirect) support of the Germans likewise wore blue shirts, berets and their army trousers.

==Fascist use of heraldry==
Fascist governments often saw the need to change the [[heraldry]] of their nations; in Germany, the arms of [[Coburg]], featuring the head of [[Saint Maurice]], was looked down upon for its religious and un-Aryan nature. It was replaced in 1934 with a coat of arms featuring a sword and swastika. [[Thuringia]] also saw the need to support the Nazi regime by adding a swastika to the paws of the lion on its coat of arms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Slater |first=Stephen |date= 2003-01-01|title=The Complete Book of Heraldry: An International History Of Heraldry And Its Contemporary Uses |url= |location= London, United Kingdom|publisher=Anness Publishing |page= 212 |isbn= 0754810623|author-link=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Italy, the [[Chief (heraldry)|chief]] of a coat of arms is often used to indicate political allegiance. Under the government of Mussolini, many families and locales adopted a red chief charged with a fasces to indicate allegiance to the [[National Fascist Party]]; this chief was called the ''capo del littorio''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Slater |first=Stephen |date= 2003-01-01|title=The Complete Book of Heraldry: An International History Of Heraldry And Its Contemporary Uses |url= |location= London, United Kingdom|publisher=Anness Publishing |page= 201 |isbn= 0754810623|author-link=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Francisco Franco]], Chief of State of [[Francoist Spain]], used a personal coat of arms featuring the [[Royal Band of Castile]], a heraldic symbol used by the Crown of Castile.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/es%5Ecs940.html Standard of the Head of State 1940-1975 (Spain), CRW Flags]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.generalisimofranco.com/Album/vida/pagB.htm www.generalisimofranco.com, Arms image]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Flag of the National Fascist Party (PNF).svg|left|thumb|Flag of the National Fascist Party, bearing the fasces, which was the primary symbol of Italian Fascism.]]
[[File:Fascist Eagle.svg|right|thumb|200px|A perched eagle clutching a fasces was a common symbol used on Italian Fascist uniforms.]]

==Italy==
The original symbol of fascism, in Italy under [[Benito Mussolini]], was the [[fasces]]. This is an ancient [[Roman Empire|Imperial Roman]] symbol of power carried by [[lictor]]s in front of [[magistrate]]s; a bundle of sticks featuring an [[axe]], indicating the power over [[life]] and [[death]]. Before the Italian Fascists adopted the fasces, the symbol had been used by Italian political organizations of various political ideologies (ranging from socialist to nationalist), called [[Fascio]] ("leagues") as a symbol of strength through unity.

Italian Fascism utilized the color [[black]] as a symbol of their movement, black being the color of the uniforms of their paramilitaries, known as [[Blackshirts]]. The blackshirt derived from Italy's daredevil elite [[shock troops]] known as the ''[[Arditi]]'', soldiers who were specifically trained for a life of violence and wore unique blackshirt uniforms.&lt;ref name=rg207&gt;Roger Griffin, Matthew Feldman. Fascism: Fascism and culture. London, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2004. p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; The colour black, as used by the Arditi, symbolized death.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley G. Payne. ''A history of fascism, 1914-1945''. Oxon, England, UK: Digital Printing, 2005. Pp. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other symbols used by the Italian Fascists included the ''[[Aquila (Roman)|aquila]]'', the [[Capitoline Wolf]], and the [[SPQR]] motto, each related to Italy's ancient Roman cultural history, which the Fascists attempted to resurrect.

==Germany==
[[File:Flag of Nazi Germany (1933-1945).svg|left|thumb|Flag of the National Socialist German Workers' Party (NSDAP), bearing the [[swastika]], the premier symbol of [[Nazism]] which remains strongly associated with it in the Western world.]]
{{main|Nazi symbolism}}
[[File:Parteiadler der Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei (1933–1945).svg|right|thumb|200px|NSDAP Parteiadler eagle]]

The nature of German fascism, as encapsulated in [[Nazism]] was similar to Italian Fascism ideologically and borrowed symbolism from the Italian Fascists such as the use of mass rallies, the straight-armed [[Roman salute]], and the use of pageantry. Nazism was different from Italian Fascism in that it was officially [[racism|racist]]. Its symbol was the [[swastika]], at the time a commonly seen symbol in the world that had experienced a [[Western use of the Swastika in the early 20th century|revival in use in the western world in the early 20th century]]. German [[Völkisch movement|völkisch Nationalists]] claimed the swastika was a symbol of the [[Aryan race]], who they claimed were the foundation of Germanic civilization and were superior to all other races.

As the Italian Fascists adapted elements of their ethnic heritage to fuel a sense of Nationalism by use of symbolism, so did Nazi Germany. Turn-of-the-century [[Germanic mysticism|German-Austrian mystic]] and author [[Guido von List]] was a big influence on [[Reichsführer-SS]] [[Heinrich Himmler]], who introduced various ancient Germanic symbols (filtered through von List's writings) most thoroughly into the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]], including the stylized double [[Sig Rune]] (von List's then-contemporary [[Armanen runes|Armanen rune]] version of the ancient ''[[sowilo]]'' [[runic alphabet|rune]]) for the organization itself.

The black-white-red tricolor of the [[German Empire]] was utilized as the color scheme of the Nazi flag. The color [[brown]] was the identifying color of Nazism (and fascism in general), due to it being the color of the [[Sturmabteilung|SA]] paramilitaries (also known as [[Brownshirts]]).

Other historical symbols that were already in use by the German Army to varying degrees prior to the Nazi Germany, such as the [[Wolfsangel]] and [[Totenkopf]], were also used in a new, more industrialized manner on uniforms and insignia.

Although the swastika was a popular symbol in art prior to the regimental use by [[Nazi Germany]] and has a long heritage in many other cultures throughout history - and although many of the symbols used by the Nazis were ancient or commonly used prior to the advent of Nazi Germany - because of association with Nazi use, the swastika is often considered synonymous with [[Nazism|National Socialism]] and some of the other symbols still carry a negative post-[[World War II]] stigma in Western countries, to the point where some of the symbols are banned from display altogether.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2015/06/24/germany_banned_its_ugly_historic_symbols_should_we_do_that_too.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bandera FE JONS.svg|left|thumb|Flag of the Spanish Falange, bearing the yoke and arrows, the premier symbol of Falangism.]]

==Spain==
{{see also|Symbols of Francoism}}
The fascist [[Falange Española de las JONS|Falange]] in Spain utilized the [[yoke and arrows]] as their symbol. It historically served as the symbol of the shield of the monarchy of [[Ferdinand and Isabella]] and subsequent [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] monarchs, representing a united Spain and the "symbol of the heroic virtues of the race".&lt;ref&gt;Wendy Parkins. ''Fashioning the body politic: dress, gender, citizenship''. Oxford, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Berg, 2002. Pp. 178&lt;/ref&gt; The original uniform of the ''Falangistas'' was the blue shirt – derived from the blue overalls of industrial workers – which was later combined with the red [[beret]] of the [[Carlism|Carlists]] to represent their merger by [[Francisco Franco|Franco]].

==Poland==
Several Polish far-right and nationalist organizations have used the ''[[Mieczyk Chrobrego]]'' ([[Boleslaus I of Poland|[Boleslaus] the Brave's]] Sword), which resembles the [[Szczerbiec]], or the coronation sword of Polish kings. The same organisations have used the ''falanga sword'', a symbol associated with the extreme right in the country after ''Mieczyk Chrobrego'' was banned; most notably it is used by the [[National Radical Camp|ONR]] and [[National Revival of Poland|NOP]] as their main identifying symbols. Among other symbols [[Toporzeł]] is also used, a symbol with strong [[anti-Semitic]] connotations.

==Other regions==
[[File:Ustaše symbol.svg|thumb|right|100px|Symbol of the Croatian [[Ustaše]].]]
Many other fascist movements did not win power or were relatively minor regimes in comparison and their symbolism is not well-remembered today in many parts of the world, although the BUF's [[Flash and Circle]] was later used by the non-fascist [[People's Action Party]] of [[Singapore]].

* The symbol of the [[Bulgaria]]n national-socialist [[Ratniks|Ratnik]] movements was a [[sun cross]] named "Bogar".
* Lightning bolts were a common symbol of [[Oswald Mosley|Sir Oswald Mosley]]'s [[British Union of Fascists]], appearing on uniforms, newspaper mastheads, badges and on the movement's flags. The symbol completely replaced the fasces used from 1932 to 1935 with the adoption of the [[Flash and Circle]].
* The symbol of the [[Croatia]]n [[Ustaše]] movement was capital letter U with the flaming grenade and the [[Coat of arms of Croatia|Croatian coat of arms]].
* A prominent symbol of the [[Greece|Greek]] [[4th of August Regime]] was the [[Labrys]]/Pelekys, the double-headed axe which [[Ioannis Metaxas]] thought to be the oldest symbol of all Hellenic civilizations.
* The symbol of [[Hungary]]'s fascistic [[Arrow Cross Party]] was the [[Arrow Cross]].
* Austria's [[Fatherland's Front (Austria)|Fatherland's Front]], that ruled the country from 1933 to 1938, used the [[crutch cross]] as its symbol.
* The symbol of the [[Norway|Norwegian]] [[Nasjonal Samling]] was as golden/yellow [[sun cross]] on red background.
* The symbol of [[António de Oliveira Salazar|Salazar]]'s [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]] regime was a stylized version of the Christ Cross and shield found on the national flag to distinguish its rivals in the [[National Syndicalists (Portugal)|Movimento Nacional-Sindicalista]] used the [[Order of Christ Cross]].
* The symbol of the [[Romania]]n [[Iron Guard]] was a triple [[cross]] (a variant of the triple parted and fretted) – three parallel verticals intersected with three parallel horizontals, usually in black; it was meant to represent prison bars, as a badge of [[martyr]]dom. It was sometimes deemed the ''[[Michael (archangel)|Archangel Michael]] Cross'', after the [[patron saint]] of the movement.
* The [[National Socialist Movement in the Netherlands]] (NSB) used the [[Wolfsangel]] as its main symbol.
* The [[Brazilian Integralist Action]] used an upper case [[sigma]] (Σ), to represent the [[summation]] of all things under the State.
* The Russian [[Movement Against Illegal Immigration]], which is often considered to be a moderate and legal neo-Nazi movement, uses the black-colored road sign "Stop Prohibited" (similar to the swastika) as their main symbol.
*The quasi-Fascist [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] [[Yugoslav National Movement|ZBOR]] used a green shield with a blade of wheat on it, with a sword crossing the shield.
*[[Pahlavi dynasty|Iran]]ian far-right groups used stylized [[lion and sun]] as their identity.

==Contemporary usage==
{{See also|List of symbols designated by the Anti-Defamation League as hate symbols}}
[[File:Neo-Nazi celtic cross flag.svg|thumb|[[Celtic cross]] on a neo-Nazi flag]]
Some [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazi]] organizations continue to use the swastika, but many have moved away from such inflammatory symbols of early fascism. Some [[neo-fascist]] groups use symbols that are reminiscent of the swastika or other cultural or ancestral symbols that may evoke nationalistic sentiment but do not carry the same racist connotations.

* [[Cross]]es:
** [[Celtic cross]] – used by neo-Nazi white nationalist groups worldwide, the Italian [[New Force (Italy)|New Force]], [[Stormfront (website)|Stormfront]], [[David Duke]]'s website and [[Volkssozialistische Bewegung Deutschlands/Partei der Arbeit|VSBD/PdA]], a banned German neo-Nazi party
** [[Cross crosslet]] – Lithuanian National Socialist Party
** [[Sun cross]] – [[Nordic Reich Party]], [[Sweden]], [[Knights Party]]
* [[Hakenkreuz]] – continues to be used by neo-Nazi groups such as the [[American Nazi Party]] the São Paulo Skinheads in [[Brazil]] and was used by the [[National Socialist Front]] of Sweden
** Bladed swastika – [[Russian National Unity]]
* [[Wolfsangel]] symbol 
** Used by the SS and ''[[Hitlerjugend]]'' as well as various neo-Nazi groups
** [[Azov Battalion]], a paramilitary militia fighting against pro-Russian separatists in Eastern Ukraine&lt;ref&gt;[https://foreignpolicy.com/2014/08/30/preparing-for-war-with-ukraines-fascist-defenders-of-freedom/] Preparing for War With Ukraine’s Fascist Defenders of Freedom&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-28329329]"Azov Battalion fighters parading with the Wolfsangel banner favoured by neo-Nazis"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.altair.com.pl/news/view?news_id=16688 USA nie będą szkolić batalionu Azow]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/news/has-the-far-right-hijacked-ukraines-revolution One year on: where are the far-right forces of Ukraine? The group proudly displays the Wolfsangel symbols - a motif used by several SS groups in Nazi Germany]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bild.de/politik/ausland/ukraine/neonazi-spuk-38159642.bild.html Gespenstischer Neonazi- Aufmarsch in der Ukraine]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tagesspiegel.de/medien/ukraine-konflikt-im-zdf-hakenkreuz-und-ss-rune-protest-von-zuschauern/10685462.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tageblatt.lu/nachrichten/story/10019435]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.welt.de/politik/ausland/article134280586/Rechtsradikaler-wird-Polizeichef-in-Kiew.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/ukraine/11025137/Ukraine-crisis-the-neo-Nazi-brigade-fighting-pro-Russian-separatists.html Ukraine crisis: the neo-Nazi brigade fighting pro-Russian separatists] The Telegraph Tom Parfitt 11 August 2014&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cogwheel – [[Hungarian Welfare Association]]
* [[Black Sun (occult symbol)|Black Sun]] - Used by the Azov Battalion and [[Vanguard America]] as well as other groups such as [[Volksfront]]. The shooter behind the [[Christchurch mosque shootings]] engraved it on his guns and put it on the cover of his [[manifesto]].
* [[Labrys]] (or Pelekys) – a Minoan double-headed axe, used by some fascist Greek nostalgics
* [[Rune]]s:
** [[Algiz]] rune – [[All-Germanic Heathens' Front]], [[National Alliance (United States)|National Alliance]]
** [[Odal rune]] - common among various neo-Nazi group
** [[Sigel rune]], especially on the [[Schutzstaffel]] badge, sometimes confused with or used interchangeably with ''[[Eihwaz]]''
** [[Tiwaz rune|Tyr]] rune was on the badge of the SA ''Reichsführerschulen'' in Nazi Germany, and is sometimes used by neo-Nazis such as [[Nordic Resistance Movement]]
** [[Orkhon script]] letters – used by followers of [[Nihal Atsiz]], e.g.Türkçü Toplumcu Budun Derneği
* [[Triskelion]]-like symbol composed of three 7s – ''[[Afrikaner Weerstandsbeweging]]'' (Afrikaner Resistance Movement), [[Republic of south africa|Republic of South Africa]]
* Neo-Nazis typically use Nordic Pagan symbols, including [[Mjölnir]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.adl.org/education/references/hate-symbols/thors-hammer General Hate Symbols: Thor's Hammer, ''Anti-Defamation League'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pejorative symbolism==
Opponents of fascism have identified symbols seen in a pejorative manner such as the [[jackboot]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Heraldry}}
* [[Anarchist symbolism]]
* [[Communist symbolism]]
* ''[[Black Sun (occult symbol)|Schwarze Sonne]]''
* [[Strafgesetzbuch section 86a]]
* [[Western use of the swastika in the early 20th century]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://flagspot.net/flags/qt-z.html Neonazi flags]
* [http://flagspot.net/flags/qt-z_sym.html Neonazi flag symbolism]
* [http://www.forbiddensymbols.com/category/political/fascist/ Fascist signs and symbols at Forbidden Symbols]

{{Fascism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fascist Symbolism}}
[[Category:Fascist symbols| ]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazism]]
[[Category:Swastika]]</text>
      <sha1>cwh75x46q56oi58qhswufz1hxdtivnv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
