<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Childhood in Maya society</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7083865</id>
    <revision>
      <id>955340752</id>
      <parentid>954799285</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-07T08:08:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.102.95.179</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Values in children */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12542" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{unbalanced|date=April 2016}}
{{weasel|date=April 2016}}
}}

[[File:Kek'Chi Maya Children.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Mayan children in 2009]]

The role of the children in ancient Mayan civilization was first and foremost to help their elders. Once children turned five or six they were expected to contribute to the family and community. They were treated as young adults and received more responsibilities as they grew older.

== Adolescents ==
[[Adolescence|Young girls]] were expected to perform [[household]] duties, while young [[boy]]s were to help their [[father]]s in [[farming]].

Mostly [[women]] raised the children, but "When a boy was about four or five his father began the training of his son."&lt;ref&gt;Sharer, 482&lt;/ref&gt;

When adolescents turned 15, they were expected to be independent. Today, this tradition of [[work ethic]] still applies to adolescents.

== Rituals and children ==
The Maya desired some unnatural physical characteristics for their children. For instance, at a very young age boards were pressed on babies' [[forehead]]s to create a flattened surface. This process was widespread among the [[upper class]].

Another practice was to cross babies' [[Human eye|eyes]]. To do this, objects were dangled in front of a newborn's eyes, until the newborn's eyes were completely and permanently crossed. In addition, there were a few unique customs regarding children. For example, most Maya children were named according to the day they were born. Every day of the [[year]] had a specific name for both boys and girls and parents were expected to follow that practice.

== Death ==
Most [[burial]] sites for children were not as elaborate as adult burial sites. "Infants/toddlers generally lacked offerings… for [children] who died before reaching the age of five, the only elaboration or special treatment consisted of inclusion within a probable family group…"&lt;ref&gt;Ardren, 67&lt;/ref&gt; However, some burial sites for children did contain more gifts than other youngsters. This suggests that the family had a great deal of remorse, and/or the child had high standings.

== Values in children ==
Several values were stressed to Maya children. Not only was a strong work [[ethics]] desirable, but working for the betterment of the community was necessary.

Families were extremely important to the Maya culture, and respecting the leaders in one's family was [[Moral imperative|imperative]]. "A sense of resp


y is another important quality which children have to learn. This includes independence, self-confidence and the ability to make decisions."&lt;ref&gt;Heckt, 325&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that the most important quality for children to have was [[common sense]], and they received this by shadowing their parents.

Among [[Yucatec Maya language|Yucatec Maya parents]], the ceremony called ''hetsmek{{okina}}'' is still practiced even among professionals living in [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]], the capital of [[Yucatán (state)|Yucatán]].

== Maya children today ==
Maya populations are present today in many areas of Central and South America, such as [[Guatemala#Culture|Guatemala]]. There is limited research on the lives of Maya children, mostly because developmental research has primarily involved European-American children.&lt;ref name="Morellietal2003_a"&gt;Morelli, G., Rogoff, B., &amp; Angelillo, C. (2003). Cultural variation in young children's access to work or involvement in specialized child-focused activities. ''International Journal of Behavioural Development, 27'', 264-274.&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is evident that the goals for Maya children's socialization and daily activities differ from those of other cultures, especially those that are most studied.&lt;ref name="Gaskins2006"&gt;Gaskins, S. (2006) The Cultural Organization of Yucatec Mayan Childrenís Social Interactions. ''Peer relationships in cultural context'', 283.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Learning ===

Children in many Maya communities often engage in different [[socialization]] patterns than those commonly found in European-American communities.&lt;ref name="Gaskins2006" /&gt; Specifically, Maya cultures commonly emphasize the primacy of community activities (in which adults and children are participants), the importance of parental beliefs, and the independence of children's [[Motivation#Education|motivation]] in their socialization.&lt;ref name="Gaskins1999"&gt;Gaskins, S. (1999). Children's Daily Lives in a Mayan village: A Case Study of Culturally Constructed Roles and Activities. In A. Göncü (Ed.), ''Children's Engagement in the World: Sociocultural Perspectives'' (pp. 25-61). Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gaskins, S. (2000). Children's Daily Activities in a Mayan Village: A Culturally Grounded Description. Cross-Cultural Research, 34, 375-389.&lt;/ref&gt; Children in Maya communities develop within the context of work and other family activities.&lt;ref name="Gaskins2006" /&gt; They commonly learn through [[Observational learning#Observational learning across cultures|observing]] and engaging in work with others.&lt;ref name="Gaskins1999" /&gt;

Children in modern-day Maya communities observe and participate in work with people of all ages.&lt;ref name="Rogoffetal2010"&gt;Rogoff, B., Morelli, G. A., &amp; Chavajay, P. (2010). Childrenís Integration in Communities and Segregation From People of Differing Ages. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 5(4), 431-440.&lt;/ref&gt; Young children in Maya communities such as [[San Pedro La Laguna]] have been observed listening in on the work of older children, adults, and elders.&lt;ref name="Rogoffetal2010" /&gt; These children are expected to observe the activities going on around them in order for their learning to take place.&lt;ref name="Morellietal2003_a" /&gt; The mix of interaction between age groups in Maya communities is important to their learning. [[Age segregation]] does not play an active role in the learning patterns of Maya children, as they interact with both adults and children of all ages.&lt;ref name="Goncu2000"&gt;Göncü, A., Mistry, J., &amp; Mosier, C. (2000). Cultural variations in the play of toddlers. International Journal of Behavioral Development, 24(3), 321-329.&lt;/ref&gt; Maya siblings also play an active role in directing each other's learning.&lt;ref name="Maynard2002"&gt;Maynard, A. E. (2002). Cultural teaching: The development of teaching skills in Maya sibling interactions. Child development, 73(3), 969-982.&lt;/ref&gt;

Children in Maya communities also observe and participate in adult work in order to become active members in their community.&lt;ref&gt;Nimmo, J. (2008). Young children's access to real life: An examination of the growing boundaries between children in child care and adults in the community. ''Contemporary Issues in Early Childhood, 9'', 3-13.&lt;/ref&gt; Though children in European American communities do not engage in as much productive or goal-driven work, [[Maya peoples|Maya]] children see this work as embodying their sense of self-worth.&lt;ref&gt;Woodhead, M. (1998). ''Children's perspectives on their working lives: A participatory study in Bangladesh, Ethiopia, the Philippines, Guatemala, El Salvador, and Nicaragua''. Stockholm: Save the Children Sweden.&lt;/ref&gt;
Maya children engage in less imaginary play than children from many middle-class Western communities.&lt;ref name="Goncu2000"/&gt; When European-American adults play with children, the play is seen as an educational exercise, but play that Maya children partake in is often an emulation of mature work happening around them&lt;ref name="Morellietal2003_c"&gt;Morelli, G., Rogoff, B., &amp; Angelillo, C. (2003).&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a child will pretend to "weave" on a make-believe loom, or "wash clothes" by pouring water on a cloth.&lt;ref name="Rogoff2011"&gt;Rogoff, Barbara (2011). Developing Destinies: A Mayan Midwife and Town. Cambridge: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, Maya children are [[Learning through play#Culture and Learning Through Play|learning through play]].

Engaging in play that emulates work, and providing actual contributions to work, are characteristic of a style of learning referred to as [[Learning by Observing and Pitching In]] (which was previously called Intent Community Participation&lt;ref name="Rogoff, B. 2003"&gt;Rogoff, B., Paradise, R., Arauz, R. M., Correa-Chavez, M., &amp; Angelillo, C. (2003). Firsthand learning through intent participation. Annual Review of Psychology, 54(1), 175-203&lt;/ref&gt;). This approach involves the learner observing and listening, directed by their own initiative and concentration. This individual drive to learn is coupled with the learner's expected participation in shared endeavors. In other words, Maya children learn through Intent Community Participation because they are self-motivated to learn, and are included and given responsibilities. Maya children are respected as capable contributors to their community from as young as age 3 or 4.&lt;ref name="Rogoff, B. 2003"/&gt;

This style of learning can be contrasted with other learning styles, such as assembly-line instruction.&lt;ref name="Rogoff, B. 2003" /&gt; Assembly-line instruction is the approach taken by most Westernized schooling. Assembly-line instruction is based on the transmission of knowledge from experts to subordinates, in a way that does not facilitate purposeful activity. Maya Children do not participate primarily in this style of learning, because they learn through inclusion and hands-on experience.  Because of this form of learning, Mayan children are much more observant in their environment as compared to European-American children.{{citation needed|date=April 2016}} Learning through observation and participation develops skills such as dual attentiveness which supports their way of life and learning.  Through methods such as [[Learning by Observing and Pitching In]], Maya children work as a community to build their skills for contributing in their community.

== Notes ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== References ==
* Ardren, Traci and Scott R. Hutson, (2006). ''The Social Experience of Childhood in Ancient Mesoamerica''. Boulder, CO: University Press of Colorado
* Sharer, Robert; (1994) ''The Ancient Maya'', Stanford.
* Heckt, Meike; (1999) ''Mayan Education In Guatemala: A Pedagogical Model and Its Political Context'' in ''International Review of Education'' Volume 45, Number 3-4, pp.&amp;nbsp;321–337.
* Cervera, M. D. (2007). El hetsmek' como expression simbolica de la construccion de los ninos mayas yucatecos como personas. Pueblos y Fronteras Digital "La nocion de persona en Mexico y Centroamerica".  Disponible en https://web.archive.org/web/20160304075903/http://www.pueblosyfronteras.unam.mx/a07n4/art_09.html
* Cervera, M. D., &amp; Mendez, R. M. (2006). ''Temperament and ecological context among Yucatec Mayan children''. International Journal of Behavioral Development, 30, 326-337. Resumen disponible en http://jbd.sagepub.com/content/30/4/326.abstract
* de Leon, L. (2001). ''¿Como construir un nino zinacanteco?: Conceptos espaciales y lengua materna en la adquisición del tzotzil". In C. Rojas, &amp; L. De León (Eds.), La adquisicion de la lengua materna: espanol, lenguas mayas, euskera (pp. 99-124). Mexico, DF: Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico y Centro de Investigaciones y Estudios Superiores en Antropologia Social.
* Euan, R. G., &amp; Cervera, M. D. (2009). Amarras lo que aprendes en la escuela y en la casa: Etnoteorias parentales y rezago educativo. In J. C. Mijangos (Ed.), La lucha contra el rezago educativo. El caso de los mayas de Yucatan (pp. 167 a 186). Merida, Yucatan.
* Gaskins, S. (1996). ''How Mayan parental theories come into play''. In C. M. Super &amp; S. Harkness (Eds.), ''Parents' cultural belief systems: Their origins, expressions, and consequences'' pp.&amp;nbsp;345 a 363). New York: Guilford.
* Redfield, R., &amp; Villa Rojas, A. (1990). Chan Kom: A Maya village. Prospect Heights, IL: Waveland.
* Göncü, A., Mistry, J., &amp; Mosier, C. (2000). Cultural variations in the play of toddlers. International Journal of Behavioral Development, 24(3), 321-329.
* Maynard, A. E. (2002). Cultural teaching: The development of teaching skills in Maya sibling interactions. Child Development, 73(3), 969-982.this website is terrible!
* Rogoff, B., Paradise, R., Arauz, R. M., Correa-Chavez, M., &amp; Angelillo, C. (2003). Firsthand learning through intent participation. Annual Review of Psychology, 54(1), 175-203.
* Rogoff, Barbara (2011). Developing Destinies: A Mayan Midwife and Town. Cambridge: Oxford University Press

{{Maya}}

[[Category:Maya society]]
[[Category:History of childhood]]
[[Category:Children by culture|Maya]]</text>
      <sha1>bsnqhq7qa0g80nc7fu8fqmb0715r85o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
