<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hollywood (miniseries)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>61660660</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962620324</id>
      <parentid>962406964</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-15T03:16:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hiplibrarianship</username>
        <id>2012100</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed grammar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="27710" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American drama web television miniseries}}
{{Use American English|date=February 2020}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2020}}
{{Infobox television
| name                     = Hollywood
| image                    = Hollywood - Netflix series title card.png
| genre                    = [[Drama (film and television)|Drama]]
| creator                  = {{Plainlist|
* [[Ryan Murphy (writer)|Ryan Murphy]]
* [[Ian Brennan (writer)|Ian Brennan]]
}}
| starring                 = {{Plainlist|
* [[David Corenswet]]
* [[Darren Criss]]
* [[Laura Harrier]]
* [[Joe Mantello]]
* [[Dylan McDermott]]
* [[Jake Picking]]
* [[Jeremy Pope (actor)|Jeremy Pope]]
* [[Holland Taylor]]
* [[Samara Weaving]]
* [[Jim Parsons]]
* [[Patti LuPone]]
}}
| composer                 =
| country                  = United States
| language                 = English
| num_episodes             = 7&lt;!--Only increment as a new episode premieres, per the documentation of the template!--&gt;
| list_episodes            = #Episodes
| executive_producer       = {{Plainlist|
* Ryan Murphy
* Ian Brennan
* [[Alexis Martin Woodall]]
* [[Janet Mock]]
* Eric Kovtun
* [[Ned Martel]]
* Darren Criss
* Jim Parsons
* David Corenswet
}}
| producer                 = {{Plainlist|
* Todd Nenninger
* [[Lou Eyrich]]
* Eryn Krueger Mekash
}}
| cinematography           = {{Plainlist|
* Simon Dennis
* Blake McClure
}}
| editor                   = {{Plainlist|
* Butch Wertman
* Andrew Groves
* Suzanne Spangler
* Lousine Shamamian
}}
| runtime                  = 44–57 minutes
| company                  = {{Plainlist|
* Ryan Murphy Television
* Prospect Films
}}
| network                  = [[Netflix]]
| first_aired              = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
| website                  = https://www.netflix.com/title/81088617
| website_title            = Official website
}}
'''''Hollywood''''' is an American [[Drama (film and television)|drama]] [[web television]] miniseries starring an [[ensemble cast|ensemble]] of [[David Corenswet]], [[Darren Criss]], [[Laura Harrier]], [[Joe Mantello]], [[Dylan McDermott]], [[Jake Picking]], [[Jeremy Pope (actor)|Jeremy Pope]], [[Holland Taylor]], [[Samara Weaving]], [[Jim Parsons]], and [[Patti LuPone]]. Created by [[Ryan Murphy (writer)|Ryan Murphy]] and [[Ian Brennan (writer)|Ian Brennan]], it was released May 1, 2020, on [[Netflix]].&lt;ref name="SeriesPremiereDate"/&gt;

The miniseries is about a group of aspiring actors and filmmakers during the [[Hollywood Golden Age]] in the post-[[World War II]] era trying to make their dreams come true. The series received mixed reviews from critics who praised the performances of the cast and production value, but criticized its tone, writing, and the [[artistic license]] taken.

==Premise==
The series follows a group of aspiring actors and filmmakers in post-[[World War II]] Hollywood (1947–1948) as they try to make it in the film industry—no matter what the cost. Each character offers a unique glimpse behind the gilded curtain of [[Classical Hollywood cinema|Hollywood's Golden Age]], noting entrenched power, challenges to that power, and biases of many kinds that continue to this day. The show is described as exposing and examining decades-old power dynamics, and what the entertainment landscape might look like if they had been dismantled.&lt;ref name="SlashFilm"&gt;{{cite web|title='Hollywood', Ryan Murphy's New Netflix Show, Arrives in May|url=https://www.slashfilm.com/hollywood-netflix/|last=Evangelista|first=Chris|date=February 20, 2020|work=[[/Film]]|accessdate=February 20, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200220214520/https://www.slashfilm.com/hollywood-netflix/|archive-date=February 20, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cast==
=== Main ===
&lt;!-- Cast listed according to show's opening credits. --&gt;
*[[David Corenswet]] as Jack Costello, a [[World War II]] veteran who moves to Hollywood in hopes of becoming an actor.
*[[Darren Criss]] as Raymond Ainsley, a half-[[Filipinos|Filipino]] aspiring film director hoping to break boundaries in Hollywood, and Camille's boyfriend.
*[[Laura Harrier]] as Camille Washington, an up-and-coming black actress facing prejudice because of her race, and Raymond's girlfriend.
*[[Joe Mantello]] as Richard "Dick" Samuels, a studio executive at Ace Studios who is a closeted gay man. Hank Steuver of the ''[[Washington Post]]'' describes him as "intimidating but receptive".&lt;ref name=Steuver&gt;{{cite web|author=Steuver, Hank|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/tv/in-ryan-murphys-hollywood-the-old-studio-system-gets-a-rousingly-revisionist-wake-up-call/2020/04/30/510b5f96-8a5a-11ea-ac8a-fe9b8088e101_story.html|title=In Ryan Murphy's ‘Hollywood,’ the old studio system gets a rousingly revisionist wake-up call|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|date=April 30, 2020|accessdate=May 17, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200506185415/https://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/tv/in-ryan-murphys-hollywood-the-old-studio-system-gets-a-rousingly-revisionist-wake-up-call/2020/04/30/510b5f96-8a5a-11ea-ac8a-fe9b8088e101_story.html|archive-date=May 6, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dylan McDermott]] as Ernest "Ernie" West, a [[pimp]], based on [[Scotty Bowers]], who runs his business out of a gas station and recruits Jack.
*[[Jake Picking]] as [[Rock Hudson|Roy Fitzgerald / Rock Hudson]], a fictionalized version of the actor, and Archie's boyfriend. Liz Cantrell of ''[[Town &amp; Country (magazine)|Town &amp; Country]]'' magazine characterized this version of Rock Hudson as "a young unknown [...] trying to make his way in the world, and beginning to understand who he really is."&lt;ref name=Cantrell&gt;{{cite web|author=Cantrell, Liz|url=https://www.townandcountrymag.com/leisure/arts-and-culture/g32222553/hollywood-netflix-cast-real-life/|title=How the ''Hollywood'' Cast Compares to Their Real-Life Counterparts, In Photos|work=[[Town and Country Magazine]]|date=May 8, 2020|accessdate=May 17, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200508164609/https://www.townandcountrymag.com/leisure/arts-and-culture/g32222553/hollywood-netflix-cast-real-life/|archive-date=May 8, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jeremy Pope (actor)|Jeremy Pope]] as Archie Coleman, a black aspiring screenwriter facing prejudice, and Rock's boyfriend
*[[Holland Taylor]] as Ellen Kincaid, a studio executive and mentor for aspiring actors at Ace Studios. Cantrell wrote that the character "gets what she wants and knows a star when she sees one."&lt;ref name=Cantrell/&gt;
*[[Samara Weaving]] as Claire Wood, an up-and-coming actress, Camille's rival, and the daughter of Ace and Avis Amberg. Cantrell described her as "an ambitious up-and-comer".&lt;ref name=Cantrell/&gt;
*[[Jim Parsons]] as [[Henry Willson]], a fictionalized version of the Hollywood talent agent whose clients included Rock Hudson
*[[Patti LuPone]] as Avis Amberg, wife of Ace Amberg, the head of Ace Studios, and a former actress

===Recurring===
&lt;!-- Only includes major recurring characters appearing in at least 4 episodes. --&gt;
*[[Maude Apatow]] as Henrietta Castello, Jack's wife who is pregnant with twins and works as a waitress. Robert Lloyd of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' wrote that the character serves "largely as a millstone" and that the storyline does not give a lot of "attention" to her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lloyd, Robert|url=https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2020-04-30/netflix-hollywood-ryan-murphy-ian-brennan-darren-criss|title=Review: ‘Hollywood’ rewrites Tinseltown’s racist, sexist, homophobic past. It’s not convincing|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=April 30, 2020|accessdate=May 17, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200515011544/https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2020-04-30/netflix-hollywood-ryan-murphy-ian-brennan-darren-criss|archive-date=May 15, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mira Sorvino]] as Jeanne Crandall, a successful but aging actress, Ace's mistress, and Camille's scene partner
*[[Michelle Krusiec]] as [[Anna May Wong]], a fictionalized version of the Chinese-American actress, whom Raymond tries to help

=== Guest ===
&lt;!-- Only includes major guest characters appearing in 1 to 3 episodes, not non-speaking/background roles.  --&gt;
*[[Rob Reiner]] as Ace Amberg, the head of Ace Studios and the husband of Avis
*Brian Chenoweth as Lon Silver, Ace's attorney
*Jake Regal as Erwin Kaye, a man Henrietta works with and has an affair with
*[[William Frederick Knight]] as Harry Golden, a veteran film editor at Ace Studios
*[[Queen Latifah]] as [[Hattie McDaniel]], a fictionalized version of the actress, who gives Camille advice
*Katie McGuinness as [[Vivien Leigh]], a fictionalized version of the actress
*[[Paget Brewster]] as [[Tallulah Bankhead]], a fictionalized version of the actress
*[[Harriet Sansom Harris]] as [[Eleanor Roosevelt]], a fictionalized version of the First Lady and Avis's friend
* [[Daniel London]] as [[George Cukor]], a fictionalized version of the director and producer known for his grand house parties
* [[Billy Boyd (actor)|Billy Boyd]] as [[Noël Coward]], a fictionalized version of the playwright, composer, director, and actor
* [[Alison Wright]] as Ms. Roswell, the gatekeeper to Ace Studios

==Episodes==
{{Episode table |background=#000000 |overall= |title= |director= |writer= |airdate=|released=y |episodes=
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 1
 |Title           = Hooray for Hollywood
 |DirectedBy      = [[Ryan Murphy (writer)|Ryan Murphy]]
 |WrittenBy       = Ryan Murphy &amp; [[Ian Brennan (writer)|Ian Brennan]]
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = In post-World War II, veteran Jack Costello moves to Los Angeles to make his big break in Hollywood. However, he struggles in the business and has a hard time even being cast as an extra. This bothers his wife Henrietta who is pregnant and wanting to buy a house. At a bar, Jack meets Ernie West who offers him a job at his gas station, which Jack accepts. Ernie reveals that he makes his attendants service female customers for extra money, which Jack begins doing. However, Jack quits when Ernie tries to force him to service a male customer, but gets his job back after discovering Henrietta is pregnant with twins. He later meets black male prostitute and aspiring screenwriter Archie Coleman, and convinces Ernie to hire him. On his first day on the job, Archie services aspiring actor Roy Fitzgerald. After servicing a casting director, Jack finally lands an acting job. However, he is later tricked by a police officer undercover as a client who has him arrested.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 2
 |Title           = Hooray for Hollywood: Part 2
 |DirectedBy      = [[Daniel Minahan]]
 |WrittenBy       = Ryan Murphy &amp; Ian Brennan
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Ernie bails Jack out of jail. Jack later services again his first client, Avis Amberg, whose husband owns the studio where he will have his first screen test and promises that she will ensure he will do well. Meanwhile, fledgling director Raymond Ainsley recruits Anna May Wong to be his leading lady. He meets with studio executive Dick Samuels who warns him about casting Wong. Although Jack bombs his screen test, executive and acting mentor Ellen Kincaid convinces Dick to put him under contract. Aspiring black actress and Raymond's girlfriend Camille Washington finds herself only able to get parts as a servant. Dick puts Raymond's film on hold, but allows him to pick a script from a pile and direct that film. He picks a script written by Archie about a woman who jumped off the Hollywood sign. Archie also continues to service Roy and the two find themselves falling for one another. Roy also meets Henry Willson, a closeted homosexual agent who agrees to take him on as a client on the condition that he submits to Willson's sexual desires and that his name be changed to Rock Hudson. Dick greenlights Raymond and Archie's film, ''Peg''.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 3
 |Title           = Outlaws
 |DirectedBy      = [[Michael Uppendahl]]
 |WrittenBy       = Ryan Murphy &amp; Ian Brennan
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Ernie reveals to the attendants that they have been invited to an exclusive Hollywood party hosted by George Cukor to service the closeted homosexual industry people. Jack desperately wants the male lead part in ''Peg'', but Archie has his eyes set on Rock for the role. Henry invites Rock to join him at the Cukor party for Rock to socialize with Dick, who will be at the party and could get Rock a screen test. Ellen begins prepping Jack for his ''Peg'' screen test. Avis' daughter, Claire, gets a screen test for ''Peg'', while Camille attempts to convince Raymond to give her the part and offers him ideas on how to tweak the script. At the party, Rock and Dick begin to have a sexual encounter, but Dick is uncomfortable and puts a stop to it. He laments about how he has always had to play a role and hide who he really is, before telling Roy to stop allowing Henry to control him. Rock then professes his love to Archie, while Raymond confesses his love to Camille and tells her that he will make her the star of ''Peg''. Dick, inspired by his interaction with Rock, and Ellen agree to fight for Camille to be the lead.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 4
 |Title           = (Screen) Tests
 |DirectedBy      = [[Janet Mock]]
 |WrittenBy       = Ian Brennan &amp; Janet Mock &amp; Ryan Murphy
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Ace Amberg, the head of the studio, greenlights ''Peg'' but demands that Archie be taken off the project, fearing an African-American screenwriter's involvement would provoke a scandal. Ace later has a heart attack in the midst of a sexual encounter. With Ace incapacitated, Avis is put in charge of the studio. Dick tells Archie the bad news about being removed from the film; Archie refuses to be sidelined which Dick accepts, but warns him about the consequences. Later, Archie and Raymond help Camille prepare for her screen test, with Raymond directing her to put more emotion into it. During his screen test, Roy constantly messes up his lines. Claire blows her audition on purpose to give Camille a fighting chance. While Camille gives a great performance in her test, Avis worries about casting a black woman and reluctantly chooses Claire. Jack is cast as the male lead, despite Henry's attempt to blackmail Avis into casting Rock. Avis' friend and First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt gives a rousing and inspiring speech to Avis on why she should cast Camille in the lead role.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 5
 |Title           = Jump
 |DirectedBy      = Michael Uppendahl
 |WrittenBy       = Ryan Murphy &amp; Ian Brennan
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Dick and Ellen finally convince Avis to cast Camille in the film. Archie's name remains attached to the film, while Roy, Claire, and Wong are cast in smaller roles. The film is retitled ''Meg''. The studio faces significant backlash, mostly from the [[Southern United States|South]], and Camille begins to receive racist telephone calls. Dick takes command of production, ensuring everything stays under budget. Dick later convinces Raymond and Archie to change the ending so Meg lives. When a local gossip magazine learns of Jack's arrest for solicitation and plans to run it, Avis recruits Henry, who manages to squash the story by ordering mobsters to brutally beat the magazine reporter. In return, Henry asks Avis to make him a producer on ''Meg'' which she agrees to. Dick berates Raymond for approving an over-budget redo and forces him to pay for it himself. Ellen flirts with Dick who rebuffs her, telling her he cannot be with anyone at the moment, and he later goes to a gay bar. Henrietta reveals to Jack that the twins are not his, but a friend she has grown close to and she is moving away with him. Desolate, Jack moves in with Archie.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 6
 |Title           = Meg
 |DirectedBy      = Janet Mock
 |WrittenBy       = Ian Brennan &amp; Janet Mock &amp; Reilly Smith
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Cast and crew members from ''Meg'' are targeted by [[White supremacy|white supremacist]] groups. Ace's lawyer threatens to suspend production, but Avis is determined to finish the film. Ernie raises the money Raymond needs to cover going over budget. Jack and Henrietta apologize to one another and say a final goodbye. To repay Ernie for his help, Jack and Archie offer him a part in the film which he accepts. Ellen coaches Ernie to improve his acting skills. The film is finally concluded. Archie asks Roy to move in with him which he accepts. Jack and Claire fall for each other and decide to attend the premiere together. Ace awakens from his coma and is advised to scrap the film, but he loves it. Dick threatens to quit unless the film is released and reveals to Ace that he is gay. Henry feels unsatisfied by the ending and demands a new scene be added, which Raymond approves. Avis demands to co-chair the studio and Ace agrees to it. The two rekindle their previously strained relationship. The next morning, Avis finds that Ace has died from heart complications, leaving her grieving. Ace's lawyer has the reel for ''Meg'' burned.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber   = 7
 |Title           = A Hollywood Ending
 |DirectedBy      = [[Jessica Yu]]
 |WrittenBy       = Ian Brennan &amp; Ryan Murphy
 |OriginalAirDate = {{Start date|2020|5|1}}
 |ShortSummary    = Avis fires the lawyer who had the film reels burned. At Ace's funeral, the film's editor reveals he made a copy for safekeeping. The studio opts for a wide release of ''Meg''. Ernie and Ellen confess their love, before he reveals his terminal lung cancer, but she accepts him anyway. Jack and Claire start a relationship. The film becomes a record-breaking success, while Camille, Wong, Raymond, Archie, and Jack all receive [[Academy Award|Oscar]] nominations. Archie and Roy make their relationship public at the ceremony. Roy fires Henry as his agent after he berates him for coming out with Archie. When Camille is told to wait outside, she refuses and sits in the front row. At the Oscars, Wong, Raymond, Archie, and Camille win. Jack loses but proposes to Claire, who accepts. Hattie congratulates Camille on her win. A year later, Henry is sober and apologizes to Roy. Dick dies of cancer and everyone involved in ''Meg'' attends his funeral. Avis greenlights Henry's new film about a homosexual couple, ''Dreamland'', with Roy, Jack, Archie, and Raymond joining as well. Ernie plans to sell his gas station and offers it as a set for ''Dreamland''.
 |LineColor       = 000
}}
}}

==Production==
===Development===
On February 23, 2019, it was announced that [[Netflix]] had given the production a straight-to-series order. The series was created by [[Ian Brennan (writer)|Ian Brennan]], and [[Ryan Murphy (writer)|Ryan Murphy]]. Brennan and Murphy were also set to executive produce the series alongside [[Darren Criss]] and [[David Corenswet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Pedersen |first1=Erik |title=Ryan Murphy Sets Next Netflix Series 'Hollywood' About Tinseltown's Golden Age |url=https://deadline.com/2019/02/ryan-murphy-netflix-series-hollywood-ian-brennan-1202562823// |website=Deadline Hollywood |accessdate=September 1, 2019 |date=February 22, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190901184218/https://deadline.com/2019/02/ryan-murphy-netflix-series-hollywood-ian-brennan-1202562823/ |archive-date=September 1, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The series was released on May 1, 2020.&lt;ref name="SeriesPremiereDate"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://deadline.com/2020/02/hollywood-premiere-date-ryan-murphy-netflix-limited-series-1202863984/|title='Hollywood' Premiere Date: Ryan Murphy's Netflix Limited Series About Postwar Tinseltown|website=Deadline Hollywood|first=Erik|last=Pedersen|date=February 20, 2020|accessdate=February 20, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200220155525/https://deadline.com/2020/02/hollywood-premiere-date-ryan-murphy-netflix-limited-series-1202863984/|archive-date=February 20, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Casting===
On September 3, 2019, it was reported that [[Patti LuPone]], [[Holland Taylor]], [[ Darren Criss]], [[Jeremy Pope (actor)|Jeremy Pope]], [[Dylan McDermott]], [[Jim Parsons]], Corenswet, and [[Joe Mantello]] had been cast in series regular roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/live-feed/ryan-murphy-adds-netflix-slate-a-chorus-line-mini-andy-warhol-docuseries-1236549|title=Ryan Murphy Adds to Netflix Slate With 'A Chorus Line' Mini, Andy Warhol Docuseries|first=Lesley|last=Goldberg|website=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=September 3, 2019|access-date=November 8, 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200105132415/https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/live-feed/ryan-murphy-adds-netflix-slate-a-chorus-line-mini-andy-warhol-docuseries-1236549|archive-date=January 5, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Sneider |first1=Jeff |title=Exclusive: Ryan Murphy's 'Hollywood' to Star Broadway Sensation Jeremy Pope |url=http://collider.com/ryan-murphy-hollywood-cast-jeremy-pope-broadway/?amp |website=[[Collider (website)|Collider]] |accessdate=September 3, 2019 |date=September 3, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190904013220/http://collider.com/ryan-murphy-hollywood-cast-jeremy-pope-broadway/?amp |archive-date=September 4, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Perski |first1=Denise |title=Darren Criss To Star In &amp; Executive Produce Ryan Murphy's 'Hollywood' Series For Netflix |url=https://deadline.com/2019/09/hollywood-darren-criss-to-star-in-executive-produce-ryan-murphys-netflix-series-1202728280/ |website=Deadline Hollywood |accessdate=September 7, 2019 |date=September 6, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190907153413/https://deadline.com/2019/09/hollywood-darren-criss-to-star-in-executive-produce-ryan-murphys-netflix-series-1202728280/ |archive-date=September 7, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Petski |first1=Denise |title='The Politician's David Corenswet To Star in Ryan Murphy's Netflix Series 'Hollywood' |url= https://deadline.com/2019/09/david-corenswet-ryan-murphy-hollywood-netflix-drama-series-the-politician-1202744640/comment-page-1/#comments | website=[[Deadline Hollywood]]|accessdate=September 26, 2019 |date=September 25, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
On [[Rotten Tomatoes]], the series holds an approval rating of 57% based on 118 reviews, with an average rating of 5.97/10. The site's critical consensus reads: "With its heart on its sleeve and style to spare, ''Hollywood'' is anything but subtle – if only its good intentions were paired with a less convoluted story."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rottentomatoes.com/tv/hollywood/s01|title=Hollywood: Season 1 (2020)|work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|publisher=[[Fandango (company)|Fandango Media]]|accessdate=June 11, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; On [[Metacritic]], the series has a weighted average score of 55 out of 100, based on 33 critics, indicating "mixed or average reviews".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.metacritic.com/tv/hollywood/season-1|title=Hollywood: Season 1 reviews|work=[[Metacritic]]|publisher=[[CBS Interactive]]|accessdate=June 11, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200509143927/https://www.metacritic.com/tv/hollywood/season-1|archive-date=May 9, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing for the ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', [[Richard Roeper]] gave the series two-and-a-half stars out of four, saying: "It's a fascinating blend of fact (or least stories based on factual characters) and fiction, and the performances from the cast of rising stars and reliable veterans are dazzling — but like many a motion picture, ''Hollywood'' can't overcome script problems that surface about midway through the story."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url= https://chicago.suntimes.com/2020/4/29/21239906/hollywood-review-netflix-series |title= ‘Hollywood’ a so-so fantasy about La La Land in its Golden Age |last= Roeper |first= Richard |author-link= Richard Roeper |date= April 29, 2020 |work= [[Chicago Sun-Times]] |access-date= May 2, 2020 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20200430035721/https://chicago.suntimes.com/2020/4/29/21239906/hollywood-review-netflix-series |archive-date= April 30, 2020 |url-status= live }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Conversely, Hugh Montgomery of the [[BBC]] described the series as "spineless and inert", giving it one out of five stars and saying "A show about Tinseltown that chose to confront and prod at these continuing, dispiriting realities rather than concoct its own vapid, hubristic fantasies would be worth 10 times this one."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20200428-hollywood-review-this-lavish-period-fantasy-is-a-disaster|title=Hollywood review: This lavish period fantasy is a disaster|work=[[BBC]]|first=Hugh|last=Montgomery|date=April 29, 2020|accessdate=April 29, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200502181030/http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20200428-hollywood-review-this-lavish-period-fantasy-is-a-disaster|archive-date=May 2, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, ''[[The Guardian]]''{{'}}s Lucy Mangan criticized its "counterfactual history", giving the series a two out of five-star review, writing: "This should be the perfect set-up for a scabrous look at prejudice, corruption, the trading of sexual currency, coercion, the well-oiled machinations that underlie an industry and how it all shapes history — all through a [[Me Too movement|#MeToo]] lens. But it becomes a mere wish-fulfilment fantasy that, whether it intends to or not, suggests that if a few people had just been that bit braver, then movies – and therefore the world! — would be a glorious, egalitarian Eden. It is a show that is smug and obtuse enough to believe la la land's self-regarding idea that celluloid art directly shapes our lives."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2020/may/01/hollywood-review-ryan-murphy-netflix|title=Hollywood review – Ryan Murphy's Netflix epic is a hollow ode to showbiz|work=[[The Guardian]]|first=Lucy|last=Mangan|date=May 1, 2020|accessdate=May 5, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200505022416/https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2020/may/01/hollywood-review-ryan-murphy-netflix|archive-date=May 5, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Netflix title|81088617}}
*{{IMDb title|9827854}}

{{Ryan Murphy}}
{{Netflix original ended series}}

[[Category:2020 American television series debuts]]
[[Category:2020 American television series endings]]
[[Category:2020s American drama television miniseries]]
[[Category:2020s American LGBT-related drama television series]]
[[Category:American drama web series]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of actors]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of Cole Porter]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of Eleanor Roosevelt]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of film directors]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of Rock Hudson]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:Gay-related films]]
[[Category:Netflix original programming]]
[[Category:Race and ethnicity in television]]
[[Category:Television series about show business]]
[[Category:Television series created by Ryan Murphy (writer)]]
[[Category:Television series set in the 1940s]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Los Angeles]]</text>
      <sha1>e2aidob4qnj5cxk80i00dju69sxxhck</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
