<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>First Amendment to the United States Constitution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962591515</id>
      <parentid>962584760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-14T23:32:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frietjes</username>
        <id>13791031</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Clean up [[:Category:Pages using duplicate arguments in template calls|duplicate template arguments]] using [[:en:User:Frietjes/findargdups|findargdups]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="135038" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|First Amendment|the first amendments to other constitutions}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Over-quotation|date=May 2020}}
{{Use American English|date = January 2019}}
{{Short description|Law guaranteeing freedom of speech, religion, assembly, press and petitions and prohibiting establishment of an official religion}}
{{good article}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2013}}
{{US Constitution article series}}
The '''First Amendment''' ('''Amendment I''') to the [[United States Constitution]] prevents the government from making laws which regulate an [[Establishment Clause|establishment of religion]], prohibit the [[Free Exercise Clause|free exercise of religion]], or abridge the [[Freedom of speech in the United States|freedom of speech]], the [[Freedom of the press in the United States|freedom of the press]], the [[Freedom of assembly|right to peaceably assemble]], or the right to [[Right to petition|petition the government for redress of grievances]]. It was adopted on December 15, 1791, as one of the ten amendments that constitute the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]].

The Bill of Rights was proposed to assuage [[Anti-Federalism|Anti-Federalist]] opposition to [[History of the United States Constitution#Ratification of the Constitution|Constitutional ratification]]. Initially, the First Amendment applied only to laws enacted by the [[United States Congress|Congress]], and many of its provisions were interpreted more narrowly than they are today. Beginning with ''[[Gitlow v. New York]]'' (1925), the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] applied the First Amendment to states—a process known as [[Incorporation of the Bill of Rights#Amendment I|incorporation]]—through the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution#Due Process Clause|Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment]].

In ''[[Everson v. Board of Education]]'' (1947), the Court drew on [[Thomas Jefferson]]'s correspondence to call for "a wall of separation between church and State", though the precise boundary of this separation remains in dispute. Speech rights were expanded significantly in a series of 20th and 21st century court decisions which protected various forms of political speech, anonymous speech, [[Campaign finance|campaign financing]], [[pornography]], and [[School speech (First Amendment)|school speech]]; these rulings also defined a series of [[United States free speech exceptions|exceptions to First Amendment protections]]. The Supreme Court overturned [[English common law]] precedent to increase the burden of proof for [[defamation]] and [[libel]] suits, most notably in ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'' (1964). Commercial speech, however, is less protected by the First Amendment than political speech, and is therefore subject to greater regulation.

The Free Press Clause protects publication of information and opinions, and applies to a wide variety of media. In ''[[Near v. Minnesota]]'' (1931) and ''[[New York Times v. United States]]'' (1971), the Supreme Court ruled that the First Amendment protected against [[prior restraint]]—pre-publication censorship—in almost all cases. The Petition Clause protects the right to petition all branches and agencies of government for action. In addition to the right of assembly guaranteed by this clause, the Court has also ruled that the amendment implicitly protects [[freedom of association]].

It is a common misconception that the First Amendment prohibits anyone from limiting free speech, including private, non-governmental entities.&lt;ref name="McGregor"/&gt; It is applicable only to [[state actors]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2019/6/17/18682099/supreme-court-ruling-first-amendment-social-media-public-forum|title=First Amendment constraints don't apply to private platforms, Supreme Court affirms|last=Lecher|first=Colin|date=2019-06-17|website=The Verge|access-date=2019-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Text==

{{quote|Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof; or abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press; or the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition the Government for a redress of grievances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/first_amendment|title=First Amendment|publisher=Cornell University Law School Legal Information Institute|accessdate=May 3, 2013|archivedate=May 1, 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130501072645/http://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/first_amendment|url-status=live|df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{wide image|Amendment_1.jpg|1999px|The hand-written copy of the proposed Bill of Rights, 1789, cropped to show just the text that would later be ratified as the First Amendment}}

==Background==

{{Further|Anti-Federalism}}

The right to petition for redress of grievances was a principle included in the 1215 [[Magna Carta]], as well as the [[Bill of Rights 1689|1689 English Bill of Rights]]. In 1776, the second year of the [[American Revolutionary War]], the [[Virginia General Assembly|Virginia colonial legislature]] passed a [[Virginia Declaration of Rights|Declaration of Rights]] that included the sentence "The freedom of the press is one of the greatest bulwarks of liberty, and can never be restrained but by despotic Governments." Eight of the other twelve states made similar pledges. However, these declarations were generally considered "mere admonitions to state legislatures", rather than enforceable provisions.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=6–7}}
[[File:James Madison.jpg|thumb|upright=0.75|[[James Madison]], drafter of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]]]]

After several years of comparatively weak government under the [[Articles of Confederation]], a [[Constitutional Convention (United States)|Constitutional Convention]] in Philadelphia proposed a new constitution on September 17, 1787, featuring among other changes a stronger chief executive. [[George Mason]], a Constitutional Convention delegate and the drafter of Virginia's Declaration of Rights, proposed that the Constitution include a bill of rights listing and guaranteeing [[civil liberties]]. Other delegates—including future Bill of Rights drafter [[James Madison]]—disagreed, arguing that existing state guarantees of civil liberties were sufficient and any attempt to enumerate individual rights risked the implication that other, unnamed rights were unprotected. After a brief debate, Mason's proposal was defeated by a unanimous vote of the state delegations.{{sfn|Beeman|2009|pp=341–43}}

For the constitution to be ratified, however, nine of the thirteen states were required to approve it in state conventions. Opposition to ratification ("Anti-Federalism") was partly based on the Constitution's lack of adequate guarantees for civil liberties. Supporters of the Constitution in states where popular sentiment was against ratification (including Virginia, Massachusetts, and New York) successfully proposed that their state conventions both ratify the Constitution and call for the addition of a bill of rights. The U.S. Constitution was eventually ratified by all thirteen states. In the [[1st United States Congress]], following the state legislatures' request, James Madison proposed twenty constitutional amendments, and his proposed draft of the First Amendment read as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The civil rights of none shall be abridged on account of religious belief or worship, nor shall any national religion be established, nor shall the full and equal rights of conscience be in any manner, or on any pretext, infringed. The people shall not be deprived or abridged of their right to speak, to write, or to publish their sentiments; and the freedom of the press, as one of the great bulwarks of liberty, shall be inviolable. The people shall not be restrained from peaceably assembling and consulting for their common good; nor from applying to the Legislature by petitions, or remonstrances, for redress of their grievances.&lt;ref&gt;Haynes, Charles, et al. ''The First Amendment in Schools: A Guide from the First Amendment Center'', [https://books.google.com/books?id=tFPtl17Xx5kC&amp;pg=PA13 p. 13] (Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, 2003). Madison also proposed a similar limitation upon the states, which was completely rejected: "No State shall violate the equal rights of conscience, or the freedom of the press, or the trial by jury in criminal cases." Madison, James. [http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/documents/bill_of_rightss11.html "House of Representatives, Amendments to the Constitution"] (June 8, 1789) via ''The Founders' Constitution''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This language was greatly condensed by Congress, and passed the House and Senate with almost no recorded debate, complicating future discussion of the Amendment's intent.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=2}}{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=10}} The First Amendment, along with the rest of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]], was submitted to the states for ratification on September 25, 1789, and adopted on December 15, 1791.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/bill_of_rights.html |title=Bill of Rights |publisher=National Archives |accessdate=April 4, 2013 |archivedate=April 4, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130404123122/http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/bill_of_rights.html |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americaslibrary.gov/jb/nation/jb_nation_bofright_1.html |title=The New United States of America Adopted the Bill of Rights: December 15, 1791 |publisher=Library of Congress |accessdate=April 4, 2013 |archivedate=December 25, 2012 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121225223835/http://www.americaslibrary.gov/jb/nation/jb_nation_bofright_1.html |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious liberty clauses==
{{Main|Freedom of religion in the United States}}

The [[Establishment Clause]] and the [[Free Exercise Clause]] are the [[Freedom of religion|religious liberty]] clauses of the First Amendment.&lt;ref name="20021226ReligiousFreedomEducationProject"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Charles C. Haynes (Director Religious Freedom Education Project)|title=History of Religious Liberty in America. Written for ''Civitas: A Framework for Civic Educatio'' (1991) by the Council for the Advancement of Citizenship and the Center for Civic Education.|url=https://www.freedomforuminstitute.org/first-amendment-center/topics/freedom-of-religion/religious-liberty-in-america-overview/history-of-religious-liberty-in-america/|accessdate=May 25, 2020|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200525035716/https://www.freedomforuminstitute.org/first-amendment-center/topics/freedom-of-religion/religious-liberty-in-america-overview/history-of-religious-liberty-in-america/|archivedate=May 25, 2020|date=December 26, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his dissenting opinion of the 1961 case ''[[McGowan v. Maryland]]'' justice [[William O. Douglas]] illustrated the broad protections offered by the First Amendment's religious liberty clauses:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The First Amendment commands government to have no interest in theology or ritual; it admonishes government to be interested in allowing religious freedom to flourish -- whether the result is to produce [[Catholicity|Catholics]], [[Judaism|Jews]], or [[Protestantism|Protestants]], or to turn the people toward the path of [[Buddhism|Buddha]], or to end in a predominantly [[Muslims|Moslem]] nation, or to produce in the long run [[Atheism|atheists]] or [[Agnosticism|agnostics]]. On matters of this kind, [[Separation of church and state in the United States|government must be neutral]]. This freedom plainly includes freedom from religion, with the right to believe, speak, write, publish and advocate anti-religious programs. ''[[West Virginia State Board of Education v. Barnette|Board of Education v. Barnette]], supra'', 319 U. S. 641. Certainly the "free exercise" clause does not require that everyone embrace the theology of some church or of some faith, or observe the religious practices of any majority or minority sect. The First Amendment, by its "establishment" clause, prevents, of course, the selection by government of an "official" church. Yet the ban plainly extends farther than that. We said in ''[[Everson v. Board of Education]]'', 330 U. S. 1, 330 U. S. 16, that it would be an "establishment" of a religion if the Government financed one church or several churches. For what better way to "establish" an institution than to find the fund that will support it? The "establishment" clause protects citizens also against any law which selects any religious custom, practice, or ritual, puts the force of government behind it, and fines, imprisons, or otherwise penalizes a person for not observing it. The Government plainly could not join forces with one religious group and decree a universal and symbolic [[circumcision]]. Nor could it require all children to be [[Baptism|baptized]] or give tax exemptions only to those whose children were baptized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=McGowan v. Maryland: 366 U.S. 420 (1961)|url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/366/420/|publisher=Justia US Supreme Court Center|accessdate=May 25, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Establishment of religion===

{{Main|Establishment Clause}}

The Establishment Clause&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Religious liberty in public life: Establishment Clause overview|url=http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/rel_liberty/establishment/index.aspx|publisher=First Amendment Center|accessdate=May 28, 2020|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100905120418/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/rel_liberty/establishment/index.aspx|archivedate=September 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; acts as a double security, for its aim is as well the prevention of religious control over government as the prevention of political control over religion.&lt;ref name="20021226ReligiousFreedomEducationProject" /&gt; The First Amendment framers knew that intertwining government with religion could lead to bloodshed or oppression, because this happened too often historically. To prevent this dangerous development they set up the Establishment Clause as a line of demarcation between the functions and operations of the institutions of religion and government in society.&lt;ref name="20200524LincolnUniversityFreedomofReligion" /&gt; Under Establishment Clause the [[Federal government of the United States]] as well as the government of the several [[U.S. state|states]] are prohibited from establishing or sponsoring religion,&lt;ref name="20021226ReligiousFreedomEducationProject" /&gt; because, as observed by the Supreme Court in ''[[Walz v. Tax Commission of the City of New York]]'' 1974, the ‘establishment’ of a religion historically implied sponsorship, financial support, and active involvement of the [[Sovereign|sovereign]] in [[Religion|religious activity]].&lt;ref name="2017FirstAmendmentEncyclopedia1970Waltz"&gt;{{cite web |author1=Geoff McGovern |title=''Walz v. Tax Commission of the City of New York'' (1970) |publisher=The First Amendment Encyclopedia presented by the John Seigenthaler Chair of Excellence in First Amendment Studies |accessdate=June 14, 2020 |archivedate=June 14, 2020|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200614171632/https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/234/gillette-v-united-states|url=https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/783/walz-v-tax-commission-of-the-city-of-new-york}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Establishment Clause thus serves to ensure laws, as said by Supreme Court in its 1970 case ''[[Gillette v. United States]]'', which are “secular in purpose, evenhanded in operation, and neutral in primary impact.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=John R. Vile |title=''Gillette v. United States'' (1971) |publisher=The First Amendment Encyclopedia presented by the John Seigenthaler Chair of Excellence in First Amendment Studies |accessdate=June 14, 2020 |archivedate=June 14, 2020|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200614171632/https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/234/gillette-v-united-states|url=https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/234/gillette-v-united-states}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Constitution Center]] observed that absent some common interpretations by jurists the precise meaning of the Establishment Clause is unclear and that decisions by the United Supreme Court relating to the Establishment Clause often are by 5–4 votes.&lt;ref name="20200415NatConstCentHamiltonMcConnell"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Marci A. Hamilton|author2=Michael McConnell|title=Common Interpretation: The Establishment Clause|url=https://constitutioncenter.org/ic-2019/interpretation/amendment-i/interps/264|publisher=[[National Constitution Center]]|accessdate=May 12, 2020|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200415042843/https://constitutioncenter.org/ic-2019/interpretation/amendment-i/interps/264|archivedate=April 15, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Establishment Clause however reflects a widely held consensus that there should be no [[State religion|nationally established church]] after the [[American Revolutionary War]].&lt;ref name="20200415NatConstCentHamiltonMcConnell" /&gt; Against this background the National Constitution Center stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Virtually all jurists agree that it would violate the Establishment Clause for the government to compel attendance or financial support of a religious institution as such, for the government to interfere with a religious organization’s selection of clergy or religious doctrine; for religious organizations or figures acting in a religious capacity to exercise governmental power; or for the government to extend benefits to some religious entities and not others without adequate secular justification.&lt;ref name="20200415NatConstCentHamiltonMcConnell" /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The precise meaning of the Establishment Clause can be traced back to the beginning of [[19th century]]. [[Thomas Jefferson]] wrote with respect to the First Amendment and its restriction on the legislative branch of the federal government in an 1802 letter to the [[Baptists in the history of separation of church and state|Danbury Baptists]] (a religious minority which was concerned about the dominant position of the [[Congregationalism in the United States|Congregational church]] in [[Connecticut]] and which [[Baptists in the history of separation of church and state#American Baptists|voiced its concerns in a letter dated October 7, 1801, to the newly elected President Thomas Jefferson against a government establishment of religion]]):

&lt;blockquote&gt;Believing with you that religion is a matter which lies solely between Man &amp; his God, that he owes account to none other for his faith or his worship, that the legitimate powers of government reach actions only, and not opinions, I contemplate with sovereign reverence that act of the whole American people which declared that their legislature should "make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof", thus building [[Separation of church and state|a wall of separation between Church &amp; State]]. Adhering to this expression of the supreme will of the nation in behalf of the rights of conscience, I shall see with sincere satisfaction the progress of those sentiments which tend to restore to man all his natural rights, convinced he has no natural right in opposition to his social duties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jefferson's Letter to the Danbury Baptists – The Final Letter, as Sent on January 1, 1802|url=https://www.loc.gov/loc/lcib/9806/danpre.html|publisher=Library of Congress|accessdate=February 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''[[Reynolds v. United States]]'' (1878) the Supreme Court used these words to declare that "it may be accepted almost as an authoritative declaration of the scope and effect of the amendment thus secured. Congress was deprived of all legislative power over mere [religious] opinion, but was left free to reach [only those religious] actions which were in violation of social duties or subversive of good order." Quoting from Jefferson's [[Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom]] the court stated further in ''Reynolds'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the preamble of this act{{nbsp}}... religious freedom is defined; and after a recital 'that to suffer the civil magistrate to intrude his powers into the field of opinion, and to restrain the profession or propagation of principles on supposition of their ill tendency, is a dangerous fallacy which at once destroys all religious liberty,' it is declared 'that it is time enough for the rightful purposes of civil government for its officers to interfere [only] when [religious] principles break out into overt acts against peace and good order.' In these two sentences is found the true distinction between what properly belongs to the church and what to the State.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Originally, the First Amendment applied only to the federal government, and some states continued official state religions after ratification. [[Massachusetts]], for example, was officially Congregational until the 1830s.&lt;ref name=EB&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/208044/First-Amendment/296558/The-establishment-clause|title=First Amendment|author=Eugene Volokh|work=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=April 11, 2013|archivedate=May 12, 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130512163336/http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/208044/First-Amendment/296558/The-establishment-clause|url-status=live|df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Everson v. Board of Education]]'' (1947), the Supreme Court [[Incorporation of the Bill of Rights|incorporated]] the Establishment Clause (i.e., made it apply against the states):
&lt;blockquote&gt;The 'establishment of religion' clause of the First Amendment means at least this: Neither a state nor the Federal Government can set up a church. Neither can pass laws which aid one religion, aid all religions, or prefer one religion to another{{nbsp}}... in the words of Jefferson, the [First Amendment] clause against establishment of religion by law was intended to erect 'a wall of separation between church and State'.{{nbsp}}... That wall must be kept high and impregnable. We could not approve the slightest breach.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel L. Driesbach, ''Thomas Jefferson and the Wall of Separation between Church and State'' NYU Press 2002, unpaginated.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'' (1961), the Supreme Court ruled that the Constitution prohibits states and the federal government from [[Religious qualifications for public office in the United States|requiring any kind of religious test for public office]]. In the ''[[Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village School District v. Grumet]]'' (1994),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village School District v. Grumet|512|687|1994}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Court concluded that "government should not prefer one religion to another, or religion to irreligion."&lt;ref&gt;''Grumet'', 512 U.S. at 703.&lt;/ref&gt; In a series of cases in the first decade of the 2000s—''[[Van Orden v. Perry]]'' (2005),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Van Orden v. Perry|link=|volume=545|page=677|pin=|year=2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[McCreary County v. ACLU]]'' (2005),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=McCreary County v. ACLU|link=|volume=545|page=844|pin=|year=2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Salazar v. Buono]]'' (2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Salazar v. Buono|link=|volume=559|page=700|year=2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt;—the Court considered the issue of religious monuments on federal lands without reaching a majority reasoning on the subject.

====Separationists====

[[File:Thomas Jefferson by Rembrandt Peale, 1800.jpg|thumb|President [[Thomas Jefferson]] [[Separation of church and state in the United States|wrote]] in 1802 of "a wall of separation".&lt;ref name=everson /&gt;]]

''Everson'' used the metaphor of a wall of [[separation between church and state]], derived from the correspondence of President [[Thomas Jefferson]]. It had been long established in the decisions of the Supreme Court, beginning with ''[[Reynolds v. United States]]'' in 1879, when the Court reviewed the history of the early Republic in deciding the extent of the liberties of Mormons. Chief Justice [[Morrison Waite]], who consulted the historian [[George Bancroft]], also discussed at some length the ''Memorial and Remonstrance against Religious Assessments'' by James Madison,&lt;ref name="Memorial&amp;Remonstrance"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Madison|first1=James|title=Memorial and Remonstrance against Religious AssessmentsPapers|url=http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/documents/amendI_religions43.html|website=The Founders' Constitution|publisher=University of Chicago Press|accessdate=26 January 2017|pages=8:298–304|date=20 June 1785}}&lt;/ref&gt; who drafted the First Amendment; Madison used the metaphor of a "great barrier".&lt;ref&gt;Edward Mannino: ''Shaping America: the Supreme Court and American society'', University of South Carolina Press, 2000; p. 149; Daniel L. Driesbach, ''Thomas Jefferson and the Wall of Separation between Church and State'' NYU Press 2002, unpaginated; Chap. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Everson'', the Court adopted Jefferson's words.&lt;ref name=everson&gt;"In the words of [Thomas] Jefferson, the clause against establishment of religion by law was intended to erect "a wall of separation between church and State". from [https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/search/display.html?terms=Everson&amp;url=/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0330_0001_ZO.html the ''Everson'' decision]&lt;/ref&gt; The Court has affirmed it often, with majority, but not unanimous, support. Warren Nord, in ''Does God Make a Difference?'', characterized the general tendency of the dissents as a weaker reading of the First Amendment; the dissents tend to be "less concerned about the dangers of establishment and less concerned to protect free exercise rights, particularly of religious minorities".&lt;ref&gt;Warren A. Nord, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=qXTziqxDgEQC&amp;pg=PT226&amp;dq=establishment+clause+conservative+liberal Does God Make a Difference?]'', Oxford University Press, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning with ''Everson'', which permitted New Jersey school boards to pay for transportation to parochial schools, the Court has used various tests to determine when the wall of separation has been breached. ''Everson'' laid down the test that establishment existed when aid was given to religion, but that the transportation was justifiable because the benefit to the children was more important. In the school prayer cases of the early 1960s, (''[[Engel v. Vitale]]'' and ''[[Abington School District v. Schempp]]''), aid seemed irrelevant; the Court ruled on the basis that a legitimate action both served a secular purpose and did not ''primarily'' assist religion. In ''[[Walz v. Tax Commission]]'' (1970), the Court ruled that a legitimate action could not entangle government with religion; in ''[[Lemon v. Kurtzman]]'' (1971), these points were combined into the [[Lemon v. Kurtzman#Lemon test|Lemon test]], declaring that an action was an establishment if:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/11/us/excerpts-from-ruling-on-use-of-education-money.html|title=Excerpts From Ruling on Use of Education Money|date=June 11, 1998|work=The New York Times|accessdate=May 3, 2013|archivedate=February 9, 2014|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140209071021/http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/11/us/excerpts-from-ruling-on-use-of-education-money.html|url-status=live|df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# the statute (or practice) lacked a secular purpose;
# its principal or primary effect advanced or inhibited religion; or
# it fostered an excessive government entanglement with religion.

The ''Lemon'' test has been criticized by justices and legal scholars, but it remains the predominant means by which the Court enforces the Establishment Clause.&lt;ref name="Kritzer, H. M 2003"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kritzer|first1=H. M.|last2=Richards|first2=M. J.|year=2003|title=Jurisprudential Regimes and Supreme Court Decisionmaking: The Lemon Regime and Establishment Clause Cases|journal=Law &amp; Society Review|volume=37|pages=827–40|doi=10.1046/j.0023-9216.2003.03704005.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Agostini v. Felton]]'' (1997), the entanglement prong of the ''Lemon'' test was demoted to simply being a factor in determining the effect of the challenged statute or practice.&lt;ref name="20200524LincolnUniversityFreedomofReligion"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lincoln.edu/criminaljustice/hr/Religion.htm|title=Freedom of Religion|website=www.lincoln.edu|publisher=[[Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200524013011/http://www.lincoln.edu/criminaljustice/hr/Religion.htm|archive-date=May 24, 2020|accessdate=May 28, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Zelman v. Simmons-Harris]]'' (2002), the opinion of the Court considered secular purpose and the absence of primary effect; a concurring opinion saw both cases as having treated entanglement as part of the primary purpose test.&lt;ref name="Kritzer, H. M 2003"/&gt; Further tests, such as the [[endorsement test]] and [[coercion test]], have been developed to determine whether a government action violated the Establishment Clause.&lt;ref&gt;For the [[Endorsement test]] see ''[[Lynch v. Donnelly]]'', {{Ussc|465|668|1984|el=no}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For the [[coercion test]] see ''[[Lee v. Weisman]]'', {{Ussc|505|577|1992|el=no}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Lemon'' the Court stated that the separation of church and state could never be absolute: "Our prior holdings do not call for total separation between church and state; total separation is not possible in an absolute sense. Some relationship between government and religious organizations is inevitable", the court wrote. "Judicial caveats against entanglement must recognize that the line of separation, far from being a 'wall', is a blurred, indistinct, and variable barrier depending on all the circumstances of a particular relationship."&lt;ref&gt;''[[Lemon v. Kurtzman]]'', 403 U.S. 602 (1971)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Accommodationists====

[[Accommodationists]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Michael P. Bobic |author2=John R. Vile |title=Accommodationism and Religion |url=https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/825/accommodationism-and-religion |publisher=The First Amendment Encyclopedia presented by the John Seigenthaler Chair of Excellence in First Amendment Studies |accessdate=June 14, 2020 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200614164258/https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/825/accommodationism-and-religion |archivedate=June 14, 2020 |year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast, argue along with Justice [[William O. Douglas]] that "[w]e are a religious people whose institutions presuppose a Supreme Being".&lt;ref name="Accommodationists" /&gt; Furthermore, as observed by Chief Justice [[Warren E. Burger]] in ''Walz v. Tax Commission of the City of New York'' (1974) with respect to the separation of church and state: "No perfect or absolute separation is really possible; the very existence of the Religion Clauses is an involvement of sorts— one that seeks to mark boundaries to avoid excessive entanglement."&lt;ref name="2017FirstAmendmentEncyclopedia1970Waltz"/&gt; The group of accommodationists holds that the ''Lemon'' test should be applied selectively.&lt;ref name="Accommodationists"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I_f6Oo9H3YsC|title=Encyclopedia of the Supreme Court|author=David Shultz|publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]]|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=I_f6Oo9H3YsC&amp;pg=PA144 144]|quote=Accommodationists, on the other hand, read the establishment clause as prohibiting Congress from declaring a national religion or preferring one to another, but laws do not have to be shorn of morality and history to be declared constitutional. They apply ''Lemon'' only selectively because '[w]e are a religious people whose institutions presuppose a Supreme Being' as Justice Douglas wrote in ''Zorach v. Clauson'' {{ussc|343|306|1952}}.|accessdate=December 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, for many [[Conservatism in the United States|conservatives]], the Establishment Clause solely prevents the establishment of a [[state church]], not public acknowledgements of God nor 'developing policies that encourage general religious beliefs that do not favor a particular sect and are consistent with the secular government's goals'.&lt;ref name="Oxford"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qXTziqxDgEQC&amp;pg=PT226&amp;dq=establishment+clause+conservative+liberal&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7#v=onepage&amp;q=establishment%20clause%20conservative%20liberal|title=Does God Make a Difference?|author=Warren A. Nord|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|quote=First Amendment Politics: At the risk of oversimplifying a very complicated situation, I suggest that conservative justices tend to favor a weak reading of both the Free Exercise and Establishment clause, while liberals tend to favor strong readings. That is, conservative justices have been less concerned about the dangers of establishment and less concerned to protect free exercise rights, particularly of religious minorities. Liberals, by contrast, have been opposed to any possibility of a religious establishment and they have been relatively more concerned to protect the free exercise rights of minorities.|accessdate=December 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Devigne"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CayIq_Ud5j0C&amp;pg=PA108&amp;dq=conservatives+establishment+clause&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4#v=onepage&amp;q=conservatives%20establishment%20clause|title=Recasting Conservatism: Oakeshott, Strauss, and the Response to Postmodernism|author=Robert Devigne|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|quote=Conservatives claim that liberals misinterpret the establishment and free exercise clauses of the First Amendment. They point to the opinion written for the Supreme Court by Hugo Black in ''Everson v. Board of Education'': "The 'establishment of religion' clause of the First Amendment means at least this: neither a state nor a Federal government can set up a church. Neither can pass laws which aid one religion, aid all religions or prefer one religion over another." The establishment clause, conservatives insist, precludes the national state from promoting any religious denomination but does not prohibit state governments and local communities from developing policies that encourage general religious beliefs that do not favor a particular sect and are consistent with the secular government's goals.|accessdate=December 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Lynch v. Donnelly]] the Supreme observed that the "concept of a "wall" of separation between church and state is a useful metaphor, but is not an accurate description of the practical aspects of the relationship that in fact exists. The Constitution does not require complete separation of church and state; it affirmatively mandates accommodation, not merely tolerance, of all religions, and forbids hostility toward any."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Lynch v. Donnelly, 465 U.S. 668 (1984) |url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/465/668/ |publisher=Justia US Supreme Court Center |accessdate=May 28, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Free exercise of religion===

{{Main|Free Exercise Clause}}

Free exercise is the liberty of persons to reach, hold, practice and change beliefs freely according to the dictates of conscience. The Free Exercise Clause prohibits government interference with religious belief and, within limits, religious practice.&lt;ref name="20021226ReligiousFreedomEducationProject" /&gt; "Freedom of religion means freedom to hold an opinion or belief, but not to take action in violation of social duties or subversive to good order."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Supreme Court Cases: Reynolds v. United States, 1879|url=http://www.phschool.com/atschool/ss_web_codes/supreme_court_cases/reynolds.html|website=PHSchool.com|publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall|access-date=August 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Reynolds v. United States]]'' (1878), the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] found that while laws cannot interfere with religious belief and opinions, laws can regulate some religious practices (e.g., human sacrifices, and the now obsolete Hindu practice of [[suttee]]). The Court stated that to rule otherwise, "would be to make the professed doctrines of religious belief superior to the law of the land, and in effect permit every citizen to become a law unto himself. Government would exist only in name under such circumstances."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Reynolds v. United States – 98 U.S. 145 (1878)|url=http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/98/145/case.html|publisher=Justia US Supreme Court Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Cantwell v. Connecticut]]'' (1940), the Court held that the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution#Due Process Clause|Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment]] [[Incorporation of the Bill of Rights|applied]] the Free Exercise Clause to the states. While the right to have religious beliefs is absolute, the freedom to act on such beliefs is not absolute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cantwell v. Connecticut – 310 U.S. 296 (1940)|url=http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/310/296/case.html|publisher=Justia US Supreme Court Center|access-date=August 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Religious freedom is a universal right of all human beings and all religions, providing for the free exercise of religion or ''free exercise equality''. Due to its nature as fundamental to the American founding and to the ordering of human society, it is rightly seen as a capricious right, i.e. universal, broad, and deep—though not absolute.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=What in the World is Religious Freedom?|url=https://www.religiousfreedominstitute.org/blog/what-in-the-world-is-religious-freedom|last=Farr|first=Thomas|date=November 1, 2019|website=Religious Freedom Institute|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200514061105/https://www.religiousfreedominstitute.org/blog/what-in-the-world-is-religious-freedom|archive-date=May 14, 2020|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stephen Johnson Field|Justice Field]] put it clearly in 1890, writing in ''[[Davis v. Beason]]'', "However free the exercise of religion may be, it must be subordinate to the criminal laws of the country, passed with reference to actions regarded by general consent as properly the subjects of punitive legislation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Davis v. Beeson |vol=333 |reporter=U.S. |opinion= |pinpoint=342-343 |court=U.S. |date=1890 |url=http://cdn.loc.gov/service/ll/usrep/usrep133/usrep133333/usrep133333.pdf |access-date= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Sherbert v. Verner]]'' (1963),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Sherbert v. Verner]]'', {{ussc|374|398|1963}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court required states to meet the "[[strict scrutiny]]" standard when refusing to accommodate religiously motivated conduct. This meant the government needed to have a "compelling interest" regarding such a refusal. The case involved Adele Sherbert, who was denied unemployment benefits by [[South Carolina]] because she refused to work on Saturdays, something forbidden by her [[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventist]] faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425002298.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509081556/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425002298.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Sherbert v. Verner 374 U.S. 398 (1963)|author=Richard E. Morgan|authorlink=Richard E. Morgan|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|access-date=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Wisconsin v. Yoder]]'' (1972), the Court ruled that a law which "unduly burdens the practice of religion" without a compelling interest, even though it might be "neutral on its face", would be unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Wisconsin v. Yoder]]'', {{ussc|406|205|1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425002736.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509120133/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425002736.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Wisconsin v. Yoder 406 U.S. 205 (1972)|author=Richard E. Morgan|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|access-date=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The need for a compelling governmental interest was narrowed in ''[[Employment Division v. Smith]]'' (1990),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Employment Division v. Smith]]'', {{ussc|494|872|1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; which held no such interest was required under the Free Exercise Clause regarding a neutral law of general applicability that happens to affect a religious practice, as opposed to a law that targets a particular religious practice (which does require a compelling governmental interest).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000842.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509102055/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000842.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Employment Division, Department of Human Resources of Oregon v. Smith 484 U.S. 872 (1990)|author=John G. West, Jr.|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Church of Lukumi Babalu Aye v. City of Hialeah]]'' (1993),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Church of Lukumi Babalu Aye v. City of Hialeah]]'', {{ussc|508|520|1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court ruled Hialeah had passed an ordinance banning ritual slaughter, a practice central to the [[Santería]] religion, while providing exceptions for some practices such as the [[Kashrut|kosher slaughter]]. Since the ordinance was not "generally applicable", the Court ruled that it needed to have a compelling interest, which it failed to have, and so was declared unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000040.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509112233/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000040.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Church of Lukumi Babalu Aye, Inc. v. City of Hialeah 1993|date=January 1, 2001|work=Supreme Court Drama: Cases that Changed America|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, the Congress passed the [[Religious Freedom Restoration Act]] (RFRA), seeking to restore the compelling interest requirement applied in ''Sherbert'' and ''Yoder''. In ''[[City of Boerne v. Flores]]'' (1997),&lt;ref&gt;''[[City of Boerne v. Flores]]'', {{ussc|521|507|1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court struck down the provisions of RFRA that forced state and local governments to provide protections exceeding those required by the First Amendment, on the grounds that while the Congress could enforce the Supreme Court's interpretation of a constitutional right, the Congress could not impose its own interpretation on states and localities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-58054592|title=The McCulloch theory of the Fourteenth Amendment: City of Boerne v. Flores and the original understanding of section 5|author=Steven A. Engel|date=October 1, 1999|work=The Yale Law Journal|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the court's ruling in ''[[Gonzales v. O Centro Espirita Beneficente Uniao do Vegetal|Gonzales v. UDV]]'' (2006),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Gonzales v. O Centro Espirita Beneficente Uniao do Vegetal|Gonzales v. UDV]]'', {{ussc|546|418|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; RFRA remains applicable to federal laws and so those laws must still have a "compelling interest".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-2586600046.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509104802/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-2586600046.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Freedom of Religion|date=January 1, 2006|work=American Law Yearkbook|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Freedom of speech and of the press==

{{further&lt;!--main is ONLY for summary-style overviews of a subarticle; further is the correct template when "the section expounds a specific aspect of the topic instead of summarizing its article"--&gt;|Freedom of speech in the United States|United States free speech exceptions}}
[[File:First Amendment inscription.JPG|thumb|Inscription of the First Amendment (December 15, 1791) in front of [[Independence Hall]] in Philadelphia]]

===Wording of the clause===

The First Amendment bars Congress from "abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press". U.S. Supreme Court Justice [[John Paul Stevens]] commented about this phraseology in a 1993 journal article: "I emphasize the word 'the' in the term 'the freedom of speech' because the definite article suggests that the draftsmen intended to immunize a previously identified category or subset of speech." Stevens said that, otherwise, the clause might absurdly immunize things like false testimony under oath.&lt;ref&gt;Stevens, John Paul. "The Freedom of Speech", ''[[Yale Law Journal]]'', Vol. 102, p. 1296 (1993).&lt;/ref&gt; Like Stevens, journalist [[Anthony Lewis]] wrote: "The word 'the' can be read to mean what was understood at the time to be included in the concept of free speech."{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=40}} But what was understood at the time is not 100% clear.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=41}} In the late 1790s, the lead author of the speech and press clauses, [[James Madison]], argued against narrowing this freedom to what had existed under English [[common law]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The practice in America must be entitled to much more respect. In every state, probably, in the Union, the press has exerted a freedom in canvassing the merits and measures of public men, of every description, which has not been confined to the strict limits of the common law.&lt;ref name=Dry&gt;Dry, Murray. Civil Peace and the Quest for Truth: The First Amendment Freedoms in Political Philosophy and American Constitutionalism, [https://books.google.com/books?id=7S02AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA70 pp. 68–70] (Lexington Books 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Madison wrote this in 1799, when he was in a dispute about the constitutionality of the [[Alien and Sedition Laws]], which was legislation enacted in 1798 by President [[John Adams]]' [[Federalist Party]] to ban [[seditious libel]]. Madison believed that legislation to be unconstitutional, and his adversaries in that dispute, such as [[John Marshall]], advocated the narrow freedom of speech that had existed in the English common law.&lt;ref name=Dry /&gt;

===Speech critical of the government===

The Supreme Court declined to rule on the [[constitutionality]] of any federal law regarding the Free Speech Clause until the 20th century. For example, the Supreme Court never ruled on the [[Alien and Sedition Acts]]; three Supreme Court justices [[riding circuit]] presided over sedition trials without indicating any reservations.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=15}} The leading critics of the law, Vice President Thomas Jefferson and James Madison, argued for the Acts' unconstitutionality based on the First Amendment and other Constitutional provisions.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=16–17}} Jefferson succeeded Adams as president, in part due to the unpopularity of the latter's sedition prosecutions; he and his party quickly overturned the Acts and pardoned those imprisoned by them.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=20}} In the majority opinion in ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'' (1964),&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'', {{ussc|376|254|1964}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court noted the importance of this public debate as a precedent in First Amendment law and ruled that the Acts had been unconstitutional: "Although the Sedition Act was never tested in this Court, the attack upon its validity has carried the day in the court of history."&lt;ref&gt;''Sullivan'', at 276&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=53}}

====World War I====

During the patriotic fervor of [[World War I]] and the [[First Red Scare]], the [[Espionage Act of 1917]] imposed a maximum sentence of twenty years for anyone who caused or attempted to cause "insubordination, disloyalty, mutiny, or refusal of duty in the military or naval forces of the United States". Specifically, the Espionage Act of 1917 states that if anyone allows any enemies to enter or fly over the United States and obtain information from a place connected with the national defense, they will be punished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Espionage Act, 1917|url=http://recordsofrights.org/records/145/espionage-act|publisher=National Archives|accessdate=27 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hundreds of prosecutions followed.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=25}} In 1919, the Supreme Court heard four appeals resulting from these cases: ''[[Schenck v. United States]]'', ''[[Debs v. United States]]'', ''[[Frohwerk v. United States]]'', and ''[[Abrams v. United States]]''.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=25–27}}
[[File:Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr circa 1930-edit.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|Justice [[Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr.|Oliver Wendell Holmes]] formulated the [[clear and present danger]] test for free speech cases.]]

In the first of these cases, [[Socialist Party of America]] official [[Charles Schenck]] had been convicted under the Espionage Act for publishing leaflets urging resistance to the draft.{{sfn|Abrams|2006|pp=65–66}} Schenck appealed, arguing that the Espionage Act violated the Free Speech Clause of the First Amendment. In ''Schenck v. United States'', the Supreme Court unanimously rejected Schenck's appeal and affirmed his conviction.&lt;ref&gt;''Schenck v. United States'', {{ussc|249|47|1919}}&lt;/ref&gt; Debate continued over whether ''Schenck'' went against the right to freedom of speech protected by the First Amendment. Justice [[Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr.]], writing for the Court, explained that "the question in every case is whether the words used are used in such circumstances and are of such a nature as to create a [[clear and present danger]] that they will bring about the substantive evils that Congress has a right to prevent."&lt;ref&gt;''Schenck'', at 52&lt;/ref&gt; One week later, in ''Frohwerk v. United States'', the court again upheld an Espionage Act conviction, this time that of a journalist who had criticized U.S. involvement in foreign wars.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=23}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Geoffrey R. Stone|author2=Professor of Law Geoffrey R Stone|title=Perilous Times: Free Speech in Wartime from the Sedition Act of 1798 to the War on Terrorism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S7ScI3Ia25sC|year=2004|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0-393-05880-2|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=S7ScI3Ia25sC&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq=%22the%20question%20in%20every%20case%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20question%20in%20every%20case%22 193]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Debs v. United States'', the Court elaborated on the "clear and present danger" test established in ''Schenck''.&lt;ref&gt;''Debs v. United States'', {{ussc|249|211|1919}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 16, 1918, [[Eugene V. Debs]], a political activist, delivered a speech in [[Canton, Ohio]], in which he spoke of "most loyal comrades were paying the penalty to the working class—these being [[w:Alfred Wagenknecht|Wagenknecht]], Baker and [[C. E. Ruthenberg|Ruthenberg]], who had been convicted of aiding and abetting another in failing to register for the draft."&lt;ref&gt;''Debs'', at 213&lt;/ref&gt; Following his speech, Debs was charged and convicted under the Espionage Act. In upholding his conviction, the Court reasoned that although he had not spoken any words that posed a "clear and present danger", taken in context, the speech had a "natural tendency and a probable effect to obstruct the recruiting services".&lt;ref name="Debs216"&gt;''Debs'', at 216&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=27}} In ''Abrams v. United States'', four Russian refugees appealed their conviction for throwing leaflets from a building in New York; the leaflets argued against President [[Woodrow Wilson]]'s intervention in Russia against the [[October Revolution]]. The majority upheld their conviction, but Holmes and Justice [[Louis Brandeis]] dissented, holding that the government had demonstrated no "clear and present danger" in the four's political advocacy.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=23}}
{{Clear}}

====Extending protections====

[[File:Brandeisl.jpg|thumb|Justice [[Louis Brandeis]] wrote several dissents in the 1920s upholding free speech claims.]]

The Supreme Court denied a number of Free Speech Clause claims throughout the 1920s, including the appeal of a labor organizer, Benjamin Gitlow, who had been convicted after distributing a manifesto calling for a "revolutionary dictatorship of the proletariat".{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=108}} In ''[[Gitlow v. New York]]'' (1925), the Court upheld the conviction, but a majority also found that the First Amendment applied to state laws as well as federal laws, via the [[Due Process Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=24}}{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=34–35}} Holmes and Brandeis dissented in several more cases in this decade, however, advancing the argument that the Free Speech Clause protected a far greater range of political speech than the Court had previously acknowledged. In ''[[Whitney v. California]]'' (1927),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Whitney v. California]]'', {{ussc|274|357|1927}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which [[Communist Party USA]] organizer [[Charlotte Anita Whitney]] had been arrested for "[[criminal syndicalism]]", Brandeis wrote a dissent in which he argued for broader protections for political speech:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Those who won our independence{{nbsp}}... believed that freedom to think as you will and to speak as you think are means indispensable to the discovery and spread of political truth; that without free speech and assembly discussion would be futile; that with them, discussion affords ordinarily adequate protection against the dissemination of noxious doctrine; that the greatest menace to freedom is an inert people; that public discussion is a political duty; and that this should be a fundamental principle of the American government.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=36}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''[[Herndon v. Lowry]]'' (1937), the Court heard the case of African American Communist Party organizer [[Angelo Herndon]], who had been convicted under the Slave Insurrection Statute for advocating black rule in the southern United States. The Court reversed Herndon's conviction, holding that [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] had failed to demonstrate any "clear and present danger" in Herndon's political advocacy.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=26}}

In 1940, Congress enacted the [[Smith Act]], making it illegal to advocate "the propriety of overthrowing or destroying any government in the United States by force and violence".&lt;ref&gt;{{usc|18|2385}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statute provided law enforcement a tool to combat Communist leaders. [[Eugene Dennis]] was convicted in the [[Foley Square trial]] for attempting to organize a Communist Party.&lt;ref&gt;''Dennis'', at 497&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Dennis v. United States]]'' (1951),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Dennis v. United States]]'' {{ussc|341|494|1951}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court upheld the law.{{efn|Justice [[Tom C. Clark]] did not participate because he had ordered the prosecutions when he was [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]].}}{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=28}} Chief Justice [[Fred M. Vinson]] relied on Holmes' "clear and present danger" test as adapted by [[Learned Hand]]: "In each case [courts] must ask whether the gravity of the 'evil', discounted by its improbability, justifies such invasion of free speech as necessary to avoid the danger."&lt;ref&gt;''Dennis'', at 510&lt;/ref&gt; Clearly, Vinson suggested, clear and present danger did not intimate "that before the Government may act, it must wait until the ''putsch'' is about to be executed, the plans have been laid and the signal is awaited."&lt;ref&gt;''Dennis'', at 509&lt;/ref&gt; In a concurring opinion, Justice [[Felix Frankfurter]] proposed a "balancing test", which soon supplanted the "clear and present danger" test:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The demands of free speech in a democratic society as well as the interest in national security are better served by candid and informed weighing of the competing interests, within the confines of the judicial process.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=28}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''[[Yates v. United States]]'' (1957), the Supreme Court limited the Smith Act prosecutions to "advocacy of action" rather than "advocacy in the realm of ideas". Advocacy of abstract doctrine remained protected while speech explicitly inciting the forcible overthrow of the government was punishable under the Smith Act.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Yates v. United States]]'', {{ussc|354|298|1957}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=29}}

During the [[Vietnam War]], the Court's position on public criticism of the government changed drastically. Though the Court upheld a law prohibiting the forgery, mutilation, or destruction of [[draft card]]s in ''[[United States v. O'Brien]]'' (1968),&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. O'Brien]]'', {{ussc|391|367|1968}}&lt;/ref&gt; fearing that [[Draft-card burning|burning draft cards]] would interfere with the "smooth and efficient functioning" of the draft system,&lt;ref&gt;{{usc|50a|462}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''O'Brien'', at 379&lt;/ref&gt; the next year, the court handed down its decision in ''[[Brandenburg v. Ohio]]'' (1969),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Brandenburg v. Ohio]]'', {{ussc|395|444|1969}}&lt;/ref&gt; expressly overruling ''Whitney v. California''.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=32}} ''Brandenburg'' discarded the "clear and present danger" test introduced in ''Schenck'' and further eroded ''Dennis''.&lt;ref&gt;''Brandenburg'', at 450–1&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=124}} Now the Supreme Court referred to the right to speak openly of violent action and revolution in broad terms:
{{quote|[Our] decisions have fashioned the principle that the constitutional guarantees of free speech and free press do not allow a State to forbid or proscribe advocacy of the use of force or law violation except where such advocacy is directed to inciting or producing [[imminent lawless action]] and is likely to incite or cause such action.&lt;ref&gt;''Brandenburg'', at 447&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''[[Cohen v. California]]'' (1971),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Cohen v. California]]'', {{ussc|403|15|1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court voted reversed the conviction of a man wearing a jacket reading "Fuck the Draft" in the corridors of a [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]] courthouse. Justice [[John Marshall Harlan II]] wrote in the majority opinion that Cohen's jacket fell in the category of protected political speech despite the use of an expletive: "One man's vulgarity is another man's lyric."{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=46}}

===Political speech===
====Anonymous speech====

In ''[[Talley v. California]]'' (1960),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Talley v. California]]'', {{ussc|362|60|1960}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court struck down a Los Angeles city ordinance that made it a crime to distribute anonymous pamphlets. Justice Hugo Black wrote in the majority opinion: "There can be no doubt that such an identification requirement would tend to restrict freedom to distribute information and thereby freedom of expression.{{nbsp}}... Anonymous pamphlets, leaflets, brochures and even books have played an important role in the progress of mankind."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-90119545|title=Cybersmear: telecommunication's 200-year-old riddle|author=Chiger, Stephen J.|date=June 1, 2002|work=Communications and the Law|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[McIntyre v. Ohio Elections Commission]]'' (1995),&lt;ref&gt;''[[McIntyre v. Ohio Elections Commission]]'', {{ussc|514|334|1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court struck down an [[Ohio]] statute that made it a crime to distribute anonymous campaign literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-913993.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509101408/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-913993.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Court Hears Case on Unsigned Leaflets|author=Biskupic, Joan|authorlink=Joan Biskupic|date=October 13, 1994|work=[[The Washington Post]]|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in ''Meese v. Keene'' (1987),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Meese v. Keene]]'', {{ussc|481|465|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court upheld the [[Foreign Agents Registration Act]] of 1938, under which several Canadian films were defined as "political propaganda", requiring their sponsors to be identified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1319383.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509081314/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1319383.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Court Upholds Government Labeling Certain Foreign Films `Propaganda'|author=Kamen, Al|date=April 29, 1987|work=The Washington Post|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Campaign finance====

{{See also|Campaign finance reform in the United States}}
[[File:Mitch McConnell 2016 official photo.jpg|thumb|U.S. Senator [[Mitch McConnell]], plaintiff in ''[[McConnell v. Federal Election Commission]]'']]

In ''[[Buckley v. Valeo]]'' (1976),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Buckley v. Valeo]]'', {{ussc|424|1|1976}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court reviewed the [[Federal Election Campaign Act]] of 1971 and related laws, which restricted the monetary contributions that may be made to political campaigns and expenditure by candidates. The Court affirmed the constitutionality of limits on campaign contributions, saying they "serve[d] the basic governmental interest in safeguarding the integrity of the electoral process without directly impinging upon the rights of individual citizens and candidates to engage in political debate and discussion."&lt;ref&gt;''Buckley'', at 58&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Court overturned the spending limits, which it found imposed "substantial restraints on the quantity of political speech".&lt;ref&gt;''Buckley'', at 39&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=177–78}}

The court again scrutinized campaign finance regulation in ''[[McConnell v. Federal Election Commission]]'' (2003).&lt;ref&gt;''[[McConnell v. Federal Election Commission]]'', {{ussc|540|93|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case centered on the [[Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act]] of 2002 (BCRA), a federal law that imposed new restrictions on campaign financing. The Supreme Court upheld provisions which barred the raising of [[Campaign finance in the United States#Hard money and soft money|soft money]] by national parties and the use of soft money by private organizations to fund certain advertisements related to elections. However, the Court struck down the "choice of expenditure" rule, which required that parties could either make coordinated expenditures for all its candidates, or permit candidates to spend independently, but not both, which the Court agreed "placed an unconstitutional burden on the parties' right to make unlimited independent expenditures".&lt;ref&gt;''McConnell'', at 213&lt;/ref&gt; The Court also ruled that the provision preventing minors from making political contributions was unconstitutional, relying on ''[[Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District]]''.

In ''[[Federal Election Commission v. Wisconsin Right to Life, Inc.]]'' (2007),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Federal Election Commission v. Wisconsin Right to Life, Inc.]]'', [https://www.oyez.org/cases/2000-2009/2006/2006_06_969/ 551 U.S. 449] (2007)&lt;/ref&gt; the Court sustained an [["as applied" challenge]] to BCRA, holding that issue ads may not be banned from the months preceding a primary or general election. In ''[[Davis v. Federal Election Commission]]'' (2008),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Davis v. Federal Election Commission]]'', [https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/07-320.ZS.html 554 U.S. 724] (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court declared the "Millionaire's Amendment" provisions of the BCRA to be unconstitutional. The Court held that easing BCRA restrictions for an opponent of a self-financing candidate spending at least $350,000 of his or her own money violated the freedom of speech of the self-financing candidate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-204614062|title='Wholly foreign to the First Amendment': the demise of campaign finance's equalizing rationale in Davis v. Federal Election Commission|author=Samuel Gedge|date=June 22, 2009|work=Harvard Journal of Law and Public Policy|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Citizens United v. Federal Election Commission]]'' (2010),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Citizens United v. FEC|volume=558|page=310|pin=|year=2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that the BCRA's federal restrictions on electoral advocacy by corporations or [[Trade union|unions]] were unconstitutional for violating the Free Speech Clause of the First Amendment. The Court overruled ''[[Austin v. Michigan Chamber of Commerce]]'' (1990),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Austin v. Michigan Chamber of Commerce|494|652|1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; which had upheld a state law that prohibited corporations from using treasury funds to support or oppose candidates in elections did not violate the First or Fourteenth Amendments. The Court also overruled the portion of ''McConnell'' that upheld such restrictions under the BCRA.&lt;ref&gt;See Part III of the Opinion of the Court in ''Citizens United''&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, the ruling was considered to hold that "political spending is a form of protected speech under the First Amendment".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/citizens-united-v-federal-election-commission/ "Citizens United v. Federal Election Commission"], [[SCOTUSblog]], n.d. Retrieved November 1, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[McCutcheon v. Federal Election Commission]]'' (2014),&lt;ref&gt;''[[McCutcheon v. Federal Election Commission]]'', [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;navby=case&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=12-536 572 U.S. ___] (2014)&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that federal aggregate limits on how much a person can donate to [[candidate]]s, [[Political party|political parties]], and [[political action committee]]s, combined respectively in a two-year period known as an "election cycle", violated the Free Speech Clause of the First Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Howe|first=Amy|title=Divided Court strikes down campaign contribution caps: In Plain English|url=http://www.scotusblog.com/2014/04/divided-court-strikes-down-campaign-contribution-caps-in-plain-english/|publisher=[[SCOTUSblog]]|accessdate=April 11, 2014|date=April 2, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Flag desecration====

The divisive issue of [[flag desecration]] as a form of protest first came before the Supreme Court in ''[[Street v. New York]]'' (1969).&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Street v. New York|394|576|1969}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to hearing an erroneous report of the murder of civil rights activist [[James Meredith]], Sidney Street burned a [[Flag of the United States|48-star U.S. flag]]. Street was arrested and charged with a New York state law making it a crime "publicly [to] mutilate, deface, defile, or defy, trample upon, or cast contempt upon either by words or act [any flag of the United States]".&lt;ref&gt;''Street'', 394 U.S. at 578 (quoting the [[New York Penal Law]], §1425, subd. 16).&lt;/ref&gt; The Court, relying on ''[[Stromberg v. California]]'' (1931),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Stromberg v. California]]'', {{ussc|name=Stromberg v. California|283|359|1931}}.&lt;/ref&gt; found that because the provision of the New York law criminalizing "words" against the flag was unconstitutional, and the trial did not sufficiently demonstrate he had been convicted solely under the provisions not yet deemed unconstitutional, the conviction was unconstitutional. The Court, however, "resist[ed] the pulls to decide the constitutional issues involved in this case on a broader basis" and left the constitutionality of flag-burning unaddressed.&lt;ref&gt;''Street'', 394 U.S. at 581.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=43}}

The ambiguity with regard to flag-burning statutes was eliminated in ''[[Texas v. Johnson]]'' (1989).&lt;ref&gt;''[[Texas v. Johnson]]'', {{ussc|491|397|1989}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that case, [[Gregory Lee Johnson]] burned an American flag at a demonstration during the [[1984 Republican National Convention]] in [[Dallas]], [[Texas]]. Charged with violating a Texas law prohibiting the vandalizing of venerated objects, Johnson was convicted, sentenced to one year in prison, and fined $2,000. The Supreme Court reversed his conviction. Justice [[William J. Brennan, Jr.]] wrote in the decision that "if there is a bedrock principle underlying the First Amendment, it is that government may not prohibit the expression of an idea simply because society finds the idea offensive or disagreeable."&lt;ref&gt;''Johnson'', at 414&lt;/ref&gt; Congress then passed a federal law barring flag burning, but the Supreme Court struck it down as well in ''[[United States v. Eichman]]'' (1990).&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Eichman]]'', {{ussc|496|310|1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jasper|1999|pp=43–44}} A [[Flag Desecration Amendment]] to the U.S. Constitution has been proposed repeatedly in Congress since 1989, and in 2006 failed to pass the Senate by a single vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/27/washington/27cnd-flag.html?_r=1&amp; |title=Amendment on Flag Burning Fails by One Vote in the Senate |author1=Hulse, Carl |author2=Holusha, John |date=June 27, 2006 |work=The New York Times |accessdate=April 4, 2013 |archivedate=March 31, 2019 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190331110217/https://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/27/washington/27cnd-flag.html?_r=1&amp; |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Falsifying military awards====

While the unauthorized wear or sale of the [[Medal of Honor]] has been a punishable offense under federal law since the early twentieth century,&lt;ref&gt;See [https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/704 Notes to 18 U.S.C. § 704], citing 42 Stat. 1286. Retrieved on June 30, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/BILLS-103hr3355enr/pdf/BILLS-103hr3355enr.pdf Pub.L. 103-322, The Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994, § 320109] (p. 318 of the PDF version). Retrieved on June 30, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Stolen Valor Act]] criminalized the act of not only wearing, but also verbally claiming entitlement to [[Awards and decorations of the United States military|military awards]] a person did not in fact earn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=John|last=Crewdson|authorlink=John M. Crewdson|date=May 27, 2008|title=Fake claims of war heroics a federal offense|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/nationworld/chi-valormay28,0,4768252.story|newspaper=Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[United States v. Alvarez]]'' (2012), the Supreme Court struck down the Act, ruling that the First Amendment bars the government from punishing people for making false claims regarding military service or honors where the false claim was not "made to effect a fraud or secure moneys or other valuable considerations". The Supreme Court could not agree on a single rationale for its decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=United States v. Alvarez|link=United States v. Alvarez|volume=567|page=709|pin=|year=2012}}. {{usgovpd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Compelled speech===

{{main|Compelled speech}}

The Supreme Court has determined that the First Amendment also protects citizens from being compelled to say or pay for certain speech.

In ''[[West Virginia State Board of Education v. Barnette]]'' (1943), the Court ruled that school children could not be punished for refusing either to say the [[Pledge of Allegiance (United States)|pledge of allegiance]] or salute the [[Flag of the United States|American flag]].

In ''[[National Institute of Family and Life Advocates v. Becerra]]'' (2018), the Court ruled that a California law requiring [[crisis pregnancy center]]s to post notices informing patients they can obtain free or low-cost abortions and include the number of the state agency that can connect the women with abortion providers violated those centers' right to free speech.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scotusblog.com/2018/06/opinion-analysis-divided-court-rules-for-anti-abortion-pregnancy-centers-in-challenge-to-california-law/#more-272072|title=Opinion analysis: Divided court rules for anti-abortion pregnancy centers in challenge to California law|author=Amy Howe|publisher=[[SCOTUSblog]]|date=June 26, 2018|accessdate=June 27, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Janus v. AFSCME]]'' (2018), the Court ruled that requiring a [[public sector]] employee to pay dues to a union to which he is not a member violated the First Amendment. According to the Court, "the First Amendment does not permit the government to compel a person to pay for another party's speech just because the government thinks that the speech furthers the interests of the person who does not want to pay."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scotusblog.com/2018/06/opinion-analysis-court-strikes-down-public-sector-union-fees/|title=Opinion analysis: Court strikes down public-sector union fees|author=Amy Howe|publisher=[[SCOTUSblog]]|date=June 27, 2018|accessdate=June 27, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Commercial speech===

{{main|Commercial speech}}

Commercial speech is speech done on behalf of a company or individual for the purpose of making a profit. Unlike political speech, the Supreme Court does not afford commercial speech full protection under the First Amendment. To effectively distinguish commercial speech from other types of speech for purposes of litigation, the Court uses a list of four indicia:&lt;ref&gt;''[[Bolger v. Youngs Drug Products]]'', {{ussc|463|60|1983}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# The contents do "no more than propose a commercial transaction".
# The contents may be characterized as advertisements.
# The contents reference a specific product.
# The disseminator is economically motivated to distribute the speech.

Alone, each indicium does not compel the conclusion that an instance of speech is commercial; however, "[t]he combination of ''all'' these characteristics{{nbsp}}... provides strong support for{{nbsp}}... the conclusion that the [speech is] properly characterized as commercial speech."&lt;ref&gt;''Bolger'', 463 U.S. at 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Valentine v. Chrestensen]]'' (1942),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Valentine v. Chrestensen|316|52|1942}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court upheld a New York City ordinance forbidding the "distribution in the streets of commercial and business advertising matter," ruling the First Amendment protection of free speech did not include commercial speech.&lt;ref&gt;''Valentine'', 316 U.S. at 53-54.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Virginia State Pharmacy Board v. Virginia Citizens Consumer Council]]'' (1976),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Virginia State Pharmacy Board v. Virginia Citizens Consumer Council|425|748|1976}}. {{usgovpd}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court overturned ''Valentine'' and ruled that commercial speech was entitled to First Amendment protection:
{{quote|What is at issue is whether a State may completely suppress the dissemination of concededly truthful information about entirely lawful activity, fearful of that information's effect upon its disseminators and its recipients.{{nbsp}}... [W]e conclude that the answer to this one is in the negative.&lt;ref&gt;''Virginia State Pharmacy Board'', 425 U.S. at 773.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''Ohralik v. Ohio State Bar Association'' (1978),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Ohralik v. Ohio State Bar Association|436|447|1978}}. {{usgovpd}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that commercial speech was not protected by the First Amendment as much as other types of speech:
{{quote|We have not discarded the 'common-sense' distinction between speech proposing a commercial transaction, which occurs in an area traditionally subject to government regulation, and other varieties of speech. To require a parity of constitutional protection for commercial and noncommercial speech alike could invite a dilution, simply by a leveling process, of the force of the [First] Amendment's guarantee with respect to the latter kind of speech.&lt;ref&gt;''Ohralik'', 436 U.S. at 455.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''[[Central Hudson Gas &amp; Electric Corp. v. Public Service Commission]]'' (1980),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Central Hudson Gas &amp; Electric Corp. v. Public Service Commission]]'', {{ussc|447|557|1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court clarified what analysis was required before the government could justify regulating commercial speech:
# Is the expression protected by the First Amendment? Lawful? Misleading? Fraud?
# Is the asserted government interest substantial?
# Does the regulation directly advance the governmental interest asserted?
# Is the regulation more extensive than is necessary to serve that interest?

Six years later, the U.S. Supreme Court, applying the ''Central Hudson'' standards in ''[[Posadas de Puerto Rico Associates v. Tourism Company of Puerto Rico]]'' (1986),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Posadas de Puerto Rico Associates v. Tourism Company of Puerto Rico]]'', {{ussc|478|328|1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; affirmed the [[Supreme Court of Puerto Rico]]'s conclusion that [[Puerto Rico]]'s ''Games of Chance Act of 1948'', including the regulations thereunder, was not facially unconstitutional. The lax interpretation of ''Central Hudson'' adopted by ''Posadas'' was soon restricted under ''[[44 Liquormart, Inc. v. Rhode Island]]'' (1996),&lt;ref&gt;''[[44 Liquormart, Inc. v. Rhode Island]]'', {{ussc|517|484|1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the Court invalidated a [[Rhode Island]] law prohibiting the publication of liquor prices.

===School speech===

{{main|School speech}}

In ''Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District'' (1969),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District]]'', {{ussc|393|503|1969}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court extended free speech rights to students in school. The case involved several students who were punished for wearing black armbands to protest the Vietnam War. The Court ruled that the school could not restrict symbolic speech that did not "materially and substantially" interrupt school activities.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=61}} Justice [[Abe Fortas]] wrote:
{{quote|First Amendment rights, applied in light of the special characteristics of the school environment, are available to teachers and students. It can hardly be argued that either students or teachers shed their constitutional rights to freedom of speech or expression at the schoolhouse gate.{{nbsp}}... [S]chools may not be enclaves of totalitarianism. School officials do not possess absolute authority over their students. Students{{nbsp}}... are possessed of fundamental rights which the State must respect, just as they themselves must respect their obligations to the State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0393_0503_ZO.html|title=''Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District''|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''[[Healy v. James]]'' (1972), the Court ruled that [[Central Connecticut State University|Central Connecticut State College]]'s refusal to recognize a campus chapter of [[Students for a Democratic Society]] was unconstitutional, reaffirming ''Tinker''.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=62}}

However, since 1969 the Court has also placed several limitations on ''Tinker'' interpretations. In ''[[Bethel School District v. Fraser]]'' (1986),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Bethel School District v. Fraser]]'', {{ussc|478|675|1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that a student could be punished for his sexual-innuendo-laced speech before a school assembly and, in ''[[Hazelwood v. Kuhlmeier]]'' (1988),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Hazelwood v. Kuhlmeier]]'', {{ussc|484|260|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court found that schools need not tolerate student speech that is inconsistent with their basic educational mission.{{sfn|Jasper|1999|pp=62–63}} In ''[[Morse v. Frederick]]'' (2007),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Morse v. Frederick]]'', {{ussc|551|393|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that schools could, consistent with the First Amendment, restrict student speech at school-sponsored events, even events away from school grounds, if students promote "illegal drug use".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P3-1753810351.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509090535/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P3-1753810351.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Uncertain Rights: Student Speech and Conflicting Interpretations of Morse v. Frederick|author1=Kozlowski, Dan V.|author2=Bullard, Melissa E.|author3=Deets, Kristen|date=April 1, 2009|work=Journalism and Mass Communication Quarterly|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the [[University of Chicago]] released the "[[Chicago principles|Chicago Statement]]", a free speech policy statement designed to combat censorship on campus. This statement was later adopted by a number of top-ranked universities including [[Princeton University]], [[Washington University in St. Louis]], [[Johns Hopkins University]], and [[Columbia University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thefire.org/get-involved/student-network/take-action/adopting-the-chicago-statement/|title=Adopting the Chicago Statement|website=FIRE|language=en-US|access-date=2019-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/tomlindsay/2018/02/28/35-universities-adopt-the-chicago-statement-on-free-speech-1590-to-go/|title=35 Universities Adopt 'The Chicago Statement' On Free Speech--1,606 To Go|last=Lindsay|first=Tom|website=Forbes|language=en|access-date=2019-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internet access===

In ''[[Packingham v. North Carolina]]'' (2017), the Supreme Court held that a [[North Carolina]] law prohibiting registered [[sex offenders]] from accessing various websites impermissibly restricted lawful speech in violation of the First Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2017/6/19/15830286/supreme-court-north-carolina-sex-offenders-social-media|title=Supreme Court strikes down North Carolina law banning sex offenders from social media|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Court held that "a fundamental principle of the First Amendment is that all persons have access to places where they can speak and listen, and then, after reflection, speak and listen once more."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.oyez.org/cases/2016/15-1194|title=Packingham v. North Carolina |website= www.oyez.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/16pdf/15-1194_08l1.pdf |title=Packingham v. North Carolina |author=&lt;!--Not stated--&gt; |date= |website=[[Supremecourt.gov]] |access-date=25 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Obscenity===

{{further&lt;!--main is ONLY for summary-style overviews of a subarticle; further is the correct template when "the section expounds a specific aspect of the topic instead of summarizing its article"--&gt;|United States obscenity law}}
[[File:US Supreme Court Justice Potter Stewart - 1976 official portrait.jpg|thumb|Justice [[Potter Stewart]] wrote that while he could not precisely define pornography, he "[knew] it when [he saw] it".]]

According to the U.S. Supreme Court, the First Amendment's protection of free speech does not apply to obscene speech. Therefore, both the federal government and the states have tried to prohibit or otherwise restrict obscene speech, in particular the form that is {{as of|2019|alt=now}} called pornography. {{as of|2019}}, pornography, except for child pornography, is in practice free of governmental restrictions in the United States, though pornography about "extreme" sexual practices is occasionally prosecuted. The change in the twentieth century, from total prohibition in 1900 to near-total tolerance in 2000, reflects a series of court cases involving the definition of obscenity. The U.S. Supreme Court has found that most pornography is not obscene, a result of changing definitions of both obscenity and pornography.&lt;ref name=EB /&gt; The legal tolerance also reflects changed social attitudes: one reason there are so few prosecutions for pornography is that [[jury nullification in the United States|juries will not convict]].&lt;ref&gt;Jury nullification:&lt;br /&gt;
* {{cite web|url=https://reason.com/2018/11/06/judge-advocates-jury-nullification/|title=Federal Judge Advocates Jury Nullification After Being Shocked by Overzealous Child Pornography Prosecution|date=June 11, 2016|publisher=reason.com}}
* {{cite web|url=https://sentencing.typepad.com/sentencing_law_and_policy/2018/11/mandatory-minimum-drives-us-district-judge-to-countenance-arguments-for-jury-nullification-in-federa.html|title=Mandatory minimum drives US District Judge to countenance arguments for jury nullification in federal child porn case|date=November 6, 2018|publisher=entencing.typepad.com}}
* {{cite web|url=https://www.law.com/newyorklawjournal/2019/05/17/nullifying-nullification-will-the-second-circuit-prohibit-a-defendants-jury-nullification-defense/?slreturn=20190507043909|title=Nullifying Nullification: Will the Second Circuit Prohibit a Defendant's Jury Nullification Defense?|date=May 17, 2019|publisher=ww.law.com}}
* {{cite web|url=https://www.cato.org/blog/defending-courts-discretion-allow-arguments-conscientious-acquittal|title=Defending a Court's Discretion To Allow Arguments for Conscientious Acquittal|date=December 20, 2018|publisher=www.cato.org}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Rosen v. United States]]'' (1896), the Supreme Court adopted the same obscenity standard as had been articulated in a famous British case, ''Regina v. Hicklin'' (1868).&lt;ref&gt;''Regina v. Hicklin'', [1868] L. R. 3 Q. B. 360&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Hicklin test|''Hicklin'' test]] defined material as obscene if it tended "to deprave or corrupt those whose minds are open to such immoral influences, and into whose hands a publication of this sort may fall".&lt;ref&gt;''Rosen'', at 43&lt;/ref&gt; In the early twentieth century, literary works including ''[[An American Tragedy]]'' ([[Theodore Dreiser]], 1925) and ''[[Lady Chatterley's Lover]]'' ([[D.H. Lawrence]], 1928) were banned for obscenity. In the [[United States district court|federal district court]] case ''[[United States v. One Book Called Ulysses]]'' (1933), Judge John M. Woolsey established a new standard to evaluate [[James Joyce]]'s novel ''[[Ulysses (novel)|Ulysses]]'' (1922), stating that works must be considered in their entirety, rather than declared obscene on the basis of an individual part of the work.&lt;ref name=obscenity&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/obscenity |title=Obscenity |date=August 19, 2010 |publisher=Legal Information Institute, Cornell University Law School |accessdate=April 10, 2013 |archivedate=April 2, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130402163508/http://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/obscenity |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Supreme Court ruled in ''[[Roth v. United States]]'' (1957)&lt;ref&gt;''[[Roth v. United States]]'', {{ussc|354|476|1957}}&lt;/ref&gt; that the First Amendment did not protect obscenity.&lt;ref name=obscenity /&gt; It also ruled that the ''Hicklin'' test was inappropriate; instead, the ''Roth'' test for obscenity was "whether to the average person, applying contemporary community standards, the dominant theme of the material, taken as a whole, appeals to the prurient interest".&lt;ref&gt;''Roth'', at 489&lt;/ref&gt; This definition proved hard to apply, however, and in the following decade, members of the Court often reviewed films individually in a court building screening room to determine if they should be considered obscene.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=135–36}} Justice [[Potter Stewart]], in ''[[Jacobellis v. Ohio]]'' (1964),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Jacobellis v. Ohio]]'', {{ussc|378|184|1964}}&lt;/ref&gt; famously said that, although he could not precisely define pornography, "[[I know it when I see it]]".&lt;ref&gt;''Jacobellis'', at 197&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Peter Lattman |title=The Origins of Justice Stewart's 'I Know It When I See It' |date=September 27, 2007 |newspaper=[[Wall Street Journal]] |publisher=LawBlog at The Wall Street Journal Online |url=https://blogs.wsj.com/law/2007/09/27/the-origins-of-justice-stewarts-i-know-it-when-i-see-it/ |accessdate=December 31, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Roth'' test was expanded when the Court decided ''[[Miller v. California]]'' (1973).&lt;ref&gt;''[[Miller v. California]]'', {{ussc|413|15|1973}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under the [[Miller test|''Miller'' test]], a work is obscene if:
{{quote|(a){{nbsp}}... 'the average person, applying contemporary community standards' would find the work, as a whole, appeals to the prurient interest{{nbsp}}... (b){{nbsp}}... the work depicts or describes, in a patently offensive way, sexual conduct specifically defined by the applicable state law, and (c){{nbsp}}... the work, taken as a whole, lacks serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value.&lt;ref&gt;''Miller'', at 39&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Note that "community" standards—not national standards—are applied whether the material appeals to the prurient interest, leaving the question of obscenity to local authorities.&lt;ref name=obscenity /&gt; [[Child pornography]] is not subject to the ''Miller'' test, as the Supreme Court decided in ''[[New York v. Ferber]]'' (1982) and ''[[Osborne v. Ohio]]'' (1990),&lt;ref&gt;''[[New York v. Ferber]]'', {{ussc|458|747|1982}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Osborne v. Ohio]]'', {{ussc|495|103|1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; ruling that the government's interest in protecting children from abuse was paramount.&lt;ref&gt;''Ferber'', at 761&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jasper|1999|p=51}}

Personal possession of obscene material in the home may not be prohibited by law. In ''[[Stanley v. Georgia]]'' (1969),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Stanley v. Georgia]]'', {{ussc|394|557|1969}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that "[i]f the First Amendment means anything, it means that a State has no business telling a man, sitting in his own house, what books he may read or what films he may watch."&lt;ref&gt;''Stanley'', at 565&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is constitutionally permissible for the government to prevent the mailing or sale of obscene items, though they may be viewed only in private. ''[[Ashcroft v. Free Speech Coalition]]'' (2002)&lt;ref&gt;''[[Ashcroft v. Free Speech Coalition]]'', {{ussc|535|234|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; further upheld these rights by invalidating the [[Child Pornography Prevention Act of 1996]], holding that, because the act "[p]rohibit[ed] child pornography that does not depict an actual child" it was overly broad and unconstitutional under the First Amendment&lt;ref&gt;''Free Speech Coalition'', at 240&lt;/ref&gt; and:
{{quote|First Amendment freedoms are most in danger when the government seeks to control thought or to justify its laws for that impermissible end. The right to think is the beginning of freedom, and speech must be protected from the government because speech is the beginning of thought.&lt;ref&gt;''Free Speech Coalition'', at 253&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''[[United States v. Williams (2008)|United States v. Williams]]'' (2008),&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Williams (2008)|United States v. Williams]]'', 553 U.S. 285 (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; the Court upheld the [[PROTECT Act of 2003]], ruling that prohibiting offers to provide and requests to obtain child pornography did not violate the First Amendment, even if a person charged under the Act did not possess child pornography.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/06-694.ZO.html Opinion of the Court in ''Williams'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-202024472|title=Protecting children speech that crosses the line|author=Craig King|date=June 1, 2009|work=The FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Memoirs of convicted criminals===

In some states, there are [[Son of Sam law]]s prohibiting convicted criminals from publishing memoirs for profit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-96711249.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924182836/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-96711249.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=September 24, 2015|title=Interview: Julie Hilden discusses laws and ethics surrounding the intellectual property rights of prisoners|author=Madeleine Brand| authorlink=Madeleine Brand|date=July 22, 2004|publisher=NPR {{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; These laws were a response to offers to [[David Berkowitz]] to write memoirs about the murders he committed. The Supreme Court struck down a law of this type in New York as a violation of the First Amendment in the case ''[[Simon &amp; Schuster v. Crime Victims Board]]'' (1991).&lt;ref&gt;''[[Simon &amp; Schuster v. Crime Victims Board]]'', {{ussc|502|105|1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; That statute did not prohibit publication of a memoir by a convicted criminal. Instead, it provided that all profits from the book were to be put in escrow for a time. The interest from the [[escrow]] account was used to fund the New York State Crime Victims Board—an organization that pays the medical and related bills of victims of crime. Similar laws in other states remain unchallenged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000057.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509105616/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000057.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Simon &amp;amp; Schuster v. Members of the New York State Crime Victims Board 1991|year=2001|work=Supreme Court Drama: Cases That Changed America|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Defamation===

{{further&lt;!--main is ONLY for summary-style overviews of a subarticle; further is the correct template when "the section expounds a specific aspect of the topic instead of summarizing its article"--&gt;|United States defamation law}}
[[File:US Supreme Court Justice William Brennan - 1976 official portrait.jpg|thumb|Justice William J. Brennan, Jr. wrote the landmark decision ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'', requiring the demonstration of "actual malice" in libel suits against public figures.]]

[[United States tort law|American tort liability]] for [[Defamation|defamatory]] speech or publications traces its origins to [[English law#Common law|English common law]]. For the first two hundred years of American jurisprudence, the basic substance of defamation law continued to resemble that existing in England at the time of the Revolution. An 1898 American legal textbook on defamation provides definitions of libel and slander nearly identical to those given by [[William Blackstone]] and [[Edward Coke]]. An action of slander required the following:{{sfn|Newell|1898|pp=37–41}}
# Actionable words, such as those imputing the injured party: is guilty of some offense, suffers from a contagious disease or psychological disorder, is unfit for public office because of moral failings or an inability to discharge his or her duties, or lacks integrity in profession, trade or business;
# That the charge must be false;
# That the charge must be articulated to a third person, verbally or in writing;
# That the words are not subject to legal protection, such as those uttered in Congress; and
# That the charge must be motivated by malice.

An action of libel required the same five general points as slander, except that it specifically involved the publication of defamatory statements.{{sfn|Newell|1898|pp=33–37}} For certain criminal charges of libel, such as seditious libel, the truth or falsity of the statements was immaterial, as such laws were intended to maintain public support of the government and true statements could damage this support even more than false ones.{{sfn|Nelson|1994|p=93}} Instead, libel placed specific emphasis on the result of the publication. Libelous publications tended to "degrade and injure another person" or "bring him into contempt, hatred or ridicule".{{sfn|Newell|1898|pp=33–37}}

Concerns that defamation under common law might be incompatible with the new republican form of government caused early American courts to struggle between [[William Blackstone]]'s argument that the punishment of "dangerous or offensive writings{{nbsp}}... [was] necessary for the preservation of peace and good order, of government and religion, the only solid foundations of civil liberty" and the argument that the need for a free press guaranteed by the Constitution outweighed the fear of what might be written.{{sfn|Nelson|1994|p=93}} Consequently, very few changes were made in the first two centuries after the ratification of the First Amendment.

The Supreme Court's ruling in ''New York Times Co. v. Sullivan'' (1964)&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; fundamentally changed American defamation law. The case redefined the type of "malice" needed to sustain a libel case. Common law malice consisted of "ill-will" or "wickedness". Now, a public officials seeking to sustain a civil action against a tortfeasor needed to prove by "clear and convincing evidence" that there was actual malice. The case involved an advertisement published in ''[[The New York Times]]'' indicating that officials in [[Montgomery, Alabama]] had acted violently in suppressing the protests of African-Americans during the [[civil rights movement]]. The Montgomery Police Commissioner, L. B. Sullivan, sued the ''Times'' for libel, saying the advertisement damaged his reputation. The Supreme Court unanimously reversed the $500,000 judgment against the ''Times''. Justice Brennan suggested that public officials may sue for libel only if the statements in question were published with "[[actual malice]]"—"knowledge that it was false or with reckless disregard of whether it was false or not".&lt;ref&gt;''Sullivan'' at 280&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jasper|1999|pp=9–10}} In sum, the court held that "the First Amendment protects the publication of all statements, even false ones, about the conduct of public officials except when statements are made with actual malice (with knowledge that they are false or in reckless disregard of their truth or falsity)."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=New York Times v. Sullivan|url=https://www.oyez.org/cases/1960-1969/1963/1963_39|work=The Oyez Project at IIT Chicago-Kent College of Law|publisher=The Oyez Project at IIT Chicago-Kent College of Law|accessdate=11 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While actual malice standard applies to public officials and public figures,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Westmoreland v. CBS]]'', {{West|SUPP|596||363|S.D. N.Y.|1984|}}&lt;/ref&gt; in ''[[Philadelphia Newspapers v. Hepps]]'' (1988),&lt;ref&gt;''Philadelphia Newspapers v. Hepps'', {{ussc|475|767|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court found that, with regard to private individuals, the First Amendment does "not necessarily force any change in at least some features of the common-law landscape".&lt;ref&gt;''Hepps'' at 775&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Dun &amp; Bradstreet, Inc. v. Greenmoss Builders, Inc.]]'' (1985)&lt;ref&gt;''[[Dun &amp; Bradstreet, Inc. v. Greenmoss Builders, Inc.]]'' {{ussc|472|749|1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that "actual malice" need not be shown in cases involving private individuals, holding that "[i]n light of the reduced constitutional value of speech involving no matters of public concern{{nbsp}}... the state interest adequately supports awards of presumed and punitive damages—even absent a showing of 'actual malice'."&lt;ref&gt;''Greenmoss'' at 761&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000783.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509094715/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000783.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=May 9, 2013 |title=Dun &amp;amp; Bradstreet, Inc. v. Greenmoss Builders, Inc. 472 U.S. 749 (1985) |date=January 1, 2000 |work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution |publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.]]'' (1974), the Court ruled that a private individual had to prove malice only to be awarded punitive damages, not actual damages.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.]]'' {{ussc|418|323|1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001077.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509080602/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001077.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.|author=Leonard W. Levy|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Hustler Magazine v. Falwell]]'' (1988),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Hustler Magazine v. Falwell]]'', {{ussc|485|46|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court extended the "actual malice" standard to [[intentional infliction of emotional distress]] in a ruling which protected [[parody]], in this case a fake advertisement in ''[[Hustler]]'' suggesting that evangelist [[Jerry Falwell]]'s first sexual experience had been with his mother in an outhouse. Since Falwell was a public figure, the Court ruled that "importance of the free flow of ideas and opinions on matters of public interest and concern" was the paramount concern, and reversed the judgement Falwell had won against ''Hustler'' for emotional distress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000024.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509092835/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000024.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Hustler Magazine v. Falwell 1988|date=January 1, 2001|work=Supreme Court Drama: Cases that Changed America|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Milkovich v. Lorain Journal Co.]]'' (1990),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Milkovich v. Lorain Journal Co.]]'', {{ussc|497|1|1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that the First Amendment offers no wholesale exception to defamation law for statements labeled "opinion", but instead that a statement must be provably false (falsifiable) before it can be the subject of a libel suit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001663.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509082207/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001663.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Milkovich v. Lorain Journal Co. 497 U.S. 1 (1990)|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, it has been argued that ''Milkovich'' and other cases effectively provide for an [[opinion privilege]].&lt;ref&gt;Esward M. Sussman, ''[http://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3170&amp;context=dlj Milkovich revisited: "Saving" the Opinion Privilege''], Duke Law Journal, pp. 415–48&lt;/ref&gt; In consequence a significant number of states have enacted state opinion privilege laws.{{Citation needed|date=June 2015}}

===Private action===

Despite the common misconception that the First Amendment prohibits anyone from limiting free speech,&lt;ref name="McGregor"&gt;{{cite news|last1=McGregor|first1=Jena|title=The Google memo is a reminder that we generally don't have free speech at work|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/on-leadership/wp/2017/08/08/the-google-memo-is-a-reminder-that-we-generally-dont-have-free-speech-at-work/|accessdate=March 1, 2019|work=The Washington Post|date=August 8, 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; the text of the amendment prohibits only the federal government, the states and local governments from doing so.&lt;ref name="Willingham"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Willingham|first1=AJ|title=The First Amendment doesn't guarantee you the rights you think it does|url=https://www.cnn.com/2017/04/27/politics/first-amendment-explainer-trnd/index.html|accessdate=March 1, 2019|work=CNN|date=September 6, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

State constitutions provide free speech protections similar to those of the U.S. Constitution. In a few states, such as California, a state constitution has been interpreted as providing more comprehensive protections than the First Amendment. The Supreme Court has permitted states to extend such enhanced protections, most notably in ''[[Pruneyard Shopping Center v. Robins]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Pruneyard Shopping Center v. Robins]]'', {{ussc|447|74|1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that case, the Court unanimously ruled that while the First Amendment may allow private property owners to prohibit trespass by political speakers and petition-gatherers, California was permitted to restrict property owners whose property is equivalent to a traditional public forum (often shopping malls and grocery stores) from enforcing their private property rights to exclude such individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-196305310|title=Returning to the PruneYard: the unconstitutionality of state-sanctioned trespass in the name of speech|author=Gregory C. Sisk|date=January 1, 2009|work=Harvard Journal of Law and Public Property|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Court did maintain that shopping centers could impose "reasonable restrictions on expressive activity".&lt;ref&gt;''Pruneyard'', at 94&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, [[New Jersey]], [[Colorado]], Massachusetts and Puerto Rico courts have adopted the doctrine;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mulligan|first=Josh|year=2004|title=Finding A Forum in the Simulated City: Mega Malls, Gated Towns, and the Promise of ''Pruneyard''|journal=Cornell Journal of Law and Public Policy|volume=13|pages=533, 557|issn=1069-0565}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Empresas Puertorriqueñas de Desarrollo, Inc. v. Hermandad Independiente de Empleados Telefónicos'', [http://www.ramajudicial.pr/Supremo2/2000tspr71.htm 150 D.P.R. 924 (2000).]&lt;/ref&gt; California's courts have repeatedly reaffirmed it.&lt;ref&gt;''Golden Gateway Ctr. v. Golden Gateway Tenants Ass'n'', [http://online.ceb.com/calcases/C4/26C4t1013.htm 26 Cal. 4th 1013] (2001); ''Costco Companies, Inc. v. Gallant'', [http://online.ceb.com/calcases/CA4/96CA4t740.htm 96 Cal. App. 4th 740] (2002); ''Fashion Valley Mall, LLC, v. National Labor Relations Board'', [http://online.ceb.com/calcases/C4/42C4t850.htm 42 Cal. 4th 850] (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Freedom of the press===

{{further&lt;!--main is ONLY for summary-style overviews of a subarticle; further is the correct template when "the section expounds a specific aspect of the topic instead of summarizing its article"--&gt;|Freedom of the press in the United States}}

The free speech and free press clauses have been interpreted as providing the same protection to speakers as to writers, except for wireless broadcasting which has been given less constitutional protection.&lt;ref&gt;Volokh, Eugene. ''The Heritage Guide to the Constitution'', [http://www.heritage.org/constitution/#!/amendments/1/essays/140/freedom-of-speech-and-of-the-press p. 409] (Forte and Spalding, eds., The Heritage Foundation 2014).&lt;/ref&gt; The Free Press Clause protects the right of individuals to express themselves through publication and dissemination of information, ideas and opinions without interference, constraint or prosecution by the government.&lt;ref name="CornellFirstAmendmentOverview" /&gt;&lt;ref name="McConnellNov2013"&gt;{{cite journal|last=McConnell|first=Michael W.|title=Reconsidering Citizens United as a Press Clause Case|journal=The Yale Law Journal|date=November 2013|volume=123 2013-2014|issue= 2 November 2013 Pages 266–529|url=http://www.yalelawjournal.org/essay/reconsidering-citizens-united-as-a-press-clause-case#_ftnref108|accessdate=19 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This right was described in ''[[Branzburg v. Hayes]]'' as "a fundamental personal right" that is not confined to newspapers and periodicals.&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|408|665|1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Lovell v. City of Griffin]]'' (1938),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Lovell v. City of Griffin]]'', {{ussc|303|444|1938}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chief Justice [[Charles Evans Hughes]] defined "press" as "every sort of publication which affords a vehicle of information and opinion".&lt;ref&gt;''Lovell'', at 452&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brown v. Entertainment Merchants Association#Opinion|This right has been extended to media]] including newspapers, books, plays, movies, and video games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/28/us/28scotus.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=1&amp; |title=Justices Reject Ban on Violent Video Games for Children |author=Adam Liptak |authorlink=Adam Liptak |date=June 27, 2011 |work=The New York Times |accessdate=April 19, 2013 |archivedate=March 31, 2019 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190331114358/https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/28/us/28scotus.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=1&amp; |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; While it is an open question whether people who [[blog]] or use [[social media]] are journalists entitled to protection by [[Shield laws in the United States|media shield laws]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mataconis|first=Doug|title=Bloggers, Media Shield Laws, And The First Amendment|url=http://www.outsidethebeltway.com/bloggers-media-shield-laws-and-the-first-amendment/|publisher=Outside The Beltway|accessdate=August 9, 2013|date=May 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; they are protected equally by the Free Speech Clause and the Free Press Clause, because both clauses do not distinguish between media businesses and nonprofessional speakers.&lt;ref name="CornellFirstAmendmentOverview"&gt;{{cite web|title=First Amendment: An Overview|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/first_amendment|work={{!}} Wex Legal Dictionary / Encyclopedia|publisher=Legal Information Institute of the Cornell University|accessdate=18 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="McConnellNov2013" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The American Heritage Foundation's Guide to the Constitution: Freedom of Speech and of the Press|url=http://www.heritage.org/constitution#!/amendments/1/essays/140/freedom-of-speech-and-of-the-press|publisher=The American Heritage Foundation|accessdate=18 April 2014|author=Eugene Volokh (Gary T. Schwartz Professor of Law at Los Angeles School of Law of the University of California|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200512180333/https://www.heritage.org/constitution|archive-date=May 12, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ECBbritannicaFA20140418" /&gt; This is further shown by the Supreme Court consistently refusing to recognize the First Amendment as providing greater protection to the institutional media than to other speakers.&lt;ref&gt;See ''[[Bartnicki v. Vopper]]'', 532 U.S. 514 (2001) where the U.S. Supreme Court "draw no distinction between the media respondents and" a non-institutional respondent.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See ''[[Cohen v. Cowles Media Co.]]'', 501 U.S. 663 (1991) where the U.S. Supreme Court held that the press gets no special immunity from laws that apply to others, including those—such as copyright law—that target communication.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also ''Henry v. Collins'', 380 U.S. 356, 357 (1965) (per curiam) (applying [[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan|''Sullivan'' standard]] to a statement by an arrestee); ''Garrison v. Louisiana'', 379 U.S. 64, 67–68 (1964) (applying Sullivan standard to statements by an elected district attorney); ''New York Times Co. v. Sullivan'', 376 U.S. at 286 (applying identical First Amendment protection to a newspaper defendant and individual defendants).&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in a case involving campaign finance laws the Court rejected the "suggestion that communication by corporate members of the institutional press is entitled to greater constitutional protection than the same communication by" non-institutional-press businesses.&lt;ref&gt;''[[First National Bank of Boston v. Bellotti]]'', {{ussc|435|765|1978}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A landmark decision for press freedom came in ''[[Near v. Minnesota]]'' (1931),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Near v. Minnesota]]'', {{ussc|283|697|1931}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the Supreme Court rejected [[prior restraint]] (pre-publication censorship). In this case, the Minnesota legislature passed a statute allowing courts to shut down "malicious, scandalous and defamatory newspapers", allowing a defense of truth only in cases where the truth had been told "with good motives and for justifiable ends".{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=43}} The Court applied the Free Press Clause to the states, rejecting the statute as unconstitutional. Hughes quoted Madison in the majority decision, writing, "The impairment of the fundamental security of life and property by criminal alliances and official neglect emphasizes the primary need of a vigilant and courageous press."{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=44–45}}
[[File:Daniel Ellsberg.jpg|thumb|The leak of the [[Pentagon Papers]] by [[Daniel Ellsberg]] (pictured here in 2018) led to ''[[New York Times Co. v. United States]]'' (1971), a landmark press freedom decision.]]

However, ''Near'' also noted an exception, allowing prior restraint in cases such as "publication of sailing dates of transports or the number or location of troops".{{sfn|Lewis|2007|pp=46–47}} This exception was a key point in another landmark case four decades later: ''[[New York Times Co. v. United States]]'' (1971),&lt;ref&gt;''[[New York Times Co. v. United States]]'', {{ussc|403|713|1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the administration of President [[Richard Nixon]] sought to ban the publication of the [[Pentagon Papers]], classified government documents about the Vietnam War secretly copied by analyst [[Daniel Ellsberg]]. The Court found that the Nixon administration had not met the heavy burden of proof required for prior restraint. Justice Brennan, drawing on ''Near'' in a concurrent opinion, wrote that "only governmental allegation and proof that publication must inevitably, directly, and immediately cause the occurrence of an evil kindred to imperiling the safety of a transport already at sea can support even the issuance of an interim restraining order." Justices Black and Douglas went still further, writing that prior restraints were never justified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001770.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509092209/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001770.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=New York Times Co. v. United States 403 U.S. 713 (1971)|author=Frederick Schauer|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The courts have rarely treated content-based regulation of journalism with any sympathy. In ''[[Miami Herald Publishing Co. v. Tornillo]]'' (1974),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Miami Herald Publishing Co. v. Tornillo]]'', {{ussc|418|241|1974}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court unanimously struck down a state law requiring newspapers criticizing political candidates to publish their responses. The state claimed the law had been passed to ensure journalistic responsibility. The Supreme Court found that freedom, but not responsibility, is mandated by the First Amendment and so it ruled that the government may not force newspapers to publish that which they do not desire to publish.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-21201322.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509083623/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-21201322.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Dan Paul, 85, leading lawyer for press freedom|author=Dennis Hevesi|date=February 2, 2010|work=The Boston Globe|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Content-based regulation of television and radio, however, have been sustained by the Supreme Court in various cases. Since there is a limited number of frequencies for non-cable television and radio stations, the government licenses them to various companies. However, the Supreme Court has ruled that the problem of scarcity does not allow the raising of a First Amendment issue. The government may restrain broadcasters, but only on a content-neutral basis. In ''[[Federal Communications Commission v. Pacifica Foundation]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''[[Federal Communications Commission v. Pacifica Foundation]]'', {{ussc|438|726|1978}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court upheld the [[Federal Communications Commission]]'s authority to restrict the use of "[[Decency|indecent]]" material in broadcasting.

State governments retain the right to tax newspapers, just as they may tax other commercial products. Generally, however, taxes that focus exclusively on newspapers have been found unconstitutional. In ''[[Grosjean v. American Press Co.]]'' (1936),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Grosjean v. American Press Co.]]'' {{ussc|297|233|1936}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court invalidated a state tax on newspaper advertising revenues, holding that the role of the press in creating "informed public opinion" was vital.{{sfn|Lewis|2007|p=46}} Similarly, some taxes that give preferential treatment to the press have been struck down. In ''Arkansas Writers' Project v. Ragland'' (1987),&lt;ref&gt;''Arkansas Writers' Project v. Ragland'', {{ussc|481|221|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; for instance, the Court invalidated an [[Arkansas]] law exempting "religious, professional, trade and sports journals" from taxation since the law amounted to the regulation of newspaper content. In ''Leathers v. Medlock'' (1991),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Leathers v. Medlock]]'', {{ussc|499|439|1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court found that states may treat different types of the media differently, such as by taxing cable television, but not newspapers. The Court found that "differential taxation of speakers, even members of the press, does not implicate the First Amendment unless the tax is directed at, or presents the danger of suppressing, particular ideas."&lt;ref&gt;''Leathers'', at 453&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Branzburg v. Hayes]]'' (1972),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Branzburg v. Hayes]]'', {{ussc|408|665|1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that the First Amendment did not give a journalist the right to refuse a [[subpoena]] from a [[grand jury]]. The issue decided in the case was whether a journalist could refuse to "appear and testify before state and Federal grand juries" basing the refusal on the belief that such appearance and testimony "abridges the freedom of speech and press guaranteed by the First Amendment".&lt;ref&gt;''Branzburg'', 667&lt;/ref&gt; The decision was that such a protection was not provided by the First Amendment. However, a concurring opinion by Justice [[Lewis F. Powell]], in which he said a claim for press privilege "should be judged on its facts by the striking of a proper balance between freedom of the press and the obligation of all citizens to give relevant testimony with respect to criminal conduct. The balance of these vital constitutional and societal interests on a case-by-case basis accords with the tried and traditional way of adjudicating such questions," has been frequently cited by lower courts since the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000283.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509085553/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425000283.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Branzburg v. Hayes 408 U.S. 665 (1972)|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Petition and assembly==

{{further&lt;!--main is ONLY for summary-style overviews of a subarticle; further is the correct template when "the section expounds a specific aspect of the topic instead of summarizing its article"--&gt;|Right to petition in the United States|Freedom of assembly}}
[[File:Chief Justice Morrison Waite.jpg|thumb|Chief Justice [[Morrison Waite]] ruled in ''[[United States v. Cruikshank]]'' (1875) that the right of assembly was a secondary right to the right to petition.]]

The Petition Clause protects the right "to petition the government for a redress of grievances".&lt;ref name="CornellFirstAmendmentOverview"/&gt; This includes the right to communicate with government officials, lobbying government officials and petitioning the courts by filing lawsuits with a legal basis.&lt;ref name="ECBbritannicaFA20140418"&gt;{{cite web|author=Eugene Volokh|title=First Amendment (United States Constitution)|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/208044/First-Amendment|work=Encyclopædia Britannica|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=18 April 2014|date=8 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Petition Clause first came to prominence in the 1830s, when Congress established the [[gag rule]] barring anti-slavery petitions from being heard; the rule was overturned by Congress several years later. Petitions against the [[Espionage Act of 1917]] resulted in imprisonments. The Supreme Court did not rule on either issue.&lt;ref name="Findlaw20121005"&gt;{{cite web|title=Rights of Assembly &amp; Petition – First Amendment U.S. Constitution – Findlaw|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/data/constitution/amendment01/21.html|publisher=findlaw.com|accessdate=October 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[California Motor Transport Co. v. Trucking Unlimited]]'' (1972),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=California Motor Transport Co. v. Trucking Unlimited|link=|volume=404|page=508|pin=|year=1972}}. {{usgovpd}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court said the right to petition encompasses "the approach of citizens or groups of them to administrative agencies (which are both creatures of the legislature, and arms of the executive) and to courts, the third branch of Government. Certainly the right to petition extends to all departments of the Government. The right of access to the courts is indeed but one aspect of the right of petition."&lt;ref&gt;''California Motor Transport Co.'', 404 U.S. at 510.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, thus, this right encompasses petitions to all three branches of the federal government—the Congress, the executive and the judiciary—and has been extended to the states through incorporation.&lt;ref name="Findlaw20121005" /&gt;&lt;ref name="FACenter"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/faq/frequently-asked-questions-petition|title=Frequently Asked Questions – Petition|publisher=First Amendment Center|accessdate=April 19, 2013|archivedate=April 28, 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130428020515/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/faq/frequently-asked-questions-petition|url-status=dead|df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Supreme Court, "redress of grievances" is to be construed broadly: it includes not solely appeals by the public to the government for the redressing of a grievance in the traditional sense, but also, petitions on behalf of private interests seeking personal gain.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{ussc|name=Eastern Railroad Presidents Conference v. Noerr Motor Freight, Inc.|365|127|1961}}&lt;/ref&gt; The right protects not only demands for "a redress of grievances" but also demands for government action.&lt;ref name="Findlaw20121005" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; The petition clause includes according to the Supreme Court the opportunity to institute non-frivolous lawsuits and mobilize popular support to change existing laws in a peaceful manner.&lt;ref name="FACenter" /&gt;

In ''[[Borough of Duryea v. Guarnieri]]'' (2011),&lt;ref name="Duryea"&gt;{{ussc|name=Borough of Duryea v. Guarnieri|link=|volume=564|page=379|pin=|year=2011}}. {{usgovpd}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court stated regarding the Free Speech Clause and the Petition Clause:
{{quote|It is not necessary to say that the two Clauses are identical in their mandate or their purpose and effect to acknowledge that the rights of speech and petition share substantial common ground{{nbsp}}... Both speech and petition are integral to the democratic process, although not necessarily in the same way. The right to petition allows citizens to express their ideas, hopes, and concerns to their government and their elected representatives, whereas the right to speak fosters the public exchange of ideas that is integral to deliberative democracy as well as to the whole realm of ideas and human affairs. Beyond the political sphere, both speech and petition advance personal expression, although the right to petition is generally concerned with expression directed to the government seeking redress of a grievance.&lt;ref name="Duryea"/&gt;}}

The right of assembly was originally distinguished from the right to petition. In ''[[United States v. Cruikshank]]'' (1875),&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Cruikshank]]'', {{ussc|92|542|1875}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court held that
&lt;blockquote&gt;the right of the people peaceably to assemble for the purpose of petitioning Congress for a redress of grievances, or for anything else connected with the powers or duties of the National Government, is an attribute of national citizenship, and, as such, under protection of, and guaranteed by, the United States. The very idea of a government, republican in form, implies a right on the part of its citizens to meet peaceably for consultation in respect to public affairs and to petition for a redress of grievances.&lt;ref&gt;''Cruikshank'', at 552&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Justice [[Morrison Waite]]'s opinion for the Court carefully distinguished the right to peaceably assemble as a secondary right, while the right to petition was labeled to be a primary right. Later cases, however, paid less attention to these distinctions.&lt;ref name="Findlaw20121005" /&gt;

In two 1960s decisions collectively known as forming the [[Noerr-Pennington doctrine]],{{efn|''[[Eastern Railroad Presidents Conference v. Noerr Motor Freight, Inc]]'' (1961) and ''[[United Mine Workers v. Pennington]]'' (1965)}} the Court established that the right to petition prohibited the application of [[antitrust law]] to statements made by private entities before public bodies: a monopolist may freely go before the city council and encourage the denial of its competitor's building permit without being subject to [[Sherman Act]] liability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1P3-321223711|title=Competition and the Noerr-Pennington doctrine: When should political activity be barred under European community competition law?|author=William Cooney|date=January 1, 2003|work=The George Washington International Law Review|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Freedom of association==

{{further|Freedom of association#United States Constitution}}

Although the First Amendment does not explicitly mention freedom of association, the Supreme Court ruled, in ''[[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People v. Alabama]]'' (1958),&lt;ref&gt;''[[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People v. Alabama]]'', {{ussc|357|449|1958}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wayne Batchis, Citizens United and the Paradox of "Corporate Speech": From Freedom of Association to Freedom of The Association, [http://socialchangenyu.com/2013/02/01/citizens-united-and-the-paradox-of-corporate-speech/ 36 N.Y.U. Rev. L. &amp; Soc. Change 5] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130513015149/http://socialchangenyu.com/2013/02/01/citizens-united-and-the-paradox-of-corporate-speech/ |date=May 13, 2013 }} (2012).&lt;/ref&gt; that this freedom was protected by the Amendment and that privacy of membership was an essential part of this freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000015.html|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20130509093108/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3457000015.html|url-status= dead|archive-date= May 9, 2013|title=National Association for the Advancement of Colored People v. Alabama 1958|date=January 1, 2000|work=Supreme Court Drama: Cases That Changed America|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Supreme Court decided in ''[[Roberts v. United States Jaycees]]'' (1984) that "implicit in the right to engage in activities protected by the First Amendment" is "a corresponding right to associate with others in pursuit of a wide variety of political, social, economic, educational, religious, and cultural ends".&lt;ref&gt;''[[Roberts v. United States Jaycees]]'', {{ussc|468|609|1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Roberts'' the Court held that associations may not exclude people for reasons unrelated to the group's expression, such as gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1P3-834011751|title=What is Really Wrong with Compelled Association?|author=Shiffrin, Seana Valentine|authorlink=Seana Shiffrin|date=January 1, 2005|work=Northwestern University Law Review|publisher=|via=[[Questia Online Library]] |url-access=subscription|accessdate=April 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in ''[[Hurley v. Irish-American Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Group of Boston]]'' (1995),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Hurley v. Irish-American Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Group of Boston]]'', {{ussc|515|557|1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that a group may exclude people from membership if their presence would affect the group's ability to advocate a particular point of view.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001252.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509082442/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-3425001252.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Hurley v. Irish-American Gay, Lesbian, And Bisexual Group of Boston 515 U.S. 557 (1995)|date=January 1, 2000|work=Encyclopedia of the American Constitution|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, in ''[[Boy Scouts of America v. Dale]]'' (2000),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Boy Scouts of America v. Dale|530|640|2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled that a New Jersey law, which forced the [[Boy Scouts of America]] to admit an openly gay member, to be an unconstitutional abridgment of the Boy Scouts' right to free association.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-2587400073.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130509105313/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-2587400073.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=May 9, 2013|title=Boy Scouts of America v. Dale|date=January 1, 2006|work=Gender Issues and Sexuality: Essential Primary Sources|publisher={{Subscription required|via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}|accessdate=April 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Freedom of speech]]
* [[Censorship in the United States]]
* [[Freedom of thought]]
* [[Free speech zones]]
* [[Government speech]]
* [[List of amendments to the United States Constitution]]
* [[List of United States Supreme Court cases involving the First Amendment]]
* [[Marketplace of ideas]]
* [[Military expression]]
* [[Photography is Not a Crime]]
* [[Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom]]
* [[Williamsburg Charter]]
* [[First Amendment audits]]
{{div col end}}

==References==

'''Notes'''
{{notelist}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist|25em}}

'''Bibliography'''
* {{cite book|last=Abrams|first=Floyd|authorlink=Floyd Abrams|title=Speaking freely|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eRQIMWrCfhEC|accessdate=April 4, 2013|date=April 4, 2006|publisher=Penguin|isbn=978-0-14-303675-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Beeman|first=Richard|authorlink=Richard Beeman|title=Plain, Honest Men: The Making of the American Constitution|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2eyCX5Vrn7wC|accessdate=April 4, 2013|year=2009|publisher=Random House|isbn=978-1-58836-726-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Margaret C. |last=Jasper|title=The Law of Speech and the First Amendment|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ITpDAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=April 4, 2013|year=1999|publisher=Oceana Publications|isbn=978-0-379-11335-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=William Edward|last=Nelson|title=Americanization of the Common Law: The Impact of Legal Change on Massachusetts Society, 1760-1830|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=64S-E0fRn4YC|accessdate=April 19, 2013|year=1994|publisher=University of Georgia Press|isbn=978-0-8203-1587-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Martin L. |last=Newell|title=The Law of Libel and Slander in Civil and Criminal Cases: As Administered in the Courts of the United States of America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iXk9AAAAIAAJ|accessdate=April 19, 2013|year=1898|publisher=Callaghan|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Lewis|first=Anthony|title=[[Freedom for the Thought That We Hate|Freedom for the Thought That We Hate: A Biography of the First Amendment]]|&lt;!--commenting; requires URL: accessdate=April 4, 2013|--&gt;year=2007|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=978-0-465-01819-2|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==

* {{cite book|last=Curtis|first=Michael Kent|title=[[Free Speech, "The People's Darling Privilege"|Free Speech, "The People's Darling Privilege": Struggles for Freedom of Expression in American History]]|year=2000|publisher=[[Duke University Press]]|isbn=0822325292}}
* Daniel L. Dreisbach and [[Mark David Hall]]. ''The Sacred Rights of Conscience: Selected Readings on Religious Liberty and Church-State Relations in the American Founding''. Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Fund Press, 2009.
* Daniel L. Dreisbach, Mark David Hall, and Jeffry Morrison. ''The Forgotten Founders on Religion and Public Life'' Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 2009.
* [[Thomas I. Emerson]], "Toward a General Theory of the First Amendment", ''Yale Law Journal'', vol. 72, no. 5 (1963), pp.&amp;nbsp;877–956. In JSTOR.
* {{cite book|last=Godwin|first=Mike|authorlink=Mike Godwin|year=2003|title=[[Cyber Rights: Defending Free Speech in the Digital Age]]|publisher=MIT Press|isbn=0262571684}}
* P. Irons, ''A People's History of the Supreme Court'' New York: Penguin, 1999.
* {{cite book|authorlink=Kembrew McLeod|first=Kembrew|last=McLeod|others=foreword by Lawrence Lessig |title=[[Freedom of Expression(R)|Freedom of Expression: Resistance and Repression in the Age of Intellectual Property]]|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=2007|isbn=0816650314}}
* Kabala, James S., ''Church-State Relations in the Early American Republic, 1787–1846''. London: Pickering and Chatto, 2013.
* J. Kilman and G. Costello (eds.), ''The Constitution of the United States of America: Analysis and Interpretation''. (2000).
* {{cite book|title=[[Freedom for the Thought That We Hate|Freedom for the Thought That We Hate: A Biography of the First Amendment]]|first=Anthony|last=Lewis|authorlink=Anthony Lewis|pages=[https://archive.org/details/freedomforthough00lewi/page/173 173–76]|publisher=Basic Books|year=2007|isbn=978-0-465-03917-3|oclc=173659591|ref=harv}}
* Nicholas P. Miller, ''The Religious Roots of the First Amendment: Dissenting Protestants and the Separation of Church and State''. New York: Oxford University Press, 2012.
* {{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Samuel P.|title=[[Beyond the First Amendment|Beyond the First Amendment: The Politics of Free Speech and Pluralism]]|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press|year=2005|isbn=0801881730}}

==External links==

{{Spoken Wikipedia|First Amendment.ogg|2006-06-30}}
{{sisterlinks|d=Q12616|c=Category:First Amendment to the United States Constitution|n=no|b=no|v=no|voy=no|wikt=First Amendment}}
* [https://www.law.cornell.edu/anncon/html/amdt1toc_user.html Cornell Law School – Annotated Constitution]
* {{webarchive |url=http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20041016163435/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/speech/adultent/topic.aspx?topic=pornography |title=First Amendment Center – The First Amendment Library |date=2004-10-16}}
* {{cite web|last=Cohen|first=Henry|title=Freedom of Speech and Press: Exceptions to the First Amendment|work=Legislative Attorney|publisher=Congressional Research Service|date=October 16, 2009|url=https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/95-815.pdf|accessdate=January 1, 2012|ref=harv}}

{{US1stAmendment|state=expanded}}
{{US Constitution}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:First Amendment To The United States Constitution}}
[[Category:1791 in American politics]]
[[Category:1791 in American law]]
[[Category:Amendments to the United States Constitution|01]]
[[Category:Christianity and law in the 18th century]]
[[Category:First Amendment to the United States Constitution| ]]
[[Category:Freedom of religion in the United States]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>m5422f36s72kvncigm2bdk69rmh5jpg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
