<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Relevance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>442688</id>
    <revision>
      <id>954938264</id>
      <parentid>954935850</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-05T02:28:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Arturiousrye</username>
        <id>39191995</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13370" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}

'''Relevance''' is the concept of one topic being [[Premise|connected]] to another topic in a way that makes it useful   to consider the second topic when considering the first. The concept of relevance is studied in many different fields, including cognitive sciences, logic, and [[library and information science]]. Most fundamentally, however, it is studied in [[epistemology]] (the theory of knowledge). Different theories of knowledge have different implications for what is considered relevant and these fundamental views have implications for all other fields as well.

==Definition==
"Something (A) is relevant to a task (T) if it increases the likelihood of accomplishing the goal (G), which is implied by T." (Hjørland &amp; Sejer Christensen,2002).&lt;ref&gt;Hjørland, B. &amp; Sejer Christensen, F. (2002). Work tasks and socio-cognitive relevance: a specific example. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 53(11), 960-965.&lt;/ref&gt;

A thing might be relevant, a document or a piece of information may be relevant. The basic understanding of relevance does not depend on whether we speak of "things" or "information". For example, the Gandhian principles are of great relevance in today's world.

== Epistemology ==
If you believe that [[schizophrenia]] is caused by bad communication between mother and child, then family interaction studies become relevant. If, on the other hand, you subscribe to a genetic theory of relevance then the study of genes becomes relevant. If you subscribe to the epistemology of empiricism, then only intersubjectively controlled observations are relevant. If, on the other hand, you subscribe to [[feminist epistemology]], then the sex of the observer becomes relevant.

Epistemology is not just one domain among others. Epistemological views are always at play in any domain. Those views determine or influence what is regarded relevant.

==Relevance logic==
[[File:Relevance.jpg|thumb|Graphic of relevance in [[digital ecosystem]]s]]

In formal reasoning, relevance has proved an important but elusive concept. It is important because the solution of any problem requires the prior identification of the relevant elements from which a solution can be constructed. It is elusive, because the meaning of relevance appears to be difficult or impossible to capture within conventional [[logical system]]s. The obvious suggestion that q is relevant to p if q is implied by p breaks down because under standard definitions of [[material conditional|material implication]], a false proposition implies all other propositions. However though 'iron is a metal' may be implied by 'cats lay eggs' it doesn't seem to be relevant to it the way in which 'cats are mammals' and 'mammals give birth to living young' are relevant to each other. If one states "I love ice cream," and another person responds "I have a friend named Brad Cook," then these statements are not relevant. However, if one states "I love ice cream," and another person responds "I have a friend named Brad Cook who also likes ice cream," this statement now becomes relevant because it relates to the first person's idea.

More recently a number of theorists{{who|date=December 2011}} have sought to account for relevance in terms of "[[possible world]] logics" in [[intensional logic]]. Roughly, the idea is that [[logical truth|necessary truth]]s are true in all possible worlds, [[contradiction]]s (logical falsehoods) are true in no possible worlds, and [[Contingency (philosophy)|contingent]] propositions can be ordered in terms of the number of possible worlds in which they are true. Relevance is argued to depend upon the "remoteness relationship" between an actual world in which relevance is being evaluated and the set of possible worlds within which it is true.

== Application ==
=== Cognitive science and pragmatics ===
{{Main|Relevance theory}}

In 1986, [[Dan Sperber]] and Deirdre Wilson drew attention to the central importance of relevance decisions in reasoning and communication. They proposed an account of the process of inferring relevant information from any given utterance. To do this work, they used what they called the "Principle of Relevance": namely, the position that ''any utterance addressed to someone automatically conveys the presumption of its own optimal relevance''. The central idea of Sperber and Wilson's theory is that all utterances are encountered in some context, and the correct interpretation of a particular utterance is the one that allows most new implications to be made in that context on the basis of the least amount of information necessary to convey it. For Sperber and Wilson, relevance is conceived as relative or subjective, as it depends upon the state of knowledge of a hearer when they encounter an utterance.

Sperber and Wilson stress that this theory is not intended to account for every intuitive application of the English word "relevance". Relevance, as a technical term, is restricted to relationships between utterances and interpretations, and so the theory cannot account for intuitions such as the one that relevance relationships obtain in problems involving physical objects. If a plumber needs to fix a leaky faucet, for example, some objects and tools are relevant (e.g. a wrench) and others are not (e.g. a waffle iron). And, moreover, the latter seems to be irrelevant in a manner which does not depend upon the plumber's knowledge, or the utterances used to describe the problem.

A theory of relevance that seems to be more readily applicable to such instances of physical problem solving has been suggested by Gorayska and Lindsay in a series of articles published during the 1990s. The key feature of their theory is the idea that relevance is goal-dependent. An item (e.g., an utterance or object) is relevant to a goal if and only if it can be an essential element of some plan capable of achieving the desired goal. This theory embraces both propositional reasoning and the problem-solving activities of people such as plumbers, and defines relevance in such a way that what is relevant is determined by the real world (because what plans will work is a matter of empirical fact) rather than the state of knowledge or belief of a particular problem solver.

=== Data quality ===
[[File:Qualitydimensions.png|thumb|alt=Quality dimensions of web 2.0 portals, encyclopedias and Wikipedia|Relevance and other [[data quality|quality]] dimensions of [[web 2.0]] portals, [[encyclopedia]]s and [[Wikipedia]]&lt;ref name="dataquality"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lewoniewski |first1=Włodzimierz |last2=Węcel |first2=Krzysztof |last3=Abramowicz |first3=Witold |date=2019 |title=Multilingual Ranking of Wikipedia Articles with Quality and Popularity Assessment in Different Topics |journal=Computers |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=60 |doi=10.3390/computers8030060|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]Relevance is one of the important dimensions in the [[data quality]] assessment.&lt;ref name="dataquality" /&gt; For example, data must be relevant and timely for use by the data consumer in the decision-making process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1080/07421222.1996.11518099|title = Beyond Accuracy: What Data Quality Means to Data Consumers|journal = Journal of Management Information Systems|volume = 12|issue = 4|pages = 5–33|year = 1996|last1 = Wang|first1 = Richard Y.|last2 = Strong|first2 = Diane M.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Relevance is especially important in collaborative [[Web 2.0]] platforms such as [[wiki]], [[Q&amp;A software|Q&amp;A Forums]] and other services since the goal is to satisfy a clear information need, described by means of a topic or a question.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1002/asi.23650|title = A general multiview framework for assessing the quality of collaboratively created content on web 2.0|journal = Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology|volume = 68|issue = 2|pages = 286–308|year = 2017|last1 = Dalip|first1 = Daniel H.|last2 = Gonçalves|first2 = Marcos André|last3 = Cristo|first3 = Marco|last4 = Calado|first4 = Pável}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, for Wikipedia features related to relevance can be measured based on number of page visits, page watchers, [[PageRank]] and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lewoniewski |first1=Włodzimierz |year=2019 |title=Measures for Quality Assessment of Articles and Infoboxes in Multilingual Wikipedia |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/330087836 |journal=Lecture Notes in Business Information Processing |volume=339 |issue= |pages=619–633 |doi=10.1007/978-3-030-04849-5_53 |isbn=978-3-030-04849-5 | access-date=2019-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Economics ===

The [[economist]] [[John Maynard Keynes]] saw the importance of defining relevance to the problem of calculating risk in economic decision-making. He suggested that the relevance of a piece of evidence, such as a true proposition, should be defined in terms of the changes it produces of estimations of the probability of future events. Specifically, Keynes proposed that new evidence &lt;math&gt; e &lt;/math&gt; is irrelevant to a proposition &lt;math&gt; x &lt;/math&gt;, given old evidence &lt;math&gt; q &lt;/math&gt;, if and only if &lt;math&gt; \frac{x}{pq}&lt;/math&gt;  &lt;math&gt;= \frac{x}{q}  &lt;/math&gt;, otherwise, the proposition is relevant.

There are technical problems with this definition, for example, the relevance of a piece of evidence can be sensitive to the order in which other pieces of evidence are received.

=== Law ===
{{Main|Relevance (law)}}
The meaning of "relevance" in U.S. law is reflected in Rule 401 of the [[Federal Rules of Evidence]]. That rule defines relevance as "having any tendency to make the existence of any fact that is of consequence to the determinations of the action more probable or less probable than it would be without the evidence." In other words, if a fact were to have no bearing on the truth or falsity of a conclusion, it would be legally irrelevant.

=== Library and information science ===
{{Main|Relevance (information retrieval)}}
{{Recommender systems}}
This field has considered when documents (or document representations) retrieved from databases are relevant or non-relevant. Given a conception of relevance, two measures have been applied: [[Precision and recall]]:

Recall = a : (a + c) X 100%, where
a = number of retrieved, relevant documents,
c = number of non-retrieved, relevant documents (sometimes termed "silence").
Recall is thus an expression of how exhaustive a search for documents is.

Precision = a : (a + b) X 100%, where 
a = number of retrieved, relevant documents,
b = number of retrieved, non-relevant documents (often termed "noise").

Precision is thus a measure of the amount of noise in document-retrieval.

Relevance itself has in the literature often been based on what is termed "the system's view" and "the user's view". Hjørland (2010) criticize these two views and defends a "subject knowledge view of relevance".

=== Politics ===
During the 1960s, ''relevance'' became a fashionable [[buzzword]], meaning roughly 'relevance to social concerns', such as [[racial equality]], [[poverty]], [[social justice]], [[famine|world hunger]], world [[economic development]], and so on. The implication was that some subjects, e.g., the study of [[medieval poetry]] and the practice of [[corporate law]], were not worthwhile because they did not address pressing [[social issues]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

== See also ==
* [[Source criticism]]
* [[Description]]
* [[Distraction]]
* [[Information-action ratio]]
* [[Information overload]]
* [[Intention]]
* [[Intuitionistic logic]]
* [[Kripke semantics]]
* [[Relevance theory]]
* [[Draft:Rubled]]

== References ==
{{More footnotes|date=June 2009}}
{{Reflist}} 
* Gorayska B. &amp; R. O. Lindsay (1993). The Roots of Relevance. ''Journal of Pragmatics'' ''19'', 301–323. Los Alamitos: IEEE Computer Society Press.
* Hjørland, Birger (2010). [http://www2.hawaii.edu/~donnab/lis670/hjorland_relevance_2010.pdf The foundation of the concept of relevance]. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 61(2), 217-237.
* Keynes, J. M. (1921). ''Treatise on Probability''. London: MacMillan
* Lindsay, R. &amp; Gorayska, B. (2002) Relevance, Goals and Cognitive Technology. ''International Journal of Cognitive Technology'', ''1'', (2), 187–232
* Sperber, D. &amp; D. Wilson (1986/1995) ''Relevance: Communication and Cognition''. 2nd edition. Oxford: Blackwell.
* Sperber, D. &amp; D. Wilson (1987). Précis of Relevance: Communication and Cognition. ''Behavioral and Brain Science'', ''10'', 697–754.
* Sperber, D. &amp; D. Wilson (2004). Relevance Theory. In Horn, L.R. &amp; Ward, G. (eds.) 2004 The Handbook of Pragmatics. Oxford: Blackwell, 607-632. http://www.dan.sperber.fr/?p=93
* Zhang, X, H. (1993). ''A Goal-Based Relevance Model and its Application to Intelligent Systems''. Ph.D. Thesis, Oxford Brookes University, Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, October, 1993.

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|relevance|relevant|irrelevant}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3TRioBKpUwY Malcolm Gladwell - Blink - full show]: [[TVOntario]] interview regarding "snap judgements" and ''[[Blink (book)|Blink]]''

{{Philosophical logic}}

[[Category:Information science]]
[[Category:Library science terminology]]
[[Category:Pragmatics]]
[[Category:Logic]]
[[Category:Descriptive technique]]</text>
      <sha1>1yq8az7z8ocawl4r652su5tnjvl0nny</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
