<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nutriepigenomics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30932051</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961905469</id>
      <parentid>961905242</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-11T01:28:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vsmith</username>
        <id>84417</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Low Birth Weight */ decap header, increase image size</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="37456" xml:space="preserve">'''Nutriepigenomics''' is the study of food [[nutrient]]s and their effects on human health through [[epigenetic]] modifications.  There is now considerable evidence that nutritional imbalances during [[gestation]] and [[lactation]] are linked to [[non-communicable disease]]s, such as [[obesity]], [[cardiovascular disease]], [[diabetes]], [[hypertension]], and [[cancer]].  If metabolic disturbances occur during critical time windows of development, the resulting epigenetic alterations can lead to permanent changes in tissue and organ structure or function and predispose individuals to disease.&lt;ref name="Gallou"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Gallou-Kabani C, Vige A, Gross MS, Junien C | year = 2007 | title = Nutri-epigenomics: Lifelong remodelling of our epigenomes by nutritional and metabolic factors and beyond | url = | journal = Clin Chem Lab Med | volume = 45 | issue = 3| pages = 321–7 | doi = 10.1515/CCLM.2007.081 | pmid = 17378726 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
[[Epigenetics]] relates to heritable changes in [[gene]] function that occur independently of alterations in primary [[DNA]] sequence.  Two major epigenetic mechanisms implicated in nutriepigenomics are [[DNA methylation]] and [[histone]] modification.  DNA methylation in [[gene promoter]] regions usually results in [[gene silencing]] and influences gene expression.  While this form of gene silencing is extremely important in development and cellular differentiation, aberrant DNA methylation can be detrimental and has been linked to various disease processes, such as cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Berdasco M, Esteller M | year = 2010 | title = Aberrant epigenetic landscape in cancer: How cellular identity goes awry | url = | journal = Dev Cell. | volume = 19 | issue = 5| pages = 698–711 | doi = 10.1016/j.devcel.2010.10.005 | pmid = 21074720 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The methyl groups used in DNA methylation are often derived from dietary sources, such as folate and [[choline]], and explains why diet can have a significant impact on methylation patterns and gene expression.&lt;ref name="Pozharny"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Pozharny Y, Lambertini L, Clunie G, Ferrara L, Lee MJ | date = Mar 2010 | title = Epigenetics in women's health care | url = | journal = Mt Sinai J Med | volume = 77 | issue = 2| pages = 225–35 | doi = 10.1002/msj.20176 | pmid = 20309920 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Gene silencing can also be reinforced through the recruitment of [[histone deacetylases]] to decrease transcriptional activation.  Conversely, [[histone acetylation]] induces transcriptional activation to increase gene expression.  Dietary components can influence these epigenetic events, thereby altering gene expression and disturbing functions such as appetite control, metabolic balance and fuel utilization.&lt;ref name="Gallou"/&gt;

Various genetic sequences can be targeted for epigenetic modification.  A [[transcriptome]]-wide analysis in mice found that a protein-restricted (PR) diet during gestation resulted in differential gene expression in approximately 1% of the fetal genes analyzed (235/22,690).  Specifically, increased expression was seen in genes involved in the [[p53]] pathway, [[apoptosis]], negative regulators of cell metabolism, and genes related to epigenetic control.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Gheorghe CP, Goyal R, Holweger JD, Longo LD | date = May 2009 | title = Placental gene expression responses to maternal protein restriction in the mouse | journal = Placenta | volume = 30 | issue = 5| pages = 411–7 | doi = 10.1016/j.placenta.2009.03.002 | pmid = 19362366 | pmc = 2674533 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Additional studies have investigated the effect of a PR-diet in rats and found changes in promoter methylation of both the [[glucocorticoid receptor]] and [[peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor]] (PPAR).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Lillycrop KA, Phillips ES, Torrens C, Hanson MA, Jackson AA, Burdge GC | date = Aug 2008 | title = Feeding pregnant rats a protein-restricted diet persistently alters the methylation of specific cytosines in the hepatic PPAR alpha promoter of the offspring | journal = Br J Nutr | volume = 100 | issue = 2| pages = 278–82 | doi = 10.1017/S0007114507894438 | pmid = 18186951 | pmc = 2564112 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Lillycrop KA, Slater-Jefferies JL, Hanson MA, Godfrey KM, Jackson AA, Burdge GC | date = Jun 2007 | title = Induction of altered epigenetic regulation of the hepatic glucocorticoid receptor in the offspring of rats fed a protein-restricted diet during pregnancy suggests that reduced DNA methyltransferase-1 expression is involved in impaired DNA methylation and changes in histone modifications | journal = Br J Nutr | volume = 97 | issue = 6| pages = 1064–73 | doi = 10.1017/S000711450769196X | pmid = 17433129 | pmc = 2211425 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Altered expression of these receptors can result in elevated blood glucose levels and affect lipid and carbohydrate metabolism.&lt;ref name="Pozharny"/&gt; Feeding a PR-diet to pregnant and/or lactating mice also increased expression of [[glucokinase]], [[acetyl-CoA carboxylase]], [[PPARα]], and [[acyl-CoA oxidase]].&lt;ref name="Burdge"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Burdge GC, Lillycrop KA | year = 2010 | title = Nutrition, epigenetics, and developmental plasticity: Implications for understanding human disease | url = | journal = Annu Rev Nutr | volume = 30 | issue = | pages = 315–39 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.nutr.012809.104751 | pmid = 20415585 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Changes in expression were reportedly due to epigenetic regulation of either the gene promoter itself, or promoters of transcription factors that regulate gene expression.  Additional genes that have been shown, either by [[in vitro]] or [[in vivo]] studies, to be regulated by epigenetic mechanisms include [[leptin]], [[SOCS3]], [[glucose transporter]] (GLUT)-4, [[POMC]], [[Hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 2|11-β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 2]] and [[Corticotrophin-releasing factor|corticotrophin releasing hormone]].  Epigenetic modification of these genes may lead to “metabolic programming” of the fetus and result in long-term changes in [[metabolism]] and energy homeostasis.&lt;ref name="Tamashiro"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Tamashiro KL, Moran TH | year = 2010 | title = Perinatal environment and its influences on metabolic programming of offspring | journal = Physiol Behav | volume = 100 | issue = 5| pages = 560–6 | doi = 10.1016/j.physbeh.2010.04.008 | pmid = 20394764 | pmc = 2886179 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nutriepigenomics and development==
The period of development in which the nutritional imbalance occurs is very important in determining which disease-related genes will be affected.  Different organs have critical developmental stages, and the time point at which they are compromised will predispose individuals to specific diseases.&lt;ref name="hanley"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Hanley B, Dijane J, Fewtrell M, Grynberg A, Hummel S, Junien C, Koletzko B, Lewis S, Renz H, Symonds M, Gros M, Harthoorn L, Mace K, Samuels F, van Der Beek EM | date = Jul 2010 | title = Metabolic imprinting, programming and epigenetics - a review of present priorities and future opportunities | url = | journal = Br J Nutr | volume = 104 | issue = | pages = S1–25 | doi = 10.1017/S0007114510003338 | pmid = 20929595 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Epigenetic modifications that occur during development may not be expressed until later in life depending on the function of the gene.&lt;ref name="Pozharny"/&gt; While the majority of studies implicate [[prenatal]] and [[perinatal]] periods as critical time windows, some research has shown that nutritional intake during [[adulthood]] can also affect the epigenome.

===Prenatal ===
[[Developmental plasticity]] is the process in which fetuses adapt to their environment.  Environmental cues, including dietary components, present in the [[in utero]] environment can induce significant changes in the expression of the genome through epigenetic modifications.&lt;ref name="Burdge"/&gt; Fetal developmental plastic responses can cause changes in lean body mass, endocrinology, blood flow and vascular loading, and lead to increased risk of various diseases in adulthood.

====Low birth weight ====
Fetal exposure to calcium, folate, magnesium, high or low protein, and zinc have all been associated with birth weight.&lt;ref name="hanley"/&gt; Numerous studies have investigated the link between birth weight and risk of disease and have found that low birth weight is significantly associated with coronary heart disease, stroke and type-2 diabetes.  Most importantly, these associations occurred after adjusting for lifestyle factors, implying a genetic basis for onset of disease.&lt;ref name = "Simmons"&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 21110912 | doi=10.1017/S0029665110003988 | volume=70 | issue=1 | title=Epigenetics and maternal nutrition: nature v. nurture | date=February 2011 | author=Simmons R | journal=Proc Nutr Soc | pages=73–81 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Impaired [[insulin]] secretion is associated with low birth weight and can lead to insulin resistance as babies accumulate body fat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Jensen CB, Storgaard H, Dela F, Holst JJ, Madsbad S, Vaag AA | date = Apr 2002 | title = Early differential defects of insulin secretion and action in 19-year-old caucasian men who had low birth weight | url = | journal = Diabetes | volume = 51 | issue = 4| pages = 1271–80 | pmid = 11916955 | doi = 10.2337/diabetes.51.4.1271 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies using intrauterine growth retarded (IUGR) rats have found that growth inhibition can lead to decreased expression of Pdx1 transcription factor, which is essential for differentiation and function of pancreatic beta cells.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Park JH, Stoffers DA, Nicholls RD, Simmons RA | date = Jun 2008 | title = Development of type 2 diabetes following intrauterine growth retardation in rats is associated with progressive epigenetic silencing of Pdx1 | journal = J Clin Invest | volume = 118 | issue = 6| pages = 2316–24 | pmid = 18464933 | doi = 10.1172/JCI33655 | pmc = 2373422 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Decreased histone acetylation at the proximal promoter of Pdx1 is responsible for reduced Pdx1 expression and subsequently results in a cascade of histone deacetylation and methylation events that can result in type-2 diabetes.
[[Image:Histones.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|alt=PDX1 is an essential transcription factor for proper development and function of pancreatic [[beta cells]].  Poor maternal nutrition is linked to intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) and low birth weight, and can result in decreased expression of PDX1 through decreased histone acetylation at the PDX1 proximal promoter.  Reduced expression of PDX1 may result in improper formation of beta cells and increase the risk of type-2 diabetes in the offspring.|Development of type 2 diabetes following intrauterine growth retardation in rats is associated with progressive epigenetic silencing of Pdx1]]

==== Obesity ====
Obesity during pregnancy and high-fat maternal diets both show strong associations with obesity in offspring.  As the number of overweight reproductive-age women increases, the number of overweight children and infants also increases.&lt;ref name="Simmons"/&gt;  It has been postulated that maternal obesity causes an accumulation of fat in fetal [[adipose tissue]] (adiposity) and predisposes babies for obesity in childhood and adulthood.&lt;ref name = "Simmons"/&gt;  Animal studies have shown that maternal overnutrition may impact brain development and cause disruptions to programming of the [[hypothalamus]].  Offspring that were exposed to a high-fat or high-caloric maternal diet had increased levels of insulin, glucose and leptin.  It is hypothesized that these elevations are due to disturbances in the complex neuronal network that includes the neuropeptide Y (NPY) and proopiomelanocortin (POMC) pathways.&lt;ref name="Tamashiro"/&gt;  This altered neuronal signaling can consequently impact food-intake behavior and lead to diet-induced obesity in adulthood.  While epigenetic modifications are most likely involved in the development of obesity, the specific target genes have yet to be identified.  Genes involved in adipogenesis, such as fibroblast growth-factor-2, phosphatase and tensin homologue, cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A and oestrogen receptor-alpha, possess multiple [[CpG islands]] in their promoter sites and may act as epigenetic targets.&lt;ref name="Campion"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Campion J, Milagro FI, Martinez JA | date = Jul 2009 | title = Individuality and epigenetics in obesity | url = | journal = Obes Rev | volume = 10 | issue = 4| pages = 383–92 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-789X.2009.00595.x | pmid = 19413700 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, it has been shown that prenatal exposure to a hypomethylating agent, such as [[bisphenol A]] (BPA), is associated with increased body weight and suggests modified DNA methylation as a mechanism for increasing susceptibility to obesity.&lt;ref name="Campion"/&gt;

==== Folate ====
It has long been realized that maternal folate intake during pregnancy is linked to fetal development and growth, and can reduce the risk of serious birth defects.  Folate is a source of [[S-adenosyl methionine]] (SAM), which is used to supply DNA methyltransferases with methyl groups.  Therefore, changes in folate supply have a substantial effect on DNA methylation patterns.  Low levels of folate are associated with an increased risk of preterm delivery, poor growth of the placenta and uterus, and intrauterine growth retardation.&lt;ref name="Pozharny"/&gt;  Several complex diseases, including cancer, cardiovascular diseases and [[autism]] have also been linked to maternal folate status.  Based on animal studies it has been hypothesized that reduced folate intake could increase the risk of [[neural tube defects]] by reducing the amount of methylayed DNA during cranial neural tube closure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Dunlevy LP, Burren KA, Mills K, Chitty LS, Copp AJ, Greene ND | date = Jul 2006 | title = Integrity of the methylation cycle is essential for mammalian neural tube closure | url = | journal = Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol | volume = 76 | issue = 7| pages = 544–52 | doi = 10.1002/bdra.20286 | pmid = 16933307 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Recently it was discovered that folate protection from congenital heart defects is linked to epigenetics and Wnt signaling.  Multiple environmental factors target the [[Wnt signaling pathway]] during embryogenesis and can cause misregulation of the pathway.  [[Folic acid]] metabolism generates SAM, thereby altering the methylation states of histones H3K9, H3K4, and H3K27 and genetically altering Wnt signaling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Linask KK, Huhta J | year = 2010 | title = Folate protection from congenital heart defects linked with canonical wnt signaling and epigenetics | journal = Curr Opin Pediatr | volume = 22 | issue = 5| pages = 561–6 | doi = 10.1097/MOP.0b013e32833e2723 | pmid = 20844350 | pmc = 3004285 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recently a [[Blind experiment|double-blind]] placebo controlled trial of high dose [[Folinic acid|Folinic Acid]] (Leucovorin Calcium) demonstrated efficacy at improving verbal communication in children with [[autism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frye|first=R. E.|last2=Slattery|first2=J.|last3=Delhey|first3=L.|last4=Furgerson|first4=B.|last5=Strickland|first5=T.|last6=Tippett|first6=M.|last7=Sailey|first7=A.|last8=Wynne|first8=R.|last9=Rose|first9=S.|date=2016-10-18|title=Folinic acid improves verbal communication in children with autism and language impairment: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial|journal=Molecular Psychiatry|volume=23|issue=2|pages=247–256|language=en|doi=10.1038/mp.2016.168|issn=1476-5578|pmid=27752075|pmc=5794882}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Perinatal ===
Another critical developmental time window is the perinatal period, the time period immediately before and after birth.   It has been shown that maternal diet in late pregnancy and an infant's diet in the beginning weeks can all have significant impacts on gene expression. Therefore, perinatal nutrition is both late-stage ''in utero'' nutrition and lactation.

==== Bone health ====
Bone mass and the development of [[osteoporosis]] have been studied in relation to perinatal nutrition.  An important factor to consider when investigating perinatal nutrition is whether the baby was [[breastfeeding|breast-fed]] or formula-fed.  Studies have shown that breast-fed babies have increased bone mass compared to those were not breast-fed, and that this small increase in bone mass during a period of critical development could potentially program the skeleton to continue along a “healthy” growth trajectory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 11000344 | volume=67 | issue=4 | title=Birth weight, birth length, and bone density in prepubertal children: evidence for an association that may be mediated by genetic factors | date=October 2000 | author=Jones G, Dwyer T | journal=Calcif. Tissue Int. | pages=304–8 | doi=10.1007/s002230001148 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It has also been shown that maternal [[vitamin D]] insufficiency during late pregnancy is associated with reduced bone size and mineral mass in late childhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 16399151 | doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(06)67922-1 | volume=367 | issue=9504 | title=Maternal vitamin D status during pregnancy and childhood bone mass at age 9 years: a longitudinal study | date=January 2006 | author=Javaid MK, Crozier SR, Harvey NC | display-authors = etal | journal=Lancet | pages=36–43 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Peak bone mass has shown to be a good predictor of risk of fracture and osteoporosis, with even a small increase in peak bone mass resulting in a much lower risk of bone fracture.&lt;ref name="hanley"/&gt; Research shows that genetic markers explain only a small proportion of variation in bone mass and risk of fracture.  Therefore, healthy bone programming is most likely influenced by various epigenetic mechanisms, such as imprinting of the growth promoting genes IGF-2, or changes to the [[hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis]] (HPA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 19536660 | doi=10.1007/978-1-4020-9173-5_3 | volume=646 | title=Developmental origins of osteoporosis: the role of maternal nutrition | year=2009 | author=Cooper C, Harvey N, Cole Z, Hanson M, Dennison E | journal=Adv. Exp. Med. Biol. | pages=31–9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Neurodevelopment ====
Imbalances in maternal nutrition can also have a significant effect on fetal [[neurodevelopment]].  Brain development occurs most rapidly during fetal development and infancy, and research has shown that exposure to certain environmental conditions can have long-lasting effects on [[cognition]].  Specifically, n-3 [[fatty acids]], [[iodine]], [[iron]] and [[choline]] have been shown to influence brain development and impact cognitive ability and behavior.  The greatest evidence for a link between nutrition and neurodevelopment comes from studies that show low birth weight associated with low IQ and increased risk of [[schizophrenia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 11159613 | volume=322 | issue=7280 | title=Birth weight and cognitive function in the British 1946 birth cohort: longitudinal population based study | pmc=26584 | date=January 2001 | author=Richards M, Hardy R, Kuh D, Wadsworth ME | journal=BMJ | pages=199–203 | doi=10.1136/bmj.322.7280.199 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 16125903 | doi=10.1016/j.schres.2005.07.022 | volume=79 | issue=2–3 | title=The association of fetal and childhood growth with risk of schizophrenia. Cohort study of 720,000 Swedish men and women | date=November 2005 | author=Gunnell D, Harrison G, Whitley E, Lewis G, Tynelius P, Rasmussen F | journal=Schizophr. Res. | pages=315–22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several studies suggest that breast-feeding promotes long-term neurodevelopment by providing the nutrients necessary for proper brain development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 9478036 | volume=128 | issue=2 Suppl | title=Programming by early nutrition: an experimental approach | date=February 1998 | author=Lucas A | journal=J. Nutr. | pages=401S–406S }}&lt;/ref&gt;  A study in mice showed that choline-deficient diets during the late gestation period impaired fetal brain development, including decreased cell proliferation and reduced visual-spatial and auditory memory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Mehedint MG, Niculescu MD, Craciunescu CN, Zeisel SH | date = Jan 2010 | title = Choline deficiency alters global histone methylation and epigenetic marking at the Re1 site of the calbindin 1 gene | journal = FASEB J | volume = 24 | issue = 1| pages = 184–95 | pmid = 19752176 | doi = 10.1096/fj.09-140145 | pmc = 2797040 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These cognitive changes appeared to be due to altered histone and DNA methylation patterns in the fetal [[hippocampus]], thus providing a link between maternal nutrition, epigenetics, and early brain development.

==== Type-1 diabetes ====
It has been postulated that breast-feeding may also protect against type-1 diabetes, with research showing that formula-fed infants are at an increased risk of developing islet [[autoantibodies]].  Individuals with type-1 diabetes experience a pre-clinical diabetes phase characterized by [[autoimmunity]] against [[pancreatic islets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Eisenbarth GS | year = 1986 | title = Type I diabetes mellitus. A chronic autoimmune disease | url = | journal = N Engl J Med | volume = 314 | issue = 21| pages = 1360–8 | doi = 10.1056/NEJM198605223142106 | pmid = 3517648 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The introduction of certain foods in the first few months of life, such as berries and cereal, is significantly associated with increased risk of islet autoantibody development compared to babies who are exposed to solid foods later in life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Ziegler AG, Schmid S, Huber D, Hummel M, Bonifacio E | year = 2003 | title = Early infant feeding and risk of developing type 1 diabetes-associated autoantibodies | url = | journal = JAMA | volume = 290 | issue = 13| pages = 1721–8 | doi = 10.1001/jama.290.13.1721 | pmid = 14519706 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  While the pathogenesis behind development of autoantibodies remains largely unknown, it is very probable that an epigenetic link exists between perinatal diet and risk of type-1 diabetes.&lt;ref name="hanley"/&gt;

=== Adulthood ===
The majority of research in nutriepigenomics has focused on nutritional imbalances during gestation and lactation periods.  However, foods that are consumed during adulthood can also impact gene expression and disease pathogenesis.  Cancer is the disease most commonly associated with adult nutrition and epigenetic modifications. DNA hypomethelation promotes cancer progression by allowing increased gene transcription, while hypermethylation can silence tumor suppressor genes and further promote uncontrolled [[cell division]] and [[tumor]] formation.  Compounds found in foods, such as [[genistein]] and [[tea polyphenols]], are able to regulate DNA methyltransferases and histone acetylation in cultured cancer cells and may provide protection against certain types of cancer.&lt;ref name="Campion"/&gt;  Other dietary compounds, such as [[diallyl disulfide]] present in garlic and [[sulforaphane]] present in cruciferous vegetables, have been associated with cancer prevention in clinical trials.&lt;ref name="Davis"&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 17345961 | volume=65 | issue=2 | title=Dietary components impact histone modifications and cancer risk | date=February 2007 | author=Davis CD, Ross SA | journal=Nutr. Rev. | pages=88–94 | doi=10.1111/j.1753-4887.2007.tb00285.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This may be due to their ability to inhibit histone deacetylase (HDAC) enzymes and prevent silencing of important regulatory genes.

== Transgenerational effects ==
[[Image:Transgenerational ProteinRestrictdiet.jpg|thumb|upright=1.75|alt=Protein-restricted (PR) diets fed to maternal mice leads to transgenerational effects in the offspring, up to the F3 generation depending on the length of protein restriction. All offspring are adequately fed, i.e. are not on a PR-diet. Grey mice represent wild-type phenotypes and pink mice represent offspring with either a genetic predisposition to hypertension (maternal rat fed PR-diet during pregnancy) or diabetes (maternal rat fed PR-diet during pregnancy and lactation). Mechanisms behind PR-diets are only proposed, as further research is needed to confirm their exact pathways|Transgenerational effects of maternal protein restriction]]
{{main|Transgenerational epigenetics}}

Many believe epigenetic regulation is cleared during the [[fertilization]] process, yet more evidence for transgenerational effects (TGEs) are being revealed.&lt;ref name="Gallou"/&gt; These TGEs take place when the epigenetic regulatory patterns are not sufficiently erased during fertilization, possibly due to nutrition levels in previous generations. Later generations may be affected from caloric and protein restriction, high-fat interventions and endocrine disruption in earlier generations.&lt;ref name="Gallou"/&gt;  Differences within the nutritional behavior of the maternal rat are believed to cause malprogramming in the F1 generation and may then be passed to subsequent generations.&lt;ref name="Gallou"/&gt;   
Maternal rats fed a PR-diet during the entire length of pregnancy led to metabolic-related problems in the F1 and F2 generations, even with normal nutrition during the F1 pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Martin JF, Johnston CR, Han CT, Benyshek DC | year = | title = Nutritional origins of insulin resistance: a rat model for diabetes-prone human populations. 2000 | url = | journal = J Nutr | volume = 130 | issue = 4| pages = 741–44 | pmid = 10736323 | date = April 2000 | doi = 10.1093/jn/130.4.741 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 15860532 | doi=10.1113/jphysiol.2005.086462 | volume=566 | issue=Pt 1 | title=Sex differences in transgenerational alterations of growth and metabolism in progeny (F2) of female offspring (F1) of rats fed a low protein diet during pregnancy and lactation | pmc=1464716 | date=July 2005 | author=Zambrano E, Martínez-Samayoa PM, Bautista CJ | display-authors = etal | journal=J. Physiol. (Lond.) | pages=225–36 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These effects have also been seen in the F3 generation depending on the length of protein restriction.&lt;ref name="Harrison"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Harrison M, Langley-Evans  | year = 2009 | title = Br | journal = J. Nutr. | volume = 101 | issue = 7| pages = 1020–30 | pmid = 18778527 | doi = 10.1017/S0007114508057607 | pmc = 2665257 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Benyshek"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Benyshek DC, Johnston CS, Martin JF | year = | title = Glucose metabolism is altered in the adequately-nourished grand-offspring (F3 generation) of rats malnourished during gestation and perinatal life. 2006 | url = | journal = Diabetologia | volume = 49 | issue = 5| pages = 1117–19 | pmid = 16557373 | doi = 10.1007/s00125-006-0196-5 | date = May 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  If protein restriction occurred solely during pregnancy, the F1 and F2 offspring had higher systolic blood pressure and lower nephron numbers, possibly predisposing them to hypertension.&lt;ref name="Benyshek"/&gt; Altered glucose utilization was detected in the grand-offspring of maternal rats fed a PR-diet during pregnancy and lactation, potentially resulting in diabetes later on in life &lt;ref name="Harrison"/&gt;

Protein-restriction in the F0 generation led to hypomethylation of promoters involved in metabolism in the F1 and F2 generations, even though the F1 pregnant rat was given a normal diet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Burdge GC, Slater-Jefferies J, Torrens C, Phillips ES, Hanson MA, Lillycrop KA | year = | title = Dietary protein restriction of pregnant rats in the F0 generation induces altered methylation of hepatic gene promoters in the adult male offspring in the F1 and F2 generations. 2007 | journal = Br J Nutr | volume = 97 | issue = 3| pages = 435–9 | doi = 10.1017/S0007114507352392 | pmid = 17313703 | pmc = 2211514 | date = March 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The exact mechanism of this situation has yet to be elucidated; however, direct transmission is a distinct possibility, meaning the epigenetic marks were preserved during [[spermatogenesis]] and [[oogenesis]], when they are normally erased.

== Models used in nutriepigenomic studies ==
Most research to date use common rodent models to investigate the role of nutrition on [[phenotype]].&lt;ref name="Simmons"/&gt; Popular areas to investigate include IUGR studies, whereby rodents, and sometimes sheep, are subjected to a variety of nutritional conditions.  A model for studying IUGR in rodent was developed by Simmons ''et al.'' (2010) and is used to investigate type II diabetes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Boloker J, Gertz SJ, Simmons RA | year = | title = Gestational diabetes leads to the development of diabetes in adulthood in the rat. 2002 | url = | journal = Diabetes | volume = 51 | issue = 5| pages = 1499–1506 | pmid = 11978648 | date = May 2002 | doi = 10.2337/diabetes.51.5.1499 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The maternal rats have their uterine arteries ligated, causing altered use of glucose and insulin in the fetus and can therefore serve as a model for diabetes. These growth-retarded rats were found to be highly similar to human fetuses, as they both display symptoms such as lowered glucose and insulin levels.  [[Gestational diabetes]] may also be studied through chemical induction using [[streptozotocin]] treatment of the pregnant rats.&lt;ref name="Fernandez"&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 21070247 | doi=10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05798.x | volume=1212 | title=Early life nutrition and metabolic programming | date=November 2010 | author=Fernandez-Twinn DS, Ozanne SE | journal=Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. | pages=78–96 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Streptozotocin can cause destruction of the beta cells within the pancreas depending on the concentration given.

The predominant means of investigating nutriepigenetics involves varying the nutritional conditions to which a subject is exposed to and monitoring the effects thereafter.  Restricting caloric and protein intake are the two most common methods.&lt;ref name="Fernandez"/&gt; A pregnant rodent may have their caloric intake reduced up to 30-50% of normal intake.  Protein restricted rodents are given 8-9% [[casein]], as opposed to control rats that are fed 20% casein. Micronutrients, such as zinc and iron, may also be restricted to investigate the effects on offspring. Additionally, rats fed diets lacking or including methyl donors are often used to study the effects of diet on epigenomics, as variations within the methylation of DNA are common means of silencing or expressing genes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 12163687 | volume=132 | issue=8 Suppl | title=Diet, methyl donors and DNA methylation: interactions between dietary folate, methionine and choline | date=August 2002 | author=Niculescu MD, Zeisel SH | journal=J. Nutr. | pages=2333S–2335S }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Supplementing maternal mice with folic acid, [[vitamin B12]], choline and [[betaine]] leads to increased levels of DNA methylation at CpG sites and causes a coat color change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Waterland R. A., Jirtle R. L. | year = | title = Transposable elements: targets for early nutritional effects on epigenetic gene regulation. 2003 | journal = Mol. Cell. Biol. | volume = 23 | issue = | pages = 5293–5300 | doi = 10.1128/MCB.23.15.5293-5300.2003 | pmid = 12861015 | pmc = 165709 | date = August 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This is an example of epigenetically modifiable loci called a “metastable epiallele”, of which only a few have been identified.  The above is an example of the “agouti” gene locus, whereby the insertion of a [[transposable element]] upstream to the Agouti gene is hypermethylated from the supplementation and causes a change in the mice's coat color. Diets containing higher carbohydrate and fat content attempt to mimic typical Western-style diets may also be used in nutriepigenetic studies.&lt;ref name="Simmons"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Fernandez"/&gt;  Another method used is “catch-up”, where offspring of rats born to mothers subjected to various diets are subsequently cross-fostered to mothers fed normal diets.&lt;ref name="Fernandez"/&gt;

== Future directions ==
[[Image:FAS Choline.jpg|thumb|upright=1.75|alt=The nutriepigenetic pathway of maternal choline-deficient diets helps to elucidate the development of fetal alcohol syndrome. Pregnant rodents fed diets low in choline were found to give rise to offspring with diminished neurological capacity. This is similar to pregnant rodents whom were fed ethanol and were found to have alterations in the metabolism of 1-carbon compounds. This leads to diminished levels of methyl donors available for methylating DNA; thus allowing for overexpression of normally silenced genes causing neurological defects in their offspring.|The nutriepigenetic pathway of maternal choline-deficient diets helps to elucidate the development of fetal alcohol syndrome]]
The possibilities of utilizing nutriepigenomics for intervention are quite expansive.  This can include preventative therapies, such as providing an optimal regime for nutrition during pregnancy and lactation.&lt;ref name="Fernandez"/&gt;  It is already common place for pregnant mothers to supplement their diets with choline and folate to prevent the development of neurological disabilities in the fetus.

A highly specific diet, termed an "EpiG diet," may be employed for an individual believed to be at higher risk of developing a metabolic disorder.&lt;ref name="Gallou"/&gt; These diets may include supplementation with methyl donors, such as folate. There are also many other natural compounds, such as [[resveratrol]], [[curcumin]] and green tea that have been termed “epigenetic modifiers”, as they have anti-cancer capabilities in addition to being used as treatments for metabolic diseases.&lt;ref name="Sziv"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Sziv KS, Ndlovu MN, Haegeman G, Vanden Berghe W | year = | title = Nature or nurture: let food be your epigenetic medicine in chronic inflammatory disorders. 2010 | url = | journal = Biochem. Pharmacol. | volume = 80 | issue = 12| pages = 1816–32 | doi = 10.1016/j.bcp.2010.07.029 | pmid = 20688047 | date = December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the functions of these compounds still require long-term studies to evaluate their effect over time.

There also exists potential for therapeutic treatments that may correct metabolic disorders, such as type II diabetes.&lt;ref name="Fernandez"/&gt;  Components of garlic and [[cruciferous vegetables]] are known to possess [[HDAC inhibitors]] that modify the acetylation of histone proteins and may contain a protection against cancer.&lt;ref name="Davis"/&gt;  These same compounds have also been implicated in [[irritable bowel syndrome]] (IBS) and [[colon cancer]], as they may modify the histones normally implicated in these diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Barnett M, Bermingham E, McNabb W, Bassett S, Armstrong K, Rounce J, Roy N | year = | title = Investigating micronutrients and epigenetic mechanisms in relation to inflammatory bowel disease | url = | journal = Mutat. Res. | volume = 690 | issue = 1| pages = 71–80 | doi = 10.1016/j.mrfmmm.2010.02.006 | pmid = 20188748 | date = August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Elucidation of disease pathways is another future direction for nutriepigenomic studies.  For example, choline-deficient diets and alcohol metabolism during pregnancy may have very similar metabolic pathways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Zeisel S | year = 2011 | title = What Choline Metabolism Can Tell Us About the Underlying Mechanisms of Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders | url = | journal = Mol. Neurobiol. | volume =  44| issue = | pages =  185–91| doi = 10.1007/s12035-011-8165-5 | pmid = 21259123 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, animal studies using choline-restricted diets may assist in investigations of [[fetal alcohol spectrum disorders]].

When compared to studies of maternal transmission, investigations into the role of paternal diets are lacking.  A review demonstrated the nutrition of both parents do in fact play a role in determining the health of their offspring.&lt;ref name="Ferguson"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Ferguson-Smith AC, Patti ME | year = 2011 | title = You are what your dad ate | url = | journal = Cell Metab | volume = 13 | issue = 2| pages = 115–7 | doi = 10.1016/j.cmet.2011.01.011 | pmid = 21284975 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[germ-line]] study reported paternal rats fed a high-fat diet led to insulin dysfunction in the F1 offspring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Ng S.F., Lin R.C., Laybutt D.R., Barres R., Owens J.A., Morris M.J. | year = | title = Chronic high-fat diet in fathers programs β-cell dysfunction in female rat offspring. 2010 | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 467 | issue = | pages = 963–966 | doi = 10.1038/nature09491 | pmid = 20962845 | date = October 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  While this likely occurs via epigenetic modifications similar to those postulated in the maternal diets, the exact mechanism remains to be defined.  Assessing the role of epigenetic mechanisms may be easier using paternal inheritance, as sperm transmits epigenetic and genetic information, whereas the female cells also transmit [[mitochondrial DNA]].&lt;ref name="Ferguson"/&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|small=yes}}
*[[Epigenetics]]
*[[Epigenome]]
*[[Epigenomics]]
*[[Genome]]
*[[Molecular epidemiology]] 
*[[Molecular pathological epidemiology]]
*[[Nutritional epidemiology]]
{{Div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2|refs=

}}

[[Category:Nutrition]]
[[Category:Epigenetics]]</text>
      <sha1>e5n5pnob7o9pdgmycaif5rchq83d8dy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
