<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lazy Jones</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2128758</id>
    <revision>
      <id>958289713</id>
      <parentid>957867545</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-22T23:39:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Filedelinkerbot</username>
        <id>20611691</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: Removing [[:File:David Whittaker - Lazy Jones.ogg]] , deleted by [[:User:Explicit|Explicit]] (Expired [[WP:PROD|PROD]], concern was: Video game ''[[Lazy Jones]]'' using this track, song "[[Kernkraft 400]]" sampling this recording, and the music style [[chiptune]] already well conveyed by their own respective articles using this file. Deleting this file wouldn't affect such understanding in any way; description about such music already understood, even when brief. Fails [[WP:NFCC#8]]. Fre...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9167" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox video game
|title = Lazy Jones
|image =[[File:Lazy Jones.jpg|200px|Lazy Jones]]
|caption = Commodore 64 cover art
|developer = David Whittaker
|publisher = Terminal Software
|designer = [[David Whittaker (video game composer)|David Whittaker]]
|composer = David Whittaker
|engine = Proprietary
|released = 1984
|genre = [[Platform game]]
|modes = [[Single-player video game|Single-player]]
|platforms = [[Commodore 64|C64]], [[ZX Spectrum]], [[MSX]], [[Tatung Einstein]]
}}

[[File:Lazy Jones Screenshot.png|thumb|Screenshot from the Commodore 64 version.]]
'''''Lazy Jones''''' is a [[computer game]] for the [[Commodore 64]], [[ZX Spectrum]], [[MSX]] and [[Tatung Einstein]]. It was written by [[David Whittaker (video game composer)|David Whittaker]] and released by Terminal Software in 1984. The Spectrum version was [[Porting|ported]] by Simon Cobb.

''Lazy Jones'' is essentially a collection of fifteen smaller [[sub-game]]s. The game takes place inside a [[hotel]] with three floors, connected by an [[elevator]]. The character is a lazy hotel employee who does not much care for his work, but prefers to sneak into the rooms to play [[video game]]s instead.

The main screen in ''Lazy Jones'' is the hotel interior. There, the character can use the elevator to travel freely between the three floors, but he must watch out for enemies: the current hotel manager on the top floor, the [[ghost]] of the previous manager on the bottom floor, and a haunted cleaning cart on the middle floor. The enemies only walk around and do not pursue the character, but contact with them is fatal.

Each floor has six rooms, three on each side of the elevator. Each room can be entered once. Inside most rooms is a video game, which the character immediately begins playing. As well as the video games, there is the hotel [[bar (establishment)|bar]], a [[bed (furniture)|bed]], a cleaning closet and a [[toilet]]. The bar works like a video game, but the bed, the cleaning closet and the toilet are useless decorations (intentionally added, because Whittaker had run out of ideas for new games).

When all rooms have been visited, the game starts over again, but increasingly faster, each time.

One of the tracks of ''Lazy Jones'''s soundtrack was sampled by German electro project [[Zombie Nation (musician)|Zombie Nation]] for their 1999 hit single "[[Kernkraft 400]]".&lt;ref name="nme"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nme.com/NME/External/News/News_Story/0,1004,9126,00.html |title=Internet Archive Wayback Machine |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2001-06-30 |accessdate=2012-09-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010630145207/http://www.nme.com/NME/External/News/News_Story/0%2C1004%2C9126%2C00.html |archivedate=30 June 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sub-games==
The plot of the game is simple- a hotel care taker named Jones is bored and decides to go in the rooms and play games.

The various sub-games are generally simplified versions of famous 1970s and 1980s video games, such as ''[[Space Invaders]]'', ''[[Frogger]]'', ''[[Snake (video game)|Snake]]'', ''[[H.E.R.O. (video game)|H.E.R.O.]]'', [[Breakout (video game)|Breakout]] or ''[[Chuckie Egg]]''. Their plots and gameplay are very simple, and in most of them the player simply must avoid incoming enemies long enough to score many points. In some, the player must shoot enemies to score points.

Whittaker developed each sub-game individually in [[BASIC]] first, to make sure they worked, then converted each one of them, almost line by line, into [[Assembly Language|Assembly]] code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.c64.com/interviews/whittaker.html |title=David Whittaker Interview |publisher=C64.COM |accessdate=2015-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each sub-game has a time limit. In some sub-games it is possible to "die", thus ending the sub-game prematurely, while others only end after the time limit expires. But this also depends of the portrayed game version. While a "death" in the Commodore 64 may return the game character to a certain point in the screen, in the MSX version the same death results in the premature end of the sub-game.

The fourteen video games are as follows:
* ''99 Red Balloons'': Red [[balloon]]s continuously fly towards the top of the screen. You have to grab hold of two balloons to fly upwards, to get to kiss a woman. Then you need to grab hold of one balloon to fly back down to kiss another woman. A [[bow (weapon)|bow]] tries to shoot [[arrow]]s to puncture your balloons.
* ''Eggie Chuck'': A simplified ''Chuckie Egg'' clone.
* ''Jay Walk'': A simplified ''Frogger'' clone. You have to cross a street without hitting any of the cars, to get to kiss a woman. Then you cross the street back to kiss another woman.
* ''Laser Jones'': A ''Space Invaders'' clone where the aliens do not shoot back.
* ''Outland'': A very simple [[shoot 'em up]]. [[starship|Spaceship]]s descend from the skies and you can shoot them to score points.
* ''Res Q'': A simplified ''[[H.E.R.O. (video game)|H.E.R.O.]]'' clone. A game of skill where you have to rescue men trapped in a [[cave]] without touching the cave walls.
* ''Scoot'': A game of skill where you have to steer some kind of hovercraft in a cave.
* ''Star Dust'': A shoot 'em up where you can shoot balls of dust.
* ''The Hills Are Alive'': A shoot 'em up very similar to ''Outland'' except this time the spaceships fly horizontally.
* ''The Reflex'': [[Bone]]s fly down from the top of the screen and you have to bounce them back up.
* ''The Turk'': One of the strangest settings. Roast [[turkey (bird)|turkey]]s slide on a [[conveyor belt]] and you have to fire a [[fork]] at them to score points. A [[telephone]] flies diagonally around the screen, getting in the way of your fork.
* ''The Wall'': A simplified ''Snake'' clone. You must steer a continuously growing garden wall without hitting yourself, the screen boundaries, or any of the plants.
* ''Wild Wafers'': A shoot 'em up where you can shoot spinning wafers.
* ''Wipeout'': A simplified [[Breakout clone|''Breakout'' clone]].

In the MSX and Tatung Einstein versions, ''Jay Walk'' is replaced by ''Wafers II'', in which the player uses two controlled spaceships (one vertically and one horizontally) to jointly hit the spinning wafers.

In the hotel bar, your character stands in front of the (rather wide) bar. The barman and the only other patron, hopelessly drunk, are both moving back and forth across the bar, at different speeds. Pressing the fire button while standing in front of both a drink and the barman at the same time earns you points. The drunk patron bars your movement but can be jumped over.

The sub-games where it is possible to "die" prematurely are ''Eggie Chuck'', ''Jay Walk'', ''Res Q'' and ''The Wall''.

The sub-games that only end when the time limit runs out are ''99 Red Balloons'', ''Laser Jones'', ''Outland'', ''Scoot'', ''Star Dust'', ''The Hills Are Alive'', ''The Reflex'', ''The Turk'', ''Wild Wafers'', ''Wipeout'', ''Wafers II'' and the hotel bar.

(In the MSX version, sub-games ending exclusively by running out of time limit: ''Outland'', ''The Reflex'', ''Wild Wafers'', ''Wafers II'', ''Wipeout'' and the bar).

==Music==
{{Listen
|filename=
|title=''Lazy Jones'' - "Star Dust" (1984)
|description="Star Dust", from the Commodore 64 game ''Lazy Jones''.{{deletable image-caption|Friday, 22 May 2020|PROD}}
}}
The game's [[chiptune]] [[video game music|music]] has a very characteristic sound that is distinct from many other C64 games. Each of the 21 subtunes is using only two voices of the [[SID chip]] which in turn use the same sawtooth sound. One voice plays a simple octave bassline for the most part, while the other one is adding the melody. All the tunes share the same tempo as well and they change seamlessly when playing another sub game.

Associations of subtunes to sub-games vary depending of the portrayed computer version, so a subtune used in the Commodore 64 version to a certain sub-game was not necessarily used as soundtrack to the same sub-game in the MSX version (see example below).

Subtune 21, named "Star Dust" (in the MSX version, soundtrack to ''The Wall'' sub-game), was used by the German producer team [[Zombie Nation (band)|Zombie Nation]] in their song [[Kernkraft 400]]. Florian Senfter ("Splank!") later paid an undisclosed sum to David Whittaker for the use of the melody.&lt;ref name="nme"/&gt;

The tune and title for 99 Red Balloons comes from the English name of the song [[99 Luftballons]] by German songstress Nena. (This having been the version which reached #1 on the [[UK Singles Chart|UK singles chart]]).

Visage's "Fade to Grey" is also heard.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{moby game|id=/lazy-jones|name=''Lazy Jones''}}
*{{WoS game|id=0002836}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2010}}

[[Category:Commodore 64 games]]
[[Category:ZX Spectrum games]]
[[Category:MSX games]]
[[Category:Tatung Einstein games]]
[[Category:Platform games]]
[[Category:1984 video games]]
[[Category:Video games scored by David Whittaker]]
[[Category:Video games about video games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>6c1pqx5b3r280iq0pqc6nfwbfusvn96</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
