<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Timeline of Steve Jobs media</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37656556</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936633844</id>
      <parentid>923910689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-20T01:49:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Spintendo</username>
        <id>3465809</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixing style/layout errors [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Fix common mistakes]] in/in</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="42505" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
[[Steve Jobs]] (February 24, 1955 – October 5, 2011) appeared in numerous speaking engagements, interviews, media appearances, and product introductions throughout his life. He spoke about a vast array of subjects including technology, entrepreneurship, society, philosophy, education, communication, movies, music, television, role models, industry, etc.

==Interviews, appearances, and speaking engagements==

{{TOCyears|startyear=1980|step=1|endyear=2011}}

{|class="wikitable sortable"
|-

! style="width:5%;" | Year
! style="width:10%;" | City
! style="width:30%;" class="unsortable"| Occasion
! style="width:15%;" class="unsortable"| Media
! style="width:40%;" class="unsortable"| Subject Matter
|-

&lt;!-- 1980 --&gt;
{{anchor|1980}}

|-
|1980
|
|Presentation donated to [[Computer History Museum]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Computer History Museum - Steve Jobs|url=http://www.computerhistory.org/atchm/steve-jobs/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0lvMgMrNDlg Video]
|
* Tools to amplify human ability. Computer is a bicycle for the mind
* [[VisiCalc]]
* Early word processors
* Computing in education
* Ease of use
* Ratio of computers to users
* Interactive software
* Interactive video
* The future of Apple Computer
* Computing power applied to ease of use
* Origin of Apple Computer name
* Differences between hardware and software
* Obsolescence
* 500 employees
* Sales dollars per employee
* Maintaining creativity in the long term

|-
|1980
|[[Cork (city)|Cork]], Ireland
|[[RTÉ]] Interview
|[https://web.archive.org/web/20120329195545/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5Gsky67O5NY Video]
|
* [[Apple II]] on the [[Space Shuttle]]

&lt;!-- 1981 --&gt;
{{anchor|1981}}

|-
|1981
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|[[CBS Evening News]]; [[Barry Petersen]] interview
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UZCu2D_T9OU Video]
|
* Life is seducing you into learning calculators, [[Automated teller machine|ATMs]], and now desktop computers
* It is not a [[Nineteen_Eighty-Four|Nineteen eighty-four]]-ish vision
* It's going to be very gradual and very human

|-
|1981
|
|[[Nightline]]; [[Ted Koppel]]
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3H-Y-D3-j-M Video]
|
*Invasion of privacy
*Computer literacy
*Children learning to use computers

|-
|1981
|[[Cupertino, California|Cupertino]], CA
|[[ABC News]]; Ken Kashiwahara
|
*[http://abcnews.go.com/Technology/video/steve-jobs-rise-silicon-valley-1981-38001792 Video (ABC News)]
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WtuJR2bzIO0 Video (YouTube)]
|
*Silicon Valley's entrepreneurial risk culture
*"The penalty for failure, for going and trying to start a company in this Valley is nonexistent. There really isn't a penalty for failure either psychologically or economically in the sense that, if you have a good idea and you go out to start your own company, even if you fail, you're generally considered worth more to the company you left because you've gained all this valuable experience, in many disciplines."

&lt;!-- 1982 --&gt;
{{anchor|1982}}
|-
|1982
|
|[[Academy of Achievement]]
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=APsrUE57GhA Audio]
|
*Money does not define success
*To be intelligent is to have a bird's eye view of the city while others are navigating the streets below.
*The key to making connections that lead to innovation is to have a collection of out of the ordinary experiences to draw from.
*Bright people are corralled onto a beaten path. Consider alternative paths.
*Visit a [[Third World|third world country]]
*Fall in love with two people at once
*[[Walt Disney]] took [[LSD]] once and that's where the idea for [[Fantasia (1940 film)|Fantasia]] came from.
*A variety of experiences will enable unique solutions.
*Don't walk by a [[Zen|Zen Buddhist]], buy him lunch.
*The people that run the world aren't that different from you
*The most ecstatic feeling is to give back to the pool of human innovation which we have all benefited from.
*You inherit the responsibility to be a guardian of the earth. 

&lt;!-- 1983 --&gt;
{{anchor|1983}}

|-
|1983
|[[Aspen, Colorado]]
|International Design Conference in Aspen (IDCA) - 'The Future Isn't What It Used To Be' keynote
|
* [https://soundcloud.com/mbtech_1434547055436/talk-by-steven-jobs-idca-1983 Audio (Soundcloud)]
* [https://archive.org/details/Talk-by-Steven-Jobs-IDCA-1983 Audio (Archive.org)]
|
* Computers are only 36 years old
* Kids growing up now will be part of the computer generation
* Computers are simple, adaptive, and fast
* The oldest person with a degree in Computer Science is 39
* Computers are very fast. They run a million instructions per second
* Programmers build a collection of low level instructions into higher level instructions
* Early electric motors of the late 1890s initially were large thus were applied to large scale applications. They didn't proliferate quickly
* Later electric motors drove a shaft through a factory to empower multiple workstations simultaneously
* The fractional horsepower electric motor was a breakthrough because it was applied to small individual applications
* There are approximately 55 fractional horsepower motors in every household
* The history of computers parallels the history of electric motors
* [[ENIAC]] the first computer, was giant, hardly anyone got a chance to use it
* A 1960s computing breakthrough was [[Time-sharing]]. Many people could share a large computer e.g. on a college campus
* "The reason Apple exists is because we stumbled on to the fractional horsepower computer 5 years before anybody else."
* "We made a computer that was about 13 pounds"
* The first PC was invented in 1976. In 1983 the industry will ship 3 million personal computers
* By 1986, we will ship more computers than automobiles in the USA
* "...I need your help. If you've looked at computers, they all look like garbage. All of the great product designers are off designing automobiles/buildings but hardly any of them are designing computers."
* The industry will sell 10 million computers whether they look ugly or great because people are going to be spellbound/elated
* "It doesn't cost any more money to make it look great"
* They are going to be these new objects that are going to be in everyone's working environment, educational environment, and home environment
* "We have a shot at putting a great object there (work, school, home) and if we don't, we are going to put one more piece of junk object there"
* By 1986 people will be spending two or three hours a day interacting with computers
* Industrial design, the software design should be given the same consideration that we give automobiles if not a lot more
* "Most of the objects of our life are not designed in America. We've blown it"
* "Computers and society are out on a first date in the 80s."
* "We have a chance to make these things beautiful. We have a chance to communicate something through the design of the objects themselves."
* Apple alone will spend over 100 million dollars over the next 12 months on media advertising. [[IBM]] will spend at least that amount
* The personal computer is a new medium of communication. One of the media. e.g. books, radio, television, newspapers
* Computer communication is different from other mediums. Telephone demands both parties of a conversation be simultaneously present. Computers do not have this requirement.
* "One of these days when we have portable computers with radio links, they can be walking around Aspen and retrieve it. (e-mail)"
* "The process of communication changes as the mediums evolve."
* When a new media emerges, we tend to fall back into old media habits
* The first TV shows are basically radio shows with a television camera pointed at them
* It took the better part of the 1950s for television to come 'into its own' as a medium
* [[John F. Kennedy]] funeral television broadcast gave people a level of intensity that would not have been possible with radio
* The [[Apollo program]] landing. That experience was not possible with the previous medium
* It took 20 years for television to evolve away from radio
* "Optical video discs" ([[Laserdisc]]) can store 55 thousand images on a side, or an hour of video randomly accessible. What are we using it for? Movies. We're dropping back into old media habits."
* 5 to 10 years from now, random access storage will 'come into its own'
* 1979 [[MIT]] experiment, [[Aspen Movie Map]]. A precursor of [[Google Street View]] is stored on [[laserdisc]] and reveals that random access storage will differentiate itself from other media
* We are still running historic applications on personal computers e.g. business accounting, [[COBOL]]
* [[Apple Lisa]] enables a person with little talent to draw artistic pictures, transmit them via e-mail
* Computer programs are an idea expressed on paper. They enable thousands of individual experiences based on one set of underlying principles
* [[Hamurabi]] video game. 7 year old kids are playing with a macro economic model. Interactive learning
* Books were a way to learn without an intermediary teacher. "The problem was, you can't ask [[Aristotle]] a question."
* Maybe in the next 50 to 100 years we will enable computer to capture an individual's underlying spirit, set of principles, world so that after they are gone we can ask the computer a question and receive an answer consistent with that individual
* Ultimately computers are going to be used for communication and over the next 5 years the standards for interconnecting computers are going to evolve. They all speak different languages right now.
* Early [[Xerox PARC]] [[Local Area Network]] list server revealed special interest groups in the office. Soon there were more interest groups than there were employees.
* As computers are networked (on the internet), they will facilitate the creation of special interest groups and bring together the people in those groups. ([[Social Networking]])
* Office [[Local Area Network]] are about 5 years away
* Home [[Local Area Network]] are about 10 to 15 years away
* "We want to put an incredibly great computer in a book that you can carry around with you, that you can learn how to use in 20 minutes. That's what we want to do. And we want to do it this decade. And we really want to do it with a radio link in it so that you dont have to hook up to anything. So you are in communication with all of these larger databases and other computers."
* Apple sets out "To design the computer that we want to put into the book eventually even though we cannot put it into the book now and it's called [[Apple Lisa|Lisa]]."
* [[Apple Lisa]] is sold out for the first year
* Eventually we will get to the point where people can create images as good as any other way.

|-
|1983
|[[Hawaii]]
|Apple Sales meeting
|
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lSiQA6KKyJo Video (YouTube)] 
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140103095022/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lSiQA6KKyJo Video (Archive.org)]
|
* In 1958 [[IBM]] fails to buy [[Xerox]]
* 1968 IBM dismisses the [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]] minicomputer as too small
* 1977 Apple invents the [[Apple II]], the first personal computer
* IBM dismisses the personal computer as too small
* 1981 [[Apple II]] is the world's most popular computer
* Apple grows to a $300 million corporation, fastest growing corporation in American history
* November 1981 IBM introduces the IBM PC
* 1983 Apple and IBM computer industry's strongest competitors
* 1983 Apple and IBM each sell $1 billion in personal computers
* First major computer firm goes bankrupt. Total computer industry losses are larger than combined profits of Apple and IBM
* 1984 Apple and IBM each invest $50 million in R&amp;D 
* 1984 Apple and IBM each invest $50 million in TV advertising
* 1984 computer dealers fear an IBM dominated marketplace
* Was [[George Orwell]] right about 1984?
* First presentation of the [[1984 (advertisement)|'1984' TV advertisement]]
* Advertisement will run one week before Macintosh is introduced
* [[Jay Chiat]] the principle of [[TBWA\Chiat\Day|Chiat Day]] is in the audience
* [[Lee Clow]] and [[Steve Hayden]] (wrote the [[Copywriting|ad copy]]) are in the audience

&lt;!-- 1984 --&gt;
{{anchor|1983}}

|-
|1984
|[[Boston]]
|[[Boston Computer Society]] 
|[http://time.com/1847/steve-jobs-mac/ Video]
|
&lt;!-- 1985 --&gt;
{{anchor|1985}}

|-
|1985
|
|[[Playboy]] Magazine Interview&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Playboy Interview: Moguls|publisher=Amazon Digital Services, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130508054927/http://www.txtpost.com/playboy-interview-steven-jobs/ Transcript 1]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20141114114205/http://longform.org/stories/playboy-interview-steve-jobs Transcript 2]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20141114114205/http://longform.org/stories/playboy-interview-steve-jobs Transcript 3] 
|
* Wealth
* Idealism of the 1960s
* Petrochemical Revolution brought free mechanical energy
* Information Revolution brought free intellectual energy
* Users don't need to understand the principles of a machine
* [[Socratic method|Socratic education]]
* "The most compelling reason for most people to buy a computer for the home will be to link it into a nationwide communications network."
* [[Alexander Graham Bell]]
* [[Telegraphy|Telegraph]] took 40 hours to learn
* [[Macintosh]] hardware took more than two years to design
* Good [[Public relations|PR]] educates people
* Apple and [[IBM]] as computing standards
* Merging of the telephone and the personal computer
* Apple's roots are selling to people not [[Fortune 500|Fortune 500s]]
* Strategic mistakes of the [[Apple Lisa|Lisa]] computer division
* Jobs was inexperienced at running a company
* Sorrow over internal disagreements about the vision 
* The Macintosh represents Jobs' unrealized vision for the Lisa: a computer for people not corporations
* 'Insanely great' people make 'insanely great' products for themselves, to their own highest standard
* The Macintosh group wanted to build the greatest computer that has ever been seen
* The IBM PC group lacked pride in their product and were motivated by money
* Average age of Apple employees is 29
* Most people in their 30s and 40s get stuck in their thought processes with rare exceptions
* "Companies, as they grow to become multibillion-dollar entities, somehow lose their vision. They insert lots of layers of middle management between the people running the company and the people doing the work."
* "Apple is an [[Ellis Island]] company. Apple is built on refugees from other companies. These are the extremely bright individual contributors who were troublemakers at other companies."
* [[Edwin H. Land|Dr. Edwin Land]] (founder of [[Polaroid Corporation|Polaroid]]) saw the intersection of art and science and business and built an organization to reflect that
* "...Dr. Land one of those brilliant troublemakers, was asked to leave his own company‐‑which is one of the dumbest things I’ve ever heard of."
* A visionary that brings together art and science is the most important thing to be, not a football player or astronaut
* In 5 to 10 years [[John Sculley]] and Jobs intend to make Apple a 10 or 20 billion dollar company 
* That scale is merely to remain competitive. The bigger concern is how that scale is achieved.
* Apple hires people that want to make large contributions today not await permission to do so years from now. 
* People/workers rarely get to contribute to the pool of innovation which we all rely upon.
* Rather than focus on [[Fortune 500]] customers, focus on how to change how small groups/businesses work.
* There should not be one computing standard. Macintosh is clearly better than IBM. Innovation emerges via competition.
* IBM will eventually crush companies that are compatible with their systems
* To reach tens of millions of people, a computer that is significantly different from IBM is needed. Hence Macintosh.
* IBM believes in service, support, security, [[Mainframe computer|mainframes]], and 'motherhood'. 
* "Apple’s key observation three years ago was that when you’re shipping 10,000,000 computers a year, even IBM does not have enough mothers to ship one with every computer. So you’ve got to build motherhood into the computer."
* If Apple makes a mistake and IBM wins, the world will enter a computer [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]] for 20 years.
* [[Frito-Lay]], a company that dominates a market via service and support and stifles newcomers in their market.
* IBM dominated and therefore did not innovate in the [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]] industry for 15 years.
* The IBM platform is a repackaging of dated [[Apple II]] level technology
* Apple and IBM won't have much competition in the hardware space. The days of significant hardware start-ups are gone.
* New, innovative companies will focus on software.

|-
|1985
|[[Svaneholm Castle]], Sweden
|Apple University Consortium Europe, [[Lund University]] with [[:sv:Håkan Westling|Håkan Westling]]
|
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2qLuerYx2IA Video (YouTube)]
* [https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/prominent-guests-at-lund-university/id491028102 Video (iTunes)]
* [http://www.macpublic.ldc.lu.se/news/files/jobs-lu-85.mov Video (Quicktime)]
|
* Computers can revolutionize education
* Cooperation of European universities
* Computer is a new medium among print, television, and radio
* Initially, new mediums are based on old mediums
* [[Aristotle]] was [[Alexander the Great|Alexander the Great's]] tutor
* Petrochemical Revolution
* Information Revolution
* Free intellectual energy from computers
* Computers will enable us to interact with Aristotles of the future
* [[Henry Ford]]
* "The automobile had a historical imperative"
* Computers will forever change education as soon as 5 years from now
* Jobs' dream is to sell Macintoshes to the [[Soviet Union]]

|-
|1985
| [[Redwood City]], CA and [[Pebble Beach]], CA
|'Entrepreneurs' documentary
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=loQhufxiorM Video]
|
* [[NeXT Computer]] logo
* Building a company
* Leadership/communicating the vision
* Product price
* Delivery window
* Financing/Expenses

&lt;!-- 1988 --&gt;
{{anchor|1988}}
|-
|1988
|[[Redwood City]], CA
|[[NeXTStep]] demonstration of [[MIDI]] and quotation application
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iTFFimZnlaU Video]
|
&lt;!-- 1990 --&gt;
{{anchor|1990}}

|-
|{{Circa|1990s|sortable=yes}}
|
|'An Immigrant's Gift' documentary interview
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XbkMcvnNq3g Video]
|
* [[Joseph M. Juran|Joe Juran]]

|-
|1990
|
|[http://www.mlfilms.com/productions/m_and_i Memory &amp; Imagination: New Pathways to the Library of Congress] with [[Stewart Brand]]
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6kalMB8jDnY Video]
|
* [[Library of Congress]]
* We shouldn't build too many more libraries, instead we should connect towns to the internet to provide access to the Library of Congress
* [[Video Game|Video Games]] as simulated learning environments
* The computer is the equivalent of a bicycle for our minds

|-
|1990
|
|Interview with [[WGBH-TV]]
|[https://web.archive.org/web/20140103163339/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2nMD6sjAe8I Video]
|
* Computer as bicycle for the mind
* [[VisiCalc]] Spreadsheet
* [[Desktop Publishing]]
* 'Interpersonal computing' - Computing applied to communication and collaboration
* [[NASA]] computers
* Factory automation
* [[ARPANET]] Computing in higher education
* Computer literacy in K-12. Not enough courseware.
* Completing the Macintosh
* Employees as artists
* Networking islands of computers
* Programmer productivity
* Computers in every home
* Multimedia as a means not an end to communication
* [[Douglas Englebart]] at [[SRI International|SRI]]
* [[Xerox PARC]]
* Computing power applied to ease of use
* Ambiguity of science and art. Mathematics as a liberal art
* Thinking vs. doing
* Death is the best invention of life
* [[Homebrew Computer Club]] at [[Stanford University|Stanford]]
* [[Blue box|Blue Box]]
* [[Steve Wozniak]]
* Atlantic City computer show
* [[West Coast Computer Faire]], San Francisco
* [[Regis McKenna]]
* [[Mike Markkula]]
* Non-incremental innovations

|-
|1990
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|NeXTstation Keynote
|
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pijt0_bdmUs Video Part 1]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3vxLpLSKV0M Video Part 2]
|
* [[NeXTstep]] 2.0
* [[NeXTstation]]
* [[NeXTcube]] 68040
* Custom applications with [[Interface Builder]]
* 'Interpersonal computing'
* [[Fax]]
* [[alpha compositing]]
* [[NeXTdimension]]
* [[NeXTstation]] Color

&lt;!-- 1991 --&gt;
{{anchor|1991}}

|-
|1991
|[[Redwood City]], CA
|NeXT internal marketing strategy video
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KRBIH0CA7ZU Video]
|

|-
|1991
|[[Portland, Oregon]]
|[[Reed College]] [[Howard Vollum Award]] acceptance speech
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KYpmTYs8rm0 Audio (YouTube)]
*[https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/convocation-audio/id391853261?mt=10 Audio (iTunes)] (with intro by [[Richard Crandall]])
|
*I never graduated from [[Reed College]]
*[[Roman Meal]] is the cheapest way to live
*Several of us would show up for meals at the [[International_Society_for_Krishna_Consciousness|Hare Krishna]] temple
*[[Situational ethics]]
*Reed College dean Jack Dudman&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beloved dean played key role in the life of Steve Jobs.|url=http://www.reed.edu/reed_magazine/in-memoriam/obituaries/november2008/john-almon-dudman-1942.html|website=Reed Magazine|accessdate=6 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Generosity
*Character is built not in good times but in bad times

&lt;!-- 1992 --&gt;
{{anchor|1992}}
|-
|1992
|[[Cambridge,_Massachusetts|Cambridge]], MA
|[[MIT_Sloan_School_of_Management|MIT Sloan]] Distinguished Speaker Series
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gk-9Fd2mEnI Video]
|

&lt;!-- 1993 --&gt;
{{anchor|1993}}

|-
|1993
|[[Redwood City]], CA
| Interview on Paul Rand
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xb8idEf-Iak Video]
|
* [[Paul Rand]]
* [[Logo]]s
* Working relationship with clients

&lt;!-- 1994 --&gt;
{{anchor|1994}}
|-
|1994
|[[Redwood City]], CA
| Steve Jobs in 1994: The [[Rolling Stone]] Interview
|[https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/news/steve-jobs-in-1994-the-rolling-stone-interview-20110117 Text] 
|

|-
|1994
|
|[http://www.siliconvalleyhistorical.org/ Santa Clara Valley Historical Society] Silicon Valley Documentary
|
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140515200559/http://www.siliconvalleyhistorical.org/home/steve_jobs_secrets_of_life#!steve-jobs-film/c1x1c Santa Clara Valley Historical Society - Steve Jobs: Visionary Entrepreneur (Archive.org)]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zkTf0LmDqKI Video Clip 1]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HFURM8O-oYI Video Clip 2]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kYfNvmF0Bqw Video Clip 3]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vk8HYHngzds Video Clip 4]
|
* [[William Redington Hewlett|Bill Hewlett]]
* Failure
* Changing the world
* [[Blue box|Blue Box]]

&lt;!-- 1995 --&gt;
{{anchor|1995}}

|-
|1995
|[[Redwood City]], CA
|[[Steve_Jobs:_The_Lost_Interview|Steve Jobs: 'The Lost Interview']]; [[Robert X. Cringely]]
|
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CW0DUg63lqU Video Clip]
|

|-
|1995
|[[Redwood City]], CA
|[[Smithsonian Institution|Smithsonian]] Oral History Project Interview
|
* [http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9220609/Steve_Jobs_interview_One_on_one_in_1995 Transcript]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121122161607/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rWDvKjdu-_4&amp;gl=US&amp;hl=en Video]
|
* [[John F. Kennedy]]
* [[Cuban Missile Crisis]]
* [[Heathkit]]s
* Jobs' childhood and schooling
* Public education
* Unions in education
* Mentors vs. Computers in education
* [[School voucher]]s
* Monopolies
* Choice in a marketplace vs. choice in schools
* Firing substandard employees
* 'Amplifying your values a million to one'
* On being an artist
* Microsoft, a monopoly, is limiting creativity
* [[John Sculley]] corrupting Apple's values
* Rational profits vs. corporate greed
* "The Macintosh will die..." "...how to create the next Macintosh, no one at Apple has a clue..."
* [[Hewlett-Packard 9100A]]
* Congressman [[Pete Stark]] and Senator [[John Danforth]]
* The Kids Can't Wait Bill
* Met two-thirds of the House and over half of the Senate
* Congressman's vs. Senator's ability to think
* [[Bob Dole]] blocked bill that would have facilitated Apple to donate 100,000 computers to schools
* Bill succeeds in California, Apple donates 10,000 computers to schools
* Advantages of NeXT hardware and software
* [[PARC (company)|Xerox PARC]] in 1979. [[GUI]], [[Object-oriented programming]], and [[Computer network|Networking]]
* [[Simula]] and [[Smalltalk]]
* [[Internet]] and the [[World Wide Web]]
* [[Net neutrality]]
* California at the leading edge of a cultural shift
* [[Pixar]], [[Lucasfilm]], [[George Lucas]]
* Analog [[generation loss]]
* Discusses [[Toy Story]] pre-release
* "Will there ever be another software platform?" Yes
* Death is the greatest invention of life
* Start-up company's advantage is that large companies are sedentary
* Passion required to start a company
* Why Silicon Valley is a hub of innovation
* [[Beat Generation]]
* Rock and Roll in California [[Joan Baez]], [[Grateful Dead]], [[Janis Joplin]], [[Jefferson Airplane]], [[Jimi Hendrix]]
* [[Stanford]] and [[University of California, Berkeley|Berkeley]]

|-
|1995
|[[Los Angeles]], CA
|[[SIGGRAPH]] 1995 Keynote Speech
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=16O5g1fD-1U Video part 1]
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Aapy_JYXCI Video part 2]
|
*Centenary of the motion picture
*Scale and complexity of [[Toy Story]]
*Place in History of Computer Graphics
*[[Auguste and Louis Lumière|Lumière brothers]] projected the first film 100 years ago in [[Paris]]
*How has technology changed the way we view motion pictures?
*1895 [[Auguste and Louis Lumière|Lumière brothers]] invented their own cameras and projectors
*1927 the next technological innovation was sound (almost 40 years later)
*[[Al Jolson|Al Jolson's]] lines ended the era of silent pictures forever
*The impact of sound: 60 million movie viewers in 1927 to 110 million viewers in 1929
*[[The Jazz Singer]] was immensely popular and saved [[Warner Bros.]] studio
*1932 The next major innovation was [[Technicolor]]
*1937 first animated feature film with [[multiplane camera]]
*2D Animation was the first new form of motion picture entertainment since the first motion picture 42 years earlier
*1939 ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'' became the first commercially successful color film
*1977 ''[[Star Wars (film)|Star Wars]]'' redefined science fiction genre. Elevated [[special effect]]s to become an equal partner to live action in storytelling in motion pictures
*''[[Alien (film)|Alien]]'', ''[[The Abyss]]'', ''[[Terminator 2: Judgment Day|Terminator 2]]'', and ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'' incorporate some computer graphics special effects (but not on the scale of ''Toy Story'')
*Scale and complexity of ''Toy Story''
*''Toy Story'' is the first completely computer generated feature-length motion picture. Completely computer synthetic.
*Computer graphics are not just providing a supporting role to live action but are actually providing the entire vision for the motion picture.
*[[Pixar]] created a 'digital back (movie) lot'
*Jobs details the workflow of creating animated movies followed by numerous statistics about ''Toy Story''
*10 person-years went into the modeling of Toy Story
*34 terabytes of [[RenderMan (software)|RenderMan]] files were [[Rendering (computer graphics)|rendered]]
*800 thousand machine hours of rendering on [[SPARCstation 20|Sun SPARCstation 20 quad processors]]
*[[Sheriff Woody|Woody]] has 723 animation control points. 58 on the mouth alone.
*[[Buzz Lightyear]] has over 600 textures
*One scene has over 1 million leaves rendered on trees
*Toy story is the classic 'buddy picture'. Two adversaries forced to work together by circumstance.
*(The [[SIGGRAPH]] computer graphics) community has finally achieved the creation of a feature-length 3D animated synthetic film
*(The SIGGRAPH computer graphics community) pioneered the next major offshoot of the motion picture (3D Animation) "It's going to be a medium in its own right."

&lt;!-- 1996 --&gt;
{{anchor|1996}}
|-
|1996
|
| [[:fr:La_T%C3%A9l%C3%A9|La Télé]] Christophe Rasch interview with Steve Jobs
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MVppAvaKJcs Video]
|
* [[Switzerland]]

|-
|1996
|
|[[NPR]]: Steve Jobs' 1996 Conversation with [[Terry Gross]]
|[https://www.npr.org/2011/10/06/141115121/steve-jobs-computer-science-is-a-liberal-art Audio]
|
* [[World Wide Web]], [[HTML]]
* Tracking Packages
* Static vs. Dynamic Web Publishing
* [[Electronic commerce]]
* [[WebObjects]]
* Bypassing middlemen with the Web. Direct to consumer sales
* Web as egalitarian medium
* Shopping for information
* Online software sales in the future
* [[Broadband]] in the home
* The Web has resources for special interest groups. e.g. online health advice
* [[PARC (company)|Xerox PARC]] in 1979. [[Graphical user interface|GUI]], [[Object-oriented programming]], and [[Computer network|Networking]]
* [[NeXT Computer]], now strictly a software company
* [[NASA Ames Research Center]]
* Jobs' programmed in [[Fortran]], [[BASIC]]
* [[Steve Wozniak]]
* [[Blue box|Blue Box]]
* [[Apple I]]
* [[Printed circuit board]]
* [[Paul Terrell|The Byte Shop]]
* [[Crisis (Marxian)|Marxian profit realization crisis]]
* One button [[mouse (computing)|mouse]] on the Mac
*[[SRI International|SRI]]
*[[Graphical user interface]]
* Pain of departing Apple
* Not being afraid to fail
* Apple's 10 year lead over Microsoft in 1985
* Apple stopped innovating
* Cost cutting is not the solution to Apple's troubles
* Apple was like Jobs' first love
* Apple's "major contribution was in bringing a liberal arts point of view to the use of computers."
* The motivation of bringing ease of use to the Macintosh was to bring fonts/typography, graphics, photographs
* Science including [[computer science]] is a [[liberal art]]
* Everyone should have a mastery of computer science to some extent
* The seed of Apple was "Computers for the rest of us."
* "Microsoft didn't really get it." (that computers should be for everyone and easy to use)
* "Are we entering a time window when we might see the first successful post-PC devices?"
* The future of the [[personal digital assistant]] and [[Internet appliance]]s
* Collegial vs. Hierarchical corporate culture
* Apple is an egalitarian company. Great ideas could come from anywhere within Apple.
* "&lt;nowiki&gt;[Apple]&lt;/nowiki&gt; hired truly great people, and gave them the room to do great work."
* "A lot of companies hired people to tell them what to do. We hired people to tell us what to do."
* "&lt;nowiki&gt;[Work]&lt;/nowiki&gt; is still my life but it is not all of my life."
* [[Edwin Catmull|Ed Catmull]], [[Lucasfilm]]
* Founding [[Pixar]]
* Jobs provided the support, negotiations, and environment to make [[Toy Story]] possible
* Pixar as a consumer of computing power vs. a creator of computing power

&lt;!-- 1997 --&gt;
{{anchor|1997}}

|-
|1997
|[[San Diego]], CA
|WebObjects presentation at Microsoft [[Professional Developers Conference]] (MSPDC)
|[https://web.archive.org/web/20120705155550/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TaX25rxOY8Q Video]
|
*[[WebObjects]]
*Server side computing
*Static vs. Dynamic Web Publishing
*Airline ticketing
*[[Electronic commerce]]

|-
|1997
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|MacWorld Expo 1997
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QhhFQ-3w5tE Video]
|
* Developer productivity
* [[PARC (company)|Xerox PARC]]
* [[Tim Berners-Lee]]
* [[OpenStep]]
* [[WebObjects]]
* [[Interface Builder]]

|-
|1997
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|[[Apple Worldwide Developers Conference|WWDC]] Fireside Chat with Steve Jobs
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6iACK-LNnzM Video]
|

|-
|1997
|
|[[CNBC]] interview with Steve Jobs
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xchYT9wz5hk Video]
|
* Apple stock is trading at 1/3x sales. Competitors trade at 3-5x sales.
* Jobs return to Apple
* Compensation
* Focussing the company's resources on core products and a few new products.
* [[Microsoft]] and Apple relationship
* Macintosh was the platform that brought Microsoft into the Applications business
* Being CEO is not a popularity contest

&lt;!-- 1998 --&gt;
{{anchor|1998}}
|-
|1998
|
|10th Anniversary of [[Wolfram Mathematica]]
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8gsQDwn8mFY Video]
|
*Congratulating [[Stephen Wolfram]]

|-
|1998
|[[Seattle]], WA
|CAUSE Annual Conference General Session
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e-B9LikzxyM Video]
| 
*Literacy (computers' role in education)
*[[Net neutrality]] (Balkanization of the Internet)
*[[Thin client]]s
*Affordable computing
*[[Web portal]]s
*Television
*Heroes and role models

&lt;!-- 1999 --&gt;
{{anchor|1999}}

&lt;!-- 2000s --&gt;
{{anchor|2000}}

{{anchor|2001}}
|-
|2001
|Japan
|[[NHK|Japanese National Public Broadcasting Organization]] interview
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GuB-d7jRkCw Video]
|
*People that succeed don't give up.
*The personal computer is entering its third great age
*The first age of the PC was productivity
*The second age was the internet
*The third age is the digital lifestyle
*It took a year to realize that the PC would become a major industry
*At first, we made the computer kits for our friends
*The circle of friends got bigger and bigger. Now 25 million people.
*Money is not a good reason to start a company
*Start a company to express an idea. Sometimes that's the only way to get people to listen.
*We try to hire very smart people and focus on doing a few things well.
*Allow people to do the best work of their lives
*Apple is in a great spot today, 3 or 4 years ago it was fragile.
*The internet has no emotion. The bandwidth isn't there to deliver emotion. 
*At Apple, we want to stand at the intersection of technology and humanities.
*We want to bring the humanist side into these tools we don't just want to serve the intellectual side.
*There are a lot of forces that attempt to funnel us into an institutionalized path.
*We have had over a million customers make movies with iMovie
*The whole personal computer industry has previously not spoken to the emotional and creative side of people. It has only spoken to the side of us that is pushing numbers.
*I think about 3 or 4 years down the road.
*Some 5 year planning is essential, but most 5 year planning changes within a few years.

{{anchor|2002}}
|-
|2002
|
|[[60 Minutes]] Overtime
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_uKR0nsrPmA Video]
|
* [[Generation_loss#Analog_generation_loss|Analog generation loss]]
* [[George Lucas]]
* Lucas hired [[Edwin Catmull]] from [[New York Institute of Technology]]
* Jobs bought computer group from Lucas in 1986 with a vision to create the world's first computer generated animated film
* [[Beatles]] as example of a team
* Business is best executed as a team effort
* My greatest strength is hanging out with great and talented people
* All of us need to be on guard against arrogance
* There wouldn't have been a Pixar if Jobs had not been fired from Apple
* Returning to Apple after being fired 12 years earlier was an example of 'the circle of life'
* Computer industry is in its infancy

&lt;!-- 2003 --&gt;
{{anchor|2003}}

&lt;!-- 2004 --&gt;
{{anchor|2004}}

&lt;!-- 2005 --&gt;
{{anchor|2005}}
|-
|2005
|[[Palo Alto]], CA
|Stanford Commencement Address
|[http://www.singjupost.com/steve-jobs-2005-stanford-commencement-address-full-transcript Text]
[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF8uR6Z6KLc Video]
|
*[[Adoption]]
*Attending and dropping out of [[Reed College]]
*[[International Society for Krishna Consciousness|Hare Krishna]]
*[[Calligraphy]]
*[[Serif]]s, [[Kerning]], and [[Typography]]
*[[Macintosh]] was the first computer with beautiful typography
*"Because believing that the dots will connect down the road will give you the confidence to follow your heart even when it leads you off the well-worn path and that will make all the difference."
*Hiring [[John Sculley]]
*Getting fired by Apple's board of directors
*[[NeXT Computer]] technology is at the heart of Apple's renaissance.
*Marriage and family with [[Laurene Powell Jobs]]
*"The only way to do great work is to love what you do."
*[[Pancreatic cancer]]
*[[Whole Earth Catalog]]
*[[Stewart Brand]]
*"Stay hungry. Stay foolish." Quote from the Whole Earth Catalog.

&lt;!-- 2006 --&gt;
{{anchor|2006}}
|-
|2006
|[[New York City]]
|[[CNBC]] interview about [[Fifth Avenue]] Apple Store opening
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qvkSRZnC9Q8 Video (YouTube)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161208072652/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qvkSRZnC9Q8 Video (Archive.org)]
|
*Apple opened its first retail store 5 years ago
*[[SoHo, Manhattan|SoHo]] Apple store was one of the most expensive to build
*There was demand for a second Manhattan store
*Real estate developer [[Harry B. Macklowe|Harry Macklowe]] invited Apple to a subterranean space under a [[Fifth Avenue]] plaza
*Apple proposed a 32-foot glass cube
*"We've never believed in the philosophy of having flagship stores that don't make money."
*"Every single one of our stores makes money."
*New Fifth Avenue store is first Apple Store to be open 24 hours
*300 employees will work in the store. We are highly service oriented.
*We want to invest more to create a better buying experience
*We only have to convince 5% of the world to buy a Mac and we will have doubled our market share.
*[[iPod|iPods]] are extremely successful in the UK. We are the number one [[MP3 player]] in France, Germany, etc. in Europe.
*[[AMD]] has got some very interesting products at the high end of the server space
*[[Intel]] has the best consumer chips right now. [[Yonah (microprocessor)|Yonah]] known as the Core Duo. 
*Intel has a strong road map for notebooks and consumer desktops.
*Will we ever see an "'iPhone'"? We never talk about unannounced products.

|-
|2006
|[[Cupertino, California]]
|Presents new plan for new campus to Cupertino City Council 
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hWYvJ6nHeGM Video]
|

&lt;!-- 2007 --&gt;
{{anchor|2007}}
|-
|2007
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|[[CNBC]] Interview on the release of the iPhone
|[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pZJPP_I04vA Video]
|

|-
|2007
|[[Emeryville, California|Emeryville, CA]]
|Interview about [[Pixar]]
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_LFIaMtyLXs Video (YouTube)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161208054209/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_LFIaMtyLXs Video (Archive.org)]
|
*[[Edwin Catmull|Ed Catmull]]
*I bought into the dream of making the first computer animated film both spiritually and financially
*The combination of a new medium and [[John Lasseter]] bringing a character to life made people say, "Oh my god!"
*Just trying to pay the bills and buy time was a failing strategy.
*Second product syndrome: Often a second product that follows an earlier successful product, will fail because of the misunderstanding of why the initial product succeeded.
*The [[Apple II]] was Apple's first product in the marketplace. It was incredibly successful. The [[Apple III]] was a dud.
*"My feeling was that if we got through our second film, we'd make it."
*"Our business depends on unplanned collaboration." 
*"We want to put everybody under one roof and we want to encourage unplanned collaboration."
*"If you look closely, most overnight successes took a long time."
*"The best scientists and engineers are just as creative as the best storytellers."

&lt;!-- 2008 --&gt;
{{anchor|2008}}

|-
|2008
|[[San Jose, California|San Jose]], CA
|[[U.S._Securities_and_Exchange_Commission|US SEC]] Deposition 
|
*[http://images.forbes.com/media/2009/04/24/jobs-deposition.pdf Text]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20160128130023/http://images.forbes.com/media/2009/04/24/jobs-deposition.pdf Text (Archive.org)]
|

&lt;!-- 2009 --&gt;
{{anchor|2009}}

&lt;!-- 2010 --&gt;
{{anchor|2010}}
|-
|2010
|[[San Francisco]], CA
|[[Apple Worldwide Developers Conference|WWDC]] Introduction of the [[iPhone 4]] and [[Facetime]]
|
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j0L3LDabve8 Video (YouTube)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161206075021/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pdkCVoBgHnc Video (Archive.org)]
|
&lt;!-- 2011 --&gt;
{{anchor|2011}}
|-
|2011
|[[Cupertino, California]]
|Presents the plan for the new Apple Campus 
|[https://web.archive.org/web/20171004113845/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oPzVsrgaxmc Video]
|
*June 11, 2011 - Last Steve Jobs public appearance. 
*Apple is growing and is out of space. Need a new campus to augment existing campus.
*Jobs called [[Bill Hewlett]] for help at age 12 and received a summer job building [[Frequency_counter|frequency counters]].
*New Apple campus will be on the former HP Computer Systems division
*Prior to being an HP campus this land was an apricot orchard.
*Hired the best architects and intend to put 12,000 people in one building
*The building is "kind of like a spaceship landed.".
*The building will be curved and this is expensive. 
*Apple already makes the biggest pieces of glass for architectural use.
*The HP site is 80% parking lot and 20% landscape.
*The Apple campus will be 80% landscape and 20% buildings.
*Hired senior arborist from [[Stanford_University|Stanford]] to plant trees.
*Parking will be subterranean.
*Building is four stories high. "We want the whole place to be human scale."
*The campus will be self powered and backed up by the grid
*The use of space is dramatically improved over the HP campus. 
*20% more work space than on the HP campus.
*350% more landscape than on the HP campus.
*60% more trees than the HP campus
*90% less pavement than the HP campus
*The cafe will feed 3000 people in a sitting.
*Apple is the largest tax payer in Cupertino
*Apple moving away would not be good for Cupertino
*Apple employs very talented people which improves Cupertino
*Apple has [[biodiesel]] buses that (in 2011) were the cleanest buses.
*Architecture students will come to Cupertino to see this building.
*Employment will increase by about 20%.
*Both of my (adopted) parents died of [[Lung cancer]] from smoking
*Break ground in 2012
*"We want to move in&lt;!--not a mistake--&gt; in 2015.".

|-
|2011
|
| [[60 Minutes]] (Posthumous)
| [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1jqSK8Qv4ZY&amp;t=5m18s Video]
|
* Definitely taking [[LSD]] was one of the most important things in my life
|}

==See also==
[http://projekter.aau.dk/projekter/files/76950691/Appendices.pdf How to Grow an Apple: Did Steve Jobs Speak Apple to Success?] Aalborg University, Lotte Skjøttgaard Sørensen, 2013

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Steve Jobs}}

[[Category:Personal timelines|Jobs]]
[[Category:Works about Steve Jobs| ]]</text>
      <sha1>1y9xnutgn5mc05b4j64x4q1cqnr566h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
