<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of the Maya civilization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46998769</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961847289</id>
      <parentid>952745383</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-10T18:40:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 3 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]] (prndis)) #IABot (v2.0.1) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="60793" xml:space="preserve">{{Maya civilization}}
The '''history of Maya civilization''' is divided into three principal periods: the Preclassic, Classic and Postclassic periods;&lt;ref&gt;Estrada-Belli 2011, pp. 1, 3.&lt;/ref&gt; these were preceded by the Archaic Period, which saw the first settled villages and early developments in agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 98. Estrada-Belli 2011, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Modern scholars regard these periods as arbitrary divisions of chronology of the [[Maya civilization]], rather than indicative of cultural evolution or decadence.&lt;ref&gt;Estrada-Belli 2011, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Definitions of the start and end dates of period spans can vary by as much as a century, depending on the author.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The Preclassic lasted from approximately 2000 BC to approximately 250 AD; this was followed by the Classic, from 250 AD to roughly 950 AD, then by the Postclassic, from 950 AD to the middle of the 16th century.&lt;ref name="Estrada-Belli11p3"&gt;Estrada-Belli 2011, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Each period is further subdivided:

{|align="center" | class="wikitable" | style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto"
|+Maya chronology&lt;ref name="Estrada-Belli11p3"/&gt;
! Period
!colspan="2"| Division
! Dates
|-
|colspan="3"|Archaic
| 8000–2000 BC&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|rowspan="6"|Preclassic
|colspan="2"| Early Preclassic
| 2000–1000 BC
|-
|rowspan="2"|Middle Preclassic
| Early Middle Preclassic
| 1000–600 BC
|-
| Late Middle Preclassic
| 600–350 BC
|-
|rowspan="3"|Late Preclassic
|Early Late Preclassic
| 350–1 BC
|-
|Late Late Preclassic
| 1 BC – AD 159
|-
|Terminal Preclassic
| AD 159–250
|-
|rowspan="3"|Classic
|colspan="2"| Early Classic
| AD 250–550
|-
|colspan="2"| Late Classic
| AD 550–830
|-
|colspan="2"| Terminal Classic
| AD 830–950
|-
|rowspan="2"|Postclassic
|colspan="2"| Early Postclassic
| AD 950–1200
|-
|colspan="2"|Late Postclassic
| AD 1200–1539
|-
|colspan="3"|Contact period
| AD 1511–1697&lt;ref&gt;Masson 2012, p. 18238. Pugh and Cecil 2012, p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Preclassic period (c. 2000 BC – 250 AD)==

{{Main article|Preclassic Maya}}
[[File:Structure5.JPG|thumb|right|Structure 5 at [[Takalik Abaj]] was built during the [[Preclassic Maya|Middle Preclassic]].&lt;ref&gt;Schieber de Lavarreda and Orrego Corzo 2010, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Maya developed their [[first civilization]] in the Preclassic period.&lt;ref&gt;Estrada-Belli 2011, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars continue to discuss when this era of Maya civilization began. Discoveries of Maya occupation at [[Cuello]], Belize have been carbon dated to around 2600 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Hammond et al. 1976, pp. 579–581.&lt;/ref&gt; Settlements were established around 1800 BC in the [[Soconusco]] region of the Pacific coast, and they were already cultivating the staple crops of the Maya diet, including maize, beans, squash, and chili pepper.&lt;ref name="Drew99p6"/&gt; This period, known as the Early Preclassic,&lt;ref name="Drew99p6"&gt;Drew 1999, p.6.&lt;/ref&gt; was characterized by [[sedentism|sedentary]] communities and the introduction of pottery and fired clay figurines.&lt;ref&gt;Coe 1999, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Mesoamerican chronology|Middle Preclassic Period]], small villages began to grow to form cities.&lt;ref name="Olmedo97p26"&gt;Olmedo Vera 1997, p.26.&lt;/ref&gt; By 500 BC these cities possessed large temple structures decorated with stucco masks representing [[List of Maya gods and supernatural beings|gods]].&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p8"&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p.8.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nakbe]] in the Petén Department of Guatemala is the earliest well-documented city in the Maya lowlands,&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p214"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p.214.&lt;/ref&gt; where large structures have been dated to around 750 BC.&lt;ref name="Olmedo97p26"/&gt; Nakbe already featured the monumental masonry architecture, sculpted monuments and causeways that characterised later cities in the Maya lowlands.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p214"/&gt; The northern lowlands of Yucatán were widely settled by the Middle Preclassic.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt; By approximately 400&amp;nbsp;BC, near the end of the Middle Preclassic period, early Maya rulers were raising stelae that celebrated their achievements and validated their right to rule.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 182, 197.&lt;/ref&gt;

Murals excavated in 2005 have pushed back the origin of Maya writing by several centuries, with a developed script already being used at [[San Bartolo (Maya site)|San Bartolo]] in Petén by the 3rd century BC, and it is now evident that the Maya participated in the wider development of Mesoamerican writing in the Preclassic.&lt;ref name="Saturno2006"&gt;Saturno, Stuart and Beltrán 2006, pp. 1281–1283.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Late Preclassic Period, the enormous city of [[El Mirador]] grew to cover approximately {{convert|16|km2|sqmi}}.&lt;ref name="Olmedo97p28"&gt;Olmedo Vera 1997, p.28.&lt;/ref&gt; It possessed paved avenues, massive [[triadic pyramid]] complexes dated to around 150 BC, and stelae and altars that were erected in its plazas.&lt;ref name="Olmedo97p28"/&gt; El Mirador is considered to be one of the first capital cities of the Maya civilization.&lt;ref name="Olmedo97p28"/&gt; The swamps of the Mirador Basin appear to have been the primary attraction for the first inhabitants of the area as evidenced by the unusual cluster of large cities around them.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen et al. 2006, p.740.&lt;/ref&gt; The city of Tikal, later to be one of the most important of the Classic Period Maya cities, was already a significant city by around 350 BC, although it did not match El Mirador.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p25-26"&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, pp. 25–26.&lt;/ref&gt; The Late Preclassic cultural florescence collapsed in the 1st century AD and many of the great Maya cities of the epoch were abandoned; the cause of this collapse is as yet unknown.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p8"/&gt;

{{Multiple image| image1 = Kaminaljuyu 7.jpg| width1 = 200| image2 = El Mirador 5.jpg| width2 = 222| footer = [[Kaminaljuyu]], in the highlands, and [[El Mirador]], in the lowlands, were both important cities in the Late Preclassic}}
In the highlands, [[Kaminaljuyu]] emerged as a principal centre in the Late Preclassic, linking the Pacific coastal trade routes with the [[Motagua River]] route, as well as demonstrating increased contact with other sites along the Pacific coast.&lt;ref&gt;Love 2007, pp. 293, 297. Popenoe de Hatch and Schieber de Lavarreda 2001, p. 991.&lt;/ref&gt; Kaminaljuyu was situated at a crossroads and controlled the trade routes westwards to the Gulf coast, north into the highlands, and along the Pacific coastal plain to the [[Isthmus of Tehuantepec]] and El Salvador. This gave it control over the distribution networks for important goods such as jade, obsidian and [[Cinnabar#Decorative use|cinnabar]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt; Within this extended trade route, [[Takalik Abaj]] and Kaminaljuyu appear to have been the two principal foci.&lt;ref&gt;Popenoe de Hatch and Schieber de Lavarreda 2001, p. 991.&lt;/ref&gt; The early Maya style of sculpture spread throughout this network.&lt;ref&gt;Orrego Corzo and Schieber de Lavarreda 2001, p. 788.&lt;/ref&gt; Takalik Abaj and [[Chocolá]] were two of the most important cities on the Pacific coastal plain during the Late Preclassic,&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Komchen]] grew to become an important site in northern Yucatán during the Preclassic.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classic period (c. 250–900 AD)==

The Classic period is largely defined as the period during which the lowland Maya raised dated monuments using the [[Mesoamerican Long Count calendar|Long Count calendar]].&lt;ref name="Coe 1999, p. 81"&gt;Coe 1999, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; This period marked the peak of large-scale construction and [[urbanism]], the recording of monumental inscriptions, and demonstrated significant intellectual and artistic development, particularly in the southern lowland regions.&lt;ref name="Coe 1999, p. 81"/&gt; The Classic period Maya political landscape has been likened to that of [[Italian Renaissance|Renaissance Italy]] or [[Classical Greece]], with multiple city-states engaged in a complex network of alliances and enmities.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:QuiriguaStela1.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Stela D from [[Quiriguá]], representing king [[Kʼakʼ Tiliw Chan Yopaat]]&lt;ref&gt;Schele and Mathews 1999, pp. 179, 182–183.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

During the Classic Period, the Maya civilization achieved its greatest florescence.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p8"/&gt; The Maya developed an agriculturally intensive, city-centred civilization consisting of numerous independent city-states – some subservient to others.&lt;ref name="whyNationsFail"&gt;Acemoglu and Robinson 2012, pp. 143–149.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Early Classic, cities throughout the Maya region were influenced by the great metropolis of Teotihuacan in the distant [[Valley of Mexico]].&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p9"&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p.9.&lt;/ref&gt; In AD 378, Teotihuacan decisively intervened at Tikal and other nearby cities, deposed its ruler and installed a new Teotihuacan-backed dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 218. Estrada-Belli 2011, pp. 123–126.&lt;/ref&gt; This intervention was led by [[Siyaj Kʼakʼ]] ("Born of Fire"), who arrived at Tikal on 8.17.1.4.12 (c. 31 January 378). The king of Tikal, [[Chak Tok Ichʼaak I]], died on the same day, suggesting a violent takeover.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 322. Martin and Grube 2000, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; A year later, Siyaj Kʼakʼ oversaw the installation of a new king, [[Yax Nuun Ayiin I]].&lt;ref name="Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 324"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 324.&lt;/ref&gt; The new king's father was [[Spearthrower Owl]], who possessed a central Mexican name, and may have been the king of either Teotihuacan, or Kaminaljuyu.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p. 30. Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 322, 324.&lt;/ref&gt; The installation of the new dynasty led to a period of political dominance when Tikal became the most powerful city in the central lowlands.&lt;ref name="Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 324"/&gt;

At its height during the Late Classic, the [[Tikal]] city [[polity]] had expanded to have a population of well over 100,000.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p1"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p.1.&lt;/ref&gt; Tikal's great rival was [[Calakmul]], another powerful city polity in the [[Petén Basin]].&lt;ref name="Olmeda97p36"&gt;Olmedo Vera 1997, p.36.&lt;/ref&gt; Tikal and Calakmul both developed extensive systems of allies and vassals; lesser cities that entered one of these networks gained prestige from their association with the top-tier city, and maintained peaceful relations with other members of the same network.&lt;ref&gt;Foster 2002, p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; Tikal and Calakmul engaged in the manoeuvering of their alliance networks against each other; at various points during the Classic period, one or other of these powers would gain a strategic victory over its great rival, resulting in respective periods of florescence and decline.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 224–226.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 629, [[Bʼalaj Chan Kʼawiil]], a son of the Tikal king [[Kʼinich Muwaan Jol II]], was sent to found a new city {{convert|120|km|mi}} to the west, at [[Dos Pilas]], in the [[Petexbatún Lake|Petexbatún]] region, apparently as an outpost to extend Tikal's power beyond the reach of Calakmul. The young prince was just four years old at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 383, 387.&lt;/ref&gt; With the establishment of the new kingdom, Dos Pilas advertised its origin by adopting the emblem glyph of Tikal as its own.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p383"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 383.&lt;/ref&gt; For the next two decades he fought loyally for his brother and overlord at Tikal. In AD&amp;nbsp;648, king [[Yuknoom Chʼeen II|Yuknoom Chʼeen&amp;nbsp;II]] ("Yuknoom the Great") of Calakmul attacked and defeated Dos&amp;nbsp;Pilas, capturing Balaj Chan Kʼawiil. At about the same time, the king of Tikal was killed. Yuknoom Cheʼen&amp;nbsp;II then reinstated Balaj Chan Kʼawiil upon the throne of Dos&amp;nbsp;Pilas as his vassal.&lt;ref&gt;Salisbury, Koumenalis &amp; Barbara Moffett 2002. Martin &amp; Grube 2000, p. 108. Sharer &amp; Traxler 2006, p.387.&lt;/ref&gt; In an extraordinary act of treachery for someone claiming to be of the Tikal royal family, he thereafter served as a loyal ally of Calakmul, Tikal's sworn enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the southeast, [[Copán]] was the most important city.&lt;ref name="Olmeda97p36"/&gt; Its Classic-period dynasty was founded in 426 by [[Kʼinich Yax Kʼukʼ Moʼ]]. The new king had strong ties with central Petén and Teotihuacan, and it is likely that he was originally from Tikal.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, pp 192–193. Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt; Copán reached the height of its cultural and artistic development during the rule of [[Uaxaclajuun Ubʼaah Kʼawiil]], who reigned from 695 to 738.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, pp. 200, 203.&lt;/ref&gt; His reign ended catastrophically in April 738, when he was captured by his vassal, king Kʼakʼ Tiliw Chan Yopaat of Quiriguá.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, pp. 203, 205.&lt;/ref&gt; The captured lord of Copán was taken back to Quiriguá and, in early May 738, he was decapitated in a public ritual.&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1999, pp. 134–135. Looper 2003, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; It is likely that this coup was backed by Calakmul, in order to weaken a powerful ally of Tikal.&lt;ref&gt;Looper 1999, pp. 81, 271.&lt;/ref&gt; Palenque and [[Yaxchilan]] were the most powerful cities in the [[Usumacinta River|Usumacinta]] region.&lt;ref name="Olmeda97p36"/&gt; In the highlands, Kaminaljuyu in the Valley of Guatemala was already a sprawling city by AD 300.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; In the north of the Maya area, [[Coba]] was the most important capital.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p554"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 554.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Calakmul - Structure I.jpg|thumb|left|[[Calakmul]] was one of the most important Classic period cities]]
Capital cities of Maya kingdoms could vary considerably in size, apparently related to how many vassal cities were tied to the capital.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p19"&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p.19.&lt;/ref&gt; Overlords of city-states that held sway over a greater number of subordinate lords could command greater quantities of tribute in the form of goods and labour.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p21"&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p.21.&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable forms of tribute pictured on Maya ceramics are [[cocoa bean|cacao]], [[Maya textiles|textiles]] and feathers.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p21"/&gt; The [[Maya society|social basis]] of the Classic Maya civilization was an extended political and [[Economy of the Maya civilization|economic network]] that reached throughout the Maya area and beyond into the greater Mesoamerican region.&lt;ref&gt;Carmack 2003, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; The dominant Classic period polities were located in the central lowlands; during this period the southern highlands and northern lowlands can be considered culturally, economically, and politically peripheral to this core area. Those loci that existed between the core and the periphery acted as centres of trade and commerce.&lt;ref&gt;Carmack 2003, pp. 76–77.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most notable monuments are the pyramid-temples and palaces they built in the centres of their greatest cities.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, the use of hieroglyphic script on monuments became widespread, and left a large body of information including dated dynastic records, alliances, and other interactions between Maya polities.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 89–90.&lt;/ref&gt; The sculpting of stone stelae spread throughout the Maya area during the Classic period,&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1999, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; and pairings of sculpted stelae and low circular altars are considered a hallmark of Classic Maya civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 235. Miller 1999, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Classic period almost every Maya kingdom in the southern lowlands raised stelae in its ceremonial centre.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart 1996, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[epigraphy|epigrapher]] [[David Stuart (Mayanist)|David Stuart]] first proposed that the Maya regarded their stelae as ''te tun'', "stone trees", although he later revised his reading to ''lakamtun'', meaning "banner stone".&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1999, pp. 78, 80.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Stuart this may refer to the stelae as stone versions of vertical standards that once stood in prominent places in Maya city centres, as depicted in ancient Maya [[Graffito (archaeology)|graffiti]].&lt;ref&gt;Stuart 1996, p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt; The core purpose of a stela was to glorify the [[Maya rulers|king]].&lt;ref&gt;Borowicz 2003, p. 217.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Maya civilization participated in long-distance trade, and important trade routes ran from the Motagua River to the Caribbean Sea, then north up the coast to Yucatán. Another route ran from Verapaz along the [[Pasión River]] to the trading port at [[Cancuen]]; from there trade routes ran east to Belize, northwards to central and northern Petén, and onwards to the Gulf of Mexico and the west coast of the Yucatán Peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt; Important elite-status trade goods included jade, fine ceramics, and [[quetzal feathers]].&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; More basic trade goods may have included obsidian, salt and cacao.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classic Maya collapse===

{{Main article|Classic Maya collapse}}
[[File:Chichen Itza ruins in Mexico -- by John Romkey.jpg|thumb|right|[[Chichen Itza]] was the most important city in the northern Maya region]]
During the 9th century AD, the central Maya region suffered major political collapse, marked by the abandonment of cities, the ending of dynasties and a northward shift in activity.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p9"/&gt; This decline was coupled with a cessation of monumental inscriptions and large-scale architectural construction. No universally accepted theory explains this collapse, but it is likely to have resulted from a combination of causes, including endemic internecine warfare, overpopulation resulting in severe environmental degradation, and drought.&lt;ref name="coe"&gt;Coe 1999, pp. 151–155.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, known as the Terminal Classic, the northern cities of Chichen Itza and [[Uxmal]] show increased activity.&lt;ref name="MartinGrube00p9"/&gt; Major cities in the northern Yucatán Peninsula continued to be inhabited long after the cities of the southern lowlands ceased to raise monuments.&lt;ref&gt;Becker 2004, p.134.&lt;/ref&gt;

There is evidence that the Maya population exceeded the [[carrying capacity]] of the environment, resulting in [[Land degradation|depleted agricultural resources]], [[deforestation]], and overhunting of [[megafauna]]. A 200-year long drought appears to have occurred around the same time.&lt;ref&gt;Beeland 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Classic Maya social organisation was based upon the ritual authority of the ruler, rather than central control of trade and food distribution. This model of rulership was poorly structured to respond to changes, with the ruler's freedom of action being limited to [[Traditional society|traditional responses]]. The rulers reacted in their culturally-bound manner, by intensifying such activities as construction, ritual, and warfare. This was counterproductive and only served to exacerbate [[systemic problem]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 246.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 9th and 10th centuries, this resulted in collapse of the system of rulership based around the divine power of the ruling lord. In the northern Yucatán, individual rule was replaced by a ruling council formed from elite lineages. In the southern Yucatán and central Petén, kingdoms generally declined; in western Petén and some other areas, the changes were catastrophic and resulted in the rapid depopulation of cities.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt; Within a couple of generations, large swathes of the central Maya area were all but abandoned.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000, p. 226.&lt;/ref&gt; Relatively rapid collapse affected portions of the southern Maya area that included the southern Yucatán Peninsula, northern Chiapas and Guatemala, and the area around Copán in Honduras. The largest cities had populations numbering 50,000 to 120,000 and were linked to networks of subsidiary sites. Both the capitals and their secondary centres were generally abandoned within a period of 50 to 100 years.&lt;ref name="Masson 2012, p. 18237"&gt;Masson 2012, p. 18237.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the late 8th century, endemic warfare had engulfed the [[Petexbatún]] region of Petén, resulting in the abandonment of Dos Pilas and [[Aguateca]].&lt;ref&gt;Coe 1999, p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; One by one, many once-great cities stopped sculpting dated monuments and were abandoned; the last monuments at Palenque, [[Piedras Negras (Maya site)|Piedras Negras]] and Yaxchilan were dated to between 795 and 810, over the following decades, Calakmul, [[Naranjo]], Copán, [[Caracol]] and Tikal all fell into obscurity. The last Long Count date was inscribed at [[Toniná]] in 909. Stelae were no longer raised, and squatters moved into abandoned royal palaces. Mesoamerican trade routes shifted and bypassed Petén.&lt;ref&gt;Foster 2002, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Postclassic period (c. 950–1539 AD)==
[[File:Zacuelu2.jpg|thumb|right|[[Zaculeu]] was capital of the Postclassic [[Mam people|Mam]] kingdom in the [[Guatemalan Highlands]]&lt;ref&gt;Sharer 2000, p. 490.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The great cities that dominated Petén had fallen into ruin by the beginning of the 10th century AD with the onset of the Classic Maya collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 499–500.&lt;/ref&gt; Although much reduced, a significant Maya presence remained into the Postclassic period after the abandonment of the major Classic period cities; the population was particularly concentrated near permanent water sources.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 613, 616.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike during previous cycles of contraction in the Maya region, abandoned lands were not quickly resettled in the Postclassic.&lt;ref name="Masson 2012, p. 18237"/&gt; Activity shifted to the northern lowlands and the Maya Highlands; this may have involved migration from the southern lowlands, since many Postclassic Maya groups had migration myths.&lt;ref&gt;Foias 2014, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chichen Itza]] rose to prominence in the north in the 8th century AD, coincident with the abandonments occurring in the south, which underlines the economic and political factors involved in the collapse.&lt;ref name="Masson 2012, p. 18237"/&gt; Chichen Itza became what was probably the largest, most powerful and most cosmopolitan of all Maya cities.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p559"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p.559.&lt;/ref&gt; Chichen Itza and its [[Puuc]] neighbours declined dramatically in the 11th century, and this may represent the final episode of the Classic period collapse. After the decline of Chichen Itza, the Maya region lacked a dominant power until the rise of the city of [[Mayapan]] in the 12th century. New cities arose near the Caribbean and Gulf coasts, and new trade networks were formed.&lt;ref name="Masson2012p18238"/&gt;

The Postclassic Period was marked by a series of changes that distinguished its cities from those of the preceding Classic Period.&lt;ref name="Arroyo01p38"&gt;Arroyo 2001, p.38.&lt;/ref&gt; The once-great city of Kaminaljuyu in the Valley of Guatemala was abandoned after a period of continuous occupation that spanned almost two thousand years.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p618"&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p.618.&lt;/ref&gt; This was symptomatic of changes that were sweeping across the highlands and neighbouring Pacific coast, with long-occupied cities in exposed locations relocated, apparently due to a proliferation of [[Maya warfare|warfare]]. Cities came to occupy more-easily defended hilltop locations surrounded by deep ravines, with ditch-and-wall defences sometimes supplementing the protection provided by the natural terrain.&lt;ref name="SharerTraxler06p618"/&gt; Walled defences have been identified at a number of sites in the north, including [[Chacchob]], Chichen Itza, [[Cuca (Maya site)|Cuca]], [[Ek Balam]], Mayapan, [[Muna (Maya site)|Muna]], [[Tulum]], Uxmal, and [[Yaxuna]].&lt;ref&gt;Foias 2014, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most important cities in the Guatemalan Highlands at this time was [[Qʼumarkaj]], also known as Utatlán, the capital of the aggressive Kʼicheʼ Maya kingdom.&lt;ref name="Arroyo01p38"/&gt; The government of Maya states, from the Yucatán to the Guatemalan highlands, was often organised as joint rule by a council. However, in practice one member of the council could act as a supreme ruler, with the other members serving him as advisors.&lt;ref&gt;Foias 2014, pp. 100–102.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mayapan chac.JPG|thumb|left|[[Mayapan]] was an important Postclassic city in the northern [[Yucatán Peninsula]]]]
Mayapan was abandoned around 1448, after a period of political, social and environmental turbulence that in many ways echoes the Classic period collapse in the southern Maya region. The abandonment of the city was followed by a period of prolonged warfare in the Yucatán Peninsula, which only ended shortly before Spanish contact in 1511. Even without a dominant regional capital, the early Spanish explorers reported wealthy coastal cities and thriving marketplaces.&lt;ref name="Masson2012p18238"&gt;Masson 2012, p. 18238.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Late Postclassic, the Yucatán Peninsula was divided into a number of independent provinces that shared a common culture but varied in their internal sociopolitical organisation.&lt;ref&gt;Andrews 1984, p. 589.&lt;/ref&gt; Two of the most important provinces were [[Maní, Yucatán|Mani]] and [[Sotuta]], which were mutually hostile.&lt;ref&gt;Caso Barrera 2002, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of Spanish contact, polities in the northern Yucatán peninsula included Mani, [[Cehpech]], [[Chakan (Maya province)|Chakan]], [[Ah Kin Chel]], [[Cupul]], [[Chikinchel]], [[Ecab]], [[Uaymil]], [[Chetumal]], [[Cochuah]], [[Tases]], [[Hocaba]], Sotuta, Chanputun (modern [[Champotón, Campeche|Champotón]]), and [[Acalan]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrews 1984, pp. 589, 591.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of polities and groups inhabited the southern portion of the peninsula incorporating the Petén Basin, Belize, and surrounding areas,&lt;ref&gt;Estrada-Belli 2011, p. 52. Rice and Rice 2009, p. 17. Feldman 2000, p. xxi.&lt;/ref&gt; including the [[Kejache]], the [[Peten Itza Kingdom|Itza]],&lt;ref name="Jones 2000, p. 353"&gt;Jones 2000, p. 353.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Kowoj]],&lt;ref&gt;Rice and Rice 2009, p. 10. Rice 2009, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Yalain]],&lt;ref&gt;Cecil, Rice and Rice 1999, p. 788.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Chinamita]], the [[Icaiche]], the [[Manche Chʼol]], and the [[Mopan people|Mopan]].&lt;ref&gt;Rice 2009, p. 17. Feldman 2000, p. xxi.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Chʼolan languages|Cholan Maya]]-speaking [[Lakandon Chʼol|Lakandon]] (not to be confused with the modern inhabitants of Chiapas by that name) controlled territory along the tributaries of the Usumacinta River spanning eastern Chiapas and southwestern Petén.&lt;ref name="Jones 2000, p. 353"/&gt;

On the eve of the Spanish conquest, the highlands of Guatemala were dominated by several powerful Maya states.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 717.&lt;/ref&gt; In the centuries preceding the arrival of the Spanish, the [[Kʼicheʼ people|Kʼicheʼ]] had carved out a small empire covering a large part of the western Guatemalan Highlands and the neighbouring Pacific coastal plain. However, in the late 15th century the [[Kaqchikel people|Kaqchikel]] rebelled against their former Kʼicheʼ allies and founded a new kingdom to the southeast, with [[Iximche]] as its capital. In the decades before the Spanish invasion the Kaqchikel kingdom had been steadily eroding the kingdom of the Kʼicheʼ.&lt;ref&gt;Restall and Asselbergs 2007, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Other highland groups included the [[Tzʼutujil people|Tzʼutujil]] around [[Lake Atitlán]], the [[Mam people|Mam]] in the western highlands and the [[Poqomam people|Poqomam]] in the eastern highlands.&lt;ref&gt;Restall and Asselbergs 2007, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The central highlands of Chiapas were occupied by a number of Maya peoples,&lt;ref&gt;Lovell 2000, p. 398.&lt;/ref&gt; including the [[Tzotzil people|Tzotzil]], who were divided into a number of provinces,&lt;ref&gt;Lenkersdorf 2004, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Tojolabal people|Tojolabal]].&lt;ref&gt;Lenkersdorf 2004, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contact period and Spanish conquest (1511–1697 AD)==
{{Main article|Spanish conquest of the Maya|Spanish conquest of Chiapas|Spanish conquest of Guatemala|Spanish conquest of Petén|Spanish conquest of Yucatán|l2=Chiapas|l3=Guatemala|l4=Petén|l5=Yucatán}}
{{See also|Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire|Spanish colonization of the Americas}}
[[File:Lienzo de Tlaxcala Iximche.gif|thumb|right|Page from the ''[[Lienzo de Tlaxcala]]'' showing the [[Spanish conquest of Guatemala|Spanish conquest]] of [[Iximche]], known as Cuahtemallan in the [[Nahuatl]] language]]
In 1511, a Spanish [[caravel]] was wrecked in the Caribbean, and about a dozen survivors made landfall on the coast of Yucatán. They were seized by a Maya lord, and most were [[Human sacrifice in Maya culture|sacrificed]], although two managed to escape. From 1517 to 1519, three separate Spanish expeditions explored the Yucatán coast, and engaged in a number of battles with the Maya inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 759–760.&lt;/ref&gt; After the Aztec capital [[Tenochtitlan]] fell to the Spanish in 1521, [[Hernán Cortés]] despatched [[Pedro de Alvarado]] to Guatemala with 180 cavalry, 300 infantry, 4 cannons, and thousands of allied warriors from central Mexico;&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 763. Lovell 2005, p. 58. Matthew 2012, pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt; they arrived in Soconusco in 1523.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 763.&lt;/ref&gt; The Kʼicheʼ capital, Qʼumarkaj, fell to Alvarado in 1524.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 764–765. Recinos 1986, pp. 68, 74.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, the Spanish were invited as allies into Iximche, the capital city of the Kaqchikel Maya.&lt;ref&gt;Schele and Mathews 1999, p.297. Guillemín 1965, p.9.&lt;/ref&gt; Good relations did not last, due to excessive Spanish demands for gold as tribute, and the city was abandoned a few months later.&lt;ref&gt;Schele and Mathews 1999, p.298.&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by the fall of Zaculeu, the Mam Maya capital, in 1525.&lt;ref&gt;Recinos 1986, p.110. del Águila Flores 2007, p.38.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Francisco de Montejo]] and his son, [[Francisco de Montejo the Younger]], launched a lengthy series of campaigns against the polities of the Yucatán Peninsula in 1527, and finally completed the conquest of the northern portion of the peninsula in 1546.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 766–772.&lt;/ref&gt; This left only the Maya kingdoms of the Petén Basin independent.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, pp. 772–773.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1697, [[Martín de Ursúa]] launched an assault upon the [[Itza people|Itza]] capital [[Tayasal|Nojpetén]] and the last remaining independent Maya city fell to the Spanish.&lt;ref&gt;Jones 1998, p. xix.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Persistence of Maya culture==
{{main article|Maya peoples}}
The Spanish conquest stripped away most of the defining features of Maya civilization. However, many Maya villages remained remote from Spanish colonial authority, and for the most part continued to manage their own affairs. Maya communities and the nuclear family maintained their traditional day-to-day life.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; The basic Mesoamerican diet of maize and beans continued, although agricultural output was improved by the introduction of steel tools. Traditional crafts such as weaving, ceramics, and basketry continued to be produced. Community markets and trade in local products continued long after the conquest. At times the colonial administration encouraged the traditional economy in order to extract tribute in the form of ceramics or cotton textiles, although these were usually made to European specifications. Maya beliefs and language proved resistant to change, in spite of the vigorous efforts of Catholic missionaries.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The 260-day ''[[tzolkʼin]]'' ritual calendar continues in use in modern Maya communities in the highlands of Guatemala and Chiapas,&lt;ref&gt;Zorich 2012, p. 29. Thompson 1932, p. 449.&lt;/ref&gt; and millions of Mayan-language speakers inhabit the territory in which their ancestors developed their civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Sharer and Traxler 2006, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Investigation of the Maya civilization==
[[File:Uxmal nunnery by Catherwood 02.jpg|thumb|right|Drawing by [[Frederick Catherwood]] of the Nunnery complex at [[Uxmal]]]]
From the 16th century onwards, Spanish soldiers, clergy and administrators were familiar with pre-Columbian Maya history and beliefs. The agents of the Catholic Church wrote detailed accounts of the Maya, in support of their efforts at evangelisation, and absorption of the Maya into the Spanish Empire.&lt;ref name="Demarest04p31"&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; The writings of 16th-century [[Bishop Diego de Landa]], who had infamously burned a large number of Maya books, contain many details of Maya culture, including their beliefs and religious practices, calendar, aspects of their hieroglyphic writing, and oral history.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by various Spanish priests and colonial officials who left descriptions of ruins they visited in Yucatán and Central America. These early visitors were well aware of the association between the ruins and the Maya inhabitants of the region.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 32–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1839 American traveller and writer [[John Lloyd Stephens]], familiar with earlier Spanish investigations, set out to visit Uxmal, Copán, Palenque, and other sites with English architect and draftsman [[Frederick Catherwood]].&lt;ref&gt;Koch 2013, pp. 1, 105.&lt;/ref&gt; Their illustrated accounts of the ruins sparked strong popular interest in the region and the people, and brought the Maya to the attention of the world.&lt;ref name="Demarest04p31"/&gt; Their account was picked up by 19th century antiquarians such as [[Augustus Le Plongeon]] and [[Désiré Charnay]], who attributed the ruins to Old World civilizations, or [[Lost lands|sunken continents]].&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; The later 19th century saw the recording and recovery of ethnohistoric accounts of the Maya, and the first steps in deciphering Maya hieroglyphs.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 33–34.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Castillo Maler.jpg|thumb|left|1892 photograph of the [[El Castillo, Chichen Itza|Castillo]] at [[Chichen Itza]], by [[Teoberto Maler]]]]
The final two decades of the 19th century saw the birth of modern scientific archaeology in the Maya region, with the meticulous work of [[Alfred Maudslay]] and [[Teoberto Maler]].&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 37–38.&lt;/ref&gt; Sites such as [[Altar de Sacrificios]], Coba, Seibal, and Tikal were cleared and documented.&lt;ref name="Demarest 2004, p. 38"&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 20th century, the [[Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology|Peabody Museum]] was sponsoring excavations at Copán and in the Yucatán Peninsula,&lt;ref name="Demarest 2004, p. 38"/&gt; and artefacts were being smuggled out of the region to the museum's collection. In the first two decades of the 20th century, advances were made in the deciphering of the Maya calendar, and identification of deities, dates, and religious concepts.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sylvanus Morley]] began a project to document every known Maya monument and hieroglyphic inscription, in some cases recording the texts of monuments that have since been destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 39–40.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Carnegie Institution for Science|Carnegie Institution]] sponsored excavations at Copán, Chichen Itza and [[Uaxactun]], and the modern foundations of Maya studies were laid.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1930s onwards, the pace of archaeological exploration increased dramatically, with large-scale excavations across the entire Maya region.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in many locations, Maya ruins have been overgrown by the jungle, becoming dense enough to hide structures just a few meters away. To find unidentified ruins, researchers have turned to [[satellite imagery]], in order to look at the visible and [[Near-infrared spectroscopy|near-infrared spectra]]. Due to their limestone construction, the monuments affected the chemical makeup of the soil as they deteriorated; some moisture-loving plants are entirely absent, while others were killed off or discoloured.&lt;ref&gt;NASA Earth Observatory.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s, the distinguished Mayanist [[J. Eric S. Thompson]] promoted the ideas that Maya cities were essentially vacant ceremonial centres serving a dispersed population in the forest, and that the Maya civilization was governed by peaceful astronomer-priests.&lt;ref name="Demarest 2004, p. 44"&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; These ideas arose from the limited understanding of Maya script at the time;&lt;ref name="Demarest 2004, p. 44"/&gt; they began to collapse with major advances in the decipherment of the script in the late 20th century, pioneered by [[Heinrich Berlin]], [[Tatiana Proskouriakoff]], and [[Yuri Knorozov]].&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; As breakthroughs in the understanding of Maya script were made from the 1950s onwards, the texts revealed the warlike activities of the Classic Maya kings, and the view of the Maya as peaceful could no longer be supported.&lt;ref&gt;Foster 2002, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Detailed settlement surveys of Maya cities revealed the evidence of large populations, putting an end to the vacant ceremonial centre model.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest 2004, pp. 49–51.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, 60.000 uncharted structures were revealed by archaeologists with the help of the revolutionary technology lasers called '[[lidar]]' in northern [[Guatemala]]. The project applied [[Lidar|Lidar technology]] on an area of 2,100 square kilometers in the [[Maya Biosphere Reserve]] in the [[Petén Department|Petén]] region of Guatemala. Unlike previous assumptions, thanks to the new findings, archaeologists believe that 7-11 million [[Maya peoples|Maya people]] inhabited in northern Guatemala during the late classical period from 650 to 800 A.D. Lidar technology digitally removed the tree canopy to reveal ancient remains and showed that Maya cities like [[Tikal]] were bigger than previously assumed. Houses, palaces, elevated highways, and defensive fortifications were unearthed because of the Lidar. According to the archaeologist Stephen Houston, it is "one of the greatest advances in over 150 years of Maya archaeology".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-42916261|title=Sprawling Maya network discovered under Guatemala jungle|last=|first=|date=|website=BBC NEWS|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2018/02/maya-laser-lidar-guatemala-pacunam/|title=This Ancient Civilization Was Twice As Big As Medieval England|date=2018-02-01|website=National Geographic News|language=en|access-date=2019-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The capital of  [[Plan de Ayutla (Maya site)|Sak Tz’i’]] (an Ancient Maya kingdom) now named Lacanja Tzeltal, was revealed by researchers led by associate anthropology professor Charles Golden and bioarchaeologist Andrew Scherer in the Chiapas in the backyard of a Mexican farmer in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.heritagedaily.com/2020/03/archaeologists-discover-lost-capital-of-ancient-maya-kingdom/126361|title=Archaeologists discover lost capital of ancient Maya Kingdom|date=2020-03-12|website=HeritageDaily - Archaeology News|language=en-US|access-date=2020-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.express.co.uk/news/science/1254403/Archaeology-news-Ancient-Maya-kingdom-discovery-Mexico-cattle-ranch|title=Archaeology breakthrough: Ancient Maya kingdom discovered in... a rancher's backyard|last=Kettley|first=Sebastian|date=2020-03-13|website=Express.co.uk|language=en|access-date=2020-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Multiple domestic constructions used by the population for religious purposes. “Plaza Muk’ul Ton” or Monuments Plaza where people used to gather for ceremonies was also unearthed by the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://phys.org/news/2020-03-ancient-maya-kingdom-unearthed-backyard.html|title=Ancient Maya kingdom unearthed in a backyard in Mexico|website=phys.org|language=en-us|access-date=2020-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ancient-origins.net/news-history-archaeology/maya-kingdom-0013407|title=Long Lost Maya Kingdom Unearthed On Mexican Cattle Ranch|last=ancient-origins|website=www.ancient-origins.net|language=en|access-date=2020-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin|indent=yes}}
:{{Cite book |author1=Acemoglu, Daron |author2=James A. Robinson |title=Why Nations Fail |year=2012 |isbn=978-0-307-71921-8 |oclc=805356561 |publisher=Random House |location=London, UK |url=https://archive.org/details/whynationsfailor00acem }}
:{{cite journal |author=Andrews, Anthony P. |title=The Political Geography of the Sixteenth Century Yucatan Maya: Comments and Revisions |journal=Journal of Anthropological Research |volume=40 |issue=4 |date=Winter 1984 |pages=589–596 |publisher=University of New Mexico |jstor=3629799 |location=Albuquerque, New Mexico, US |issn=0091-7710 |oclc=1787802|doi=10.1086/jar.40.4.3629799 }} {{subscription only}}
:{{cite journal |author=Arroyo, Bárbara  |title=El Poslclásico Tardío en los Altos de Guatemala |trans-title=The Late Postclassic in the Guatemalan Highlands |journal=Arqueología Mexicana |volume=IX |issue=50 |date=July–August 2001 |editor=Enrique Vela |pages=38–43 |publisher=Editorial Raíces |issn=0188-8218|language=es |location=Mexico City, Mexico |oclc=40772247}}
:{{cite journal |author=Becker, Marshall Joseph  |title=Maya Heterarchy as Inferred from Classic-Period Plaza Plans |journal=Ancient Mesoamerica |issn=0956-5361 |volume=15 |year=2004 |pages=127–138 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |doi=10.1017/S0956536104151079 |url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=234946&amp;fileId=S0956536104151079 |oclc=43698811}} {{subscription required}}
:{{cite web |author=Beeland, DeLene |url=http://news.ufl.edu/2007/11/08/mayan-game/ |title=UF study: Maya politics likely played role in ancient large-game decline |publisher=University of Florida News |date=2007-11-08 |accessdate=2010-08-01 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141112225020/http://news.ufl.edu/archive/2007/11/uf-study-maya-politics-likely-played-role-in-ancient-large-game-decline.html |archivedate=2014-11-12 |location=Gainesville, Florida, US}}
:{{cite book |author=Borowicz, James |year=2003 |chapter=Images of Power and the Power of Images: Early Classic Iconographic Programs of the Carved Monuments of Tikal |editor=Geoffrey E. Braswell |title=The Maya and Teotihuacan: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |url=https://archive.org/details/mayateotihuacanr00bras_314 |url-access=limited |pages=[https://archive.org/details/mayateotihuacanr00bras_314/page/n235 217]–234 |location=Austin, Texas, US |publisher=[[University of Texas Press]] |isbn=978-0-292-70587-6 |oclc=49936017}}
:{{cite journal |author=Carmack, Robert M. А. |title=Historical Antropological Perspective on the Maya Civilization |journal=[[Social Evolution &amp; History]] |volume=2 |issue=1 |date=March 2003 |pages=71–115 |url=http://www.socionauki.ru/journal/articles/130151/ |publisher=Uchitel |location=Moscow, Russia |oclc=50573883 |issn=1681-4363}}
:{{cite book |author=Caso Barrera, Laura |title=Caminos en la selva: migración, comercio y resistencia: Mayas yucatecos e itzaes, siglos XVII–XIX |trans-title=Roads in the Forest: Migration, Commerce and Resistance: Yucatec and Itza Maya, 17th–19th Centuries |publisher=El Colegio de México, Fondo de Cultura Económica |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MPt5AAAAMAAJ |year=2002 |isbn=978-968-16-6714-6 |location=Mexico City, Mexico |oclc=835645038|language=es}}
:{{cite journal |author=Cecil, Leslie |author2=Prudence M. Rice |author3=Don S. Rice |year=1999 |title=Los estilos tecnológicos de la cerámica Postclásica con engobe de la región de los lagos de Petén |trans-title=The Technological Styles of Postclassic Slipped Ceramics in the Petén Lakes Region |journal=Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala |volume=XII (1998) |editor=J. P. Laporte |editor2=H. L. Escobedo |pages=788–795 |language=es |publisher=Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |oclc=42674202 |accessdate=2012-11-26 |url=http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/61.98%20-%20Leslie.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131102230356/http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/61.98%20-%20Leslie.pdf |archivedate=2013-11-02 }}
:{{cite book |author=Coe, Michael D. |year=1999 |title=The Maya|edition=Sixth |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |location=New York |isbn=978-0-500-28066-9 |oclc=40771862}}
:{{cite web |author=del Águila Flores, Patricia   |title=Zaculeu: Ciudad Postclásica en las Tierras Altas Mayas de Guatemala |year=2007 |trans-title=Zaculeu: Postclassic City in the Maya Highlands of Guatemala |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |url=http://www.mcd.gob.gt/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/zaculeu-ciudad-postclasica-en-las-tierras-altas-mayas-de-guatemala.pdf |accessdate=2011-08-06 |publisher=[[Ministerio de Cultura y Deportes]] |oclc=277021068 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721084703/http://www.mcd.gob.gt/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/zaculeu-ciudad-postclasica-en-las-tierras-altas-mayas-de-guatemala.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-21|language=es}}
:{{cite book |author=Demarest, Arthur  |authorlink=Arthur Demarest |year=2004 |title=Ancient Maya: The Rise and Fall of a Forest Civilization |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |isbn=978-0-521-53390-4 |oclc=51438896}}
:{{Cite book|author=Drew, David |year=1999 |title=The Lost Chronicles of the Maya Kings |publisher=Phoenix Press |location=London, UK |isbn=978-0-7538-0989-1 |oclc=59565970}}
:{{cite book |author=Estrada-Belli, Francisco |year=2011 |title=The First Maya Civilization: Ritual and Power Before the Classic Period |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=Abingdon, UK and New York, US |isbn=978-0-415-42994-8 |oclc=614990197}}
:{{cite book |author=Foias, Antonia E. |year=2014 |origyear=2013 |title=Ancient Maya Political Dynamics |isbn=978-0-8130-6089-7 |publisher=University Press of Florida |location=Gainesville, Florida, US |oclc=878111565}}
:{{cite book |author=Foster, Lynn |title=Handbook to Life in the Ancient Maya World |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, US |isbn=978-0-19-518363-4 |oclc=57319740}}
:{{cite book |author=Guillemín, Jorge F.   |year=1965 |title=Iximché: Capital del Antiguo Reino Cakchiquel |publisher=Tipografía Nacional de Guatemala |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |oclc=1498320|language=es |trans-title=Iximche: Capital of the Ancient Kaqchikel Kingdom}}
:{{cite journal |author1=Hammond, Norman |author2=Duncan Pring |author3=Rainer Berger |author4=V. R. Switsur |author5=A. P. Ward |title=Radiocarbon chronology for early Maya occupation at Cuello, Belize |journal=Nature |issue=260 |publisher=Nature.com |doi=10.1038/260579a0 |date=1976-04-15 |issn=0028-0836 |volume=260 |pages=579–581}}
:{{cite journal |author1=Hansen, Richard D. |author2=Beatriz Balcárcel |author3=Edgar Suyuc |author4=Héctor E. Mejía |author5=Enrique Hernández |author6=Gendry Valle |author7=Stanley P. Guenter |author8=Shannon Novak |year=2006 |title=Investigaciones arqueológicas en el sitio Tintal, Petén |trans-title=Archaeological investigations at the site of Tintal, Peten |url=http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/68_-_Hansen_et_al_-_2.05_-_Digital.pdf |volume=XIX (2005) |journal=Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala |editor=J.P. Laporte |editor2=B. Arroyo |editor3=H. Mejía |pages=739–751 |publisher=Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |accessdate=2011-08-19 |language=es |oclc=71050804 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110813130852/http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/68_-_Hansen_et_al_-_2.05_-_Digital.pdf |archivedate=2011-08-13 }}
:{{cite book |author=Feldman, Lawrence H.   |year=2000 |title=Lost Shores, Forgotten Peoples: Spanish Explorations of the South East Maya Lowlands |publisher=[[Duke University Press]] |location=Durham, North Carolina, US |isbn=978-0-8223-2624-3 |oclc=254438823}}
:{{cite book |author=Jones, Grant D.   |year=1998 |title=The Conquest of the Last Maya Kingdom |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PeOWl54Mt7UC&amp;pg=RA2-PT82#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]] |location=Stanford, California, US |isbn=9780804735223}}
:{{cite book |author=Jones, Grant D.   |year=2000 |chapter=The Lowland Maya, from the Conquest to the Present |editor=Richard E.W. Adams |editor2=Murdo J. Macleod |title=The Cambridge History of the Native Peoples of the Americas, Vol. II: Mesoamerica, part 2 |location=Cambridge, UK |publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages=346–391|isbn=978-0-521-65204-9 |oclc=33359444}}
:{{cite book |author=Koch, Peter O. |title=John Lloyd Stephens and Frederick Catherwood: Pioneers of Mayan Archaeology |publisher=McFarland |year=2013 |isbn=9780786471072 |oclc=824359844 |location=Jefferson, North Carolina, US}}
:{{cite book |author=Lenkersdorf, Gudrun  |year=2004 |origyear=1995 |chapter=La resistencia a la conquista española en Los Altos de Chiapas |trans-title=Resistance to the Spanish Conquest in the Chiapas Highlands |editor=Juan Pedro Viqueira |editor2=Mario Humberto Ruz |title=Chiapas: los rumbos de otra historia |location=Mexico City, Mexico |publisher=Centro de Investigaciones Filológicas with Centro de Investigaciones y Estudios Superiores en Antropología Social (CIESAS) |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141113192201/http://www.unich.edu.mx/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/LARESI-1.PDF |chapter-url=http://www.unich.edu.mx/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/LARESI-1.PDF |archivedate=2014-11-13 |pages=71–85 |isbn=978-968-36-4836-5 |oclc=36759921 |language=es}}
:{{cite journal|author=Looper, Matthew G.   |year=1999 |title=New Perspectives on the Late Classic Political History of Quirigua, Guatemala |journal=Ancient Mesoamerica |location=Cambridge and New York|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=263–280 |issn=0956-5361 |oclc=86542758|doi=10.1017/S0956536199101135}}
:{{Cite journal|author=Love, Michael |date=December 2007 |title=Recent Research in the Southern Highlands and Pacific Coast of Mesoamerica |journal=Journal of Archaeological Research |volume=15 |issue=4 |pages=275–328 |publisher=[[Springer Netherlands]] |issn=1573-7756 |doi=10.1007/s10814-007-9014-y }}&lt;!--|accessdate=2006-02-01--&gt;
:{{cite book |author=Lovell, W. George   |year=2000 |chapter=The Highland Maya |editor=Richard E.W. Adams |editor2=Murdo J. Macleod |title=The Cambridge History of the Native Peoples of the Americas, Vol. II: Mesoamerica, part 2 |location=Cambridge, UK |publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages=392–444|isbn=978-0-521-65204-9 |oclc=33359444}}
:{{cite book |author=Lovell, W. George   |year=2005 |title=Conquest and Survival in Colonial Guatemala: A Historical Geography of the Cuchumatán Highlands, 1500–1821 |publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]] |location=Montreal, Canada |edition=3rd |isbn=978-0-7735-2741-6 |oclc=58051691 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=05wSqQiu52MC}}
:{{cite book |author=Martin, Simon |authorlink=Simon Martin (Mayanist) |author2=Nikolai Grube |year=2000 |title=Chronicle of the Maya Kings and Queens: Deciphering the Dynasties of the Ancient Maya |location=London and New York |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |isbn=978-0-500-05103-0 |oclc=47358325 |url=https://archive.org/details/chronicleofmayak00mart }}
:{{cite journal |author=Masson, Marilyn A. |date=2012-11-06 |title=Maya collapse cycles |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=109 |issue=45 |pages=18237–18238 |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |jstor=41829886 |issn=1091-6490 |location=Washington, DC, US |doi=10.1073/pnas.1213638109|pmid=22992650 |pmc=3494883 }} {{subscription required}}
:{{cite book |author=Matthew, Laura E.   |year=2012 |title=Memories of Conquest: Becoming Mexicano in Colonial Guatemala |publisher=[[University of North Carolina Press]] |location=Chapel Hill, North Carolina, US |isbn=978-0-8078-3537-1 |oclc=752286995 |series=First Peoples |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RVAFbknbo_EC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |format=hardback}}
:{{cite book |author=Miller, Mary |authorlink=Mary Miller (art historian) |year=1999 |title=Maya Art and Architecture |location=London, UK and New York, US |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |isbn=978-0-500-20327-9 |oclc=41659173 |url=https://archive.org/details/mayaartarchitect00mill }}
:{{cite web |author=NASA Earth Observatory |author-link=NASA Earth Observatory |url=http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=6293 | title=Maya Ruins | publisher=[[Goddard Space Flight Center]] | accessdate=2006-04-28 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121203180433/http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=6293 |archivedate=2012-12-03 |location=Greenbelt, Maryland, US}}
:{{cite book |author=Olmedo Vera, Bertina |year=1997 |editor=A. Arellano Hernández|title=The Mayas of the Classic Period |location=Mexico City, Mexico |publisher=Consejo Nacional para la Cultura y las Artes (CONACULTA) |pages=9–99 |isbn=978-970-18-3005-5 |oclc=42213077|display-editors=etal}}
:{{cite journal |author=Popenoe de Hatch, Marion |author2=Christa Schieber de Lavarreda |year=2001 |title=Una revisión preliminar de la historia de Takʼalik Abʼaj, departamento de Retalhuleu |trans-title=A Preliminary Revision of the History of Takalik Abaj, Retalhuleu Department |volume=XIV (2000) |journal=Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala |editor=J.P. Laporte |editor2=A.C. Suasnávar |editor3=B. Arroyo |pages=990–1005 |publisher=Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |url=http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/77.00.pdf |accessdate=2009-02-01 |language=es |oclc=49563126 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091211140452/http://www.asociaciontikal.com/pdf/77.00.pdf |archivedate=2009-12-11 }}
:{{cite journal |author1=Pugh, Timothy W. |author2=Leslie G. Cecil |year=2012 |title=The contact period of central Petén, Guatemala in color |journal=Social and Cultural Analysis, Department of |volume=Paper 6 |series=Faculty Publications |url=http://scholarworks.sfasu.edu/sca/6/ |publisher=Stephen F. Austin State University |location=Nacogdoches, Texas, US}}
:{{cite book |author=Recinos, Adrian   |authorlink=Adrián Recinos |origyear=1952 |year=1986 |title=Pedro de Alvarado: Conquistador de México y Guatemala |trans-title=Pedro de Alvarado: Conqueror of Mexico and Guatemala |edition=2nd |location=Antigua Guatemala, Guatemala |publisher=CENALTEX Centro Nacional de Libros de Texto y Material Didáctico "José de Pineda Ibarra" |oclc=243309954|language=es}}
:{{cite book |author=Restall, Matthew  |authorlink=Matthew Restall |author2=Florine Asselbergs |year=2007 |title=Invading Guatemala: Spanish, Nahua, and Maya Accounts of the Conquest Wars |publisher=[[Pennsylvania State University Press]] |location=University Park, Pennsylvania, US |isbn=978-0-271-02758-6 |oclc=165478850}}
:{{cite book |author=Rice, Prudence M.   |year=2009 |chapter=Who were the Kowoj? |editor=Prudence M. Rice |editor2=Don S. Rice |title=The Kowoj: identity, migration, and geopolitics in late postclassic Petén, Guatemala |url=https://archive.org/details/kowojidentitymig00rice   |url-access=limited   |location=Boulder, Colorado, US |publisher=[[University Press of Colorado]] |pages=[https://archive.org/details/kowojidentitymig00rice/page/n39 17]–19 |isbn=978-0-87081-930-8 |oclc=225875268}}
:{{cite book |author=Rice, Prudence M. |author2=Don S. Rice |year=2009 |chapter=Introduction to the Kowoj and their Petén Neighbors |editor=Prudence M. Rice |editor2=Don S. Rice |title=The Kowoj: identity, migration, and geopolitics in late postclassic Petén, Guatemala |url=https://archive.org/details/kowojidentitymig00rice |url-access=limited |location=Boulder, Colorado, US |publisher=University Press of Colorado |pages=[https://archive.org/details/kowojidentitymig00rice/page/n25 3]–15|isbn=978-0-87081-930-8 |oclc=225875268}}
:{{cite journal|author=Salisbury, David |author2=Mimi Koumenalis |author3=Barbara Moffett |date=19 September 2002 |title=Newly revealed hieroglyphs tell story of superpower conflict in the Maya world |url=http://exploration.vanderbilt.edu/print/pdfs/news/news_dospilas_feature.pdf |journal=Exploration: The Online Research Journal of Vanderbilt University |publisher=[[Vanderbilt University]] Office of Science and Research Communications |location=Nashville, TN  |oclc=50324967|accessdate=2015-05-20 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141102134600/http://exploration.vanderbilt.edu/print/pdfs/news/news_dospilas_feature.pdf |archivedate=2014-11-02 }}
:{{cite journal |author1=Saturno, William A. |author2=David Stuart |author3=Boris Beltrán |title=Early Maya Writing at San Bartolo, Guatemala |journal=Science |series=New Series |volume=311 |issue=5765 |date=2006-03-03 |pages=1281–1283 |publisher=American Association for the Advancement of Science |jstor=3845835 |issn=1095-9203 |oclc=863047799 |doi=10.1126/science.1121745 |pmid=16400112}} {{subscription required}}
:{{cite book |author=Schele, Linda |authorlink=Linda Schele |author2=Peter Mathews |year=1999 |title=The Code of Kings: The language of seven Maya temples and tombs |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York, US |isbn=978-0-684-85209-6 |oclc=41423034 |url=https://archive.org/details/codeofkingslangu00lind }}
:{{cite journal |author=Schieber de Lavarreda, Christa |author2=Miguel Orrego Corzo  |year=2010 |title=La Escultura "El Cargador del Ancestro" y su contexto. Mesa Redonda: Pozole de signos y significados. Juntándonos en torno a la epigrafía e iconografía de la escultura preclásica. Proyecto Nacional Takʼalik Abʼaj, Ministerio de Cultura y Deportes, Dirección General del Patrimonio Cultural y Natural/IDAEH |trans-title=The "Ancestor Carrier" and its context. Round Table: A hotpot of signs and meanings. Linking us in turn to the epigraphy and iconography of Preclassic sculpture. Takalik Abaj National Project, Ministry of Culture and Sports, General Directorate of Cultural and Natural Heritage/IDAEH |journal=Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala |volume=XXIII (2009) |publisher=Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología |location=Guatemala City, Guatemala |language=es |oclc=662509369 |isbn=9789929400375}}
:{{cite book |author=Sharer, Robert J. |authorlink=Robert Sharer |year=2000 |chapter=The Maya Highlands and the Adjacent Pacific Coast |editor=Richard E.W. Adams |editor2=Murdo J. Macleod |title=The Cambridge History of the Native Peoples of the Americas, Vol. II: Mesoamerica, part 1 |location=Cambridge, UK |publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages=449–499|isbn=978-0-521-35165-2 |oclc=33359444}}
:{{cite book |author=Sharer, Robert J. |author2=Loa P. Traxler |year=2006 |title=The Ancient Maya |edition=6th, fully revised |location=Stanford, California, US |publisher=Stanford University Press |isbn=978-0-8047-4817-9 |oclc=57577446 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/ancientmaya0006shar }}
:{{cite journal |author=Stuart, David |authorlink=David Stuart (Mayanist) | date=Spring–Autumn 1996 |title=Kings of Stone: A Consideration of Stelae in Ancient Maya Ritual and Representation |journal=RES: Anthropology and Aesthetics |issue=29/30 The Pre–Columbian |pages=148–171 |publisher=[[President and Fellows of Harvard College]] acting through the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts, US |issn=0277-1322 |jstor=20166947}}
:{{cite journal |author=Thompson, J. Eric S. |authorlink=J. Eric S. Thompson |title=A Maya Calendar from the Alta Vera Paz, Guatemala |journal=American Anthropologist |series=New Series |volume=34 |issue=3 |date=July–September 1932 |pages=449–454 |publisher=Wiley on behalf of the American Anthropological Association |jstor=661903 |issn=0002-7294 |oclc=1479294 |doi=10.1525/aa.1932.34.3.02a00090}} {{subscription required}}
:{{cite journal |author=Zorich, Zach |title=The Maya Sense of Time |journal=Archaeology |volume=65 |issue=6 |date=November–December 2012 |pages=25–29 |publisher=Archaeological Institute of America |jstor=41804605 |location=New York, US |issn=0003-8113 |oclc=1481828}} {{subscription required}}
{{refend}}

{{Maya}}

[[Category:Maya civilization|*]]
[[Category:History of Mesoamerica]]
[[Category:History of the Yucatán Peninsula]]
[[Category:History of the Maya civilization]]</text>
      <sha1>nm63rxvk82p0udfxq84muj01zrp9z1m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
