<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Crane (bird)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>198041</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959813167</id>
      <parentid>959812748</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-30T19:09:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LizardJr8</username>
        <id>5320876</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2A00:23C8:8804:1101:5876:8310:2782:D09F|2A00:23C8:8804:1101:5876:8310:2782:D09F]] ([[User talk:2A00:23C8:8804:1101:5876:8310:2782:D09F|talk]]) to last revision by 92.5.15.163 ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="31246" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Family of birds}}
{{About|the bird family||Crane (disambiguation)}}
{{automatic taxobox
| image = Double Trouble (4919788838).jpg
| image_caption = [[Sandhill crane]]s&lt;br/&gt;(''Antigone canadensis'')
| taxon = Gruidae
| authority = [[Nicholas Aylward Vigors|Vigors]], 1825
| subdivision_ranks = Genera
| subdivision = 
See text
}}
'''Cranes''' are a family, the '''Gruidae''', of large, long-legged, and long-necked [[bird]]s in the group [[Gruiformes]]. The 15 species of cranes are placed in 3 genera, [[Antigone (genus)|Antigone]], [[Balearica]], and [[Grus (genus)|Grus]]. Unlike the similar-looking but unrelated [[heron]]s, cranes fly with necks outstretched, not pulled back. Cranes live on all continents except [[Antarctica]] and [[South America]].

They are opportunistic feeders that change their diets according to the season and their own nutrient requirements. They eat a range of items from suitably sized small [[rodent]]s, [[fish]], [[amphibian]]s, and [[insect]]s to [[cereal|grain]] and [[Berry|berries]].

Cranes construct platform nests in shallow water, and typically lay two eggs at a time. Both parents help to rear the young, which remain with them until the next breeding season.&lt;ref name=EoB&gt;{{cite book |editor=Forshaw, Joseph|author= Archibald, George W.|year=1991|title=Encyclopaedia of Animals: Birds|publisher= Merehurst Press|location=London|pages= 95–96|isbn= 1-85391-186-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some species and populations of cranes [[bird migration|migrate]] over long distances; others do not migrate at all. Cranes are solitary during the breeding season, occurring in pairs, but during the nonbreeding season, they are gregarious, forming large flocks where their numbers are sufficient.

Most species of cranes have been affected by human activities and are at the least classified as threatened, if not critically endangered. The plight of the [[whooping crane]]s of North America inspired some of the first [[United States|US]] legislation to protect [[endangered species]].

==Description==
[[File:Sandhill bare areas.jpg|thumb|left|The bare area of skin on the face of a [[sandhill crane]] can change colour or even expand in area when the bird is excited.]]
Cranes are very large birds, often considered the world's tallest flying birds. They range in size from the [[demoiselle crane]], which measures {{convert|90|cm|in|abbr=on}} in length, to the [[sarus crane]], which can be up to {{convert|176|cm|in|abbr=on}}, although the heaviest is the [[red-crowned crane]], which can weigh {{convert|12|kg|abbr=on}} prior to migrating. They are long-legged and long-necked birds with streamlined bodies and large, rounded wings. The males and females do not vary in external appearance, but males tend to be slightly larger than females.&lt;ref name = "HBW"&gt;{{Cite book | first = George | last = Archibald | first2 = Curt | last2 = Meine | editor-first = Josep | editor-last = del Hoyo | editor2-first = Andrew | editor2-last = Elliott | editor3-last = Sargatal | editor3-first = Jordi | contribution = Family Gruidae (Cranes) | title = [[Handbook of the Birds of the World]]. Volume 3, Hoatzin to Auks | year = 1996 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/handbookofbirdso0001unse/page/60 60–81] | place = Barcelona | publisher = Lynx Edicions | isbn = 84-87334-20-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[plumage]] of cranes varies by habitat. Species inhabiting vast, open wetlands tend to have more white in their plumage than do species that inhabit smaller wetlands or forested habitats, which tend to be more grey. These white species are also generally larger. The smaller size and colour of the forest species is thought to help them maintain a less conspicuous profile while nesting; two of these species (the [[common crane|common]] and [[sandhill crane]]s) also daub their feathers with mud to further hide while nesting.

[[File:SarusTrachea.jpg|thumb|The long coiled [[Vertebrate trachea|trachea]] that produces the trumpeting calls of cranes ([[sarus crane]], ''Antigone antigone'')]]
Most species of cranes have some areas of bare skin on their faces; the only two exceptions are the [[blue crane|blue]] and demoiselle cranes. This skin is used in communication with other cranes, and can be expanded by contracting and relaxing muscles, and change the intensity of colour. Feathers on the head can be moved and erected in the blue, wattled, and demoiselle cranes for signaling, as well.

Also important to communication is the position and length of the [[Vertebrate trachea|trachea]]. In the two crowned cranes, the trachea is shorter and only slightly impressed upon the bone of the [[sternum]], whereas the trachea of the other species is longer and penetrates the sternum. In some species, the entire sternum is fused to the bony plates of the trachea, and this helps amplify the crane's [[bird vocalization|calls]], allowing them to carry for several kilometres.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;&lt;ref name="sternum"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gaunt|first=Abbot |author2=Sandra L. L. Gaunt |author3=Henry D. Prange |author4=Jeremy S. Wasser|title=The effects of tracheal coiling on the vocalizations of cranes (Aves; Gruidae)|journal=Journal of Comparative Physiology A|year=1987|volume=161|issue=1|pages=43–58|doi=10.1007/BF00609454}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evolution==
The [[fossil]] record of cranes leaves much to be desired. Apparently, the subfamilies were well distinct by the Late [[Eocene]] (around 35 [[mya (unit)|mya]]). The present genera are apparently some 20 mya old. [[Biogeography]] of known fossil and the living taxa of cranes suggests that the group is probably of ([[Laurasia]]n?) Old World origin. The extant diversity at the genus level is centered on (eastern) [[Africa]], making it all the more regrettable that no decent fossil record exists from there. On the other hand, it is peculiar that numerous fossils of [[Ciconiiformes]] are documented from there; these birds presumably shared much of their [[habitat]] with cranes back then already. Cranes are sister taxa to [[Eogruidae]], a lineage of flightless birds; as predicted by the fossil record of true cranes, eogruids were native to the Old World. A species of true crane, ''[[Grus cubensis]]'', has similarly become flightless and ratite-like.

[[File:Ergilornis-commission.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Eogruidae]] is an extinct lineage of mostly flightless stem-cranes. Pictured is the two-toed ''[[Ergilornis]]''.]]

Fossil genera are tentatively assigned to the present-day subfamilies:

'''Gruinae'''
* ''[[Palaeogrus]]'' (Middle Eocene of Germany and Italy – Middle Miocene of France)&lt;!-- AmMusNovit711. BullAMNH151:1. --&gt;
* ''[[Pliogrus]]'' (Early Pliocene of Eppelsheim, Germany)&lt;!-- BullAMNH151:1. Condor54:174. --&gt;
* ''Camusia'' (Late Miocene of Menorca, Mediterranean)&lt;!-- AnuOrnitolBalears16:3 --&gt;
* ''"Grus" conferta'' (Late Miocene/Early Pliocene of Contra Costa County, US)&lt;ref name=Miller/&gt;&lt;!-- Condor44:126,46:25. --&gt;
'''Sometimes considered Balearicinae'''
* ''[[Geranopsis]]'' (Hordwell Late Eocene – Early Oligocene of England)&lt;!-- BullAMNH151:1 --&gt;
* ''[[Anserpica]]'' (Late Oligocene of France)
'''Sometimes considered Gruidae ''incertae sedis'''''
* ''[[Eobalearica]]'' (Ferghana Late? Eocene of Ferghana, Uzbekistan)&lt;!-- BullAMNH151:1 --&gt;
* ''[[Probalearica]]'' (Late Oligocene? – Middle Pliocene of Florida, US, France?, Moldavia and Mongolia) – A ''[[nomen dubium]]''?&lt;!-- BullAMNH151:1. Condor54:174. --&gt;
* ''[[Aramornis]]'' (Sheep Creek Middle Miocene of Snake Creek Quarries, US)&lt;!-- AmMusNovit211:1. BullAMNH151:1. --&gt;

==Distribution and habitat==
{{See also|List of Gruiformes by population}}
[[File:Anthropoides virgo -Mongolia -flying-8.jpg|thumb|[[Demoiselle crane]]s in [[Mongolia]]: Central Asian populations of this species migrate to Northern India in the winter.]]
The cranes have a [[cosmopolitan distribution]], occurring across most of the world continents. They are absent from Antarctica and, mysteriously, South America. East Asia is the centre of crane diversity, with eight species, followed by Africa, which holds five resident species and wintering populations of a sixth. Australia, Europe, and North America have two regularly occurring species each. Of the four crane genera, ''Balearica'' (two species) is restricted to Africa, and ''Leucogeranus'' (one species) is restricted to Asia; the other two genera, ''Grus'' (including ''Anthropoides'' and ''Bugeranus'') and ''Antigone'', are both widespread.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;&lt;ref name = ioc/&gt;

Most species of cranes are dependent on wetlands and require large areas of open space. Most species nest in shallow wetlands. Some species nest in wetlands, but move their chicks up onto grasslands to feed (while returning to wetlands at night), whereas others remain in wetlands for the entirety of the breeding season. Even the demoiselle crane and blue crane, which may nest and feed in grasslands (or even arid grasslands or deserts), require wetlands for roosting at night. The only two species that do not always roost in wetlands are the two African crowned cranes (''Balearica''), which are the only cranes to roost in trees.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;

Some crane species are sedentary, remaining in the same area throughout the year, while others are highly [[bird migration|migratory]], traveling thousands of kilometres each year from their breeding sites. A few species have both migratory and sedentary populations.

==Behaviour and ecology==
[[File:PikiWiki Israel 7524 Cranes.JPG|thumb|[[Common crane]]s in Israel: Many species of crane gather in large groups during migration and on their wintering grounds.]]
The cranes are [[Diurnality|diurnal]] birds that vary in their sociality by season. During the [[breeding season]], they are territorial and usually remain on their territory all the time. In contrast in the non-breeding season, they tend to be gregarious, forming large flocks to roost, socialize, and in some species feed. Species that feed predominately on vegetable matter in the non-breeding season feed in flocks to do so, whereas those that feed on animals  usually feed in family groups, joining flocks only during resting periods, or in preparation for travel during migration. Large aggregations of cranes are important for safety when resting and also as places for young unmated birds to meet others.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;

===Calls and communication===
Cranes are highly vocal and have a large vocabulary of specialized [[bird vocalization|calls]]. The vocabulary begins soon after hatching with low, purring  calls for maintaining contact with their parents, as well as food-begging calls. Other calls used as chicks include alarm calls and "flight intention" calls, both of which are maintained into adulthood. The cranes' duet calls are most impressive. They can be used for individual recognition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.craneworld.de |title=craneworld.de |publisher=craneworld.de |accessdate=2012-07-29 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120720225944/http://www.craneworld.de/ |archive-date=2012-07-20 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Feeding===
[[File:Black Necked Cranes(Grus Nigricollis) pair at Tsokar,Ladakh.jpg|thumb|A pair of black-necked cranes foraging]]
The cranes as a family consume a wide range of food, both animal and plant matter. When feeding on land, they consume seeds, leaves, nuts and acorns, berries, fruit, insects, worms, snails, small reptiles, mammals, and birds. In wetlands, roots, rhizomes, tubers, and other parts of emergent plants, other molluscs, small fish and amphibians are also consumed, as well. The exact composition of the diet varies by location, season, and availability. Within the wide range of items consumed, some patterns emerge; the shorter-billed species usually feed in drier uplands, while the longer-billed species feed in wetlands.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;

Cranes employ different foraging techniques for different food types. Tubers and rhizomes are dug for and a crane digging for them remains in place for some time digging and then expanding a hole to find them. In contrast both to this and the stationary wait and watch hunting methods employed by many herons, they forage for insects and animal prey by slowly moving forwards with their heads lowered and probing with their bills.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;

Where more than one species of cranes exists in a locality, each species adopts separate niches to minimise competition and niche overlap. At one important lake in [[Jiangxi Province]] in China, the [[Siberian crane]]s feed on the mudflats and in shallow water, the [[white-naped crane]]s on the wetland borders, the [[hooded crane]]s on sedge meadows, and the last two species also feed on the agricultural fields along with the common cranes.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt;

===Breeding===
[[File:Blue Cranes (Anthropoides paradiseus) couple parading ... (32457893122).jpg|left|thumb|Blue crane pair displaying]]
Cranes are perennially monogamous breeders, establishing long-term pair bonds that may last the lifetime of the birds. Pair bonds begin to form in the second or third years of life, but several years pass before the first successful breeding season. Initial breeding attempts often fail, and in many cases, newer pair bonds dissolve (divorce) after unsuccessful breeding attempts. Pairs that are repeatedly successful at breeding remain together for as long as they continue to do so.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt; In a study of sandhill cranes in Florida, seven of the 22 pairs studied remained together for an 11-year period. Of the pairs that separated, 53% was due to the death of one of the pair, 18% was due to divorce, and the fate of 29% of pairs was unknown.&lt;ref name="Nesbitt"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Nesbitt|first=Stephen A.|title=The Significance of Mate Loss in Florida Sandhill Cranes|journal=Wilson Bulletin|year=1989| volume=101|issue=4|pages=648–651|url=http://sora.unm.edu/sites/default/files/journals/wilson/v101n04/p0648-p0651.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar results had been found by acoustic monitoring (sonography/frequency analysis of duet and guard calls) in three breeding areas of common cranes in Germany over 10 years.&lt;ref name=Wessling/&gt;

Cranes are territorial and generally seasonal breeders. Seasonality varies both between and within species, depending on local conditions. Migratory species begin breeding upon reaching their summer breeding grounds, between April and June. The breeding season of tropical species, however, is usually timed to coincide with the wet or monsoon seasons. Territory sizes also vary depending on location. Tropical species can maintain very small territories, for example sarus cranes in India can breed on territories as small as one hectare where the area is of sufficient quality and disturbance by humans is minimised. In contrast, red-crowned crane territories may require 500 hectares, and pairs may defend even larger territories than that, up to several thousand hectares. Territory defence is usually performed by the male.&lt;ref name = "HBW"/&gt; Because of this, females are much less likely to retain the territory than males in the event of the death of a partner.&lt;ref name="Nesbitt"/&gt;

== Taxonomy and systematics ==
[[File:Grey crowned crane at Martin Mere.JPG|thumb|upright|[[Grey-crowned crane]] in captivity at [[Martin Mere]], UK]]
[[File:Japanse kraanvogels in Akan International Crane Centre, -24 februari 2012 a.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Red-crowned crane]]s (''Grus japonensis'')]]

The 15 living [[species]] of cranes are placed in three [[genus|genera]].&lt;ref name=ioc&gt;{{cite web| editor1-last=Gill | editor1-first=Frank | editor1-link=Frank Gill (ornithologist) | editor2-last=Donsker | editor2-first=David | year=2019 | title=Flufftails, finfoots, rails, trumpeters, cranes, limpkin | work=World Bird List Version 9.2 | url=https://www.worldbirdnames.org/bow/flufftails/ | publisher=International Ornithologists' Union | accessdate=26 June 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[molecular phylogenetic]] study published in 2010 found that the genus ''Grus'', as then defined, was [[polyphyletic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite journal | last1=Krajewski  | first1=C. | last2=Sipiorski | first2=J.T. | last3=Anderson | first3=F.E. | year=2010 | title=Mitochondrial genome sequences and the phylogeny of cranes (Gruiformes:  Gruidae) | journal=Auk | volume=127 | issue=2 | pages=440–452 | doi=10.1525/auk.2009.09045 | url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/277486138_Complete_Mitochondrial_Genome_Sequences_and_the_Phylogeny_of_Cranes_Gruiformes_Gruidae }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the resulting rearrangement to create [[monophyletic]] genera, the [[Siberian Crane]] was moved to the resurrected [[monotypic]] genus ''Leucogeranus'', while the sandhill crane, the white-naped crane, the sarus crane, and the brolga were moved to the resurrected genus ''[[Antigone (genus)|Antigone]]''.&lt;ref name=ioc/&gt; Some authorities recognize the additional genera ''Anthropoides'' (for the [[demoiselle crane]] and [[blue crane]]) and ''Bugeranus'' (for the [[wattled crane]]) on morphological grounds.
{| class="wikitable collapsible"
|-
! [[subfamily|SUBFAMILY]]
! Image
! Genus
! Species
|-
! style="text-align:center;"| '''[[subfamily|SUBFAMILY]] BALEARICINAE''' &lt;br&gt; crowned cranes
|[[File:Grey crowned crane at Martin Mere.JPG|120px]]
|'''''[[Balearica]]'''''
|
* [[Black crowned crane]], ''Balearica pavonina''
* [[Grey crowned crane]], ''Balearica regulorum''
|-
! rowspan="3" style="text-align:center;"| '''SUBFAMILY GRUINAE''' &lt;br&gt; typical cranes
|[[File:Grus leucogeranus male.jpg|120px]]
|'''''[[Leucogeranus]]'''''
|
* [[Siberian crane]], ''Leucogeranus leucogeranus''
|-
|[[File:White-naped Crane at Saijyo Ehime2.jpg|120px]]
|'''''[[Antigone (genus)|Antigone]]'''''
|
* [[Sandhill crane]], ''Antigone canadensis''
* [[White-naped crane]], ''Antigone vipio''
* [[Sarus crane]], ''Antigone antigone''
* [[Brolga]], ''Antigone rubicunda''
|-
|[[File:Grus americana Sasata.jpg|120px]]
|'''''[[Grus (bird)|Grus]]'''''
|
* [[Wattled crane]], ''Grus carunculata''
* [[Blue crane]], ''Grus paradisea''
* [[Demoiselle crane]], ''Grus virgo''
* [[Red-crowned crane]], ''Grus japonensis''
* [[Whooping crane]], ''Grus americana''
* [[Common crane]], ''Grus grus'', also known as the Eurasian crane
* [[Hooded crane]], ''Grus monacha''
* [[Black-necked crane]], ''Grus nigricollis''
|}

==In mythology and symbolism==
{{Further|Crane in Chinese mythology}}

[[File:Crane in its vigilance - illustration in the Harley Bestiary.jpeg|thumb|Illustration in the English manuscript ''Harley Bestiary'' (13th century) of the legend of the vigilant cranes: At night, cranes take turns keeping watch for enemies.]]
[[File:Edward Julius Detmold71.jpg|thumb|upright|A 1909 illustration of the fable of the geese and the cranes, from [[Aesop's Fables]]: The geese and the cranes were feeding in the same meadow, when a birdcatcher came to ensnare them in his nets. The cranes, being light of wing, fled away at his approach, while the geese, being slower of flight and heavier in their bodies, were captured.]]
The cranes' beauty and spectacular mating dances have made them highly symbolic birds in many cultures with records dating back to ancient times. Crane mythology is widely spread and can be found in areas such as India, the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]], South [[Arabian peninsula|Arabia]], [[China]], [[Korea]], [[Japan]], and  Native American cultures of North America. In northern [[Hokkaidō]], the women of the [[Ainu people]] performed a crane dance that was captured in 1908 in a photograph by [[Arnold Genthe]]. In Korea, a crane dance has been performed in the courtyard of the Tongdosa Temple since the [[Silla Dynasty]] (646 CE).

The [[Sanskrit]] epic poet [[Valmiki]] was inspired to write the first ''[[śloka]]'' couplet by the pathos of seeing a male sarus crane shot while mating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Leslie|first=J.|year=1998|title=A bird bereaved: The identity and significance of Valmiki's kraunca|journal=Journal of Indian Philosophy|volume=26|issue=5|pages=455–487|doi=10.1023/A:1004335910775}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hammer|first=Niels|year=2009|title= Why Sārus Cranes epitomize Karuṇarasa in the Rāmāyaṇa|journal=[[Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain &amp; Ireland]] | series =  (Third Series)|volume= 19|pages=187–211|doi=10.1017/S1356186308009334|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Mecca]], in pre-Islamic South Arabia, [[Al-lāt|Allāt]], [[Uzza]], and [[Manāt]] were believed to be the three chief goddesses of Mecca, they were called the "three exalted cranes" (''gharaniq'', an obscure word on which 'crane' is the usual [[Gloss (transliteration)|gloss]]). See [[Satanic Verses|''The Satanic Verses'']] for the best-known story regarding these three goddesses.{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

In [[China]], several styles of kung fu take inspiration from the movements of cranes in the wild, the most famous of these styles being Wing Chun, Hung Gar (tiger crane), and the Shaolin Five Animals style of fighting. Crane movements are well known for their fluidity and grace.{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

The [[Greek language|Greek]] for crane is Γερανος (''geranos''), which gives us the [[cranesbill]], or hardy geranium. The crane was a bird of omen. In the tale of [[Ibycus]] and the cranes, a thief attacked Ibycus (a poet of the sixth century BCE) and left him for dead. Ibycus called to a flock of passing cranes, which followed the attacker to a theater and hovered over him until, stricken with guilt, he confessed to the crime.{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

[[Pliny the Elder]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}} wrote that cranes would appoint one of their number to stand guard while they slept.  The sentry would hold a stone in its claw, so that if it fell asleep, it would drop the stone and waken. A crane holding a stone in its claw is a well-known symbol in [[heraldry]], and is known as a crane in its vigilance. Notably, however, the crest of [[Clan Cranstoun]] depicts a sleeping crane still in vigilance and holding the rock in its raised claw.&lt;ref name="Davies"&gt;[[Arthur Fox-Davies]], ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', T.C. and E.C. Jack, London, 1909, 247, https://archive.org/details/completeguidetoh00foxduoft.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aristotle]] describes the migration of cranes in the ''[[History of Animals]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classics.mit.edu/Aristotle/history_anim.8.viii.html |title=The Internet Classics Archive &amp;#124; The History of Animals by Aristotle |publisher=Classics.mit.edu |accessdate=2012-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; adding an account of their fights with [[Pygmy peoples|Pygmies]] as they wintered near the source of the [[Nile]].  He describes as untruthful an account that the crane carries a [[Touchstone (assaying tool)|touchstone]] inside it that can be used to test for gold when vomited up.  (This second story is not altogether implausible, as cranes might ingest appropriate gizzard stones in one locality and regurgitate them in a region where such stone is otherwise scarce.){{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

Greek and Roman myths often portrayed the dance of cranes as a love of joy and a celebration of life, and the crane was often associated with both [[Apollo]] and [[Hephaestus]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

In pre-modern Ottoman Empire, sultans would sometimes present a piece of crane feather [Turkish: ''turna teli''] to soldiers of any group in the army (janissaries, sipahis etc.) who performed heroically during a battle. Soldiers would attach this feather to their caps or headgears which would give them some sort of a rank among their peers. &lt;ref&gt; Rami Mehmed Paşa, Münşeat, p. 141b. Flügel Catalogue, H.O. 179, Austrian National Library.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Throughout Asia, the crane is a symbol of [[happiness]] and [[eternal youth]]. In Japan, the crane is one of the mystical or holy creatures (others include the [[Japanese dragon|dragon]] and the [[Cultural depictions of turtles and tortoises#Japan|tortoise]]) and symbolizes good fortune and longevity because of its fabled life span of a thousand years. The crane is a favourite subject of the tradition of ''[[origami]]'', or paper folding. An ancient Japanese legend promises that anyone who folds a [[thousand origami cranes]] will be granted a wish by a crane. After [[World War II]], the crane came to symbolize peace and the innocent victims of war through the story of schoolgirl [[Sadako Sasaki]] and her thousand origami cranes. Suffering from [[leukemia]] as a result of [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|the atomic bombing of Hiroshima]] and knowing she was dying, she undertook to make a thousand origami cranes before her death at the age of 12. After her death, she became internationally recognised as a symbol of the innocent victims of war and remains a heroine to many Japanese girls.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Pine, Plum and Cranes.jpg|''Pine, Plum and Cranes'', 1759, by Shen Quan (1682—1760), hanging scroll, ink and colour on silk, the [[Palace Museum]], [[Beijing]]
File:Main hall, Văn Miếu (Hanoi, Vietnam - 2006).jpg|The "Turtle Carrying Crane on its Back" statue in [[Temple of Literature, Hanoi|Văn Miếu]] (Temple of Literature) in [[Hà Nội]], [[Vietnam]]
File:Hdgs Cranes fighting Dwarfes.gif|[[Dwarf (Germanic mythology)|Dwarves]] fighting cranes in northern Sweden, a 16th-century drawing by [[Olaus Magnus]]
File:Cranes made by Origami paper.jpg|Cranes folded in [[origami paper]]
File:Brooklyn Museum - Cranes and Pines - Songha.jpg|''Songha'' (Korean), ''Cranes and Pines'', 19th century. [[Brooklyn Museum]]
File:Brooklyn Museum - Tortoise Has New Year's Dream of Crane and Pine - Kôbun Yoshimura.jpg|''Tortoise Has New Year's Dream of Crane and Pine'', around 1850, Brooklyn Museum
File:Brass Crane Perched on a Tortoise, c. 1800-1894.jpg|Brass Crane Perched on a Tortoise, c. 1800–1894, from the Oxford College Archive of [[Emory University]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Species==
List of all world [[Gruidae]] [[species]] according to the [[Catalogue of Life]]:&lt;ref name = "COL"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.catalogueoflife.org/annual-checklist/2011/search/all/key/Gruidae/match/1|title= Species 2000 &amp; ITIS Catalogue of Life: 2011 Annual Checklist.|author= Bisby F.A., Roskov Y.R., Orrell T.M., Nicolson D., Paglinawan L.E., Bailly N., Kirk P.M., Bourgoin T., Baillargeon G., Ouvrard D. (red.)|year= 2011|publisher= Species 2000: Reading, UK.|accessdate= 5 March 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Image !! Scientific name !! Common Name !! Distribution
|-
|[[File:Sarus crane (Grus antigone).jpg|120px]] || ''Antigone antigone'' || [[Sarus crane]]  ||  Indian subcontinent, Southeast [[Asia]] and [[Australia]].
|-
|[[File:Sandhill_Crane_in_New_Mexico.jpg|120px]] || ''Antigone canadensis''  || [[Sandhill crane]] || [[North America]] and extreme Northeastern [[Siberia]]
|-
|[[File:Brolga-1-Healesville,-Vic,-3.1.2008.jpg|120px]] || ''Antigone rubicunda'' || [[Brolga]]  || Southeastern [[Australia]] and [[New Guinea
|-
|[[File:White-naped Crane at Saijyo Ehime2.jpg|120px]] || ''Antigone vipio''|| [[White-naped crane]] || Northeastern [[Mongolia]], Northeastern [[China]], and adjacent areas of Southeastern [[Russia]]. 
|-
|[[File:Black_Crowned_Crane_(Balearica_pavonina)_captive_(32172262143).jpg|120px]] || ''Balearica pavonina'' || [[Black Crowned Crane]] || [[Sub-Saharan Africa]]
|-
|[[File:Grey_crowned_crane_at_Martin_Mere.JPG|120px]] || ''Balearica regulorum'' || [[Grey Crowned Crane]] || [[Sub-Saharan Africa]]
|-
|[[File:Grus americana Sasata.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus americana''  || [[Whooping crane]] ||  [[North America]].
|-
|[[File:Bugeranus carunculatus -Dallas Zoo, Texas, USA-8 (1).jpg|120px]] || ''Grus carunculata''  || [[Wattled crane]] ||  [[Africa]], South of the [[Sahara|Sahara Desert]].
|-
|[[File:Common crane grus grus.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus grus'' || [[Common crane]] || [[Europe]]
|-
|[[File:Mandschurenkranich.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus japonensis''  || [[Red-crowned crane]] || [[Siberia]] (Eastern [[Russia]]), Northeastern [[China]], [[Hokkaido|Hokkaidō]] (Northern Japan), the [[Korean Peninsula]], and occasionally in Northeastern [[Mongolia]].
|-
|[[File:Anthropoides paradiseus (male, Etosha).jpg|120px]] || ''Grus paradisea''  || [[Blue crane]] ||  [[South Africa]]
|-
|[[File:Grus monacha Phila Zoo.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus monacha''  || [[Hooded crane]] || South-central and South-eastern [[Siberia]], Mongolia, China.
|-
|[[File:Grus nigricollis -Bronx Zoo-8-3c.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus nigricollis''  || [[Black-necked crane]] ||  The [[Tibetan Plateau]] and remote parts of [[India]] and [[Bhutan]].
|-
|[[File:Grue Demoiselle 0001.jpg|120px]] || ''Grus virgo''  || [[Demoiselle crane]] || Central [[Eurasia]], ranging from the [[Black Sea]] to [[Mongolia]] and Northeastern [[China]]. There is also a small breeding population in [[Turkey (country)|Turkey]].
|-
|}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=Wessling&gt;{{cite web |last=Wessling |first=B. |year=2003 |title=Acoustic individual monitoring over several years (mainly Common Crane and Whooping Crane) |url=http://www.craneworld.de/deutsch/resume/resume03.html |publisher=Craneworld.de |access-date=2012-03-21 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150923210955/http://www.craneworld.de/deutsch/resume/resume03.html |archive-date=2015-09-23 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Miller&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Miller, Alden H.  |author2=Sibley, Charles G. |year=1942|title= A New Species of Crane from the Pliocene of California|journal=[[Condor (journal)|Condor]]|volume=44|issue=3|pages= 126–127|url=http://sora.unm.edu/sites/default/files/journals/condor/v044n03/p0126-p0127.pdf|doi=10.2307/1364260 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==
*Hayes, M.A. (2005): ''Divorce and extra-pair paternity as alternative mating strategies in monogamous sandhill cranes''. MS thesis, University of South Dakota, Vermilion, S.D.. 86 p. PDF fulltext at the [https://web.archive.org/web/20060928014657/https://www.savingcranes.org/conservation/our_projects/program.cfm?id=35 International Crane Foundation's Library]

== External links ==
{{Commons+cat|Gruidae|Gruidae}}
* [http://www.savingcranes.org/ Saving Cranes website (ICF)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120720225944/http://www.craneworld.de/ Craneworld website, mainly in German]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060509064101/http://www.craneworld.de/deutsch/resume/resume03.html individual recognition of cranes using frequency analysis of their calls]
* [http://ibc.lynxeds.com/family/cranes-gruidae Gruidae videos] on the Internet Bird Collection
* [http://www.xeno-canto.org/browse.php?query=gruidae Crane sounds] on xeno-canto.org
* [http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/bioscicranes/ ''Cranes of the World,'' by Paul Johnsgard]

=== Myths and lores ===
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20041010053428/http://www.yscity.or.kr/yangsan-city/sub_1doc/e_sub/sub4/main_01_4.htm Crane Dance at the Tongdosa Temple] ([[Internet Archive|archive]] link, was [[Dead link|dead]])
* [https://web.archive.org/web/19981206170234/http://rosella.apana.org.au/%7Emlb/cranes/lore.htm#Family Thousand Cranes] lore

{{Birds}} 
{{Gruidae|state=all}} 
{{Portal bar|Birds}}

{{Taxonbar|from=Q25365}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Gruidae|*]]
[[Category:Taxa named by Nicholas Aylward Vigors]]</text>
      <sha1>srpxt1usr8wh4efmp07tns7d92w6xxg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
