<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Red Terror (Spain)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11248681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962817683</id>
      <parentid>962205748</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-16T05:53:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LSGH</username>
        <id>38910429</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 962205748 by [[Special:Contributions/2601:85:C101:BA30:5995:8A2F:4C74:1204|2601:85:C101:BA30:5995:8A2F:4C74:1204]] ([[User talk:2601:85:C101:BA30:5995:8A2F:4C74:1204|talk]]) (Vandalism)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="47230" xml:space="preserve">[[File:SpanishLeftistsShootStatueOfChrist.jpg|thumb|300px|"Execution" of the [[Sacred Heart of Jesus|Sacred Heart]] by a Republican firing squad is a famous example of "an assault on the public presence of Catholicism".&lt;ref&gt;[[Ealham, Chris]] and Michael Richards, [https://books.google.com/books/cambridge?id=ypBS6N0aFJgC&amp;pg=PA80&amp;dq=%22most+famous+ritual+destruction%22 The Splintering of Spain], p. 80, 168, Cambridge University Press, 2005, {{ISBN|0-521-82178-9}}, {{ISBN|978-0-521-82178-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The image was originally published in the London ''[[Daily Mail#Inter-war period|Daily Mail]]'' with a caption noting the "Spanish Reds' war on religion".&lt;ref&gt;[http://libraries.ucsd.edu/speccoll/swphotojournalism/m629-f02-19.html Shots of War: Photojournalism During the Spanish Civil War]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Modern persecutions of the Catholic Church}}
The '''Red Terror''' in Spain ({{lang-es|Terror Rojo}})&lt;ref&gt;''Unearthing Franco's Legacy'', Julian Casanova, pp. 105-106, University of Notre Dame Press, 2010 {{ISBN|0-268-03268-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the name given by some historians to various acts of violence committed from 1936 until the end of the [[Spanish Civil War]] "by sections of nearly all the [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] groups".&lt;ref name=uca/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Beevor, Antony]] (2006), The Battle For Spain; The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939, p. 81 Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson&lt;/ref&gt; News of the [[Spanish coup of July 1936|rightist military coup in July 1936]] unleashed a social revolutionary response, and no leftist region escaped revolutionary and anticlerical violence, but it was minimal in the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]].&lt;ref&gt;Mary Vincent, ''The Splintering of Spain'', pp. 70-71&lt;/ref&gt; The violence consisted of the killing of tens of thousands of people (including 6,832&lt;ref name="cueva355"&gt;{{Harvnb|Cueva|1998|p=355}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Priesthood in the Catholic Church|Roman Catholic priests]], the vast majority in the summer of 1936 in the wake of the military coup) as well as attacks on the [[Spanish nobility]], industrialists, and conservative politicians as well as the [[desecration]] and burning of monasteries and churches.&lt;ref name="cueva355"/&gt;

A process of political polarisation had characterised the [[Second Spanish Republic]], and party divisions became increasingly embittered and questions of religious identity came to assume a major political significance. Electorally, the Church had identified itself with the right, which had set itself against social reform.&lt;ref&gt;Hilari Raguer, ''Gunpowder and Incense'', p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;

The failed coup of July 1936 set loose a violent onslaught on those that revolutionaries in the Republican zone identified as enemies; "where the rebellion failed, for several months afterwards merely to be identified as a priest, a [[Religious (Western Christianity)|religious]] or simply a militant Christian or member of some apostolic or pious organization, was enough for a person to be executed without trial".&lt;ref&gt;Raguer, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, the Catholic Church has beatified hundreds of the victims, 498 of them on 28 October 2007 in a spectacular ceremony, the largest single number of beatifications in its history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=25781 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-09-23 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071117094230/http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=25781 |archivedate=2007-11-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some estimates of the Red Terror range from 38,000&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony. ''The Battle for Spain; The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939''. Penguin Books. 2006. London. p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; to ~72,344 lives.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://opinie.wp.pl/francisco-franco-jedyny-przywodca-ktory-pokonal-stalina-6126039183566977a|title=Francisco Franco - jedyny przywódca, który pokonał Stalina|last=Zychowicz|first=Piotr|date=2015-03-20 &lt;!-- (14:15) --&gt; |work=Wp.Opinie/ Historia do Rzeczy|access-date=|quote=Komuniści i ich lewaccy sojusznicy wymordowali 72 344 ludzi i zagłodzili ponad 100 tys.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul Preston]], speaking in 2012 at the time of the publication of his book ''The Spanish Holocaust'', put the figure at a little under 50,000.

Historian Julio de la Cueva wrote that "despite the fact that the Church... suffer[ed] appalling persecution", the events have so far met not only with "the embarrassing partiality of ecclesiastical scholars, but also with the embarrassed silence or attempts at justification of a large number of historians and memoirists".&lt;ref name="cueva355" /&gt; Analysts such as [[Helen Graham (historian)|Helen Graham]] have linked the Red and [[White Terror (Spain)|White Terrors]], pointing out that it was the coup that allowed the culture of brutal violence to flourish: "its original act of violence was that it killed off the possibility of other forms of peaceful political evolution".&lt;ref&gt;''Unearthing Franco's Legacy'', University of Notre Dame Press, {{ISBN|0-268-03268-8}} p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Others see the persecution and violence as predating the coup and found in what they see as a "radical and antidemocratic" anticlericalism of the Republic and its constitution, with the dissolution of the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]] in 1932, the nationalisation of virtually all church property in 1933, the prohibition of teaching religion in schools, the prohibition of teaching by clergy and the violent persecution beginning in 1934 in [[Asturias]], with the murder of 37 priests, religious and seminarians and the burning of 58 churches.&lt;ref name="The Martyrs of Spain's Civil War"/&gt;

==Background==
The revolution of 1931 that established the Second Republic and the [[Spanish Constitution of 1931]] brought to power an [[anticlerical]] government.&lt;ref name="britannica"&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/27867/anticlericalism/337/Spain Anticlericalism] Britannica Online Encyclopedia&lt;/ref&gt; The relationship between the new, secular Republic and the Catholic Church was fraught from the start. Cardinal [[Pedro Segura y Sáenz]], the primate of Spain, urged Catholics to vote in future elections against an administration that wanted to destroy religion.&lt;ref&gt;A. Beevor, ''Battle for Spain'' p.23&lt;/ref&gt; Those who sought to lead the 'ordinary faithful' had insisted that Catholics had only one political choice, the [[Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right]] (CEDA): "Voting for the CEDA was presented as a simple duty; good Catholics would go to Mass on Sunday and support the political right".&lt;ref&gt;Mary Vincent, ''Catholicism in the Spanish Second Republic'', p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

The constitution respected civil liberties and representation, but placed restrictions on the church's use of its property and prohibited religious orders from engaging in education.&lt;ref name="libro.uca.edu"&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne25.htm Payne, Stanley G. ''A History of Spain and Portugal'', Vol. 2, Ch. 25, p. 632 (Print Edition: University of Wisconsin Press, 1973) (LIBRARY OF IBERIAN RESOURCES ONLINE Accessed May 30, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; The controversial Articles 26 and 27 of the constitution strictly controlled Church property and prohibited religious orders from engaging in education.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Angel, [https://books.google.com/books?id=IFuxO9NO-voC&amp;dq Historical Dictionary of Spain], p. 195, Rowman &amp; Littlefield 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Even advocates of church/state separation saw the constitution as hostile; one such advocate, [[José Ortega y Gasset]], stated, "the article in which the Constitution legislates the actions of the Church seems highly improper to me".&lt;ref&gt;Paz, Jose Antonio Souto [http://digitalcommons.law.byu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2076&amp;context=lawreview Perspectives on religious freedom in Spain] Brigham Young University Law Review June 1, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933, [[Pope Pius XI]] condemned the Spanish Government's deprivation of the [[civil liberties]] of Catholics in the [[encyclical]] ''[[Dilectissima Nobis]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian Vicente Carcel Orti asserts that [[anticlericalism and Freemasonry|anticlerical Freemasons]] played a large part in the anti-Catholic acts of the government since they held key government positions, including at least 183 deputies in the [[Cortes Generales]] (the Spanish parliament) and so they were instrumental in the making of [[anti-Catholic]] laws.&lt;ref name="The Martyrs of Spain's Civil War"&gt;Redzioch, Wlodzimierz (interviewing historian Vicente Carcel Orti) [http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?id=7999&amp;CFID=23811582&amp;CFTOKEN=60559071 The Martyrs of Spain's Civil War], Catholic Culture&lt;/ref&gt; As early as March 1933, Abilia Arroyo de Roman had declared at a rally in the Salamancan pueblo of [[Macotera]] that Spain was governed by Masonic lodges, intent on 'decatholicizing' Spain, and the ''Gaceta Regional'' blamed the Law of Congregations on 'an occult power' that had taken refuge in Spain 'to carry out its experiments'.

Since the left considered reform of the anticlerical aspects of the constitution totally unacceptable, Historian [[Stanley G. Payne]] believed "the Republic as a democratic constitutional regime was doomed from the outset",&lt;ref name="libro.uca.edu"/&gt; and it has been posited that such a [[Separation of church and state#Friendly and hostile separation|"hostile" approach to the issues of church and state]] was a substantial cause of the breakdown of democracy and the onset of civil war.&lt;ref&gt;Stepan, Alfred, [https://books.google.com/books?id=nR2tF4k1PXUC&amp;dq Arguing Comparative Politics], p. 221, Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; One legal commentator has stated plainly "the gravest mistake of the Constitution of 1931—Spain's last democratic Constitution prior to 1978—was its hostile attitude towards the Catholic Church".&lt;ref&gt;Martinez-Torron, Javier [http://digitalcommons.law.byu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2077&amp;context=lawreview Freedom of religion in the case law of the Spanish Constitutional court] Brigham Young University Law Review 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

The historian Mary Vincent, in her study of the Church in [[Salamanca (province)|Salamanca]] in the 1930s, believes the Republican legislation, in affecting the devotional lives of ordinary Catholics, "greatly eased the task of its opponents".{{citation needed|date=July 2013|reason=page number etc}}

Following the [[1936 Spanish general election|general election]] of February 16, 1936, political bitterness grew in Spain. Violence between the government and its supporters, the [[Popular Front (Spain)|Popular Front]], whose leadership was clearly moving towards the left (abandoning constitutional Republicanism for leftist revolution&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 646–647&lt;/ref&gt;), and the opposition accelerated, culminating in the coup of right-wing generals in July. As the year progressed Nationalist and Republican persecution grew, and Republicans began attacking churches, occupying land for redistribution and attacking nationalist politicians in a process of [[wikt:tit for tat|tit-for-tat]] violence.

==1933 election and aftermath==
Leading up to the Civil War, the state of the political establishment had been brutal and violent for some time. In the [[Spanish general election, 1933|1933 elections]] to the Cortes Generales, the CEDA won a plurality of seats, but President [[Niceto Alcalá-Zamora]] declined to invite the leader of the CEDA to form a government. Instead he invited the [[Radical Republican Party]] and its leader, [[Alejandro Lerroux]], to do so. CEDA supported the Lerroux government and made it give three ministerial positions. Hostility between the left and the right increased after the formation of the government. Spain experienced general strikes and street conflicts. Noted among the strikes was the miners' revolt in northern Spain and riots in Madrid. Nearly all rebellions were crushed by the government, and political arrests followed.

Lerroux's alliance with the right, his harsh suppression of the revolt in 1934 and the [[Stra-Perlo]] scandal combined to leave him and his party with little support going into the 1936 election. (Lerroux himself lost his seat in parliament.)

==1934 murder of priests and religious in Asturias==
The murder of 37 priests, brothers and seminarians by leftists in [[Asturias]] marks what some see as the beginning of the Red Terror.&lt;ref name="The Martyrs of Spain's Civil War"/&gt; In October 1934, the [[Asturian Revolution]] was strongly anticlerical and involved violence against priests and religious and the destruction of 58 churches, which had been rare until then.&lt;ref&gt;Coverdale, John F., [https://books.google.com/books?id=bPhSpqRI4kQC&amp;dq Uncommon faith: the early years of Opus Dei, 1928-1943], p. 148, Scepter 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Turón (Mieres)|Turón]], one of the locales of anticlerical violence, a coal-mining town in the Asturias Province, was a hub of anti-government and anticlerical agitation.&lt;ref name="Martyrs of Turon"&gt;[http://db.cbconf.org/cbc.nsf/pages/222A1C2E18EE0B8B86256F230055FBB7 Martyrs of Turon]{{dead link|date=April 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Institute of the Brothers of the Christian Schools|De La Salle]] Brothers, who ran a school there, angered the leftists who ran Turón, because of their exercise of religion and their flouting of the constitutional prohibition on religious instruction. On October 5, 1934, the agents of the local rebel government invaded the order's residence on the pretext that they had concealed weapons. A Passionist priest, Father Inocencio, now [[Saint Innocencio of Mary Immaculate]], who had arrived the evening of October 4 was about to say Mass for the brothers. He and the brothers were taken and held without trial and summarily shot in the middle of the night in the cemetery.&lt;ref name="Martyrs of Turon"/&gt;

==1936 Popular Front victory and aftermath==
In the 1936 elections, a new coalition of socialists ([[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party]], PSOE), liberals ([[Republican Left (Spain)|Republican Left]] and the Republican Union Party), Communists, and various regional nationalist groups won the extremely tight election. The results gave 34 percent of the popular vote to the Popular Front and 33 percent to the incumbent government of the CEDA. This result, when coupled with the Socialists' refusal to participate in the new government, led to a general fear of revolution. The fear was worsened when [[Largo Caballero]], hailed as "the Spanish Lenin" by ''[[Pravda]]'', announced that the country was on the cusp of revolution.

==Early outbreak of violence==
Following the outbreak of full-scale civil war there was an explosion of atrocities in both the Nationalist and Republican zones.

The greatest anticlerical bloodletting was at the beginning of the civil war when large areas of the country fell under the control of local loyalists and militias.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Beevor|2006|pp=83–86}}&lt;/ref&gt; A large part of the terror consisted of a perceived revenge against bosses and clergy, as they lost their powerful position in the social revolution, and the move towards extremism that took place in the first months of the civil war.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Beevor|2006|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian Antony Beevor, "In republican territory the worst of the violence was mainly a sudden and quickly spent reaction of suppressed fear, exacerbated by desires of revenge for the past" in contrast with
"the relentless purging of 'reds and atheists' in nationalist territory".&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; After the coup, the remaining days in July saw 861 priests and religious murdered, 95 of them on 25 July, feast day of St James, patron saint of Spain. August saw a further 2,077 clerical victims. After just two months of civil war, 3,400 priests, monks and nuns had been murdered.&lt;ref&gt;''The Splintering of Spain'', p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; The same day of the fatal injury of [[Buenaventura Durruti]] 52 prisoners were executed by anarchists militiamen as reprisals.&lt;ref&gt;Julius Rutiz The 'Red Terror' and the Spanish Civil War: Revolutionary Violence In Madrid, Publisher: Cambridge University Press
[https://books.google.gr/books?id=HqBcAwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Julius+Rutiz&amp;hl=el&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiq5uPEmYbkAhWILlAKHUmcCdAQ6AEIJzAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Durruti&amp;f=false link] line publication date: June 2014 page 284&lt;/ref&gt;
According to recent research, some of the Republican [[death squads]] were heavily staffed by members of the [[Soviet Union]]'s secret police, the [[NKVD]]. According to author [[Donald Rayfield]], "[[Stalin]], [[Yezhov]], and [[Beria]] distrusted Soviet participants in the Spanish war. Military advisors like [[Vladimir Antonov-Ovseenko]], journalists like [[Mikhail Koltsov|Koltsov]] were open to infection by the heresies, especially [[Trotsky]]'s, prevalent among the Republic's supporters. NKVD agents sent to Spain were therefore keener on abducting and murdering anti-Stalinists among Republican leaders and [[International Brigade]] commanders than on fighting [[Francisco Franco]]. The defeat of the Republic, in Stalin's eyes, was caused not by the NKVD's diversionary efforts, but by the treachery of the heretics".&lt;ref&gt;Donald Rayfield, ''Stalin and his Hangmen: The Tyrant and Those Who Killed for Him'', [[Random House]], 2004. pp. 362–363.&lt;/ref&gt; The most famous member of the Loyalist assassination squads was [[Erich Mielke]], future head of [[East Germany]]'s [[Stasi]].&lt;ref&gt;John Koehler, "The Stasi", p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Payne, "During the first months of the fighting most of the deaths did not come from combat on the battlefield but from political executions in the rear&amp;mdash;the 'Red' and 'White' terrors. The terror consisted of semi-organized actions perpetrated by almost all of the leftist groups, [[Basque nationalism|Basque]] nationalists, largely Catholic but still mostly aligned with the Republicans, being an exception".&lt;ref name=uca&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne, Stanley G. A History of Spain and Portugal, Vol. 2, Ch. 26, p. 650 (Print Edition: University of Wisconsin Press, 1973) (Library of Iberian Resources Online, Accessed May 15, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; Payne also contends that unlike the repression by the right, which "was concentrated against the most dangerous opposition elements", the Republican attacks were more irrational, "murdering innocent people and letting some of the more dangerous go free. Moreover, one of the main targets of the Red terror was the clergy, most of whom were not engaged in overt opposition".&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 650&lt;/ref&gt; Describing specifically the Red Terror, Payne states that it "began with the murder of some of the rebels as they attempted to surrender after their revolt had failed in several of the key cities. From there it broadened out to wholesale arrests, and sometimes wholesale executions, of landowners and industrialists, people associated with right-wing groups or the Catholic Church".&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 649&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Paracuellos Lapidas en Fosa II Ruiz Casaux.JPG|thumb|Martyrs Cemetery of [[Paracuellos massacres|Paracuellos]] in Madrid]]
The Red Terror was "not an irrepressible outpouring of hatred by the man in the street for his 'oppressors,' but a semi-organized activity carried out by sections of nearly all the leftist groups".&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 649.&lt;/ref&gt;

By contrast, historians such as Helen Graham,&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Helen. ''The Spanish Civil War. A Very Short Introduction.'' Oxford University Press. 2005. p.30&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Preston,&lt;ref name="Preston, Paul 2006. p. 307"&gt;Preston, Paul. ''The Spanish Civil War. Reaction, revolution &amp; revenge.'' Harper Perennial. 2006. London. p. 307&lt;/ref&gt; Antony Beevor,&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony. ''The Battle for Spain, The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939''. Penguin Books. 2006. London. pp.86-87&lt;/ref&gt; Gabriel Jackson,&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gabriel. ''The Spanish Republic and the Civil War, 1931-1939'' Princeton University Press. 1967. Princeton. p.305&lt;/ref&gt; Hugh Thomas, and Ian Gibson&lt;ref&gt;Gibson, Ian. ''The Assassination of Federico García Lorca.'' Penguin Books. London. 1983. p.168&lt;/ref&gt; have stated that the mass executions behind the Nationalist lines were organised and approved by the Nationalist authorities, and the executions behind the Republican lines were the result of the breakdown of the Republican state and the anarchy. That is concurred by Francisco Partaloa, prosecutor of the Madrid High Court of Justice ''(Tribunal Supremo de Madrid)'' and [[Queipo de Llano]]'s friend, who observed repression in both zones.&lt;ref name=CH-sa&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scielo.cl/scielo.php?pid=S0719-12432013000200002&amp;script=sci_arttext|title=Cuadernos de historia (Santiago) - LA REPRESIÓN: EL ADN DEL FRANQUISMO ESPAÑOL|publisher=|accessdate=8 May 2015|language=Spanish}} I had the opportunity of being a witness to the repression in both areas. In the Nationalist side it was planned, methodical, cold. As they did not trust the people the authorities imposed their will by means of terror, committing atrocities in order to achieve their aim. Atrocities also took place in the Popular Front zone; that was something which both areas had in common. But the main difference was that in the Republican zone the crimes were carried out by the populace in moments of passion, not by the authorities. The latter always tried to stop them. The assistance that I received from the Spanish Republican authorities in order to flee to safety, is only one of the many examples. But this was not the case in the Nationalist zone"&lt;/ref&gt;

Julius Ruiz argues that Republican killings were partially rooted in the left's political culture:&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Julius. "2 Fighting the Fifth Column: The Terror in Republican Madrid during the Spanish Civil War.", pp56-57&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;These anti-fascists acted on the assumption that terror was integral to the anti-fascist war effort. The fear of a dehumanised and homicidal ‘fifth column’ was rooted in the exclusionist political culture of the left. After the proclamation of the Second Republic on 14 April 1931, Socialists and centre-left bourgeois Republicans conflated the new democracy with the heterogeneous political coalition that brought it into being after the departure of King Alonso XIII: the Republic’s future rested on the right being permanently excluded from power. The victory of the centre-right in the November 1933 elections, the failed Socialist-led insurrection of October 1934 and its subsequent repression promoted a common antifascist discourse based on the dichotomy of the virtuous productive ‘people’ (‘pueblo’) (i.e. the left) and a parasitical inhuman ‘fascist’ enemy (i.e. the right). While the Popular Front’s narrow electoral victory in February 1936 was interpreted as the definitive triumph of the antifascist ‘pueblo’, the struggle against the Republic’s right-wing enemies had to continue.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
However, Ruiz also notes that the idea of a homicidal, dehumanised enemy within was further reinforced by news of Nationalist atrocities; it convinced Republicans of the need for total victory. When Mola's army appeared in the mountains north of Madrid, this heightened the sense of urgency within the city of the necessity of dealing with alleged fifth columns, which had been blamed for prior Republican defeats. Infrequent Nationalist bombing raids also created further fear, as Republicans became convinced fascists within the society were directing rebel aircraft to their targets. In reality, during the terror of 1936 there was no fifth column in place as Nationalist sympathisers within the city were convinced Mola's northern armies and Franco's southern ones, lead by professional officers, would easily crush the militia defending the city, negating any need for risky subversive activity. It was only after the failure of Franco's onslaught in the winter of 1936-37, when it became clear the war would last longer and the front lines had stabilised, that a fifth column did emerge, though it was never as powerful or extensive as the Republicans feared; it largely focused on mutual assistance, espionage and undermining Republican morale, eschewing terrorist activities such as bombings and assassinations. While fifth columnists did contribute to the Nationalist war effort, the fall of Madrid was not caused by internal subversion but defeat in battle.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Julius. "2 Fighting the Fifth Column: The Terror in Republican Madrid during the Spanish Civil War.", pp57-58&lt;/ref&gt; The largest and most efficient of these groups was about 6000 strong and was a Falangist women's welfare network known as  ''Hermanidad Auxilio Azul María Paz''.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Julius. "Seventy years on: Historians and Repression during and after the Spanish Civil War." Journal of Contemporary History 44, no. 3 (2009): 449-472, p.464&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as 11 May 1931, when mob violence against the Republic's perceived enemies had led to the burning of churches, convents, and religious schools, the Church had sometimes been seen as the ally of the authoritarian right. The academic Mary Vincent has written: "There was no doubt that the Church would line up with the rebels against the Republic. The Jesuit priests of the city of [[Salamanca]] were among the first volunteers to present themselves to the military authorities.... The tragedy of the Second Republic was that it abetted its own destruction; the tragedy of the Church was that it became so closely allied with its self-styled defenders".&lt;ref&gt;Mary Vincent, ''Catholicism in the Second Spanish Republic'', pp. 248, 258&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, the Nationalists claimed that 20,000 priests had been killed; the figure is now put at 4,184 priests, 2,365 members of other religious institutes and 283 nuns, the vast majority during the summer of 1936.&lt;ref&gt;Callahan, ''La Iglesia catolica en Espana'', p. 282&lt;/ref&gt;

Payne has called the terror the "most extensive and violent persecution of Catholicism in Western History, in some way even more intense than that of the [[dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|French Revolution]]", driving Catholics, left with little alternative, to the Nationalists even more than would have been expected to do so.&lt;ref&gt;Payne, Stanley [https://books.google.com/books?id=KPgPFqXub14C&amp;vq Franco and Hitler: Spain, Germany, and World], p. 13, 2008 Yale University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death toll==
Figures for the Red Terror range from 38,000 to 72,344. Historian Beevor "reckons Franco's ensuing 'white terror' claimed 200,000 lives. The 'red terror' had already killed 38,000."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;[http://www.economist.com/books/displaystory.cfm?story_id=7081116 "Men of La Mancha"]. Rev. of Antony Beevor, ''The Battle for Spain''. ''The Economist'' (June 22, 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; According to Julio de la Cueva, the toll of the Red Terror was 72,344 lives.&lt;ref name="Dela"&gt;Cueva, Julio de la, "Religious Persecution", ''Journal of Contemporary History'', 3, 198, pp. 355-369. {{jstor|261121}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hugh Thomas and Paul Preston said that the death toll was 55,000,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Hugh. ''The Spanish Civil War.'' Penguin Books. 2001. London. p. 900&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul. ''The Spanish Civil War. Reaction, revolution &amp; revenge.'' Harper Perennial. 2006. London. p.233&lt;/ref&gt; and Spanish historian Julian Casanova said that the death toll was fewer than 60,000.&lt;ref&gt;Casanova, Julian. ''The Spanish republic and civil war.'' Cambridge University Press. 2010. New York. p. 181&lt;/ref&gt;

Previously, Payne had suggested, "The toll taken by the respective terrors may never be known exactly. The left slaughtered more in the first months, but the Nationalist repression probably reached its height only after the war had ended, when punishment was exacted and vengeance wreaked on the vanquished left. The White Terror may have slain 50,000, perhaps fewer, during the war. The Franco government now gives the names of 61,000&amp;nbsp;victims of the Red Terror, but this is not subject to objective verification. The number of victims of the Nationalist repression, during and after the war, was undoubtedly greater than that".&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 650.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Checas de Madrid'' ({{ISBN|84-9793-168-8}}), journalist and historian César Vidal comes to a nationwide total of 110,965 victims of Republican repression; 11,705 people being killed in Madrid alone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firmaspress.com/285.htm International justice begins at home] by Carlos Alberto Montaner, [[Miami Herald]], August 4, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[Santos Juliá]], in the work ''Víctimas de la guerra civil'' provides approximate figures: about 50,000 victims of the Republican repression; about 100,000 victims of the Francoist repression during the war with some 40,000 after the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | language = Spanish | title = Víctimas de la guerra civil (''Victims of the civil war'') | chapter = Apéndice. Las cifras. Estado de la cuestión (''Appendix. The figures. State-of-the-art'') | pages=411 | location = Barcelona | year = 2005 | isbn = 84-8460-333-4| last1 = Juliá | first1 = Santos | last2 = Casanova | first2 = Julián }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable"
!Estimate
!Sources
|-
|38 000
|Antony Beevor&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
|-
|50 000
|Stanley Payne&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
|-
|60 000
|Paweł Skibiński&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sowieci: Opowieści niepoprawne politycznie - Część. II|last=Zychowicz|first=Piotr|publisher=Rebis|year=2016|isbn=9788380621022|location=|pages=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Martín Rubio&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Mity wojny domowej. Hiszpania 1936-1939|last=Pio|first=Moa|publisher=Fronda|year=2007|isbn=978-83-603-3561-1|location=|pages=207}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pio Moa&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;
|-
|72 344
|Ramón Salas Larrazaba&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;Carroll, Warren H. (2007). ''Ostatnia Krucjata''. Warszawa: Fronda. p. 198. {{ISBN|9788360562093}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Warren H. Carroll]]&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

Marek Jan Chodakiewicz&lt;ref&gt;Jan Chodakiewicz, Marek (2010). ''Zagrabiona pamięć. Wojna w Hiszpanii 1936-1939''. Fronda. {{ISBN|978-83-62268-08-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Julio de la Cueva&lt;ref name="Dela" /&gt;
|-
|110 905
|César Vidal&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Wojna domowa w Hiszpanii 1936-1939|last=Zubiński|first=Tadeusz|publisher=Fronda|year=2015|isbn=9788371779732|location=|pages=423}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Toll on clergy===
{{see also|Martyrs of the Spanish Civil War}}

Estimates of the number of religious men killed vary greatly. One estimate is that of the 30,000 priests and monks in Spain in 1936, 13% of the secular priests and 23% of the monks were killed, amounting to 6800 religious personnel altogether.&lt;ref name="cueva355" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{cite book|author=Gabriel Jackson|title=Spanish Republic and the Civil War, 1931-1939|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vpOwwZWGtBcC&amp;pg=PA531|origyear=1965|year=2012|publisher=Princeton U.P.|pages=530–31|isbn=978-1400820184}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some 283 women religious were killed, some of them badly tortured.&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"&gt;Jedin 617&lt;/ref&gt; 13&amp;nbsp;bishops were killed from the dioceses of [[Sigüenza|Siguenza]] [[Lleida]], [[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]], [[Barbastro]], [[Segorbe]], [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]], [[Ciudad Real]], [[Almeria]], [[Guadix]], [[Barcelona]], [[Teruel]] and the auxiliary of [[Tarragona]].&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt; Aware of the dangers, they all decided to remain in their cities: "I cannot go, only here is my responsibility, whatever may happen," said [[:es:Cruz Laplana y Laguna|the Bishop of Cuenca]].&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt; In addition 4,172&amp;nbsp;diocesan priests, 2,364&amp;nbsp;monks and friars, among them 259&amp;nbsp;[[Claretians]], 226&amp;nbsp;[[Franciscan]]s, 204&amp;nbsp;[[Piarist]]s, 176&amp;nbsp;Brothers of Mary, 165&amp;nbsp;[[Institute of the Brothers of the Christian Schools|Christian Brothers (also called the De La Salle Brothers)]], 155&amp;nbsp;[[Augustinians]], 132&amp;nbsp;[[Dominican Order|Dominicans]], and 114&amp;nbsp;[[Jesuit]]s were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Beevor|2006|pp=???}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some dioceses, the number of secular priests killed was overwhelming:

* In [[Barbastro]], 123 of 140 priests were killed,&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt; about 88%.
* In [[Lleida]], 270 of 410 priests were killed,&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt; about 66%.
* In [[Tortosa]], 44% of the secular priests were killed.&lt;ref name="cueva355" /&gt;
* In [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], 286 of 600 priests were killed.&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt;
* In the dioceses of [[Málaga]], [[Menorca]] and [[Segorbe]], about half of the priests were killed.&lt;ref name="cueva355" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Jedin 617"/&gt;

In 2001, the Catholic Church [[beatification|beatified]] hundreds of [[martyrs of the Spanish Civil War]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/NWEVNGST.HTM ''New Evangelization with the Saints'', ''L'Osservatore Romano'' 28 November 2001, p. 3(Weekly English Edition)]&lt;/ref&gt; and beatified 498 more on October 28, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azstarnet.com/allheadlines/187121 Tucson priests one step away from sainthood Arizona Star 06.12.2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, Spanish newspaper ''[[La Razón (Madrid)|La Razon]]'' published an article on the number of murders of Catholic clergy members and religious people.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.larazon.es/3/seccion/Espa%F1a{{dead link|date=April 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} (bad link)&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation not found}}
* May 1931: 100 church buildings are burned while firefighters refuse to extinguish the flames.
* 1932: 3000 Jesuits are expelled. Church buildings are burned with impunity in 7 cities.
* 1934: 33 priests are murdered in the [[Asturias Revolution]].
* 1936: one day before July 18, the day the war started, 17 clergymen are murdered.
* From July 18 to August 1: 861 clergymen are murdered in 2 weeks.
* August 1936: 2077 clergymen are murdered, more than 70 a day, 10 of them bishops.
* September 14: 3400 clergymen are murdered during the first stages of the war.

==Attitudes==
=== Republican side ===
Attitudes to the "red terror" varied on the Republican side. President [[Manuel Azaña]] made the well-publicized comment that all of the convents in Madrid were not worth one Republican life.&lt;ref name="mitchell17"&gt;{{Harvnb|Mitchell|1983 |p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet equally commonly cited, for example, is the speech by Socialist leader [[Indalecio Prieto]] on the Madrid radio on 9 August 1936 pleading that Republican militiamen not to "imitate" the murderous actions of the military rebels and the public condemnation of arbitrary "justice" by [[Julián Zugazagoitia]], the editor of ''El Socialista'', the Socialist Party newspaper, on 23 August.&lt;ref name="ruiz100"&gt;{{Harvnb|Ruiz|2007|p=100}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Julius Ruiz goes on to note, however, that "not cited... are ''El Socialista'''s regular reports extolling the work of the Atadell brigade", a group of Republican agents who engaged in detentions and frequently murders of (in the end) up to 800 Nationalists. "On 27 September 1936", Ruiz continues, "an editorial on the brigade stressed that its 'work, more than useful, is necessary. Indispensable.' Similarly, the Prieto-controlled Madrid daily ''Informaciones'' carried numerous articles on the activities of the Atadell brigade during the summer of 1936".&lt;ref name="ruiz100" /&gt;

===Nationalist side===
The Catholic hierarchy believed that the violence directed against it was the result of a plan, "a program of systematic persecution of the Church was planned to the last detail".&lt;ref&gt;Montero, 52&lt;/ref&gt; [[José Calvo Sotelo]] told the Spanish Parliament in April 1936 that in the six weeks since the government, from mid-February 15 to April 2, 1936, had been in power, some 199 attacks were carried out, 36 of them in churches. He listed 136 fires and fire bombings, which included 106 burned churches and 56 churches otherwise destroyed. He claimed they there were 74 persons dead and 345 persons injured.&lt;ref name="Jedin 616"&gt;Jedin 616&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas 1976, p. 206–208.&lt;/ref&gt;

The attitudes of the Catholic side towards the government and the ensuing Civil War was expressed in a joint episcopal letter from July 1, 1937, addressed by the Spanish bishops to all other Catholic bishops.&lt;ref name="Granados, 348"&gt;Granados, 348&lt;/ref&gt; Spain was said to be divided into two hostile camps, one side expresses anti-religious and anti-Spanish, the other side upholding the respect for the religious and national order. The Church was pastorally oriented and not willing to sell its freedom to politics but had to side with those who started out defending its freedom and right to exist.&lt;ref name="Granados, 348"/&gt;

The attitudes of the people in the national zone were characterized by fear, hope and religious revival. Victories were celebrated with religious services, anticlerical laws were abolished and religious education was made legal again. Catholic chaplains were reintroduced into the army. Attitudes to the Church had changed from hostility to admiration.&lt;ref&gt;Jedin 618&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reported murders==
&lt;!-- missing image [[File:House of the people.jpg|thumb|300px|Spanish anti-clericals turn Church into a "casa del pueblo" (house of the people)]] --&gt;
* Murder of 6,832&lt;ref name="cueva355"/&gt; members of the Catholic clergy and [[religious institute]]s as well as the killing thousands of lay people.
* The parish priest of [[Navalmoral]] was put through a [[parody]] of Christ's Crucifixion. At the end of his suffering the [[militiamen]] debated whether actually to [[crucify]] him or just shoot him. They finished with a shooting.&lt;ref name="thomas173"/&gt;
* The [[Bishop of Jaén]] Manuel Basulto y Jiménez and his sister were murdered in front of two thousand celebrating spectators by a special executioner, a woman nicknamed ''La Pecosa'', the freckled one.&lt;ref name="thomas174"&gt;{{Harvnb|Thomas|1961|p=174}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Although rare, it was reported that some nuns were raped by militiamen before they were shot.&lt;ref name="thomas173" /&gt; However, according to Antony Beevor, the 1946 nationalist indictment of Republican atrocities contained no evidence for any such incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Beevor|2006|pp=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The priest of [[Ciempozuelos]] was thrown into a [[corral]] with fighting bulls where he was gored into unconsciousness. Afterwards one of his ears was cut off to imitate the feat of a [[matador]] after a successful [[bullfight]].&lt;ref name="Thomas, p. 173"&gt;Thomas, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Ciudad Real]], a priest was [[castrated]] and his [[sexual organs]] stuffed in his mouth.&lt;ref name="Thomas, p. 173"/&gt;
* There are accounts of the people connected to the Catholic Church being forced to swallow rosary beads, being thrown down mine shafts and of priests being forced to dig their own graves before being buried alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Thomas|1961|p=272}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* An eyewitness to some of the persecution, Cristina de Arteaga, who was soon to become a nun, commented that they "attacked the [[Salesian]]s, people who are totally committed to the poor.  There was a rumor that nuns were giving poisoned sweets to children. Some nuns were grabbed by the hair in the streets. One had her hair pulled out...".&lt;ref name="mitchell17" /&gt;
* On the night of July 19, 1936 alone, 50&amp;nbsp;churches were burned.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mitchell|1983|p=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In Barcelona, out of the 58&amp;nbsp;churches, only the Cathedral was spared, and similar events occurred almost everywhere in Republican Spain.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mitchell|1983 |p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* All the Catholic churches in the Republican zone were closed, but the attacks were not limited to Catholic churches, as synagogues were also pillaged and closed, though some small Protestant churches were spared.&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm Payne] p. 215&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Bishop of Almeria was murdered while working on a history of [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]]. His card index file was destroyed.&lt;ref name="thomas174" /&gt;
* In Madrid, a nun was killed because she refused a proposition of marriage from a militiaman who helped storm her [[convent]].&lt;ref name="thomas173"&gt;{{Harvnb|Thomas|1961|p=173}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
With the total victory of the Nationalists over the Republicans in 1939, the Red Terror ended in the country, but individual terror attacks continued sporadically by remnant Communists {{Dubious|date=January 2012}} and Socialists hiding in French border regions, with little result.{{citation needed|date=April 2017}} Throughout the country, the Catholic Church held ''[[Te Deum (religious service)|Te Deum]]''s to thank God for the outcome. Numerous left-wing personalities were tried for the Red Terror, not all of them guilty. Franco's victory was followed by thousands of [[summary execution]]s (remains of 35,000 people are estimated by the [[Association for the Recovery of Historical Memory]] (ARMH) to lie in mass graves)&lt;ref&gt;The estimate of 35,000 by the [[Association for the Recovery of Historical Memory]] is based on recent searches conducted with parallel excavations of mass graves in Spain. See, for example, [http://www.elmundo.es/cronica/2002/351/1026114970.html Fosas Comunes - Los desaparecidos de Franco. La Guerra Civil no ha terminado], ''[[El Mundo (Spain)|El Mundo]]'', 7 July 2002 {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; and imprisonments, and many were put to [[forced labour]], building railways, drying out swamps, digging canals (''La Corchuela'', the Canal of the [[Guadalquivir|Bajo Guadalquivir]]), construction of the [[Valle de los Caídos]] monument, etc. The 1940 shooting of the president of the [[Generalitat de Catalunya|Catalan government]], [[Lluís Companys]], was one of the most notable cases of this early repression.

The new [[Pope Pius XII]] sent a radio message of congratulation to the Spanish government, clerics and people on April 16, 1939. He referred to the denunciation of his predecessor, [[Pope Pius XI]], who had described past horrors and the need to defend and restore the rights of God and religion. The pope stated that the victims of terror died for [[Jesus Christ]]. He wished peace and prosperity upon the Spanish people and appealed to them to punish criminals but to exercise leniency and Spanish generosity against the many who were on the other side.&lt;ref&gt;Schmidlin, 222&lt;/ref&gt; He asked for their full participation in society and entrusted them to the compassion of the Church in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;''Discorsi e Radiomessaggi di sua Santita'', Primo Anno di Pontificato, Tipografia Poliglotta, Roma 1940, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the Vatican beatified 498 priests killed by the Republican army during the civil war. Relatives of religious Republican killed by the Nationalists have requested similar recognition, criticizing the unequal treatment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2007/10/29/index.php?section=mundo&amp;article=034n1mun La Jornada - Beatifican a 498 religiosos asesinados por republicanos en la guerra civil española]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Spanish Civil War]]
* [[White Terror (Spain)]]
* [[Martyrs of the Spanish Civil War]]
* [[233 Spanish Martyrs]]
* [[498 Spanish Martyrs]]
* [[Paracuellos massacre]]
* [[Republican repression in Madrid (1936-1939)]]

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
* {{Citation |last=Beevor |first=Antony | authorlink = Antony Beevor |title=The Battle For Spain; The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939 |place=London|publisher= Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |year= 2006 }}.
* {{Citation |last=Callahan |first=William J. |title=The Catholic Church in Spain, 1875-1998 |origyear=1998 |edition=reprint |year=2012}}
* {{Citation|last=Cueva |first=Julio de la|title=Religious Persecution, Anticlerical Tradition and Revolution: On Atrocities against the Clergy during the Spanish Civil War |journal=Journal of Contemporary History |volume= XXXIII |number=3 |year=1998 |pages=355–369|jstor=261121}}
* {{Citation |first=August |last=Franzen |first2=Remigius |last2=Bäumer |title=Papstgeschichte (Papal history) |publisher=Herder |location=Freiburg  |year=1988 |ref={{SfnRef|Franzen|1988}} }}  (cit Franzen 1988)
* {{Citation |first=August |last=Franzen |first2=Remigius |last2=Bäumer |title=Kirchengeschichte (Church history) |publisher=Herder |location=Freiburg |year=1991 |ref={{SfnRef|Franzen II|1991}} }}(cit Franzen II 1991)
* {{Citation |first=Anastasio |last=Granados |title=El Cardinal Goma, Primado de Espana |publisher=Espasa Calpe |location=Madrid |year=1969 |language=Spanish}}
* {{Citation |editor-last=Jedin |editor-first=Hubert |editorlink=Hubert Jedin |editor2-first=Konrad |editor2-last=Repgen  |editor3-first=John |editor3-last=Dolan |title=History of the Church: The Church in the Twentieth Century |publisher=Burn&amp; Oates |location=London &amp; New York |origyear=1981 |year=1999 |volume=X |ref=SfnRef{{Jedin|1999}} }} (cit Jedin 1999)
* {{Citation |first=Frances |last=Lannon |title=Privilege, Persecution, and Prophecy. The Catholic Church in Spain 1875-1975 |location=Oxford |year=1987 |isbn=0-19-821923-7}}
* {{Citation |last=Seppelt |first=Franz |first2=Klemens |last2=Löffler |title=Papstgeschichte, von den Anfängen bis zur Gegenwart |publisher=Verlag Josef Kösel &amp; Friedrich Pustet |location=Munich |year=1933 |language=German}} (Papal history)
* {{Citation |first=Antonio |last=Montero Moreno |title=Historia de la persecución religiosa en España 1936-1939 |journal=La Editorial Católica |year=1961}}
* {{Citation |last=Mitchell |first=David |title=The Spanish Civil War |place=New York
|publisher=Franklin Watts |year=1983 |isbn= 9780531098967}}.
* {{Citation |last=Ruiz |first=Julius |title=The 'Red Terror' and the Spanish Civil War: Revolutionary Violence in Madrid |place=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2015 |isbn=978-1107682931}}
* {{Citation |last=Ruiz |first=Julius Ruiz |title=Defending the Republic: The García Atadell Brigade in Madrid, 1936 |journal=Journal of Contemporary History |volume=42 |issue=1 |year=2007|doi=10.1177/0022009407071625 |pages=97–115 |jstor=30036431}}.
* {{Citation |first=Josef |last=Schmidlin |title=Papstgeschichte der neuesten Zeit Vol IV, Pius XI, 1922–1939 |publisher=Verlag Josef Kösel &amp; Friedrich Pustet |location=Munich |year=1939 |language=German }} (Papal history)
* {{Citation|last=Thomas | first=Hugh |title=The Spanish Civil War | place=??? |publisher=Touchstone |year= 1961| isbn= 0-671-75876-4}}.
* {{Citation |last=Thomas | first=Hugh |authorlink=Hugh Thomas (writer) |title=The Spanish Civil War |edition= Revised and enlarged |year=1977 |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=0-06-014278-2}}
* {{Citation |last=Casanova |first=Julian |title=The Spanish Republic and the civil war |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=New York |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-521-73780-7}}

{{Spanish Civil War}}

[[Category:Anti-Catholicism in Spain]]
[[Category:Anti-Christian sentiment in Europe]]
[[Category:Catholicism and Freemasonry]]
[[Category:Communist repression]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Political repression in Spain]]
[[Category:Politicides]]
[[Category:Political and cultural purges]]
[[Category:Politics of Spain]]
[[Category:Persecution of Catholics]]
[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Terrorism in Spain]]
[[Category:War crimes of the Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Soviet Union–Spain relations]]
[[Category:Communist terrorism]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses in Spain]]</text>
      <sha1>f1zbqlmnir3wgrivsbm4uwzxa5jpe52</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
