<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31669</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959495145</id>
      <parentid>959420120</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-29T02:12:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SMP0328.</username>
        <id>6129137</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Effect */ Clarified a paragraph that is based on the thoughts of Judge Bybee</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="44536" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Amendment establishing the direct election of senators}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{US Constitution article series}}
[[File:17th Amendment Pg1of1 AC.jpg|190px|thumb|The Seventeenth Amendment in the [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]]]]
The '''Seventeenth Amendment''' ('''Amendment XVII''') to the [[United States Constitution]] established the popular election of [[United States Senate|United States senators]] by the people of the states. The amendment supersedes [[Article One of the United States Constitution#Section 3: Senate|Article I, §3]], Clauses 1 and 2 of the Constitution, under which senators were elected by [[State legislature (United States)|state legislatures]]. It also alters the procedure for filling [[United States Senate#Vacancies|vacancies in the Senate]], allowing for state legislatures to permit their governors to make temporary appointments until a [[By-election|special election]] can be held.

The amendment was proposed by the [[62nd United States Congress|62nd Congress]] in 1912 and became part of the Constitution on April 8, 1913 on ratification by three-fourths (36) of the state legislatures. Sitting senators were not affected by the Amendment's provisions until their existing terms expired, so the Amendment took six years to fully implement. The transition began with two special elections in 1913—the first in [[1913 United States Senate election in Georgia|Georgia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=BACON, Augustus Octavius (1839-1914)|url=https://bioguideretro.congress.gov/Home/MemberDetails?memIndex=B000014|website=Biographical Directory of the U.S. Congress|accessdate=February 24, 2020|quote=became the first U.S. Senator elected by popular vote following ratification of the 17th Amendment, on July 15, 1913}}&lt;/ref&gt; and second in [[1913 United States Senate special election in Maryland|Maryland]]. The transition then began in earnest with the [[1914 United States Senate elections|November 1914 election]], and was complete on 4 March 1919 when the senators chosen at the [[1918 United States Senate elections|November 1918 election]] took office.

==Text==
{{quote|The Senate of the United States shall be composed of two Senators from each State, elected by the people thereof, for six years; and each Senator shall have one vote. The electors in each State shall have the qualifications requisite for electors of the most numerous branch of the State legislatures.

When vacancies happen in the representation of any State in the Senate, the executive authority of such State shall issue writs of election to fill such vacancies: Provided, That the legislature of any State may empower the executive thereof to make temporary appointments until the people fill the vacancies by election as the legislature may direct.

This amendment shall not be so construed as to affect the election or term of any Senator chosen before it becomes valid as part of the Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution_amendments_11-27.html#17|title=The Constitution of the United States Amendments 11–27|publisher=[[National Archives and Records Administration]]|accessdate=7 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Background==
===Original composition===
[[File:JusticeJamesWilson.jpg|right|thumb|[[James Wilson (justice)|James Wilson]], the only member of the [[Constitutional Convention (United States)|Constitutional Convention]] who supported electing the [[United States Senate]] by popular vote]]
Originally, under [[Article One of the United States Constitution#Section 3: Senate|Article I, § 3]], Clauses 1 and 2 of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]], each [[State legislature (United States)|state legislature]] elected its state's senators for a six-year term.&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;169&lt;/ref&gt; Each state, regardless of size, is entitled to two senators as part of the [[Connecticut Compromise]] between the small and large states.&lt;ref&gt;Vile (2003) p.&amp;nbsp;404&lt;/ref&gt; This contrasted with the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]], a body elected by popular vote, and was described as an uncontroversial decision; at the time, [[James Wilson (justice)|James Wilson]] was the sole advocate of popularly electing the Senate, but his proposal was defeated 10–1.&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1994) p.&amp;nbsp;1013&lt;/ref&gt; There were many advantages to the original method of electing senators. Prior to the Constitution, a federal body was one where states effectively formed nothing more than permanent treaties, with citizens retaining their loyalty to their original state. However, under the new Constitution, the federal government was granted substantially more power than before. Having the state legislatures elect the senators reassured [[Anti-Federalism|anti-federalists]] that there would be some protection against the federal government swallowing up of states and their powers,&lt;ref&gt;Riker (1955) p.&amp;nbsp;452&lt;/ref&gt; and providing a [[Separation of powers|check]] on the power of the federal government.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;516&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, the longer terms and avoidance of popular election turned the Senate into a body that could counter the populism of the House. While the representatives operated in a two-year [[direct election]] cycle, making them frequently accountable to their constituents, the senators could afford to "take a more detached view of issues coming before Congress".&lt;ref name=byb515&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;515&lt;/ref&gt; State legislatures retained the theoretical right to "instruct" their senators to vote for or against proposals, thus giving the states both direct and indirect representation in the federal government.&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1994) p.&amp;nbsp;1019&lt;/ref&gt; The Senate was part of a formal bicameralism, with the members of the Senate and House responsible to completely distinct constituencies; this helped defeat the problem of the federal government being subject to "special interests".&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;176&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the [[Constitutional Convention (United States)|Constitutional Convention]] considered the Senate to be parallel to the British [[House of Lords]] as an "upper house", containing the "better men" of society, but improved upon as they would be conscientiously chosen by the upper houses of state republican legislatures for fixed terms, and not merely inherited for life as in the British system, subject to a monarch's arbitrary expansion. It was hoped that they would provide abler deliberation and greater stability than the House of Representatives due to the senators' status.&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;180&lt;/ref&gt;

===Issues===
According to Judge [[Jay Bybee]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit]], those in favor of popular elections for senators believed that two primary problems were caused by the original provisions: legislative corruption and electoral deadlocks.&lt;ref name=Bybee538&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;538&lt;/ref&gt; There was a sense that senatorial elections were "bought and sold", changing hands for favors and sums of money rather than because of the competence of the candidate. Between 1857 and 1900, the Senate investigated three elections over corruption. In 1900, for example, [[William A. Clark]] had his election voided after the Senate concluded that he had bought votes in the Montana legislature. But analysts Bybee and [[Todd Zywicki]] believe this concern was largely unfounded; there was a "dearth of hard information" on the subject.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;539&lt;/ref&gt; In more than a century of legislative elections of U.S. senators, only ten cases were contested for allegations of impropriety.&lt;ref name=zywicki1022&gt;Zywicki (1994) p.&amp;nbsp;1022&lt;/ref&gt;

Electoral deadlocks were another issue. Because state legislatures were charged with deciding whom to appoint as senators, the system relied on their ability to agree. Some states could not, and thus delayed sending representatives to Congress; in a few cases, the system broke down to the point where states completely lacked representation in the Senate.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;541&lt;/ref&gt; Deadlocks started to become an issue in the 1850s, with a deadlocked [[Indiana]] legislature allowing a Senate seat to sit vacant for two years.&lt;ref name=SenateWebsite&gt;{{cite web|title=Direct Election of Senators|url=https://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/briefing/Direct_Election_Senators.htm|website=United States Senate|accessdate=26 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1891 and 1905, 46 elections were deadlocked across 20 states;&lt;ref name=zywicki1022/&gt; in one extreme example, a Senate seat for Delaware went unfilled from 1899 until 1903.&lt;ref name=bybee542&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;542&lt;/ref&gt; The business of holding elections also caused great disruption in the state legislatures, with a full third of the [[19th Oregon Legislative Assembly|Oregon House of Representatives choosing not to swear the oath of office in 1897]] due to a dispute over an open Senate seat. The result was that [[Oregon Legislative Assembly|Oregon's legislature]] was unable to pass legislation that year.&lt;ref name=bybee542/&gt;

Zywicki again argues that this was not a serious issue. Deadlocks were a problem, but they were the exception rather than the norm; many legislatures did not deadlock over elections at all. Most of those that did in the 19th century were the newly admitted western states, which suffered from "inexperienced legislatures and weak party discipline...as western legislatures gained experience, deadlocks became less frequent." While Utah suffered from deadlocks in 1897 and 1899, they became what Zywicki refers to as "a good teaching experience," and Utah never again failed to elect senators.&lt;ref&gt;Zywicki (1994) p.&amp;nbsp;1024&lt;/ref&gt; Another concern was that when deadlocks occurred, state legislatures were unable to conduct their other normal business; James Christian Ure, writing in the ''[[South Texas Law Review]]'', notes that this did not in fact occur. In a deadlock situation, state legislatures would deal with the matter by holding "one vote at the beginning of the day—then the legislators would continue with their normal affairs".&lt;ref&gt;Ure (2007) p.&amp;nbsp;286&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually, legislative elections held in a state's Senate election years were perceived to have become so dominated by the business of picking Senators that the state's choice for Senator distracted the electorate from all other pertinent issues.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;543&lt;/ref&gt; Senator [[John H. Mitchell]] noted that the Senate became the "vital issue" in all legislative campaigns, with the policy stances and qualifications of state legislative candidates ignored by voters who were more interested in the indirect Senate election.&lt;ref name=DSchleicher&gt;{{cite magazine|last1=Schleicher|first1=David|title=States' Wrongs|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2014/02/conservatives_17th_amendment_repeal_effort_why_their_plan_will_backfire.single.html|accessdate=9 October 2014|magazine=Slate|date=27 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; To remedy this, some state legislatures created "advisory elections" that served as de facto general elections, allowing legislative campaigns to focus on local issues.&lt;ref name=DSchleicher/&gt;

===Calls for reform===
[[File:BRYAN, WILLIAM JENNINGS LCCN2016856655 (cropped).jpg|thumb|left|[[William Jennings Bryan]], who campaigned for the popular election of U.S. senators]]
Calls for a constitutional amendment regarding Senate elections started in the early 19th century, with [[Henry R. Storrs]] in 1826 proposing an amendment to provide for popular election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stathis|first=Stephen W.|title=Landmark debates in Congress: from the Declaration of independence to the war in Iraq|year=2009|publisher=CQ Press|isbn=978-0-87289-976-6|oclc=232129877|page=253}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar amendments were introduced in 1829 and 1855, with the "most prominent" proponent being [[Andrew Johnson]], who raised the issue in 1868 and considered the idea's merits "so palpable" that no additional explanation was necessary.&lt;ref name=Bybee536&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;536&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1860s, there was a major congressional dispute over the issue, with the House and Senate voting to veto the appointment of [[John P. Stockton]] to the Senate due to his approval by a plurality of the New Jersey Legislature rather than a majority. In reaction, the Congress passed a bill in July 1866 that required state legislatures to elect senators by an absolute majority.&lt;ref name=Bybee536/&gt;

By the 1890s, support for the introduction of direct election for the Senate had substantially increased, and reformers worked on two fronts. On the first front, the [[People's Party (United States)|Populist Party]] incorporated the direct election of senators into its [[Omaha Platform]], adopted in 1892.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Boyer|first1=Paul S.|last2=Dubofsky|first2=Melvyn|title=The Oxford companion to United States history|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-508209-8|oclc=185508759|page=[https://archive.org/details/oxfordcompaniont00paul_0/page/612 612]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordcompaniont00paul_0/page/612}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[List of Oregon ballot measures#1908|In 1908]], [[Oregon]] passed the first law that based the selection of U.S. senators on a popular vote. Oregon was soon followed by [[Nebraska]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/briefing/Direct_Election_Senators.htm "Direct Election of Senators"], United States Senate webpage, Origins and Development – Institutional.&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents for popular election noted that ten states already had non-binding primaries for Senate candidates,&lt;ref name="Bybee 1997 p.&amp;nbsp;537"&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;537&lt;/ref&gt; in which the candidates would be voted on by the public, effectively serving as advisory referenda instructing state legislatures how to vote;&lt;ref name="Bybee 1997 p.&amp;nbsp;537"/&gt; reformers campaigned for more states to introduce a similar method.

[[William Randolph Hearst]] opened a nationwide popular readership for direct election of U.S. senators in a 1906 series of articles using flamboyant language attacking "The Treason of the Senate" in his ''[[Cosmopolitan (magazine)#History|Cosmopolitan]]'' magazine. David Graham Philips, one of the "yellow journalists" whom President [[Theodore Roosevelt|Teddy Roosevelt]] called "muckrakers", described [[Nelson Aldrich]] of Rhode Island as the principal "traitor" among the "scurvy lot" in control of the Senate by theft, perjury, and bribes corrupting the state legislatures to gain election to the Senate. A few state legislatures began to petition the Congress for direct election of senators. By 1893, the House had the two-thirds vote for just such an amendment. However, when the joint resolution reached the Senate, it failed from neglect, as it did again in 1900, 1904 and 1908; each time the House approved the appropriate resolution, and each time it died in the Senate.&lt;ref&gt;MacNeil, Neil and Richard A. Baker, ''The American Senate: An Insider's History'' 2013, {{ISBN|978-0-19-536761-4}}. pp.&amp;nbsp;22–23.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the second national legislative front, reformers worked toward a constitutional amendment, which was strongly supported in the House of Representatives but initially opposed by the Senate. Bybee notes that the state legislatures, which would lose power if the reforms went through, were supportive of the campaign. By 1910, 31 state legislatures had passed resolutions calling for a constitutional amendment allowing direct election, and in the same year ten [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] senators who were opposed to reform were forced out of their seats, acting as a "wake-up call to the Senate".&lt;ref name="Bybee 1997 p.&amp;nbsp;537"/&gt;

Reformers included [[William Jennings Bryan]], while opponents counted respected figures such as [[Elihu Root]] and [[George Frisbie Hoar]] among their number; Root cared so strongly about the issue that after the passage of the Seventeenth Amendment, he refused to stand for re‑election to the Senate.&lt;ref name=Bybee538/&gt; Bryan and the reformers argued for popular election through highlighting perceived flaws with the existing system, specifically corruption and electoral deadlocks, and through arousing populist sentiment. Most important was the populist argument; that there was a need to "Awaken, in the senators...a more acute sense of responsibility to the people", which it was felt they lacked; election through state legislatures was seen as an anachronism that was out of step with the wishes of the American people, and one that had led to the Senate becoming "a sort of aristocratic body – too far removed from the people, beyond their reach, and with no special interest in their welfare".&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;544&lt;/ref&gt; The settlement of the West and continuing absorption of hundreds of thousands of immigrants expanded the sense of "the people."

Hoar replied that 'the people' were both a less permanent and a less trusted body than state legislatures, and that moving the responsibility for the election of senators to them would see it passing into the hands of a body that "[lasted] but a day" before changing. Other counterarguments were that renowned senators could not have been elected directly, and that since a large number of senators had experience in the House, which was already directly elected, a constitutional amendment would be pointless.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;545&lt;/ref&gt; The reform was considered by opponents to threaten the rights and independence of the states, who were "sovereign, entitled...to have a separate branch of Congress...to which they could send their ambassadors". This was countered by the argument that a change in the mode in which senators were elected would not change their responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;546&lt;/ref&gt;

The Senate freshman class of 1910 brought new hope to the reformers. Fourteen of the thirty newly elected senators had been elected through party primaries, which amounted to popular choice in their states. More than half of the states had some form of primary selection for the Senate. The Senate finally joined the House to submit the Seventeenth Amendment to the states for ratification, nearly ninety years after it first was presented to the Senate in 1826.&lt;ref&gt;MacNeil, Neil and Richard A. Baker, ''The American Senate: An Insider's History'' 2013, {{ISBN|978-0-19-536761-4}}. p.&amp;nbsp;23.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1912, 239 political parties at both the state and national level had pledged some form of direct election, and 33 states had introduced the use of direct primaries.&lt;ref&gt;Rossum (1999) p.&amp;nbsp;708&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-seven states had called for a [[Convention to propose amendments to the United States Constitution|constitutional convention]] on the subject, with 31 states needed to reach the threshold; [[Arizona]] and [[New Mexico]] each achieved statehood that year (bringing the total number of states to 48), and were expected to support the motion. [[Alabama]] and [[Wyoming]], already states, had passed resolutions in favor of a convention without formally calling for one.&lt;ref&gt;Rossum (1999) p.&amp;nbsp;710&lt;/ref&gt;

==Proposal and ratification==

===Proposal in Congress===
In 1911, the House of Representatives passed House Joint Resolution 39 proposing a constitutional amendment for direct election of senators. The original resolution passed by the House contained the following clause:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/legislative/features/17th-amendment/hjres39.html|title=17th Amendment: Direct Election of U.S. Senators|date=August 15, 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The times, places, and manner of holding elections for Senators shall be as prescribed in each State by the legislature thereof.}}

This so-called "race rider" clause would have strengthened the powers of states over senatorial elections and weakened those of Congress by overriding Congress's power to override state laws affecting the manner of senatorial elections.&lt;ref&gt;Zachary Clopton &amp; Steven E. Art, [http://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5085&amp;context=journal_articles "The Meaning of the Seventeenth Amendment and a Century of State Defiance"], 107 Northwestern University Law Review 1181 (2013), pp. 1191–1192&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the turn of the century, most blacks in the South, and many poor whites, had been [[Disfranchisement after Reconstruction era|disenfranchised]] by state legislatures passing constitutions with provisions that were discriminatory in practice. This meant that their millions of population had no political representation. Most of the South had one-party states. When the resolution came before the Senate, a substitute resolution, one without the rider, was proposed by [[Joseph L. Bristow]] of Kansas. It was adopted by a vote of 64 to 24, with 4 not voting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/legislative/features/17th-amendment/|title=17th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution: Direct Election of U.S. Senators|date=August 15, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly a year later, the House accepted the change. The [[conference report]] that would become the Seventeenth Amendment was approved by the Senate 42 to 36 on April 12, 1912, and by the House 238 to 39, with 110 not voting on May 13, 1912.

===Ratification by the states===
[[File:17th Amendment Ratification map.svg|thumb|{{legend|#377eb8|Original ratifier of amendment}}{{legend|#9EC7F3|Ratified after adoption}}{{legend|#E0584E|Rejected amendment}}{{legend|#D3D3D3|No action taken on amendment}}]]
Having been passed by Congress, the amendment was sent to the states for ratification and was ratified by:&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Constitution of the United States and Amendments Thereto|year=1961|publisher=Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government|page=49|editor=James J. Kilpatrick}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Massachusetts]] – May 22, 1912
# [[Arizona]] – June 3, 1912
# [[Minnesota]] – June 10, 1912
# [[New York (state)|New York]] – January 15, 1913
# [[Kansas]] – January 17, 1913
# [[Oregon]] – January 23, 1913
# [[North Carolina]] – January 25, 1913
# [[California]] – January 28, 1913
# [[Michigan]] – January 28, 1913
# [[Iowa]] – January 30, 1913
# [[Montana]] – January 30, 1913
# [[Idaho]] – January 31, 1913
# [[West Virginia]] – February 4, 1913
# [[Colorado]] – February 5, 1913
# [[Nevada]] – February 6, 1913
# [[Texas]] – February 7, 1913
# [[Washington (state)|Washington]] – February 7, 1913
# [[Wyoming]] – February 8, 1913
# [[Arkansas]] – February 11, 1913
# [[Maine]] – February 11, 1913
# [[Illinois]] – February 13, 1913
# [[North Dakota]] – February 14, 1913
# [[Wisconsin]] – February 18, 1913
# [[Indiana]] – February 19, 1913
# [[New Hampshire]] – February 19, 1913
# [[Vermont]] – February 19, 1913
# [[South Dakota]] – February 19, 1913
# [[Oklahoma]] – February 24, 1913
# [[Ohio]] – February 25, 1913
# [[Missouri]] – March 7, 1913
# [[New Mexico]] – March 13, 1913
# [[Nebraska]] – March 14, 1913
# [[New Jersey]] – March 17, 1913
# [[Tennessee]] – April 1, 1913
# [[Pennsylvania]] – April 2, 1913
# [[Connecticut]] – April 8, 1913&lt;br&gt;With 36 states having ratified the Seventeenth Amendment, it was certified by [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[William Jennings Bryan]] on May 31, 1913, as part of the Constitution.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; The amendment has subsequently been ratified by:
# [[Louisiana]] – June 11, 1914
# [[Alabama]] – April 11, 2002&lt;ref name=148CongRecS9419&gt;[http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CREC-2002-09-26/pdf/CREC-2002-09-26-pt1-PgS9418-6.pdf POM-309], House Joint Resolution No. 12, ''A joint resolution adopted by the Legislature of the State of Alabama relative to ratifying the Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution'', Volume 148 ''Congressional Record'' page 18241 (permanent, bound edition) and page S9419 (preliminary, soft-cover edition). September 26, 2002. Retrieved May 10, 2012.{{Chronology citation needed|date=May 2012|reason=I can only verify it was noted by U.S. Senate by Sept. 26, 2002; not Alabama's actual date of ratification}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Delaware]] – July 1, 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://legis.delaware.gov/LIS/lis145.nsf/2bede841c6272c888025698400433a04/d789187e5c34856f852576f8006366f2?OpenDocument|title=Formally Ratifying the 17th Amendment to the Constitution of the United States Providing for the Popular Election of Senators to the United States Senate|publisher=State of Delaware|accessdate=February 9, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; (After rejecting the amendment on March 18, 1913)
# [[Maryland]] – April 1, 2012&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Senate Joint Resolution 2|date=April 1, 2012|url=http://mgaleg.maryland.gov/webmga/frmMain.aspx?tab=subject3&amp;ys=2012rs/billfile/sj0002.htm|accessdate=April 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=House Joint Resolution 3|date=April 1, 2012|url=http://mgaleg.maryland.gov/webmga/frmMain.aspx?tab=subject3&amp;ys=2012rs/billfile/hj0003.htm|accessdate=April 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Bills signing May 22, 2012|date=May 22, 2012|url=http://www.gov.state.md.us/documents/Signed5.22.12.pdf|accessdate=May 23, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130115035606/http://www.gov.state.md.us/documents/Signed5.22.12.pdf|archive-date=January 15, 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Rhode Island]] – June 20, 2014

The [[Utah State Legislature|Utah legislature]] rejected the amendment on February 26, 1913. No action on the amendment has been completed by: [[Florida]],&lt;ref&gt;At the time, Article XVI, Section 19, of the Florida Constitution provided that "No Convention nor Legislature of this State shall act upon any amendment of the Constitution of the United States proposed by Congress to the several States, unless such Convention or Legislature shall have been elected after such amendment is submitted." The first legislature elected after such submission did not meet until April 5, 1913. See Fla. Const. of 1885, Art. III, § 2. By that time, the amendment had been ratified by 35 states, and, as noted above, would be ratified by the 36th state on April 8, 1913, a circumstance which made any action by the Florida Legislature unnecessary.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[Kentucky]], [[Mississippi]], [[South Carolina]], [[Virginia]], [[Alaska]] or [[Hawaii]]. Alaska and Hawaii were not yet states at the time of the amendment's proposal, and have never taken any official action to support or oppose the amendment since achieving statehood.

==Effect==
The Seventeenth Amendment altered the process for electing United States senators and changed the way vacancies would be filled. Originally, the Constitution required state legislatures to fill Senate vacancies.

According to Judge Bybee, the Seventeenth Amendment had a dramatic impact on the political composition of the U.S. Senate.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;552.&lt;/ref&gt; Before the Supreme Court required "[[one man, one vote]]" in ''[[Reynolds v. Sims]]'' (1964), [[malapportionment]] of state legislatures was common. For example, rural counties and cities could be given "equal weight" in the state legislatures, enabling one rural vote to equal 200 city votes. The malapportioned state legislatures would have given the Republicans control of the Senate in the [[United States Senate elections, 1916|1916 Senate elections]]. With direct election, each vote represented equally, the Democrats retained control of the Senate.&lt;ref&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;552. Similarly, he believes the [[Republican Revolution]] of 1994 would not have happened; instead, the Democrats would have controlled 70 seats in the Senate to the Republicans' 30. See Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;553&lt;/ref&gt;

The reputation of corrupt and arbitrary state legislatures continued to decline as the Senate joined the House of Representatives implementing popular reforms. Bybee has argued that the amendment led to complete "ignominy" for state legislatures without the buttress of a state-based check on Congress. In the decades following the Seventeenth Amendment, the federal government was enabled to enact [[Progressivism in the United States|progressive]] measures.&lt;ref name=byb535&gt;Bybee (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;535. This was partially fueled by the Senators; he wrote in the ''[[Northwestern University Law Review]]'':{{quote|Politics, like nature, abhorred a vacuum, so senators felt the pressure to do something, namely enact laws. Once senators were no longer accountable to and constrained by state legislatures, the maximizing function for senators was unrestrained; senators almost always found in their own interest to procure federal legislation, even to the detriment of state control of traditional state functions.}} See Bybee, p.&amp;nbsp;536.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Schleiches argues that the separation of state legislatures and the Senate had a beneficial effect on the states, as it led state legislative campaigns to focus on local rather than national issues.&lt;ref name=DSchleicher/&gt;

[[New Deal]] legislation is another example of expanding federal regulation overruling the state legislatures promoting their local state interests in coal, oil, corn and cotton.&lt;ref&gt;Rossum (1999) p.&amp;nbsp;715&lt;/ref&gt; Ure agrees, saying that not only is each senator now free to ignore his state's interests, senators "have incentive to use their advice-and-consent powers to install Supreme Court justices who are inclined to increase federal power at the expense of state sovereignty".&lt;ref&gt;Ure (2007) p.&amp;nbsp;288&lt;/ref&gt; Over the first half of the 20th century, with a popularly elected Senate confirming nominations, both Republican and Democratic, the Supreme Court began to [[Incorporation of the Bill of Rights|apply the Bill of Rights to the states]], overturning state laws whenever they harmed individual state citizens.&lt;ref&gt;Kochan (2003) p.&amp;nbsp;1053 Donald J. Kochan, for an article in the ''[[Albany Law Review]]'', analyzed the effect of the Seventeenth Amendment on Supreme Court decisions over the constitutionality of state legislation. He found a "statistically significant difference" in the number of cases holding state legislation unconstitutional before and after the passage of the Seventeenth Amendment, with the number of holdings of unconstitutionality increasing sixfold. Besides the Seventeenth Amendment, decline in the influence of the states also followed economic changes. Zywicki observes that interest groups of all kinds began to focus efforts on the federal government, as national issues could not be directed by influencing only a few state legislatures of with Senators of the most seniority chairing the major committees. He attributes the rise in the strength of interest groups partially to the development of the U.S.&amp;nbsp;economy on an interstate, national level. See Zywicki (1997) p.&amp;nbsp;215. Ure also argues that the Seventeenth Amendment led to the rise of [[Special Interest Group|special interest groups]] to fill the void; with citizens replacing state legislators as the Senate's electorate, with citizens being less able to monitor the actions of their Senators, the Senate became more susceptible to pressure from interest groups, who in turn were more influential due to the centralization of power in the federal government; an interest group no longer needed to [[Lobbying|lobby]] many state legislatures, and could instead focus its efforts on the federal government. See Ure (2007) p.&amp;nbsp;293&lt;/ref&gt;

===Filling vacancies===
The Seventeenth Amendment requires a governor to call a [[By-election|special election]] to fill [[United States Senate#Vacancies|vacancies in the Senate]].&lt;ref&gt;Vile (2010) p.&amp;nbsp;197&lt;/ref&gt; It also allows a state's legislature to permit its [[Governor (United States)|governor]] to make temporary appointments, which last until a special election is held to fill the vacancy. Currently, all but five states — North Dakota, Oklahoma, Oregon, Rhode Island, and Wisconsin — permit such appointments.&lt;ref name="CRS_R44781"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R44781.pdf|title=U.S. Senate Vacancies: Contemporary Developments and Perspectives|last1=Neale|first1=Thomas H.|date=April 12, 2018|website=fas.org|publisher=Congressional Research Service|access-date=October 13, 2018|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180605230617/https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R44781.pdf|archivedate=June 5, 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Constitution does not set out how the temporary appointee is to be selected.

===First direct elections to the Senate===

[[Oklahoma]], admitted to statehood in 1907, chose a senator by legislative election three times: twice in 1907, when admitted, and once in 1908. In 1912, Oklahoma reelected [[Robert Latham Owen|Robert Owen]] by advisory popular vote.&lt;ref name=Dubin/&gt;

[[Oregon]] held primaries in 1908 in which the parties would run candidates for that position, and the state legislature pledged to choose the winner as the new senator.{{Fact|date=August 2018}}

[[New Mexico]], admitted to statehood in 1912, chose only its first two senators legislatively. [[Arizona]], admitted to statehood in 1912, chose its first two senators by advisory popular vote. [[Alaska]], and [[Hawaii]], admitted to statehood in 1959, have never chosen a U.S. senator legislatively.&lt;ref name=Dubin/&gt;

The first direct elections to the Senate following the Seventeenth Amendment being adopted were:&lt;ref name=Dubin&gt;{{cite book|author=Dubin, Michael J.|title=United States Congressional elections, 1788–1997: the official results of the elections of the 1st through 105th Congresses|publisher=McFarland|location=Jefferson, NC|year=1998|isbn=0-7864-0283-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[United States Senate special election in Maryland, 1913|In Maryland on November 4, 1913]]: a [[Classes of United States Senators|class 1]] [[List of special elections to the United States Senate|special election]] due to a vacancy, for a term ending in 1917.
* [[United States Senate special election in Alabama, 1914|In Alabama on May 11, 1914]]: a class 3 special election due to a vacancy, for a term ending in 1915.
* [[United States Senate elections, 1914|Nationwide in 1914]]: All 32 class 3 senators, term 1915–1921
* [[United States Senate elections, 1916|Nationwide in 1916]]: All 32 class 1 senators, term 1917–1923
* [[United States Senate elections, 1918|Nationwide in 1918]]: All 32 class 2 senators, term 1919–1925

===Court cases and interpretation controversies===
In ''[[Trinsey v. Pennsylvania]]'' (1991),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Trinsey v. Pennsylvania|vol=941|court=F.2d|year=1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit]] was faced with a situation where, following the death of Senator [[John Heinz]] of [[Pennsylvania]], Governor [[Bob Casey Sr.|Bob Casey]] had provided for a replacement and for a special election that did not include a [[Primary election|primary]].&lt;ref&gt;Gold (1992) p.&amp;nbsp;202&lt;/ref&gt; A voter and prospective candidate, John S. Trinsey,&amp;nbsp;Jr., argued that the lack of a primary violated the Seventeenth Amendment and his right to vote under the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;Novakovic (1992) p.&amp;nbsp;940&lt;/ref&gt; The Third Circuit rejected these arguments, ruling that the Seventeenth Amendment does not require primaries.&lt;ref&gt;Novakovic (1992) p.&amp;nbsp;945&lt;/ref&gt;

Another subject of analysis is whether statutes restricting the authority of governors to appoint temporary replacements are constitutional. [[Vikram Amar]], writing in the ''Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly'', claims that Wyoming's requirement that its governor fill a senatorial vacancy by nominating a person of the same party as the person who vacated that Senate seat violates the Seventeenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;Amar (2008) p.&amp;nbsp;728&lt;/ref&gt; This is based on the text of the Seventeenth Amendment, which states that "the legislature of any state may empower the executive thereof to make temporary appointments". The amendment only empowers the legislature to delegate the authority to the governor and, once that authority has been delegated, does not permit the legislature to intervene. The authority is to decide whether the governor shall have the power to appoint temporary senators, not who the governor may appoint.&lt;ref&gt;Amar (2008) pp.&amp;nbsp;729–30&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sanford Levinson]], in his rebuttal to Amar, argues that rather than engaging in a [[Textualism|textual]] interpretation, those examining the meaning of constitutional provisions should interpret them in the fashion that provides the most benefit, and that legislatures being able to restrict gubernatorial appointment authority provides a substantial benefit to the states.&lt;ref&gt;Levinson (2008) pp.&amp;nbsp;718–9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reform and repeal efforts===
Notwithstanding controversies over the effects of the Seventeenth Amendment, advocates have emerged to reform or repeal the amendment. Under President [[Barack Obama]]'s [[Presidency of Barack Obama|administration]] in 2009, four sitting Democratic senators left the Senate for executive branch positions: Barack Obama (President), [[Joe Biden]] (Vice President), [[Hillary Clinton]] (Secretary of State), and [[Ken Salazar]] (Secretary of the Interior). Controversies developed about the successor appointments made by [[Governor of Illinois|Illinois governor]] [[Rod Blagojevich]] and [[List of Governors of New York|New York governor]] [[David Paterson]]. New interest was aroused in abolishing the provision for the Senate appointment by the governor.&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/11/us/politics/11senate.html|title=New Idea on Capitol Hill: To Join Senate, Get Votes|last=Hulse|first=Carl|date=March 10, 2009|work=[[The New York Times]]|publisher=[[The New York Times Company]]|accessdate=September 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, Senator [[Russ Feingold]] of Wisconsin&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=S.J.Res.7 – A joint resolution proposing an amendment to the Constitution of the United States relative to the election of Senators.|url=http://beta.congress.gov/bill/111th-congress/senate-joint-resolution/7/text|accessdate=June 15, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Representative [[David Dreier]] of California proposed an amendment to remove this power; senators [[John McCain]] and [[Dick Durbin]] became co-sponsors, as did Representative [[John Conyers]].&lt;ref name="nyt" /&gt;

Some members of the [[Tea Party movement]] argued for repealing the Seventeenth Amendment entirely, claiming that it would protect [[states' rights]] and reduce the power of the federal government.&lt;ref name="NYT"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/01/opinion/01tue4.html?hp|title=So You Still Want to Choose Your Senator?|last=Firestone|first=David|date=May 31, 2010|work=[[New York Times]]|publisher=[[The New York Times Company]]|accessdate=September 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 2, 2016, the Utah legislature approved Senate Joint Resolution No. 2 asking Congress to offer an amendment to the United States Constitution that would repeal the Seventeenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://le.utah.gov/~2016/bills/static/SJR002.html|title=SJR002|publisher=State of Utah}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{As of|2010}}, no other states had supported such an amendment, and some politicians who had made statements in favor of repealing the amendment had subsequently reversed their position on this.&lt;ref name="NYT"/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|last=Amar|first=Vikram David|year=2008|title=Are Statutes Constraining Gubernatorial Power to Make Temporary Appointments to the United States Senate Constitutional Under the Seventeenth Amendment?|ssrn=1103590|journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly|publisher=[[University of California, Hastings College of the Law]]|volume=35|issue=4|issn=0094-5617}}
* {{cite journal|last=Bybee|first=Jay S.|authorlink=Jay Bybee|year=1997|title=Ulysses at the Mast: Democracy, Federalism, and the Sirens' Song of the Seventeenth Amendment|journal=Northwestern University Law Review|url=http://scholars.law.unlv.edu/facpub/350/|publisher=Northwestern University School of Law|volume=91|issue=1|issn=0029-3571}}
* {{cite journal|last=Gold|first=Kevin M.|year=1992|title=Trinsey v. Pennsylvania: State Discretion to Regulate United States Senate Vacancy|journal=[[Widener Journal of Law and Public Policy]]|publisher=[[Widener University School of Law]]|volume=2|issue=1|issn=1064-5012}}
* {{cite book|last=Hoebeke|first=Christopher Hyde|title=The road to mass democracy: original intent and the Seventeenth Amendment|year=1995|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=1-56000-217-4}}
* {{cite journal|last=Kochan|first=Donald J.|year=2003|title=State Laws and the Independent Judiciary: An Analysis of the Effects of the Seventeenth Amendment on the Number of Supreme Court Cases Holding State Laws Unconstitutional| ssrn=907518 |journal=Albany Law Review|volume=66|issue=1|issn=0002-4678}}
* {{cite journal|last=Levinson|first=Sanford|year=2008|title=Political Party and Senatorial Succession: A Response to Vikram Amar on How Best to Interpret the Seventeenth Amendment|journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly|publisher=[[University of California, Hastings College of the Law]]|volume=35|issue=4|issn=0094-5617}}
* {{cite journal|last=Novakovic|first=Michael B.|year=1992|title=Constitutional Law: Filling Senate Vacancies|journal=Villanova Law Review|publisher=[[Villanova University School of Law]]|volume=37|issue=1|issn=0042-6229}}
* {{cite journal|last=Riker|first=William H.|year=1955|title=The Senate and American Federalism|journal=American Political Science Review|publisher=American Political Science Association|volume=49|issue=2|issn=0003-0554}}
* {{cite journal|last=Rossum|first=Ralph A.|year=1999|title=The Irony of Constitutional Democracy: Federalism, the Supreme Court, and the Seventeenth Amendment|journal=San Diego Law Review|publisher=[[University of San Diego School of Law]]|volume=36|issue=3|issn=0886-3210}}
* {{cite book|last=Tushnet|first=Mark|title=The Constitution of the United States of America: A Contextual Analysis|year=2010|publisher=Hart Publishing|isbn=978-1-84113-738-4}}
* {{cite journal|last=Ure|first=James Christian|year=2007|title=You Scratch My Back and I'll Scratch Yours: Why the Federal Marriage Amendment Should Also Repeal the Seventeenth Amendment|journal=[[South Texas Law Review]]|publisher=[[South Texas College of Law]]|volume=49|issue=1|issn=1052-343X}}
* {{cite book|last=Vile|first=John R.|title=Encyclopedia of constitutional amendments, proposed amendments, and amending issues, 1789–2002|edition=2nd|year=2003|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-85109-428-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Vile|first=John R.|title=A companion to the United States Constitution and its amendments|edition=5th|year=2010|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-38008-2}}
* {{cite journal|last=Zywicki|first=Todd J.|year=1994|title=Senators and Special Interests: A Public Choice Analysis of the Seventeenth Amendment |url=http://mason.gmu.edu/~tzywick2/Oregon%20Senators.pdf|journal=Oregon Law Review|publisher=University of Oregon School of Law|volume=73|issue=1|issn=0196-2043}}
* {{cite journal|last=Zywicki|first=Todd J.|year=1997|title=Beyond the Shell and Husk of History: The History of the Seventeenth Amendment and its Implications for Current Reform Proposals|journal=Cleveland State Law Review|url=http://mason.gmu.edu/~tzywick2/Cleveland%20State%20Senators.pdf|publisher=Cleveland-Marshall College of Law|volume=45|issue=1|issn=0009-8876}}
* Wendy J. Schiller and Charles Stewart III (2013), The 100th Anniversary of the 17th Amendment: A Promise Unfulfilled?, Issues in Governance Studies, Number 59 May 2013

==External links==
{{Commons category|Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution}}

{{US Constitution}}
{{Voting rights in the United States}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:17}}
[[Category:1913 in American law|Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:1913 in American politics]]
[[Category:Amendments to the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:Federalism in the United States|Seventeenth]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1865–1918)]]
[[Category:History of voting rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Progressive Era in the United States]]
[[Category:United States Senate]]
[[Category:1912 in American law]]
[[Category:1912 in American politics]]</text>
      <sha1>fv0e6td8kg2135dh1gr04plg1g4vwt5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
