<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>North Hollywood, Los Angeles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>435035</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962445393</id>
      <parentid>962391479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-14T03:23:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keizers</username>
        <id>2622622</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* After annexation */ more of the retail history - this was actually one of the largest malls in the country in the mid-1950s.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="34337" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
| name                = North Hollywood
| official_name       = 
| settlement_type     = [[Neighborhoods of Los Angeles|Neighborhood of Los Angeles]]
| pushpin_map         = United States San Fernando Valley#United States Los Angeles
| pushpin_map_caption = Location within Los Angeles/San Fernando Valley
| coordinates         = {{coord|34.1739|-118.3790|region:US-CA|format=dms|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type    = [[List of sovereign states|Country]]
| subdivision_name    = [[United States of America]]
| subdivision_type1   = [[U.S. state|State]]
| subdivision_name1   = [[California]]
| subdivision_type2   = [[List of counties in California|County]]
| subdivision_name2   = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
| subdivision_type3   = [[List of cities in California|City]]
| subdivision_name3   = [[Los Angeles]]
| footnotes           = 
| population_total    = 87,241
| population_as_of    = 2008
}}
'''North Hollywood''' is a neighborhood in the east [[San Fernando Valley]] region of the city of [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. It is home to the [[NoHo Arts District]] and the [[Academy of Television Arts &amp; Sciences]], and it has seven public and eight private schools. There is a municipal park and a recreation center. The neighborhood is an important transportation center for the region.

North Hollywood was established by the Lankershim Ranch Land and Water Company in 1887. It was first named '''Toluca''' before being renamed '''Lankershim''' in 1896 and finally '''North Hollywood''' in 1927.

==Demographics==
The 2000 U.S. census counted 77,848 residents in the 5.87-square-mile North Hollywood neighborhood—or 13,264 people per square mile, about an average [[population density]] for the city but among the highest for the county. In 2008, the city estimated that the population had increased to 87,241. In 2000 the median age for residents was 30, considered an average age for city and county neighborhoods; the percentage of residents aged 19 to 34 was among the county's highest.&lt;ref name=MappingLANorthHollywood&gt;{{cite web|url=http://maps.latimes.com/neighborhoods/neighborhood/north-hollywood |title=North Hollywood Profile – Mapping L.A. – Los Angeles Times |website=Maps.latimes.com |date= |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The neighborhood was considered "moderately diverse" ethnically within Los Angeles. The breakdown was 57.7% [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latino]], 27% [[Non-Hispanic White]], 5.7% [[Asian American|Asian]], 5.6 % [[African American|black]], and 4% from other groups. Foreign-born residents made up 46.4% of residents, a high percentage for Los Angeles; Mexico (43.2%) and El Salvador (16%) were the most common places of birth for this portion of the population. The percentages of never-married men and never-married women were among the county's highest.&lt;ref name=MappingLANorthHollywood/&gt;

The median yearly household income in 2008 dollars was $42,791, considered average for the city but low for the county. The percentages of households that earned $40,000 or less were high for the county. Renters occupied 75.4% of the housing stock, and house- or apartment-owners held 24.6%.&lt;ref name=MappingLANorthHollywood/&gt;

==Geography==
North Hollywood is bordered on the north by [[Sun Valley, Los Angeles|Sun Valley]] and on the northeast and east by [[Burbank, California|Burbank]]. [[Toluca Lake, Los Angeles|Toluca Lake]] borders North Hollywood on the southeast and south, and [[Studio City, Los Angeles|Studio City]] abuts it on the southwest. It is flanked by [[Valley Village, Los Angeles|Valley Village]] and [[Valley Glen, Los Angeles|Valley Glen]] on the west.&lt;ref name=MappingLAColoredMap&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/includes/projects/img/mapping_la/mappingla.pdf |title=Map |website=Latimes.com |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

North Hollywood is not contiguous with [[Hollywood, Los Angeles, California|Hollywood]], being separated by other parts of the San Fernando Valley and the [[Hollywood Hills]].

North Hollywood displays a hot summer [[Mediterranean Climate]] ([[Köppen climate classification]] Csa).

{{Weather box
|location = North Hollywood, Los Angeles
|single line = Y
|collapsed =
|Jan high F = 65.1
|Feb high F = 66.4
|Mar high F = 69.2
|Apr high F = 72.9
|May high F = 75.4
|Jun high F = 79.2
|Jul high F = 87.6
|Aug high F = 88.3
|Sep high F = 87.1
|Oct high F = 80.3
|Nov high F = 74.6
|Dec high F = 68.9
|year high F= 76.2
|Jan low F = 38.7
|Feb low F = 40.5
|Mar low F = 42.8
|Apr low F = 47.0
|May low F = 50.3
|Jun low F = 52.8
|Jul low F = 57.9
|Aug low F = 56.9
|Sep low F = 54.9
|Oct low F = 49.1
|Nov low F = 40.9
|Dec low F = 40.6
|year low F= 47.7
|rain colour = green
|Jan rain inch = 3.47
|Feb rain inch = 3.80
|Mar rain inch = 2.62
|Apr rain inch = 1.18
|May rain inch = 0.15
|Jun rain inch = 0.01
|Jul rain inch = 0.01
|Aug rain inch = 0.04
|Sep rain inch = 0.30
|Oct rain inch = 0.45
|Nov rain inch = 1.32
|Dec rain inch = 2.99
|source = https://wrcc.dri.edu/cgi-bin/cliMAIN.pl?ca6256
}}

==History==
[[File:Lankershim Ranch Land and Water Company 1887.png|thumb|Lankershim Ranch Land and Water Company, 1887]]

===Before annexation===
{{Main|History of the San Fernando Valley to 1915}}
North Hollywood was once part of the vast landholdings of the [[Mission San Fernando Rey de España]], which was confiscated by the government during the Mexican period of rule.

A group of investors assembled as the San Fernando Farm Homestead Association purchased the southern half of the [[Rancho Ex-Mission San Fernando]].{{when|date=July 2013}} The leading investor was [[Isaac Lankershim]], a Northern California stockman and grain farmer, who was impressed by the Valley's wild oats and proposed to raise sheep on the property. In 1873, Isaac Lankershim's son and future son-in-law, [[James Boon Lankershim]] and [[Isaac Newton Van Nuys]], moved to the San Fernando Valley and took over management of the property. Van Nuys thought the property could profitably grow wheat using the [[dryland farming]] technique developed on the [[Great Plains]] and leased land from the Association to test his theories. In time, the Lankershim property, under its third name, the Los Angeles Farming and Milling Company, would become the world's largest wheat-growing empire.&lt;ref name="L27"&gt;Link 1991, p.27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roderick 2001, pp. 32–34, 44–45&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1887, J.B. Lankershim and eight other developers organized the Lankershim Ranch Land and Water Company, purchasing {{convert|12000|acre|km2|0}} north of the Cahuenga Pass from the Lankershim Farming and Milling Company.&lt;ref name="L31"&gt;Link 1991, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; Lankershim established a townsite which the residents named Toluca along the old road from [[Cahuenga Pass]] to [[San Fernando, California|San Fernando]]. On April 1, 1888, they offered ready-made small farms for sale, already planted with deep-rooted deciduous fruit and nut trees—mostly peaches, pears, apricots, and walnuts—that could survive the rainless summers of the Valley by relying on the high [[water table]] along the [[Tujunga Wash]] rather than surface irrigation.&lt;ref name="J82"&gt;Jorgenson 1982, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Link 1991, pp. 31, 33&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A group of students outside of Lankershim School in San Fernando Valley, California, ca.1889 (CHS-6646).jpg|thumb|left|Lankershim School, located near what is now the intersection of Vineland and Riverside, and the first school in the San Fernando Valley, c. 1889]]

The land boom of the 1880s went bust by the 1890s, but despite another brutal drought cycle in the late 1890s, the fruit and nut farmers remained solvent. The Toluca Fruit Growers Association was formed in 1894. The next year the Southern Pacific opened a branch line slanting northwest across the Valley to [[Chatsworth, Los Angeles, California|Chatsworth]]. The Chatsworth Limited made one freight stop a day at Toluca, though the depot bore the new name of Lankershim. With the post office across the street being called Toluca, controversy over the town's name continued, and the local ranchers used to quip, "Ship the merchandise to Lankershim, but bill it to Toluca." In 1896, under pressure from Lankershim, the post office at Toluca was renamed "Lankershim" after his father, although the new name of the town would not be officially recognized until 1905.&lt;ref&gt;Link 1991, pp. 34–35&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roderick 2001. p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1903, the area was known as "The Home of the Peach". In 1912, the area's major employer, the Bonner Fruit Company, was canning over a million tons of peaches, apricots, and other fruits.&lt;ref name="BF"&gt;Bearchell and Fried 1988, p. 124&lt;/ref&gt; When the [[Los Angeles Aqueduct]] opened in 1913, Valley farmers offered to buy the surplus water, but the federal legislation that enabled the construction of the aqueduct prohibited Los Angeles from selling the water outside of the city limits.&lt;ref&gt;Bearchell and Fried 1988, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

At first, resistance to the real-estate development and downtown business interests of Los Angeles remained strong enough to keep the small farmers unified in opposition to annexation. However, the fruit packing company interests were taken over by the Los Angeles interests. The two conspired to decrease prices and mitigate the farmers' profit margins, making their continued existence tenuous. When droughts hit the valley again, rather than face foreclosure, the most vulnerable farmers agreed to mortgage their holdings to the fruit packing company and banks in Los Angeles for the immediate future and vote on annexation.{{citation needed|date=July 2013}}

===After annexation===
[[File:Circus Liquor, North Hollywood, California.JPG|thumb|upright|Circus Liquor, landmark sign dating from 1959]]

West Lankershim (more or less today's Valley Village) agreed to be annexed to the City of Los Angeles in 1919. Lankershim proper joined in 1923.&lt;ref&gt;Roderick 2001, p. 62–63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://navigatela.lacity.org/common/mapgallery/pdf/annex34x44.pdf|title=City of Los Angeles Annexation and Detachment Map|accessdate=16 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the promised water delivery was withheld, and many of the ranchers one by one had their holding foreclosed or transferred to the packing companies. In turn, these were bought up by the real-estate developers and by the late 1920s a massive effort was underway to market the area to prospective home owners throughout the country. As part of this effort, in 1927, in an effort to capitalize on the glamour and proximity of Hollywood, Lankershim was renamed "North Hollywood".&lt;ref name="BF" /&gt; The result was a massive development of housing which transformed the area into a suburban development of Los Angeles.

In the late 1940s and 1950s the area saw the first department-store-anchored, auto-oriented shopping center in the Valley: [[Valley Plaza]], covering both a development at Laurel Canyon at Victory boulevards but also a loose collection of other retail stores south along Laurel Canyon to Oxnard, including a branch of the [[May Company California|May Co.]], the second-largest suburban department store branch in the U.S. at the time. In the mid-1950s Valley Plaza claimed to be the largest shopping center on the [[West Coast of the United States]] and the third-largest in the country.&lt;ref name="vtim"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Esquivel |first1=Ralph |title=Survey of Sales Reveals Record by Valley Plaza |url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/53383610/survey-of-sales-reveals-record-by/ |publisher=Valley Times (North Hollywood, CA) |date=May 1, 1956}}&lt;/ref&gt; The May Co. at the south end of the Valley Plaza shopping district built its own attached, enclosed mall, [[Laurel Plaza]], opening in 1968.&lt;ref name="lat-1968mar07"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/doc/155911693.html|title=Laurel Plaza Shop Center Opens Today|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;|date=March 7, 1968|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|page=sf6|quote=Laurel Plaza, May Co.'s shopping center, is scheduled for opening today at Laurel Canyon and Oxnard St. The 600,000 square foot shopping center is completely enclosed and air conditioned. Besides the May Co. store, it has 30 specialty and high fashion shops, an ice skating rink, restaurants, snack facilities and a central mall.|url-access=subscription}} [http://search.proquest.com/docview/155911693/ Alternate Link]{{subscription}} via [[ProQuest]].&lt;/ref&gt; The last department of Valley Plaza's anchors, [[Sears]], closed in 2019&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=It's the end of an era for the Valley Plaza Sears in North Hollywood |url=https://www.dailynews.com/2019/11/08/its-the-end-of-an-era-for-the-valley-plaza-sears-in-north-hollywood/ |publisher=Daily News |date=November 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; as department store-anchored shopping centers lost favor. As of 2020, much of the Valley Plaza retail space is either empty, portion is now a middle school, and the Laurel Plaza site is under construction to become NOHO West, a [[mixed-use development]] including retail.&lt;ref&gt; https://www.dailynews.com/regal-cinemas-24-hour-fitness-and-old-navy-headed-to-noho-west-project-at-former-laurel-plaza-shopping-center&lt;/ref&gt;

By the late 1950s, many of the original owners were aging, and their children were moving to other areas. School integration in the subsequent years, [[blockbusting]], and subsequent ethnic turmoil encouraged many remaining families to move out, who in turn were replaced with black and Hispanic families moving from the downtown areas. By the 1990s, the demographic changes had almost completely transformed the region.

The [[North Hollywood shootout]] occurred in 1997, leaving 12 [[Los Angeles Police Department]] officers and eight civilians injured and the two armed robbers dead.

===21st century===
[[File:New high-density apartments north hollywood.jpg|thumb|left|High-density property development in "NoHo"]]

Since 2000, the community has been developing and undergoing many changes, thanks in large part to the formation of the 743-acre North Hollywood Development District and the subsequent NoHo Commons projects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diamondwest.net/news/124-new-project-breaks-ground |title=NoHo Commons Third Phase Breaks Ground |publisher=Diamondwest.net |date= |accessdate=2013-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, Lankershim Boulevard in North Hollywood was part of the first San Fernando Valley [[CicLAvia]], an event sponsored by the [[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority]] in which major roads are temporarily closed to motorized vehicle traffic and used for recreational [[human-powered transport]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title       = Valley CicLAvia Crowd Estimated at 100K
| date        = 2015-03-23
| url         = http://losangeles.cbslocal.com/2015/03/23/valley-ciclavia-crowd-estimated-at-100k/
| work        = CBS Los Angeles
| archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150324033436/http://losangeles.cbslocal.com/2015/03/23/valley-ciclavia-crowd-estimated-at-100k/
| archivedate = 2015-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attractions==
[[File:Idle Hour Cafe North Hollywood (vertical) 2015-02-15.jpg|thumb|upright|The Idle Hour Cafe on Vineland Ave.]]

North Hollywood is home to the [[Academy of Television Arts &amp; Sciences]].

[[Valhalla Memorial Park Cemetery|Pierce Brothers Valhalla Memorial Park]] is located in the area, and includes the [[Portal of the Folded Wings Shrine to Aviation]].

[[Universal Studios]] is also located on the border between [[Hollywood]] and North Hollywood, easily accessible through one of NoHo's main streets, Lankershim Boulevard. Universal Studios has several attractions inside the actual park and in the non-paid CityWalk section. North Hollywood has several art houses, restaurants and theaters as well.

==Government and infrastructure==
The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] has the Antelope Valley Area Health Office and the San Fernando Valley Area Health Office in a facility in North Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/spa1/ Antelope Valley Area Health Office]." [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/spa2/ SPA2- San Fernando Valley Area Health Office]." [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The department operates the North Hollywood Health Center in North Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/northhollywood.pdf North Hollywood Health Center]." [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition the department operates the Glendale Health Center in [[Glendale, California|Glendale]], serving North Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/glendale.pdf Glendale Health Center]." [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the North Hollywood Post Office at 7035 Laurel Canyon Boulevard,&lt;ref&gt;"[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/67507?p=3&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=North+Hollywood Post Office Location – NORTH HOLLYWOOD]{{Dead link|date=April 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}." ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the Valley Plaza Post Office at 6418 Bellingham Avenue,&lt;ref&gt;"[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/60199?p=4&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=North+Hollywood Post Office Location – VALLEY PLAZA]{{Dead link|date=April 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}." ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Victory Center Post Office at 6535 Lankershim Boulevard.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/66138?p=4&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=North+Hollywood Post Office Location – VICTORY CENTER]{{Dead link|date=April 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}." ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transportation===
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2013}}
[[File:North Hollywood station LA Metro.jpg|thumb|North Hollywood [[Los Angeles Metro Rail|LA Metro]] station]]
[[File:North Hollywood Pacific Electric Car Station, 1919 (LAVC15).jpg|thumb|North Hollywood Pacific Electric Car Station, 1919]]

The Los Angeles County Transportation Commission took years, but finally in 1990 approved the construction of the subway connecting North Hollywood to Hollywood, East Hollywood, Koreatown, Westlake and downtown Los Angeles along the Metro Rail Red Line. The decision followed the [[Los Angeles City Council]] unanimously endorsing North Hollywood as the northern terminal of the Red Line with the final route having termini at Union Station and North Hollywood. The [[North Hollywood (Los Angeles Metro station)|North Hollywood Metro Subway station]] opened in June 2000. Close to half a million people took advantage of free rides on the {{convert|17.4|mi|km|adj=on}} Red Line subway in its first weekend in operation. The station is the starting point for the [[Red Line (Los Angeles Metro)|Red Line Metro system]], which cost $4.5&amp;nbsp;billion to construct.

The tunnel to connect the Metro Red Line Hollywood leg to the San Fernando Valley extension cost $136&amp;nbsp;million. It included the cost of digging a tunnel under the Santa Monica Mountains. The tunneling work was done by a Traylor Brothers/Frontier-Kemper joint venture. The Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy and the Sierra Club had fought to prevent the tunneling but ultimately lost. Environmentalists were concerned that the removal of billions of gallons of ground water might affect springs, wildlife and vegetation.

Tunneling from North Hollywood for the subway started in 1995. Workers dug {{convert|70|ft|m}} deep using tunneling machines. Work progressed an average of {{convert|50|to|200|ft|m}} daily, performed by work crews round-the-clock six days a week. The machines bored through soil that once lined the bottoms of ancient oceans.

The two tunnels between the North Hollywood and Universal City stations were a total of {{convert|10541|ft|m}}. The cost of building the two tunnels was $65.4&amp;nbsp;million and involved 250 workers.

A further Red Line extension was replaced by the [[Orange Line (Los Angeles Metro)|Metro Orange Line]] [[bus rapid transit]]. Its terminus is located across the [[street]] from the [[North Hollywood (Los Angeles Metro station)|subway station]]. This expanded the station area into a [[transport hub|transit hub]], and many [[Metro Local (Los Angeles County)|local]] and [[Metro Rapid (Los Angeles County)|rapid]] [[bus]]es now stop at the station. Proposals have been made to extend the Red Line northeasterly to Bob Hope Airport in Burbank and the Burbank Metrolink station in central Burbank, or to extend it in a northwesterly direction along Lankershim Boulevard and eventually to Sylmar, a proposal which was mentioned in at least one published account in the press by former Los Angeles Mayor Antonio Villaraigosa. Neither project is currently funded nor is in Metro's Long Term  Transportation Plan.

==Education==
[[File:East Valley High School North Hollywood 2016-03-20.jpg|thumb|[[East Valley High School (Los Angeles)|East Valley High School]]]]
Eighteen percent of North Hollywood residents aged 25 and older had earned a [[four-year degree]] by 2000, an average figure for both the city and the county. The percentage of the same-age residents with less than a [[high school diploma]] was high for the county.&lt;ref name=MappingLANorthHollywood/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/education/less-than-high-school/neighborhood/list/ |title=Less Than High School Ranking – Mapping L.A. – Los Angeles Times |website=Projects.latimes.com |date= |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Schools within the North Hollywood boundaries are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/north-hollywood/schools |title=North Hollywood Schools – Mapping L.A. – Los Angeles Times |website=Projects.latimes.com |date= |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public===
* Bellingham Primary Center Elementary School, 6728 Bellingham Avenue
* Fair Avenue Elementary School, 6501 Fair Avenue
* Lankershim Elementary School, elementary, 5250 Bakman Avenue
* Maurice Sendak Elementary School, 11414 West Tiara Street
* Oxnard Street Elementary School, 10912 Oxnard Street
* Victory Boulevard Elementary School, 6315 Radford Avenue
* James Madison Middle School, 13000 Hart St
* Roy Romer Middle School, 6501 Laurel Canyon Boulevard
* [[North Hollywood High School]], 5231 Colfax Avenue 
* [[East Valley High School (Los Angeles)|East Valley High School]], 5525 Vineland Avenue
* North Hollywood Adult Learning Center, LAUSD Adult Education, 10952 Whipple Street&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nvoc.org/index.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-11-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141106062749/http://www.nvoc.org/index.html |archivedate=2014-11-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Private===
[[File:Dubnoff School for Educational Therapy street view from northeast 2015-05-09.jpg|thumb|Dubnoff School main building, built 1967]]
* Dubnoff Center for Child Development, K–12, 10526 Dubnoff Way. The school's main building was designed in 1965 by [[Ena Dubnoff]] in association with Flores, Gelman and Green.
* San Fernando Valley Professional School, K–12, 6215 Laurel Canyon Boulevard
* St. Paul's First Lutheran, Pre-K-8, 11330 McCormick Street, a school of the [[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod]] (WELS)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=BUILDING FOR LIFE AND ETERNITY |url=https://stpaulsfirst.org/school/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* St. Patrick Elementary School, 10626 Erwin Street &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stpatrickcatholicschool.com/|title=St. Patrick School – North Hollywood|website=St. Patrick School – North Hollywood}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Montessori Academy of North Hollywood, elementary, 6000 Ensign Avenue
* Laurel Hall, elementary, 11919 Oxnard Street
* [[Oakwood School, Los Angeles|Oakwood High School]], 11600 Magnolia Blvd
* Or Hachaim Academy, elementary, 6021 Laurel Canyon Boulevard
* The Wesley School, elementary, 4832 Tujunga Avenue
* St. Charles Borromeo, elementary, 10650 Moorpark Street

==Recreation and parks==
The North Hollywood Recreation Center is mostly in North Hollywood, with a portion in [[Valley Village, Los Angeles, California|Valley Village]].&lt;ref name="VVMap"&gt;"[http://www.myvalleyvillage.com/pdfs/VVMap.pdf Map] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081026182558/http://www.myvalleyvillage.com/pdfs/VVMap.pdf |date=2008-10-26 }}." Valley Village Neighborhood Council. Retrieved on September 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="NOHOPark"&gt;"[http://www.laparks.org/dos/reccenter/facility/northHollywoodRC.htm North Hollywood Recreation Center]." City of Los Angeles. Retrieved on March 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The park has an auditorium, lighted indoor baseball diamond courts, lighted outdoor baseball diamonds, lighted outdoor basketball courts, a children's play area, lighted handball courts, picnic tables, an outdoor unheated seasonal pool, and lighted tennis courts. In addition the center has an indoor gymnasium which can be used as a second auditorium and a community room; the gymnasium's capacity is 250 people.&lt;ref name="NOHOPark"/&gt;

The Valley Plaza Recreation Center in North Hollywood includes an auditorium, barbecue pits, a lighted baseball diamond, lighted outdoor basketball courts, a children's play area, a 40-person community room, a lighted American football&lt;!--Please keep the disambig so non-US residents can understand--&gt; field, an indoor gymnasium without weights, an outdoor gymnasium without weights, picnic tables, lighted tennis courts, and unlighted volleyball courts.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.laparks.org/dos/reccenter/facility/valleyPlazaRC.htm Valley Plaza Recreation Center]." City of Los Angeles. Retrieved on March 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The Jamie Beth Slaven Park, an unstaffed pocket park with unlighted outdoor basketball courts, a children's play area, and picnic tables, is in North Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.laparks.org/dos/parks/facility/slavinPk.htm Jamie Beth Slavin Park]." City of Los Angeles. Retrieved on March 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable people==
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Gene Autry]], actor&lt;ref&gt;[https://search.proquest.com/docview/166005644 Hedda Hopper, "Autry Can't Get Around to Resting," ''Los Angeles Times,'' July 31,1949, page D-1]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Corbin Bernsen]], actor&lt;ref name="usabio"&gt;[http://www.usanetwork.com/series/psych/theshow/characterprofiles/henryspencer/bio.html Biography] from a [[USA Network]] website for ''[[Psych]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=LB&amp;p_theme=lb&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=1212A353C6FAD998&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|title=NewsLibrary Search Results|website=nl.newsbank.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Brennan Boesch]], MLB baseball player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://articles.latimes.com/2003/jun/04/sports/sp-hsbests4 |newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]] |title=Top Performers |accessdate=September 3, 2011 |archivedate=March 8, 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140308114049/http://articles.latimes.com/2003/jun/04/sports/sp-hsbests4 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sondheimer |first=Eric |title=Powered Up at Harvard-Westlake |url=https://articles.latimes.com/2003/apr/08/sports/sp-hsnusondcol8 |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |date=April 8, 2003 |accessdate=September 3, 2011 |archivedate=March 8, 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140308114112/http://articles.latimes.com/2003/apr/08/sports/sp-hsnusondcol8 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Everett G. Burkhalter]] (1897–1975), California politician&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/north-hollywood/?q=11005+Morrison+St%2C+San+Fernando+Valley%2C+CA+91601%2C+USA&amp;lat=34.161069&amp;lng=-118.3707343&amp;g=Geocodify |title=North Hollywood Profile – Mapping L.A. – Los Angeles Times |website=Projects.latimes.com |date= |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CityCouncilCandidates&gt;[https://search.proquest.com/docview/167834434 "City Council Candidates"], ''Los Angeles Times,'' March 12, 1961. page SF-4&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Adam Carolla]], North Hollywood High School&lt;ref name="2003-04-01"&gt;{{cite episode | title = April 1, 2003 | series = Loveline | serieslink = Loveline | airdate = April 1, 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nudie Cohn]], tailor&lt;ref name=rhinestone&gt;{{cite news |first= Chris|last= Dixon|authorlink= |author2= |title=A Rhinestone Cowboy Who Grabbed Cars by the Horns. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/04/automobiles/04AUTO.html |quote=Cohn made his mark by adorning Western-cut suits with galaxies of rhinestones, forests of fringe and symphonies of sparkling oversize G clefs. He fitted Elvis in gold lamé; created a shocking ensemble for [[Gram Parsons]], the proto-country rocker, embellished with pills and marijuana leaves; designed hundreds of shirts for [[Roy Rogers]]; and parked a star-studded 10-gallon hat on [[Elton John]]. |work=[[The New York Times]] |date= September 4, 2005|accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vince DiMaggio]], baseball player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/04/obituaries/vince-dimaggio-is-dead-at-74.html|title=Vince DiMaggio is Dead at 74|agency=[[Associated Press]]|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=October 4, 1986|accessdate=December 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tina Marie Jordan|Tina Jordan]], model&lt;ref name=Playboy&gt;''[[Playboy]]'' magazine, March 2002, page 90.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dorothy Lamour]], actress&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;{{cite news|title= Dorothy Lamour, 81, Sultry Sidekick in Road Films, Dies|work= The New York Times|date=September 23, 1996|url= https://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/23/us/dorothy-lamour-81-sultry-sidekick-in-road-films-dies.html?scp=66&amp;sq=murder%20she%20wrote&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-08-20 | first=Richard | last=Severo}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Robin Lopez]] and [[Brook Lopez]], NBA basketball players&lt;ref name="world of lopez"&gt;{{cite web|last=LaPointe|first=Joe|title=Wonderful World of Lopez Twins|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/26/sports/ncaabasketball/26stanford.html?pagewanted=all|work=The New York Times|accessdate=April 3, 2013|date=March 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nerd herd"&gt;{{cite web|last=Gustafson|first=John|title=The nerd herd|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espnmag/story?id=3608450|work=ESPN the Magazine|accessdate=April 3, 2013|date=October 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://basketballrecruiting.rivals.com/barrier_noentry.asp?ReturnTo=&amp;sid=&amp;script=content.asp&amp;cid=387104&amp;fid=&amp;tid=&amp;mid=&amp;rid= |title=BasketballRecruiting.Rivals.com |website=BasketballRecruiting.Rivals.com |date= |accessdate=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bruce Manson]], tennis player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1975/08/24/archives/procelebrity-tennis-is-a-hit-tennis-pros-celebrities-a-hit-here.html|title=Pro‐Celebrity Tennis is a Hit|first=Parton|last=Keese|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Randy Rhoads]] (1956–1982), guitarist&lt;ref name="ozzyhead"&gt;{{cite web |author=Perry, Randy |title=Randy Rhoads Biography/Timeline |url=http://www.ozzyhead.com/randbio.htm |publisher=ozzyhead.com |accessdate=May 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tony Robbins]], author, motivational speaker
* [[Hervé Villechaize]] (1943–1993), actor&lt;ref name=Frank&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wilkins|first1=Frank|title=The Suicide of Herve Villechaize – Tattoo|url=http://www.franksreelreviews.com/shorttakes/tattoo/tattoo.htm|website=Reel Reviews|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jim Wilson (Los Angeles)|Jim Wilson]], City Council member&lt;ref name=LibraryFile&gt;[http://dbase1.lapl.org/webpics/calindex/documents/15/486205.pdf Los Angeles Public Library reference file] Dbasel.lapl.org&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}

==See also==
* {{Portal-inline|size=tiny|Los Angeles}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
* Bearchell, Charles, and Larry D. Fried, ''The San Fernando Valley Then and Now'', Windsor Publications, 1988, {{ISBN|0-89781-285-9}}
* Coscia, David, ''Pacific Electric and the Growth of the San Fernando Valley'', Shade Tree Books, 2011, {{ISBN|1-57864-735-5}}
* Jorgensen, Lawrence C., ''The San Fernando Valley Past and Present'', Pacific Rim Research, 1982, {{ISBN|0-941014-00-2}}
* Link, Tom: ''Universal City – North Hollywood, a Centenniel Portrait'', Windsor Publications, 1991, {{ISBN|0-89781-393-6}}
* Mullaly, Larry, and Bruce Petty, ''The Southern Pacific in Los Angeles 1873–1996'', Golden West Books/Los Angeles Railroad Heritage Foundation, 2002, {{ISBN|0-87095-118-1}}
* Roderick, Kevin, ''The San Fernando Valley: America's Suburb'', Los Angeles Times Books, 2001, {{ISBN|1-883792-55-X}}

==External links==
{{Wikivoyage|North Hollywood}}
{{commons category}}
* ''Los Angeles Times'', Real Estate section, Neighborly Advice column: "[https://articles.latimes.com/2003/jul/27/realestate/re-guide27 North Hollywood: NoHo finds its mojo in a colorful, artsy sort of way]" (27 July 2003)
* [http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/north-hollywood/crime/ North Hollywood crime map and statistics]

{{Template group
|title = Articles related to North Hollywood, LA
|list  =
{{Geographic location
| Centre    = North Hollywood
| North     = [[Sun Valley, Los Angeles|Sun Valley]]
| Northeast = [[Bob Hope Airport]]
| East      = [[Burbank, California|Burbank]]
| Southeast = [[Toluca Lake, Los Angeles|Toluca Lake]]
| South     = [[Toluca Lake, Los Angeles|Toluca Lake]] &amp; [[Studio City, Los Angeles|Studio City]]
| Southwest = [[Studio City, Los Angeles|Studio City]] &amp; [[Los Angeles Valley College]]
| West      = [[Valley Village, Los Angeles|Valley Village]] &amp; [[Valley Glen, Los Angeles|Valley Glen]]
| Northwest = [[Panorama City, Los Angeles|Panorama City]] &amp; [[Arleta, Los Angeles|Arleta]]
}}
{{North Hollywood, Los Angeles}}
{{Los Angeles}}
{{Los Angeles San Fernando Valley}}
}}

[[Category:North Hollywood, Los Angeles| ]]
[[Category:1887 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Communities in the San Fernando Valley]]
[[Category:Neighborhoods in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1887]]</text>
      <sha1>qmbxvuxtekvvzt7dwofygj819uax30m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
