<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peter Lance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38054560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961491655</id>
      <parentid>954905217</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-08T19:51:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.186.224.114</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="42247" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name        = Peter Lance
| image       = Peter Lance hi-res photo by Ron Finley.jpeg
| caption     = 
| birthname   = Peter Lance
| birth_place = [[Newport, Rhode Island]], [[United States]]
| death_date  = 
| death_place = 
| education   = Studied law at [[Fordham University]]&lt;br&gt;Studied journalism at [[Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism]]&lt;br&gt;Studied philosophy at [[Northeastern University]]
| occupation  = Journalist, author
| years_active = 1968–present
| alias       = 
| title       = 
| spouse      = 
| children    = 
| relatives   = 
| ethnicity   = 
| salary      = 
| networth    = 
| credits     = Nonfiction Books: ''Cover Up: What the Government Is Still Hiding About the War on Terror''; ''1000 Years for Revenge: International Terrorism and the FBI—The Untold Story''; ''Triple Cross: How Bin Laden's Master Spy Penetrated the CIA, the FBI, and the Green Berets''; ''Stingray : The Lethal Tactics of the Sole Survivor''. Fictional Books: ''Stranger 456''; ''First Degree Burn''. Book forward to ''Murder, Inc. The Inside Story of The Syndicate Killing Machine'' by [[Burton Turkus]] and Sid Feder. TV News: ''[[20/20 (U.S. TV series)]]''; ''[[Nightline]]''; [[WABC-TV]] News; [[ABC News]]; [[ABC World News]] with [[Peter Jennings]]; ''[[WNET-TV]]''. Television writing: ''[[Crime Story (U.S. TV series)]]''; ''[[Miami Vice]]''; Co-executive TV Producer: ''[[Wiseguy]]''. Co-creator, writer/producer: ''[[Missing Persons (TV series)]]''; ''[[JAG (TV series)]]''; ''[[The Sentinel (TV series)]]''. Film: ''[[Blackjack (1998 film)|Blackjack]]''
| agent       = 
| website     = {{url|peterlance.com}}
}}

'''Peter Lance''' is an [[United States|American]] [[journalist]] and [[author]]. He is a five-time winner of the [[News &amp; Documentary Emmy Award]], the recipient of a [[Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Award]], and other accolades detailed below. In April 2010, Lance was appointed as a one-year Visiting Scholar at [http://www.global.ucsb.edu/orfaleacenter/people/visitingscholars.html The Orfalea Center for Global &amp; International Studies] at the [[University of California, Santa Barbara]].&lt;ref&gt;https://dev-orfaleacenterucsbedu.pantheonsite.io/people/past-visiting-scholars/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and education==

Peter Anthony Lance was born in [[Newport, Rhode Island]], the son of Joseph James Lance, a Navy Chief who had served on the [[USS Arkansas (BB-33)|USS ''Arkansas'' (BB-33)]] in World War II. His mother was Albina Marie Lance, the former deputy clerk for the Superior Court in Newport. Lance attended public grammar schools and was valedictorian of his class in 1966 at De La Salle Academy, a Catholic Christian Brothers boys high school. He majored in philosophy at [[Northeastern University]] in Boston where he was Managing Editor of the student newspaper, ''The Northeastern News''. While a student, Lance worked weekends as a news producer for [[WEZE|WEEI]], the former CBS radio owned and operated station in Boston.

After getting a B.A. from Northeastern in 1971 he earned an M.S. at The [[Columbia Graduate School of Journalism]] in 1972 and later a J.D. from [[Fordham University School of Law]] in 1978.

==Early career==

Lance began his journalism career as a cub reporter for ''[[The Newport Daily News]]'' while a student at Northeastern University. In his second summer with the paper he researched and reported a four-part investigative series on slum housing in Newport that won the 11th Annual Sevellon Brown Award given by the New England Associated Press Managing Editor's Association.&lt;ref&gt;[https://newspaperarchive.com/newport-daily-news/1969-05-19/ "Globe Honored for Stories on Deputies Fees"] May 19, 1969. Retrieved August 29, 2012.{{dead link|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Working as a researcher for [[Ralph Nader]]'s Center for The Study of Responsive Law, Lance spent one month each living with the families of a brick layer, a garbage collector and a policeman in Boston as part of a study that was published as ''The Workers: Portraits of Nine American Job Holders.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/workersportraits00lass/ Internet Archive page for ''The Workers: Portraits of Nine American Job Holders''] {{ISBN|0670782823}}, 1971 Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;'' Lance contributed research and writing to the book, authored by Kenneth Lasson. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://peterlance.com/Nader's_Raider_The_Workers_cover_credit_page.pdf Credits page for ''The Workers: Portraits of Nine American Job Holders''] Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Workers'' was one of dozens of books and reports produced during Nader's summer "task forces" during 1969–72, the interns of which came to be known as "Nader's Raiders".&lt;ref&gt;[http://csrl.org/about/ "History of the Center for Study of Responsive Law"] Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972, after graduating from the Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism, Lance worked as the assistant to the program director at [[WNET-TV]], the [[PBS]] flagship station in New York. He soon began producing for ''The 51st State'', a nightly news magazine where he won the first of his two New York Area Emmy awards for ''The Great American Land Hustle'' Part One.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyemmys.org/attachments/contentmanagers/65/18th%20Annual%20New%20York%20Emmy%20Awards.pdf 1993-1994 New York City Area Emmy Awards] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120430154300/http://www.nyemmys.org/attachments/contentmanagers/65/18th%20Annual%20New%20York%20Emmy%20Awards.pdf |date=2012-04-30 }} [http://www.nyemmys.org The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences, New York] Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1973 Lance moved to [[WABC-TV]], where he won a second New York Area Emmy, the National Station Emmy,&lt;ref name="Lance Awards"&gt;[http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?page_id=50 Awards page on Peter Lance website] Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Award]] for ''The Willowbrook Case: The People vs. The State of New York''.&lt;ref name="Lance Awards"/&gt;

In 1975, while working as a news producer at WABC-TV, Lance attended Fordham University School of Law as a night student. Studying at [[NYU Law School]] in the summer of 1977 he graduated from Fordham with a J.D. in 1978.

==ABC News==

After graduating from Fordham University in 1978 Lance went to work as a producer for ABC News ''[[20/20 (U.S. TV program)|20/20]]'', where he won one National News &amp; Documentary Emmy Awards in 1980 for ''Arson For Profit'', and another in 1981 for ''Unnecessary Surgery'', where he also served as a correspondent.&lt;ref name="Lance Awards"/&gt; In 1984 Lance began reporting as a correspondent for ABC News [[Nightline]](1984–85). In 1985 he joined a new investigative unit on [[World News Tonight with Peter Jennings]] where he worked until 1987, reporting dozens of stories from Pentagon cost overruns to a scandal involving how the FAA had manipulated the number of near mid-air collisions. Between 1979 and 1982 Lance received three additional Emmy nominations for his investigative reporting.&lt;ref name="Lance Awards"/&gt;

In December, 1987 Lance left ABC News and began working as a writer and later story editor, producer and [[show runner]] in episodic television.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0004145/ "Peter Lance"]. IMDb. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; While he worked on several hit television shows including [[Miami Vice]] and [[Wiseguy]], Lance's continuing work as an investigative journalist and nonfiction book author around 9/11 attracted the most national attention.

==9/11 investigation==

Lance was the first mainstream journalist to argue that the two attacks on the World Trade Center—the 1993 bombing and the attacks of 9/11—were linked via [[Ramzi Yousef]]. A Kuwaiti national trained in Wales, Yousef was Qaeda's chief bomb maker. He is also the nephew of the terrorist the FBI calls "the 9/11 mastermind" [[Khalid Sheikh Mohammed|Khalid Shaikh Mohammed (KSM)]]. Lance's investigative work linking Yousef and al Qaeda master spy [[Ali Mohamed]] to the 9/11 attacks has been cited repeatedly in "The Complete 9/11 Timeline" compiled by the nonprofit [[History Commons]] the respected compendium of open source 9/11 intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historycommons.org/searchResults.jsp?searchtext=%22Peter+Lance%22&amp;events=on&amp;entities=on&amp;articles=on&amp;topics=on&amp;timelines=on&amp;projects=on&amp;titles=on&amp;descriptions=on&amp;dosearch=on&amp;search=Go History Commons curation of evidence reported by Peter Lance on the links between the two World Trade Center bombings]. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2003, Lance's ''1000 Years for Revenge'', a broad survey of Al-Qaida operations in the US prior to 9/11&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.usatoday.com/life/books/excerpts/2003-09-10-1000-years_x.htm/ Excerpt from ''1000 Years for Revenge'']. ''USA Today'' Retrieved September 3, 2012. {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111019091443/http://www.usatoday.com/life/books/excerpts/2003-09-10-1000-years_x.htm |date=October 19, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was published by Harper Collins.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harpercollins.com/browseinside/index.aspx?isbn13=9780061738128 "1000 Years for Revenge By Peter Lance"]{{Dead link|date=May 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}. Harper Collins. Retrieved September 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The book presents evidence that the FBI missed dozens of opportunities to stop the attacks of September 11, dating back to 1989. Lance describes how an elusive al Qaeda mastermind defeated an entire American security system in "the greatest failure of intelligence since the Trojan Horse".

On September 2, 2003, CBS News Correspondent [[Dan Rather]], broadcasting from Baghdad during the [[Iraq War]], reviewed the evidence presented in ''1000 Years for Revenge'' for two days in a row, devoting two 4-minute segments as the lead stories on ''The CBS Evening News With Dan Rather''. On the first broadcast from Iraq, Rather said:&lt;ref&gt;[http://peterlance.com/cbs-1000years-1.wmv] Part I of ''The CBS Evening News With Dan Rather'' coverage of ''1000 Years for Revenge''. Retrieved September 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;One thing seems clear, had there not been the murderous attacks of 9/11 there probably would have been no war. Now a new book to be released tomorrow, ''1000 Years For Revenge: International Terrorism and the FBI'', contends that the FBI could have and should have prevented the 9/11 attacks.

(Lance) traces these lapses back to 1989 and an FBI surveillance of a group of Middle Eastern men at a Calverton, Long Island shooting range. Yet inexplicably they (the FBI) suddenly stopped watching after just one month.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rather explains that the Calverton men became devoted followers of blind cleric [[Omar Abdel Rahman]]. Rahman brought in professional bomber [[Ramzi Yousef]] and the men began to plot the first World Trade Center bombing. The broadcast includes interviews with Lance, who states:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Of the man photographed by the FBI in 1989 three were later convicted in the original World Trade Center bombing, one was convicted in the murder of Rabbi Meir Kahane, and one was convicted in The Day of Terror plot to blow up the bridges and tunnels around Manhattan.... It was absolutely possible for the FBI to have identified and stopped Yousef in the fall of 1992 as he built the bomb. If they had stopped Ramzi Yousef in 1992, they would have stopped 9/11.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The FBI, Lance says in the report, could have stopped Yousef because they had an informant, [[Emad Salem]], already in place. He was close enough to take a video, shown in the ''CBS Evening News'' broadcast, of a celebration that included several members of the original Calverton group and to hear whispers about bomb plot. But interoffice fighting at the FBI forced Salem to quit, leaving a chilling warning:

 &lt;blockquote&gt;The last thing Emad Salem said to Nancy Floyd, his (FBI) control agent, before he left: 'Don't call me when the bombs go off.'&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The next day, on September 3, 2003, Rather again led with coverage of ''1000 Years for Revenge'':&lt;ref&gt;[http://peterlance.com/cbs-1000years-2.wmv] Part II of ''The CBS Evening News With Dan Rather'' coverage of ''1000 Years for Revenge''. Retrieved September 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ramzi Yousef, the bomber responsible for the 1993 World Trade Center bombing, had fled to the Philippines where police discovered his bomb factory. Yousef again escaped but his accomplice (Abdul Hakim Murad) was arrested and spilled the chilling plot to Philippines Police Colonel Rodolfo Mendoza.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Dan Rather than shows the Colonel, Mendoza, in a taped interview, talking to Lance:

&lt;blockquote&gt; Lance: "He (Abdul Hakim Murad) said that there was a plan at least to hijack planes and fly them into targets in the United States?"

Mendoza: "Yeah. Targets in the United States. CIA headquarters in Langley, Virginia."

Lance: "And did he mention any other targets to you?"

Medoza: "Later, later he told me about the possibility of hitting the Pentagon. He told me also that there is an unidentified nuclear facility." &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rather reported that Mendoza also provided "one more piece of information", quoting Lance as saying, "He said there were 10 Islamic pilots, at that moment in 1995 in America training in U.S. flight schools." Colonel Mendoza, says Lance, gave that information to the U.S. Embassy, including information that Osama bin Laden was funding Ramzi Yousef's plots.

In 2004, Harper Collins published a follow-up book to ''1000 Years for Revenge''.

''Cover Up: What the Government Is Still Hiding About the War on Terror'' concludes that [[Al-Qaida]] showed signs of launching the impending 9/11 attacks in 1995, but were able to evade arrest by exploiting the poor relations between the [[FBI]] and [[CIA]] and problems within their respective infrastructures.

Another follow-on book, ''Triple Cross:How bin Laden's Master Spy Penetrated the CIA, the Green Berets, and the FBI—and Why Patrick Fitzgerald Failed to Stop Him'', published in September 2006, covers the Al Qaeda operative [[Ali Mohamed]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peterlance.com/TRIPLE%20CROSS%20Timeline.pdf Timeline published in Triple Cross] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110715070607/http://www.peterlance.com/TRIPLE%20CROSS%20Timeline.pdf |date=2011-07-15 }} The timeline shows links between the first and second bombings of the [[World Trade Center (1973–2001)|World Trade Center]]. Retrieved August 29, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; A review of the book by Rory O'Connor in [[The Guardian]] states: "In the annals of espionage, few men have moved in and out of the deep black world between the hunters and the hunted with as much audacity as Ali Mohamed.... The FBI allowed the chief spy for al-Qaida to operate right under their noses...They let him plan the bombings of the embassies in Africa right under their noses. Two hundred twenty-four people were killed and more than 4,000 wounded because of their negligence."&lt;ref&gt;O'Conner, Rory: [https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/nov/16/the911conspiracyofincompet "Joining the dots of ineptitude"], ''The Guardian'', November 16, 2006, retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The publisher's summary for ''Triple Cross'' states:&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/Triple-Cross-Penetrated-FBI---Fitzgerald/dp/0060886889/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1346819884&amp;sr=1-1 Publisher's summary of ''Triple Cross'' on amazon.com.] Retrieved September 5, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; This is the story of the most dangerous triple-agent in US history. Peter Lance, author of the highly acclaimed ''1000 Years for Revenge'' and ''Cover Up'', returns to uncover the story of Ali Mohamed, a trusted security advisor of Osama bin Laden who hoodwinked the United States for more than a decade. As Lance reveals for this first time, this one man served in a series of high-security position within the United States security establishment, as a Special Forces advisor, FBI informant, and CIA operative, while simultaneously helping orchestrate the al Qaeda campaign of terror that led to 9/11. In October 2000, after tricking three U.S. intelligence agencies for almost two decades, Ali Mohamed appeared in handcuffs and a blue prison jumpsuit in a Federal District courtroom on Manhattan's Lower East Side, where he pleaded guilty five times. His crimes included brokering terror summits, financing an attack on two Black Hawk helicopters, training jihadis in improvised bomb building and the creation of secret cells. And yet, for decades Mohamed had lived the life of a Silicon Valley computer executive. How did this evildoer move in and out of and around the U.S. is just one of the questions answered. From the Able Danger scandal of the Clinton Administration to today's CIA Leakgate, Mohamed appears at nearly every crucial turn of America's terror probes. An important final piece to the 9/11 investigation, ''Triple Cross'' penetrates Mohamed's secret past and the dark reaches of Al Qaeda to reveal the danger that still threatens America and its internal security.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The conclusion of the 9/11 Commission in Staff Statement No. 15 was that it was "a matter of debate" whether Yousef was a member of al Qaida.&lt;ref name="9/11 Commission #15"&gt;{{cite news |date= June 16, 2004 |publisher=NBC News |url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/5224036 |title=9/11 Commission Staff Statement No. 15 |accessdate=August 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the Commission called Yousef "part of a loose network of extremist Sunni Islamists who, like Bin Ladin, began to focus their rage on the United States".&lt;ref name="9/11 Commission #15"/&gt; But on April 10, 2011, ''[[The New York Times]]'' ran a story confirming Lance's theory: In the piece titled "In Federal Court, a Docket Number for Global Terror", reporter Benjamin Weiser detailed how the Justice Department had amended the original 1993 World Trade Center bombing indictment to include KSM.&lt;ref&gt;Weiser, B: [https://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/11/nyregion/11indict.html?_r=1 "In Federal Court, a Docket Number for Global Terror"]. ''The New York Times'', April 10, 2011. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The story was linked to a superseding indictment&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/04/11/nyregion/20110411-indict-docs.html?ref=nyregion "New York Terrorism Indictments"], ''The New York Times'', April 10, 2011, Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; which now named KSM along Yousef and [[Abdul Hakim Murad (militant)|Abdul Hakim Murad]], the pilot trained in four U.S. flights schools whom Lance first reported, based on intelligence from The Philippines National Police, was to be the original pilot in the "planes as missiles plot".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peterlance.com/Peter_Lance/Peter_Lances_blog/Entries/2007/10/22_The_FBI_and_DOJ_on_the_road_to_9_11.html "The FBI and DOJ on the Road to 911"] Chapter 18 of ''Cover Up'' by Peter Lance {{ISBN|0060543558}} Retrieved August 29, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attempt by Federal Prosecutor Patrick Fitzgerald to prevent publication of ''Triple Cross''===

In the fall of 2007, Federal prosecutor [[Patrick Fitzgerald]], who was an assistant U.S. attorney in New York in the 1990s, threatened to sue publisher [[HarperCollins]] over the new edition of ''Triple Cross'' they published in June 2009 if it defamed him or cast him in a false light, calling the book "a deliberate lie masquerading as the truth".&lt;ref&gt;Mike Robinson, [http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/chi-ap-il-fitzgerald-book,0,4941791.story "Fitzgerald threatens to sue publisher over book"] [[Associated Press]], [[Chicago Tribune]], June 8, 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; California is a [[false light]] defamation state which means that it is possible to sue for libel under certain circumstances not permitted in other states. However the publisher is located in New York.

Fitzgerald pressed his claim in 32 pages of threat letters sent to HarperCollins over 20 months.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peterlance.com/Fitzgerald_Libel_Claim_Letters_HCP_Response.pdf pdf files of threat letters from Patrick Fitzgerald to publisher Harper Collins] Retrieved August 29, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. attorney's threats resulted in a firestorm of coverage in the media,&lt;ref&gt;Kachka, Boris: [http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2009/06/05/a-prosecutor-gets-personal.html "A Prosector Gets Personal"]. ''Newsweek'' June 5, 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nymag.com/news/intelligencer/57196/ "Prosecutor As Book Publicist - Was Fitzgerald libeled?"] ''New York'' magazine, June 5, 2009 Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Garvin, Glenn: [http://www.peterlance.com/The_Miami_Herald_6.19.09_P.F.pdf "Liberals' Darlin Strikes Out"]. ''The Miami Herald'' June 27, 2009 Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; while Lance's research in Triple Cross was called "meticulous" by a writer for Forbes.com.&lt;ref&gt;Kaylan, Melik: [https://www.forbes.com/2009/06/29/triple-cross-peter-lance-opinions-columnists-book-review-terrorism.html "Ignore At Your Peril"]. June 30, 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In June, 2009 HarperCollins defied Fitzgerald threats, publishing a new updated edition in trade paperback form.&lt;ref&gt;[http://harpercollins.com/browseinside/index.aspx?isbn13=9780061189418 ''Triple Cross'']{{Dead link|date=May 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}. HarperCollins. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fitzgerald never made good on his threat to sue, despite a "dare" from Lance published in The Huffington Post a month after the publication of ''Triple Cross''. Published under the headline, "Mr. Fitzgerald, In Your Threat to Sue for Libel, Please, Either Put Up or Shut Up" Lance wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Seven weeks ago Patrick Fitzgerald, the most intimidating Federal prosecutor in America, sent my publisher (HarperCollins) and me a letter threatening to sue us for libel if ''Triple Cross'', a book I wrote, critical of his anti-terrorism track record, was published.

Yesterday marked the four-week anniversary of the book's pub date and although it's been out for a month, we're still waiting for his summons and complaint.

It was the fourth threat letter that Fitzgerald had sent since October 2007 and the man who'd succeeded in getting New York Times reporter Judith Miller jailed for 85 days in the CIA leak probe was growing impatient....&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/peter-lance/mr-fitz-in-your-threat-to_b_233530.html "Mr. Fitzgerald, In Your Threat to Sue for Libel, Please, Either Put Up or Shut Up"]. [[The Huffington Post]], July 15, 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The new (2009) edition of ''Triple Cross'' added material, including 26 pages detailing Fitzgerald's attempts to suppress the book. At a press conference for the new edition at the National Press Club in Washington, covered by the [[Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press]], Lance is quoted as saying "Fitzgerald is particularly sensitive to the issues discussed in the book because if they prove true, the prosecutor could face legal fallout of his own."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rcfp.org/browse-media-law-resources/news/book-released-despite-threats-federal-prosecutor "Book released despite threats from federal prosecutor"]. June 16, 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Lance further chronicled the Fitzgerald censorship controversy and tied it into his investigation of the FBI's counterterrorism failures in "The Chilling Effect", a June 2009 article published in ''Playboy''.&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [https://www.scribd.com/doc/35002681/The-Chilling-Effect-Playboy-6-16-09 "The Chilling Effect"]. ''Playboy'' June 2009. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Solving a 19-year-old al-Qaeda-related cold case==
In 2010, Lance was contacted by [[Emad Salem]], the ex-Egyptian army officer who had infiltrated the cell around blind Sheikh [[Omar Abdel-Rahman]] and the 1993 [[World Trade Center bombing]] conspiracy. Lance worked with Salem and ex-NYPD homicide detective James Moss to solve the homicide case of [[Mustafa Shalabi]], who was killed by [[al-Qaeda]] operatives in 1992.

Lance's investigative reporting into the WTC bombing and Shalabi was published in "The Spy Who Came In for the Heat", an article for the August 2010 issue of ''Playboy'',&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [https://www.scribd.com/doc/38785851/Peter-Lance-Spy-PLAYBOY "The Spy Who Came In for the Heat"]. ''Playboy'', August 2010 Retrieved September 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; recapping his findings on the television show ''[[Morning Joe]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20100925072749/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3036789/vp/38689632#38689632 Peter Lance on ''Morning Joe'': Lessons Learned from The War on Terror]. August 13, 2010. Retrieved September 2, 2012. &lt;/ref&gt; Lance expanded his reporting in ''First Blood'', another investigative piece published in ''[[Tablet Magazine]].''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.tabletmag.com/jewish-news-and-politics/44243/first-blood |last=Lance |first=Peter |title=First Blood:  Was Meir Kahane's Murder Al-Qaida's Earliest Attack on U.S. soil? |work=Tablet |date=September 1, 2010 |accessdate=September 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that story Lance revealed new evidence of a second gunman in the 1991 assassination of Rabbi [[Meir Kahane]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=199 |last=Lance |first=Peter |title=Tabletmag.com: Second gunman discovered in the Meir Kahane assassination |year=2013 |accessdate=September 2, 2012}}. (Recap of ''Tablet'' magazine article "First Blood:  Was Meir Kahane's Murder Al-Qaida's Earliest Attack on U.S. soil?")&lt;/ref&gt; Lance offered proof that [[El Sayyid Nosair]], the convicted killer of Kahane, also intended to murder former Israeli Prime Minister [[Ariel Sharon]], a revelation that made page-one news in ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Shefler, Gil: [http://www.jpost.com/International/Sharon-was-Kahane-killers-target "Sharon was Kahane killer's target"]. ''The Jerusalem Post'', August 15, 2010. Retrieved September 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Censorship of "Operation Dark Heart" and Lt. Col Anthony Shaffer==

In "The Private War of Anthony Shaffer", published in ''Playboy'', January, 2011,&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://www.operationdarkheart.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Private-War-Anthony-Shaffer-cut.pdf "The Private War of Anthony Shaffer"]. ''Playboy'', January 2011. Retrieved September 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Lance detailed how The Pentagon censored ''[[Operation Dark Heart]]'', the Afghan war memoir by [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]] recipient Lt. Col. [[Anthony Shaffer (intelligence officer)]]. In Lance's book ''Triple Cross'', Lance writes of Lt. Col. Shaffer's involvement in Operation [[Able Danger]], a secret data-mining operation run from 1998-1999 that uncovered evidence that [[Mohammed Atta]], the lead hijacker in the 9/11 plot, had been on the [[United States Department of Defense|DOD's]] radar months prior to when the 9/11 Commission claimed he'd entered the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=227 "Operation Able Danger"] (excerpt from the book, ''Triple Cross'') June 16, 2009 ISBN 978-0-06- 118941-8 Retrieved September 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==9/11, ''Murder Inc.'' and ''Deal with the Devil''==

Lance's research into the FBI and its close relations with Mafia informants began at ABC News ''Nightline,'' and was further informed by the nonfiction bestseller, ''Murder, Inc. The Story of the Syndicate'' by Brooklyn Assistant D.A. [[Burton Turkus]] and Sid Feder, first published in 1951. ''Murder, Inc.'' is a true account of the prosecution by Turkus of the [[organized crime|organized crime syndicate]] "killing machine" known as "[[Murder, Inc.]]".

In 2012, Lance's imprint, Tenacity Media Books republished ''Murder, Inc.'' In the forward to that book Lance discusses how his examination of the FBI's counter-terrorism investigations led him to discover an extraordinary link between the FBI and a 1996 Bureau sting of an al Qaeda terrorist, in Federal jail in Lower Manhattan, conducted with the help of a captain in the [[Colombo crime family]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In the course of my research I uncovered dozens of FBI 302 memos documenting a sting by Greg Scarpa Jr. that was authorized by the FBI in which the mobster intercepted a series of notes from Yousef (al Qaeda terrorist and World Trade Center bomber Ramzi Yousef) including threats to hijack planes and plant bombs on US airliners so that he could achieve a mistrial in the prosecution of the "Bojinka" plot which the feds decided to try first in the summer of 1996.

One piece of intelligence from Scarpa Jr. was worth its weight in platinum – the location of KSM who is hiding out in Doha Qatar. But by the time the FBI sent it to elite Hostage Rescue Team (HRT) to nab him, KSM had escaped only to succeed on 9/11 in doing what his nephew had failed to do in 1993 – take down the Twin Towers.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On his website, Lance provides a link to [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=682 the FBI 302 memos] that document Scarpa Jr.'s 11 month sting of Yousef. Also on his website, Lance states he spent the next 6 years following publication of ''Triple Cross'' documenting the FBI's 30+ year relationship with Scarpa Jr's father [[Gregory Scarpa|Gregory Scarpa Sr]], who, for more than 30 years, had been a "Top Echelon" informant for the Bureau and who once bragged that he "stopped counting" after 50 homicides.&lt;ref&gt;Ginsberg, Alex: [http://www.nypost.com/p/news/regional/item_0KDKDyCpBQvYrCyBcBwU4 "Hit Man For Mob Lost Count Of Corpses"] ''New York Post'' October 19, 2007. Retrieved September 5, 2012.{{dead link|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Deal With The Devil''===

In July 2013 HarperCollins published [https://www.amazon.com/Deal-Devil-Secret-Thirty-Year-Relationship/dp/0061455342 ''Deal With The Devil''], the fourth investigative book in the series authored by Lance critical of the FBI in its organized crime and terrorism performance in the years leading up to the 9/11 attacks. ''Devil'' is a follow-on to Lance's preceding three books, ''1000 Years for Revenge'' (2003), ''Cover-Up'' (2004), and ''Triple Cross'' (2006).

According to the publisher's book description on Amazon.com:&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/Deal-Devil-Secret-Thirty-Year-Relationship/dp/0061455342/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1356297124&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=Peter+Lance Book description of ''Deal With The Devil'']. Amazon.com. Retrieved July 24, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In his more than three decades in law enforcement, FBI Special Agent R. Lindley DeVecchio was considered one of the Bureau's top agents on organized crime. With contacts at the highest levels of the mob, he offered the Feds an unprecedented window into the workings of the Brooklyn families—and tips he supplied led to more than 70 successful prosecutions that helped propel a young district attorney named Rudolph Giuliani to national prominence. Yet, by the 1990s it was charged that "Mr. Organized Crime", as DeVecchio was known, had taken his infiltration too far. As Emmy-winning reporter Peter Lance discovered while researching his 2004 book Cover Up, DeVecchio had developed a very close relationship with Colombo crime family killer Greg Scarpa Sr., known as "The Grim Reaper". For years Scarpa was DeVecchio's informant—but some evidence allegedly suggested that Scarpa had provided him information that the mobster used in three murders during the Colombo mob wars of the 1980s. Though the DeVecchio story was only a subplot in a cover up, after its publication Hynes' office filed charges against DeVecchio—and cited Lance's investigation as a wonderful springboard to understand the story. Lance was subpoenaed by defense attorneys in connection with the 2007 trial. And yet in late 2007, the case against DeVecchio was dramatically dropped when the credibility of a key witness (unrelated to Lance's reporting) was impugned.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

During a two-hour presentation on the book at [http://themobmuseum.org The Mob Museum] in Las Vegas televised by [http://www.c-span.org/video/?314433-1/book-discussion-deal-devil C-Span2's Book TV] Lance announced he was developing ''Deal With The Devil'' as a multi-year dramatic cable TV series.

'Deal With the Devil', a phrase used in a decision by the late Judge Gustin Reichbach in his dismissal of the Lin DeVecchio murder case,&lt;ref&gt;[http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=4570 Decision by the late Judge Gustin Reichbach in his dismissal of the Lin DeVecchio murder case]. Retrieved July 24, 2014&lt;/ref&gt; is based on a case Brooklyn DA [[Charles Hynes]] called "the most stunning example of official corruption that I have ever seen".&lt;ref&gt;Rashbaum, William K: [https://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/31/nyregion/31agent.html?pagewanted=all "Retired F.B.I. Agent Is Accused of Role in Killings"] ''The New York Times'' March 31, 2006. Retrieved September 5, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Investigation into police corruption in Santa Barbara ==

On January 1, 2011, Lance was driving home from a New Year's Eve party. Shortly after 1:00 am he was pulled over by Santa Barbara Police Officer Kasi Beutel who breath-tested Lance and then arrested him for [[DUI|Driving under the influence]] (of alcohol).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.noozhawk.com/article/062311_santa_barbara_police_defend_dui_officer_targeted_in_newspaper_series/ |author=Lt. Paul McCaffrey |publisher=Santa Barbara Police Department |title=Santa Barbara Police Department Defends DUI Officer Targeted in Newspaper Series |date=July 23, 2011 |accessdate=October 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lance pleaded innocent, and was exonerated after his criminal case was dismissed on November 15, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://peterlance.com/New-Press-Lance_Case-Dismissed_11_16_11.pdf "Lance Case Dismissed"] ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' November 16, 2011. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

While contesting the charges against him Lance proceeded with his own investigation of the practices of the Santa Barbara police department, the results published in a 13-part series for the ''[[Santa Barbara News-Press]]''. In the series, Lance alleges that the police systematically falsified evidence to obtain DUI convictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-onthemedia-20110702,0,7977144.column | work=Los Angeles Times | first=James | last=Rainey | title=On the Media: A DUI cop exposé — by a DUI suspect | date=July 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His reportage was controversial because, among other things, Lance was being charged with DUI during the same period of time that he was investigating the police department and reporting his findings.&lt;ref&gt;Welsh, Nick: [http://www.independent.com/news/2011/jun/30/putting-ow-back-bow-wow/ "Putting the 'Ow' Back in Bow-Wow"]. ''Santa Barbara Independent'' June 30, 2011. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 2, 2011, the mayor and city administrator of Santa Barbara City pledged to investigate Lance's findings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.noozhawk.com/article/080211_helene_schneider_and_jim_armstrong/ "City of Santa Barbara Will Review Allegations in DUI Series"] ''Noozhawk'' August 2, 2011. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' series charged that officer Beutel used pre-filled forms that would meet certain criteria "to guarantee a successful DUI arrest". Lance told the ''Santa Barbara Independent'': "This is the essence of a dirty DUI cop framing innocent people." He compared the use of pre-filled forms to "something that would happen in the old Soviet Union".&lt;ref&gt;Robbins, Rebecca: [http://www.independent.com/news/2011/aug/26/dui-case-against-peter-lance-could-be-collapsing/ "DUI Case Against Peter Lance Could Be Collapsing Handwriting Expert Finds Pre-Checked Boxes on Blood Test Waiver"]. ''Santa Barbara Independent'' August 26, 2012. Retrieved October 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2011 ''News-Press'' series Lance also wrote that officer Beutel "may have committed bankruptcy fraud in 2000"; that she "perjured herself during divorce proceedings in 2005"; and that "she'd suborned the perjury of the minister who married her in 1999 by asking him to back-date her marriage license so that she might receive more post-divorce support".&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://www.newspress.com/Top/Article/article.jsp?Section=LOCAL&amp;ID=566505461298364451&amp;Archive=true "A DUI Arrest Tale of Two Cities"] ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' October 3, 2012 Retrieved October 10, 2012. {{subscription required}} [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=1326 PDF]. Retrieved October 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 6, 2011 Lance filed a 21-page formal complaint against Police Chief Cam Sanchez of the [[Santa Barbara Police Department]], asking for a full investigation of his allegations.&lt;ref&gt;Steepleton, Scott: [http://peterlance.com/News-Press_3.3.12_Judge_Beutel_complied_with_Lance_subpoena.pdf "Judge: Beutel complied with Lance subpoena"]. ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' March 3, 2012. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV) dropped all charges against Lance on March 6, 2012. On March 8, 2012, the ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' revealed that an outside consulting firm had been paid $12,000 for a report on the matter that they then kept secret.&lt;ref&gt;Steepleton, Scott: [http://peterlance.com/News-Press_DMV_%20dismissal_3.8.12.pdf "DMV follows judge, drops case against Lance"]. ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' March 8, 2012. Retrieved August 29, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2012 the ''News-Press'' published a new five-part series by Lance that reported on "a local defense lawyer (who) suspected that someone in law enforcement had planted heroin on one of his clients — a woman arrested on suspicion of DUI by Officer Beutel"&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://www.newspress.com/Top/Article/article.jsp?Section=LOCAL&amp;ID=566507557242404967&amp;Archive=false "A DUI arrest and a bindle of heroin"] ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' October 3, 2012 Retrieved October 10, 2012.{{subscription required}} [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=1514 Pdf]. Retrieved October 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; On October 7, 2012, Lance wrote:&lt;ref&gt;Lance, Peter: [http://www.newspress.com/Top/Article/article.jsp?Section=LOCAL&amp;ID=566507711861227609&amp;Archive=false "Investigation of officer leaves unanswered questions"]. ''Santa Barbara News-Press'' October 7, 2012 Retrieved October 10, 2012. {{subscription required}} [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=1526 PDF]. Retrieved October 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;At first I didn't believe it, despite the evidence I'd assembled by then, proving that Officer Beutel, the former head of the Santa Barbara Police Department's Drinking Driver Team and two-time Top DUI officer in the county had falsified police reports, committed perjury on a DMV form, witnessed at least five forged blood test waivers, withheld evidence from two suspects in violation of Brady rules, and pre-checked DUI forms before going into the field, suggesting a pre-determined mindset to frame innocent drivers.

I'd uncovered additional evidence regarding the accountant-turned-cop possibly committing bankruptcy fraud in 2000 and perjury in the course of divorce proceedings just months before she donned the uniform of the Santa Barbara Police Department in 2005.

Knowing all of that, I refused to accept that a sworn officer of the law could do something as repugnant as planting drugs on a suspect, much less heroin. Still, as with all the evidence in this investigation, I vetted the allegation with an open mind.

Over the months since then, as more and more information surfaced, including a videotape from County Jail where the discovery of the drug took place, I came to believe that it wasn't just possible, but probable that someone in law enforcement — perhaps Officer Beutel — had intentionally planted that bindle of black tar heroin at the feet of the DUI suspect, causing the District Attorney's Office to charge her on additional charges beyond driving under the influence.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On December 5, 2012, the Santa Barbara City Council voted to spend $208,000 to install video cameras in 27 Santa Barbara Police Department patrol cars. The move came after the recommendation of the Santa Barbara County Grand Jury in October, 2011 following Lance's first series in which he reported for the first time that the SBPD was the largest police agency in the county without onboard video in patrol units; a factor that can lead to misconduct in DUI arrests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Emily Parker |url=http://www.newspress.com/Top/Article/article.jsp?Section=LOCAL&amp;ID=566541745182081069&amp;Archive=true |title=Council OKs money for police video cameras : Installation in 27 patrol units expected by February |newspaper=Santa Barbara News-Press |date=December 5, 2012 |accessdate=December 23, 2012}} {{subscription required}} [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=1627 PDF].&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Books==
* ''Deal with the Devil: The FBI's Secret Thirty-Year Relationship with a Mafia Killer'' {{ISBN|0061455342}}; {{ISBN|978-0061455346}}
* ''Cover Up: What the Government Is Still Hiding About the War on Terror'' {{ISBN|0-06-054355-8}}
* ''1000 Years for Revenge: International Terrorism and the FBI—The Untold Story'' {{ISBN|0-06-059725-9}}
* ''Triple Cross: How Bin Laden's Chief Security Adviser Penetrated the CIA, the FBI, and the Green Berets'' {{ISBN|0-06-088688-9}}
* ''Stingray : The Lethal Tactics of the Sole Survivor'' {{ISBN|1-885840-03-9}}
* ''First Degree Burn'' {{ISBN|0-425-15698-2}}

==Awards==
*[[Emmy]] (five times) [http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=54]
*[http://peterlance.com/wordpress/?p=54 List of Awards on Peter Lance website] Retrieved September 6, 2012

==External links==
*[http://www.scotthortonshow.com/?s=Peter+Lance Downloadable audio interview] with [[Scott Horton (radio host)|Scott Horton]]
*http://www.peterlance.com/
* {{IMDb name|id=0004145|name=Peter Lance}}

===Listening===
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20061130111240/http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=06%2F11%2F29%2F1438234 Peter Lance on ''Democracy Now!'' program], November 29, 2006

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lance, Peter}}
[[Category:American male writers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Place of birth missing (living people)]]
[[Category:Year of birth missing (living people)]]</text>
      <sha1>n77h90ir96vn5shpluy5z04i3g2pe0m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
