<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Papal ferula</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39481799</id>
    <revision>
      <id>945754792</id>
      <parentid>934373424</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-15T22:57:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>HTTP → HTTPS for the [[Vatican]], replaced: http://www.vatican.va/ → https://www.vatican.va/ (4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8488" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Pastoral staff in the Catholic Church used by the pope}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2017}}
{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| header    = ''Ferula''&lt;br&gt;Pastoral staff
| width     = 180
| image1    = PapaJCruz Brazil.jpg
| alt1      = Pope John Paul II holding the ferula of Pope Paul VI,&lt;ref name="The Staff"&gt;[https://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/details/ns_lit_doc_20091117_ferula_en.html The Staff] By The Office of The Liturgical Celebrations Of The Sovereign Pontiff&lt;/ref&gt; on 5 October 1997
| caption1  = [[Pope John Paul II]] holding the ''ferula'' of [[Pope Paul VI]],&lt;ref name="The Staff"/&gt; on 5 October 1997
| image2    = Benoît XVI synode 2008.jpg
| alt2      = Pope Benedict XVI holding the ferula of Pius IX on 5 October 2008.
| caption2  = [[Pope Benedict XVI]] holding the 1877 ''ferula'' of Pius IX on 5 October 2008.
}}
The '''papal ferula''' (from [[Latin]] ''ferula'', 'rod') is the pastoral staff used in the [[Catholic Church]] by the [[pope]]. It is a rod with a knob on top surmounted by a cross. It differs from a [[crosier]], the staff carried by other bishops of Latin-rite churches, which is curved or bent at the top in the style of a [[shepherd's crook]].

==History==

===Early usage and dispute===
Traditionally, the popes did not use any ''ferula'', [[crosier]], or pastoral staff as part of the papal liturgy.&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/details/ns_lit_doc_20091117_ferula_en.html|title=The Office of the Liturgical Celebrations of the Supreme Pontiff: The Staff|publisher=[[Holy See Press Office]]|accessdate=23 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of a staff is not mentioned in descriptions of Papal Masses in the ''[[Ordines Romani]]'' (Roman Ordinals). In the early days of the church, a crosier was carried on some occasions by the pope, but this practice disappeared by the time of [[Pope Innocent III]]. Innocent III noted in his ''De Sacro altaris mysterio'' (“Concerning the Sacred Mystery of the Altar,” I, 62): “The Roman Pontiff does not use the shepherd's staff.” The reason was that a crosier is often given by the metropolitan archbishop (or by another bishop) to a newly elected bishop during his investiture. In contrast, the pope does not receive investiture from another bishop and is invested with the [[pallium]] during his coronation or inauguration.&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"/&gt;

===Re-adoption===
During the High Middle Ages, the popes once again began using a staff known as a ''ferula'' as insignia to signify temporal power and governance, which included "the power to mete out punishment and impose penances".&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"/&gt; The actual form of the staffs from this period is not well known, but were likely staffs topped with a knob with single-barred cross on top.&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"/&gt; The staff was not a liturgical item, and its use was limited to a few extraordinary ceremonial occasions, such as the opening of the [[Holy Door]] and the consecration of churches, during which the pope "took hold of the staff to knock on the door three times and to trace the Greek and Latin letters on the floor of the church".&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"/&gt; Sometimes, the staff also took the form of a triple-barred cross (or [[papal cross]], a symbol of the papacy), but this was rare in contrast to the single-barred cross. Use of the staff was soon again phased out.

In 1877, the Circolo San Pietro (an organization founded in 1869 to support the papacy) presented a staff or ''ferula'' to [[Pope Pius IX]] on the occasion of the fiftieth anniversary of his episcopal consecration and is sometimes referred to as the "''ferula'' of Pius IX". This ''ferula'' was used by popes from [[Pope Pius IX]] until [[Pope Paul VI]], again only for extraordinary, non-liturgical ceremonies. [[Pope Leo XIII]] at times made use of a crosier in the same shape as that of other bishops. In addition, a triple-barred cross ''ferula'' was made for Leo XIII for the Golden Jubilee of his Priesthood in 1888. [[Pope John XXIII]] had begun using the 1877 ''ferula'' of Pius IX for various liturgical celebrations during the [[Second Vatican Council]]. It was during the pontificate of Paul VI that the popes more permanently began using a ''ferula'' as a pastoral staff for solemn liturgical celebrations, rather than a symbol of governance. In effect, the papal ''ferula'' became the equivalent of a bishop's crosier or pastoral staff.

===Modern usage===
The pastoral staff carried by the popes since Pope Paul VI is a contemporary&lt;ref&gt;Fr. Brian T. Austin, FSSP. - The Liturgical Reform of Pope Benedict XVI, EWTN On Location, 7 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; single-barred [[crucifix]], designed by the Italian artist Lello Scorzelli&lt;ref&gt;Ralf van Bühren 2008, p. 319, 336-337, fig. 54-57.&lt;/ref&gt; in 1963 and carried and used in the same manner as a bishop uses his [[crosier]]. Paul VI had actually used three other ''ferulas'', similar in style, with the other versions having a cross bar which was straight, or bent upward.&lt;ref name ="sbsb"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://saintbedestudio.blogspot.com.au/2013/03/papal-retrospective-paul-vi-5.html |title=Papal Retrospective: Paul VI : 5 (Includes pictures of all ferulas used by Pope Paul VI)|publisher=The Saint Bede Studio Blog|date=11 March 2013|accessdate=25 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scorzelli's well known version has the cross bar bent downward, much like the ''paterissa'' carried by a bishop within the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]]. Paul VI first used this staff on 8 December 1965, at the closing of the [[Second Vatican Council]]. The Scorzelli staff was the one retained by his successors starting with [[Pope John Paul I]]. This ''ferula'' design is often associated with [[Pope John Paul II]].&lt;ref name ="vaticanstaff"/&gt;

On 25 March 1983, Pope John Paul II used the ''ferula'' of Leo XIII with three horizontal bars in the opening of the [[Holy Door]] during the [[Jubilee (Christianity)|Jubilee]], the Holy Year of the Redemption. In 1990, Scorzelli made a replica of the Paul VI ''ferula'' for John Paul II, which was lighter than the previous one.

On 16 March 2008, at the [[Palm Sunday]] celebrations in [[Saint Peter's Square]], Pope Benedict XVI used the ''ferula'' that had been previously used from the pontificate of Pope Pius IX.&lt;ref&gt;Cindy Wooden, {{cite web|url=http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0801930.htm|title=In U.S. Masses, pope to carry pastoral staff of Blessed Pope Pius IX|publisher=[[Catholic News Service]]|date=10 April 2008|accessdate=14 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This cross was used until 28 November 2009 at the First Vespers for Advent. A new ''ferula'' was given to Pope Benedict XVI as a gift of the Circolo San Pietro and, according to Monsignor [[Guido Marini]], the Master of Apostolic Ceremonies and head of the [[Office for the Liturgical Celebrations of the Supreme Pontiff]], it "can be considered to all intents and purposes the pastoral staff of Benedict XVI."

[[Pope Francis]] continued to use the ''ferula'' of Benedict XVI at the beginning of his pontificate. On 7 April 2013, at the Mass for the Possession of the Chair of the Bishop of Rome in the [[Archbasilica of Saint John Lateran]] in Rome, Francis returned to using the original 1965 ''ferula'' of Paul VI with the corpus on it and has alternated its use with the ''ferula'' of Benedict XVI.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[[Ralf van Bühren|Bühren, Ralf van]]: ''Kunst und Kirche im 20. Jahrhundert. Die Rezeption des Zweiten Vatikanischen Konzils'' (Konziliengeschichte, Reihe B: Untersuchungen), Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh 2008 ({{ISBN|978-3-506-76388-4}})

==External links==
*[https://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/details/ns_lit_doc_20091117_ferula_en.html The Office of the Liturgical Celebrations of the Supreme Pontiff: The Staff] {{in lang|en}}
*[https://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/details/ns_lit_doc_20091117_ferula_it.html L'Ufficio delle celebrazioni liturgiche del sommo pontefice: La ferula] {{in lang|it}}
*[http://www.dieter-philippi.de/en/ecclesiastical-fineries/crozier-bishops-staff-posoch-zezel-pilgrims-staff Philippi Collection: Crozier - Bishops' Staff - Posoch - Zezel - Pilgrim's Staff]
*[http://annunciations.files.wordpress.com/2008/03/piusxii.jpg  Pope John Paul II carrying a ferula from the time of Leo XIII, with three horizontal bars near the top]

{{Papal symbols and rituals}}

[[Category:Papal vestments]]</text>
      <sha1>2sudu547q0lc76ru4a9twdr9pnqllrh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
