<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ancient Maya art</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6721754</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962864994</id>
      <parentid>962864722</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-16T12:34:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Retal</username>
        <id>2920822</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Stone sculpture */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="48113" xml:space="preserve">{{Maya civilization}}
'''Ancient Maya art''' is about the material arts of the [[Maya civilization]], an eastern and south-eastern [[Mesoamerica|Mesoamerican]] culture shared by a great number of kingdoms in present-day southern Mexico, Guatemala, Belize and western Honduras. Thus, many regional artistic traditions existed side by side, usually coinciding with the changing boundaries of Maya polities. This civilization took shape in the course of the later Preclassic Period (c. 750 BC to 100 BC), when the first cities and monumental architecture started to develop and the hieroglyphic script came into being. Its greatest artistic flowering occurred during the seven centuries of the Classic Period (c. 250 to 950 CE). 
 
Maya art forms tend to be more stiffly organized during the Early Classic (250-550 CE) and to become more expressive during the Late Classic phase (550-950 CE). In the course of history, influences of various other Mesoamerican cultures were absorbed. In the late Preclassic, the influence of the [[Olmec]] style is still discernable (as in the [[San Bartolo (Maya site)|San Bartolo]] murals), whereas in the Early Classic, the style of central Mexican [[Teotihuacan]] made itself felt, just as that of the [[Toltec]] in the Postclassic. 

After the demise of the Classic riverine kingdoms, ancient Maya art went through an extended Postclassic phase (950-1550 CE) centered on the Yucatan peninsula, before the upheavals of the sixteenth century destroyed courtly culture and put an end to the Mayan artistic tradition. Traditional art forms mainly survived in weaving and the design of peasant houses.

==Mayan art history==

The nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century publications on Maya art and archaeology by [[John Lloyd Stephens|Stephens]], [[Frederick Catherwood|Catherwood]], [[Alfred Maudslay|Maudslay]], [[Teoberto Maler|Maler]] and [[Désiré Charnay|Charnay]] for the first time made available reliable drawings and photographs of major Classic Maya monuments.[[File:IzamalHeadCatherwoodEngraving.jpg|thumb|left|Studying a ruin at [[Izamal]], Catherwood engraving]] Following this initial phase, the 1913 publication of Herbert Spinden's 'A Study of Maya Art' (now over a century ago ) laid the foundation for all later developments of Maya art history (including iconography).&lt;ref&gt;Spinden 1975&lt;/ref&gt; The book gives an analytical treatment of themes and motifs, particularly the ubiquitous serpent and dragon motifs, and a review of the 'material arts', such as the composition of temple facades, roof combs and mask panels. Spinden's chronological treatment of Maya art was later (1950) refined by the motif analysis of the architect and specialist in archaeological drawing, [[Tatiana Proskouriakoff]], in her book 'A Study of Classic Maya Sculpture'.&lt;ref&gt;Proskouriakoff 1950&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Kubler|Kubler's]] 1969 inventory of Maya iconography, containing a site-by-site treatment of 'commemorative' images and a topical treatment of ritual and mythical images (such as the 'triadic sign'), conclude a period of gradual increase of knowledge that was soon to be overshadowed by new developments.

Starting in the early 1970s, the historiography of the Mayan kingdoms – first of all Palenque – came to occupy the forefront. Art-historical interpretation joined the historical approach pioneered by Proskouriakoff as well as the mythological approach initiated by [[Michael D. Coe|M.D. Coe]], with a professor of art, Linda Schele, serving as a driving force. Schele's seminal interpretations of Maya art are found throughout her work, especially in ''The Blood of Kings'', written together with art historian [[Mary Miller (art historian)|M. Miller]].&lt;ref&gt;Schele and Miller 1986&lt;/ref&gt; Maya art history was also spurred by the enormous increase in sculptural and ceramic imagery, due to extensive archaeological excavations, as well as to organized looting on an unprecedented scale. On from 1973, M.D. Coe published a series of books offering pictures and interpretations of unknown Maya vases, with the Popol Vuh Twin myth for an explanatory model.&lt;ref&gt;Coe 1973, 1975, 1978, 1982&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981, Robicsek and Hales added an inventory and classification of Maya vases painted in codex style,&lt;ref&gt;Robicsek and Hales 1981&lt;/ref&gt; thereby revealing even more of a hitherto barely known spiritual world.

As to subsequent developments, important issues in Schele's iconographic work have been elaborated by [[Karl Taube]].&lt;ref&gt;E.g., Miller and Taube 1993; Taube et al. 2010&lt;/ref&gt; New approaches to Maya art include studies of ancient Maya ceramic workshops,&lt;ref&gt;Reents-Budet 1994&lt;/ref&gt; the representation of bodily experience and the senses in Maya art,&lt;ref&gt;Houston et al. 2005&lt;/ref&gt; and of hieroglyphs considered as iconographic units.&lt;ref name="Stone and Zender 2011"&gt;Stone and Zender 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the number of monographs devoted to the monumental art of specific courts is growing.&lt;ref&gt;Tate 1992, Looper 2003, Simmons Clancy 2009, O'Neil 2012&lt;/ref&gt; A good impression of recent Mexican and North American art historical scholarship can be gathered from the exhibition catalogue 'Courtly Art of the Ancient Maya' (2004).&lt;ref&gt;Miller and Martin 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture==
{{main|Maya architecture}}

[[File:Copan T11-2.jpg|thumb|Copan, 'Reviewing Stand' with simian musicians]] 
[[File:Labna-Palace-Vaulted-Passage.jpg|thumb|Labna, Palace, vaulted passage]]

The layout of the Maya towns and [[Maya city|cities]], and more particularly of the ceremonial centers where the royal families and courtiers resided, is characterized by the rhythm of immense horizontal stucco floors of plazas often located at various levels, connected by broad and often steep stairs, and surmounted by temple pyramids.&lt;ref&gt;Stierlin 1994&lt;/ref&gt; Under successive reigns, the main buildings were enlarged by adding new layers of fill and stucco coating. Irrigation channels, reservoirs, and drains made up the hydraulic infrastructure. Outside the ceremonial center (especially in the southern area sometimes resembling an [[acropolis]]) were the structures of lesser nobles, smaller temples, and individual shrines, surrounded by the wards of the commoners. Dam-like causeways ([[sacbe]]ob) spread from the 'ceremonial centers' to other nuclei of habitation. Fitting in with the concept of a '[[theatre state]]', more attention appears to have been given to aesthetics than to solidity of construction. Careful attention, however, was placed on directional orientation.

Among the various types of structures should be mentioned:
*Ceremonial platforms (usually less than 4 meters in height).
*Courtyards and palaces.
*Other residential buildings, such as a writers' house &lt;ref&gt;Coe and Kerr 1997: 100-101&lt;/ref&gt; and a possible council house in Copan.
*Temples and temple pyramids, the latter often containing burials in their base or fill, with sanctuaries on top. The outstanding example are the many clustered dynastic burial temples of Tikal's [[North Acropolis, Tikal|North Acropolis]].   
*[[Mesoamerican ball court|Ball courts]].
 
Among the structural ensembles are:
*'[[Triadic pyramid]]s' consisting of a dominant structure flanked by two smaller inward-facing buildings, all mounted upon a single basal platform;
*'[[E-Group|E-groups]]' consisting of a square platform with a low four-stepped pyramid on the west side and an elongated structure, or, alternatively, three small structures, on the eastern side;
*'[[Twin pyramid complex]]es', with identical four-stepped pyramids on the east and west sides of a small plaza; a building with nine doorways on the south side; and a small enclosure on the north side housing a sculpted stela with its altar and commemorating the king's performance of a [[k'atun]]-ending ceremony.

In the palaces and temple rooms, the '[[corbelled vault]]' was often applied. Though not an effective means to increase interior space, as it required thick stone walls to support the high ceiling, some temples utilized repeated arches, or a corbelled vault, to construct an inner sanctuary (e.g., that of the Temple of the Cross at Palenque).

The northern Maya area (Campeche and Yucatán) shows characteristics of its own. Its Classic [[Puuc]], Chenes, and [[Rio Bec]] architecture&lt;ref&gt;Gendrop 1983&lt;/ref&gt; is characterized by the geometrical reduction of realistic decoration; the stacking of rain god snouts to build facades; the use of portals shaped like serpent mouths; and, in the Rio Bec area, the use of solid pseudo temple-pyramids. The most important Puuc site is [[Uxmal]]. [[Chichen Itza]], dominating Yucatán from the Late Classic to well into the Post-Classic, features Classic buildings in Chenes and Puuc style as well as Post-Classic building types of Mexican derivation, such as the radial four-staircase pyramid, the colonnaded hall, and the circular temple. The latter features were inherited by the succeeding kingdom of [[Mayapan]].

&lt;gallery widths="170px" heights="170px"&gt;
MayaHouse.JPG|Chichen Itza, traditional Maya house

0150 Palenque.JPG|Palenque, Temple of the Inscriptions, Late Classic

Sayil Palacio.jpg|Multistoried palace, Sayil, Yucatan, Classic

File:Copán Ballcourt.jpg|Ball court, Copan, Late Classic

Chichen Itza 3.jpg|Chichen Itza, radial pyramid ''[[El Castillo, Chichen Itza|El Castillo]]'', Postclassic
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Stone sculpture==
{{see also|Maya stelae}}
[[File:Cancuenpanel3.jpg|thumb|left|250px|[[Cancuen]], panel 3, seated king with two subordinates. Second half 8th century.]]
[[File:Stela A Copan 02.jpg|thumb|right|upright|180px|Copan stela A, Maudslay cast]]
The main Preclassic sculptural style from the Maya area is that of [[Izapa]], a large settlement on the Pacific coast where many stelas and (frog-shaped) altars were found showing motifs also present in [[Olmec]] art.&lt;ref&gt;Guernsey 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The stelas, mostly without inscriptions, often show mythological and narrative subjects, some of which appear to relate to the Twin myth of the [[Popol Vuh]]. Nonetheless, it remains uncertain if the inhabitants of Izapa were ethnically Mayan. For the Classic Period of the Mayas, the following major classes of stone sculpture may be distinguished.

*'''Stelas'''. These are large, elongated stone slabs usually covered with carvings and inscriptions, and often accompanied by round altars. Typical of the Classical period, most of them depict the rulers of the cities they were located in, often disguised as gods. Although the rulers' faces, particularly during the later Classic Period, are naturalistic in style, they usually do not show individual traits; but there are notable exceptions to this rule (e.g., [[Piedras Negras (Maya site)|Piedras Negras]], stela 35). The most famous stelas are from [[Copan]] and nearby [[Quirigua]]. These are outstanding for their intricateness of detail, those of Quirigua also for sheer height (stela E measuring over 7 metres above ground level and 3 below). Both the Copan and [[Tonina]] stelas approach sculptures in the round. From [[Palenque]], otherwise a true Maya capital of the arts, no significant stelae have been preserved.
*'''[[lintel (architecture)|Lintels]]''', spanning doorways or jambs. Particularly [[Yaxchilan]] is renowned for its long series of lintels in deep relief, some of the most famous of which show meetings with [[Maya religion|ancestors]] or, perhaps, local deities.&lt;ref&gt;Tate 1992&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Panels and tablets''', set in the walls and piers of buildings and the sides of platforms. Particularly [[Palenque]] is famous for the large tablets adorning the inner sanctuaries of the Cross Group temples, and for refined masterworks such as the 'Palace Tablet', the 'Tablet of the Slaves', and the multi-figure panels of the temple XIX and XXI platforms.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart and Stuart 2008&lt;/ref&gt; King [[Pakal]]'s carved sarcophagus lid - without equal in other Maya kingdoms - might also be included here.
*'''Relief columns''' flanking doorways in public buildings from the [[Puuc]] region (northwestern Yucatan) and similar in decoration to stelas.&lt;ref&gt;Mayer 1981&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Altars''', rounded or rectangular, sometimes resting on three or four boulder-like legs. They may be wholly or partly figurative (e.g., Copan turtle altar) or have a relief image on top, sometimes consisting of a single ''[[Ajaw|Ahau]]'' day sign (Caracol, Tonina).&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000: 89&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Zoomorphs''', or large boulders sculpted to resemble living creatures and covered with highly complicated relief ornamentation. Zoomorphs seem to be restricted to the kingdom of [[Quirigua]] during the Late Classic period&lt;ref&gt;Looper 2003: 172-178, 186-192&lt;/ref&gt; and may have functioned as altars.
*'''Ball court markers''', or rounded relief carvings placed in the central axis of the floors of ball courts (such as those of Copan, [[Chinkultic]], Tonina), and usually showing royal ball game scenes. 
*'''Monumental stairs''', most famously the giant hieroglyphic stairway of Copan. The hewn stone blocks of hieroglyphic stairways together constitute an extensive text. Stairways can also be decorated with a great variety of scenes ([[La Corona]]), particularly the ball game. Sometimes, the ball game becomes the stairs' chief theme ([[Yaxchilan]]), with a captive depicted inside the ball, or, elsewhere ([[Tonina]]), a full-figure captive stretched out along the step.
*'''Thrones''', with a broad, square seat, and a back sometimes iconically shaped like the wall of a cave, and worked open to show human figures. Examples from Palenque and Copan have supports showing cosmologic carriers ([[Bacab]]s, [[Chaak]]s).
*'''Stone sculpture in the round''' is especially known from Copan and Toniná. It is represented by statuary, such as a seated Copan scribe as well as captive figures and small stelas from Toniná; by certain figurative architectural elements, such as the twenty maize deities from the façade of Copan Temple 22;&lt;ref&gt;Schwerin 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and by giant sculptures such as the symmetrically-positioned jaguars and simian musicians of Copán, that were integral parts of architectural design.

&lt;gallery widths="170px" heights="170px"&gt;

Yaxchilan Lintel 24.jpg|[[Yaxchilan]] lintel 24, king holding torch and queen letting blood, 723–726 CE ([[British Museum]])

Maya Presentation of Captives Kimbell.jpg|Yaxchilan lintel, war chief presenting captives to  the king, 783 CE ([[Kimbell Art Museum]])

Column, Costumed Figure MET DP250922-Gallery358.jpg|Relief column, Late Classic ([[Metropolitan Museum of Art]])

Piedrasnegrastrono.jpg|Piedras Negras throne 1, with heads restored, Late Classic (Museo Nacional de Antropología e Historia de Guatemala)

Itzamna e Ixchel.JPG|Back of throne, Late Classic ([[Museo Amparo]])

Monument 151 de Tonina, prisonnier, exposition "Mayas", Musée du Quai Branly, Paris.jpg|[[Tonina]] monument 151, bound prisoner, Classic
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Wood carving==
[[File:Mirror-Bearer MET DT1254.jpg|thumb|upright|250px|Possible mirror bearer; 6th century ([[Metropolitan Museum of Art]])]]
It is believed that carvings in wood were once extremely common, but only a few examples have survived. Most 16th-century wood carvings, considered objects of idolatry, were destroyed by the Spanish colonial authorities. The most important Classic examples consist of intricately worked lintels, mostly from the main [[Tikal]] pyramid sanctuaries,&lt;ref&gt;W.R. Coe et al. 1961&lt;/ref&gt; with one specimen from nearby [[El Zotz]]. The Tikal wood reliefs, each consisting of several beams, and dating to the 8th century, show a king on his seat with a protector figure looming large behind, in the form of a Teotihuacan-style 'war serpent' (Temple I lintel 2), a jaguar (Temple I lintel 3), or a human impersonator of the [[Maya jaguar gods|jaguar god of terrestrial fire]] (Temple IV lintel 2). Other Tikal lintels depict an obese king wearing a jaguar dress and standing in front of his seat (Temple III lintel 2); and most famously, a victorious king, dressed as an astral death god, and standing on a palanquin underneath an arching feathered serpent ([[Tikal Temple IV|Temple IV lintel 3]]). A rare utility object is a tiny lidded box from [[Tortuguero (Maya site)|Tortuguero]] with a hieroglyphic text all around it. Free sculpture in wood, dating back to the 6th century, is represented by a dignified seated man possibly functioning as a mirror bearer.

==Stucco modeling==
[[Image:PyramideDesMasquesKohunlich.jpg|thumb|left|400px|Stucco mask panels, Early Classic, Kohunlich]]
[[Image:K'inich Janaab Pakal I v2.jpg|thumb|right|120px|Stucco portrait of K'inich Janaab Pakal I, 615–683 CE ([[National Museum of Anthropology (Mexico)]] ]]
At least since Late Preclassic times, modeled and painted stucco plaster covered the floors and buildings of the town centers and provided the setting for their stone sculptures. Often, large mask panels with the plastered heads of deities in high relief (particularly those of sun, rain, and earth) are found attached to the sloping retaining walls of temple platforms flanking stairs (e.g., [[Kohunlich]]). Stucco modeling and relief work can also cover the entire building, as shown by Temple 16 of [[Copan]], in its 6th-century form (known as 'Rosalila'). Dedicated to the first king, [[Yax K'uk' Mo']], this early temple has preserved plastered and painted facades. The stuccoed friezes, walls, piers, and roof combs of the Late Preclassic and Classic periods show varying and sometimes symbolically complicated decorative programs.
 
Several solutions for dividing up and ordering the stuccoed surfaces of buildings were applied, serialization being one of them. The Early Classic walls of the 'Temple of the [[Maya jaguar gods#The Jaguar God of Terrestrial Fire and War ('Night Sun')|Night Sun]]' in [[El Zotz]] consist of a series of subtly varied deity mask panels, whereas the frieze of a [[Balamku]] palace, also from the Early Classic, originally had a series of four rulers enthroned above the open ophidian mouths of four different animals (a toad among them) associated with symbolic mountains. Conversely, friezes may be centered on a single ruler again sitting on a symbolic (maize) mountain, such as a frieze from [[Holmul]], with two feathered serpents emanating from below the ruler's seat, and another one from [[Xultun]], on which the ruler carries a large ceremonial bar with emerging jaguar-like figures.&lt;ref&gt;newmedia.ufm.edu/gsm/index.php/Saturnoxultun&lt;/ref&gt; An Early-Classic temple frieze from Placeres, Quintana Roo, has the large mask panel of a young lord or deity in the middle, with two lateral [[Mam (Maya mythology)|'Grandfather']] deities extending their arms.

Often, a frieze is divided into compartments. Late Preclassic friezes of [[El Mirador]], for example, show the intervening spaces of an undulating serpent's body filled out with aquatic birds, and the sections of an aquatic band with swimming figures.&lt;ref&gt;Doyle and Houston 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, a Classic palace frieze in [[Acanceh]] is divided into panels holding different animal figures&lt;ref&gt;V.E. Miller 1991&lt;/ref&gt; reminiscent of [[wayob]], while a wall in [[Tonina]] has lozenge-shaped fields suggesting a scaffold and presenting continuous narrative scenes that relate to human sacrifice.&lt;ref&gt;see Yadeun 1993:108-115&lt;/ref&gt;

Plastered roof combs are similar to some of the friezes above in that they usually show large representations of rulers, who may again be seated on a symbolic mountain, and also, as on Palenque's Temple of the Sun, set within a cosmological framework. Further examples of Classic stucco modeling include the piers of the Palenque Palace, embellished with a series of lords and ladies in ritual dress, and the 'baroque', Late-Classic [[Chenes]]-style stucco entrance, beset with naturalistic human figures, on the Acropolis (Str. 1) of [[Ek' Balam]].

Unique in Mesoamerica, Classic Period stucco modeling includes realistic portraiture of a quality equalling that of Roman ancestral portraits, with the lofty stucco heads of Palenque rulers and portraits of dignitaries from [[Tonina]] as outstanding examples. The modeling recalls that of certain Jaina ceramic statuettes. Some, but not all, of these portrait heads were once part of life-size stucco figures adorning temple crests.&lt;ref&gt;Martin and Grube 2000: 168&lt;/ref&gt; In the same way, one finds stucco glyphs that were once a part of stuccoed texts.

==Mural painting==
[[File:Bonampak, Temple of the Murals, musicians (14179847567).jpg|thumbnail|left|400px|Bonampak mural, room 1, east wall: Musicians]]
[[File:SBmural.jpg|thumb|upright|200px|San Bartolo mural: The king as Hunahpu]]
Although, due to the humid climate of [[Central America]], relatively few Mayan paintings have survived to the present day integrally, important remnants have been found in nearly all major court residences. This is especially the case in substructures, hidden under later architectural additions. Mural paintings may show more or less repetitive motifs, such as the subtly varied flower symbols on walls of House E of the Palenque Palace; scenes of daily life, as in one of the buildings surrounding the central square of [[Calakmul]] and in a palace of Chilonche; or ritual scenes involving deities, as in the Post-Classic temple murals of Yucatán's and Belize's east coast ([[Tancah]], [[Tulum]], Santa Rita).&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1982; Gann 1900&lt;/ref&gt;

They may also evince a more narrative character, usually with hieroglyphic captions present. The colourful [[Bonampak]] murals, for example, dating from 790 AD, and extending over the walls and vaults of three adjacent rooms, show spectacular scenes of nobility, battle and sacrifice, as well as a group of ritual impersonators in the midst of a file of [[Maya music|musicians]].&lt;ref&gt;M.E. Miller 1986; M.E. Miller and Brittenham 2013&lt;/ref&gt; At [[San Bartolo (Maya site)|San Bartolo]], murals dating from 100 BCE relate to the myths of the [[Maya maize god]] and the hero twin [[Hunahpu]], and depict a double inthronization; antedating the Classic Period by several centuries, the style is already fully developed, with colours being subtle and muted as compared to those of Bonampak or Calakmul.&lt;ref&gt;Saturno et al. 2005; Taube et al. 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Outside the Mayan area, in a ward of East-Central Mexican [[Cacaxtla]], murals painted in a predominantly Classic Mayan style, with often stark colors, have been found, such as a savage battle scene extending over 20 meters; two figures of Mayan lords standing on serpents; and an irrigated maize and cacao field visited by [[God L|the Maya merchant deity]].&lt;ref&gt;Lozoff Brittenham and Uriarte 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

Wall painting also occurs on vault capstones, in tombs (e.g., [[Río Azul]]), and in caves (e.g., [[Naj Tunich]]),&lt;ref&gt;Stone 1995&lt;/ref&gt; usually executed in black on a whitened surface, at times with the additional use of red paint. Yucatec vault capstones often show a depiction of the enthroned [[god K|lightning deity]] (e.g., [[Ek' Balam]]).

A bright turquoise blue colour - '[[Maya Blue]]' - has survived through the centuries due to its unique chemical characteristics; this color is present in [[Bonampak]], [[Cacaxtla]], Jaina, [[El Tajín]], and even in some Colonial Convents. The use of Maya Blue survived until the 16th century, when the technique was lost.&lt;ref&gt;Reyes-Valerio 1993; Houston et al. 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writing and bookmaking==
{{main|Maya script|Maya codices}}
[[File:Mexico - Museo de antropologia - Livre maya.JPG|thumb|Madrid Codex]]
The Maya writing system consists of about 1000 distinct characters or hieroglyphs ('glyphs'), and like many ancient writing systems is a mixture of syllabic signs and [[logogram]]s. This script was in use from the 3rd century BCE until shortly after the Spanish conquest in the 16th century. As of now (2019), a considerable proportion of the characters has a reading, but their meaning and configuration as a text is not always understood. The books were folded and consisted of bark paper or leather leaves with an adhesive stucco layer on which to write; they were protected by jaguar skin covers or, perhaps, wooden boards.&lt;ref&gt;Coe and Kerr 1997&lt;/ref&gt; Since every diviner probably needed a book, there must have existed large numbers of them. 

Today, three [[Maya codices|Maya books]], all from the Post-Classic period, are still in existence: the [[Dresden Codex|Dresden]], [[Paris Codex|Paris]], and [[Madrid Codex (Maya)|Madrid]] codices. A fourth book, the [[Grolier Codex|Grolier]], is Maya-[[Toltec]] rather than Maya; apart from calendar signs, it has no text. Fragmentary and of very poor workmanship, it shows many anomalies, reason for which its authenticity has long remained in  doubt.&lt;ref&gt;Love 2017&lt;/ref&gt; These books are largely of a divinatory and priestly nature, containing almanacs, astrological tables, and ritual programs; the Paris Codex also includes [[Katun (Maya calendar)|katun]]-prophecies. Great attention was paid to a harmonious balance of texts and (partly coloured) illustrations.

Besides the codical glyphs, there existed a cursive script of an often dynamic character, found in wall-paintings and on ceramics, and imitated in stone on panels from Palenque (such as the 'Tablet of the 96 glyphs'). Often, written captions are enclosed in square 'boxes' of various shapes within the representation. Wall paintings may also entirely consist of texts ([[Ek' Balam]], [[Naj Tunich]]), or, more rarely, contain astrological computations ([[Xultun]]); sometimes, written on a white stuccoed surface, and executed with particular care and elegance, these texts are like enlargements of book pages.
 
Hieroglyphs are ubiquitous and were written on every available surface, including the human body. The glyphs themselves are highly detailed, and particularly the [[logogram]]s are deceivingly realistic. As a matter of fact, from an art-historical point of view, they should also be viewed as art motifs, and ''vice versa''.&lt;ref name="Stone and Zender 2011"/&gt; Sculptors at Copan and Quirigua have consequently felt free to convert hieroglyphic elements and calendrical signs into animated, dramatic miniature scenes ('full figure glyphs').

==Ceramics and 'ceramic codex'==
{{main|Maya ceramics}}
[[File:Codex vase Collection Henry Law 154.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Codex style cylinder vessel, courtly ritual]]
[[File:Maya Classic Clay Figurine Called "The Cowboy," Jaina Island, Campeche.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Jaina, nobleman]]
Unlike utility ceramics found in such large numbers among the debris of archaeological sites, most of the decorated pottery (cylinder vessels, lidded dishes, vases, bowls) once was '[[social currency]]' among the Maya nobility, and, preserved as heirlooms, also accompanied the nobles into their graves.&lt;ref&gt;Reents-Budet 1994: 72ff&lt;/ref&gt; The aristocratic tradition of gift-giving feasts&lt;ref&gt;Tozzer 1941: 92&lt;/ref&gt; and ceremonial visits, and the emulation that inevitably went with these exchanges, goes a long way towards explaining the high level of artistry reached in Classical times.

Made without a potter's wheel, decorated pottery was delicately painted, carved into relief, incised, or - chiefly during the Early Classic period - made with the Teotihuacan [[fresco]] technique of applying paint to a wet clay surface. The precious objects were manufactured in numerous workshops distributed over the Mayan kingdoms, some of the most famous being associated with the [[Chama (Maya site)|'Chama-style']], the [[Holmul#Holmul-style|'Holmul-style']], the so-called [[Motul de San Jose#Ik style ceramics|'Ik-style']]&lt;ref&gt;Just 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and, for carved pottery, the 'Chochola-style.'&lt;ref&gt;Tate 1985&lt;/ref&gt;
  
Vase decoration shows great variation, including palace scenes, courtly ritual, mythology, divinatory glyphs, and even dynastical texts taken from chronicles, and plays a major role in reconstructing Classical Maya life and beliefs. Ceramic scenes and texts painted in black and red on a white underground, the equivalents of pages from the lost folding books, are referred to as being in '[[Codex Style]]' (e.g., the so-called [[Princeton Vase]]). The hieroglyphical and pictural overlap with the three extant books is (at least up to now) relatively small.

Sculptural ceramic art includes the lids of Early Classic bowls mounted by human or animal figures; some of these bowls, burnished black, are among the most distinguished Mayan works of art ever created. 

Ceramic sculpture also includes [[censer|incense burners]] and burial urns. Best known are the profusely decorated Classic burners from the kingdom of Palenque, which have the modeled face of a deity or of a king attached to an elongated hollow tube. The deity most frequently depicted, the [[Maya jaguar gods|jaguar deity of terrestrial fire]], also adorns large Classic burial urns from the Guatemalan department of El Quiché.&lt;ref&gt;McCampbell 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The elaborate Post-Classic, mold-made effigy incense burners especially associated with [[Mayapan]] represent standing deities (or priestly deity impersonators) often carrying offerings.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 1957; Milbrath 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

Finally, figurines, often mold-made, and of an amazing liveliness and realism, constitute a minor but highly informative genre. Apart from deities, [[Maya religion#Animal persons|animal persons]], rulers and dwarfs, they show many other characters as well as scenes taken from daily life. Some of these figurines are ocarinas and may have been used in rituals. The most impressive examples stem from [[Jaina Island]].

&lt;gallery widths="170px" heights="170px"&gt;
Codex-Style Vase with Mythological Scene MET DP-579-002.jpg|Codex-style vase with mythological scene, 7th–8th century (Metropolitan Museum of Art)

Vessel, Throne Scene MET DT4514.jpg|Vessel with throne scene, Chamá style, late 7th–8th century (Metropolitan Museum of Art)

Vase - Classic Maya - Ethnological Museum, Berlin - DSC00742.JPG|Relief vase with head of aquatic serpent, Chocholá style, Yucatan, Late Classic (Ethnologisches Museum, Berlin)

Tripod Bird Bowl MET DT4867.jpg|Tripod bowl with heron lid, Early Classic (Metropolitan Museum of Art)

Mayan - Incensario (Incense Burner) - Walters 482770.jpg|Lower part of incense burner, Palenque style, Late Classic (Walters Art Museum)

Mayan - Maya Polychrome Lidded Urn with Seated Figure - Walters 482793.jpg|Urn with jaguar deity lid, Late Classic (Walters Art Museum)

Costumed Figure MET 1979.206.953 a.jpeg|Costumed figure, 7th–8th century (Metropolitan Museum of Art) 

Young Corn God MET DT9946.jpg|Bust of young nobleman in the heart of a flower, Jaina style, 8th century (Metropolitan Museum of Art)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Precious stone and other sculpted materials==
[[File:Palenque - Pakal - Grabbeigabe.jpg|thumb|190px|right|Jade belt assemblage with celt pendants, from the tomb of king [[Pakal]], Palenque]]
[[File:Placa de jade, Nebaj, museu Nacional d'Arqueologia i Etnologia, Guatemala.jpg|thumb|350px|left|Jade plaque from Nebaj, showing king amidst maize stalks]]

It is remarkable that the Maya, who had no metal tools, created many objects from a very thick and dense material, jade ([[jadeite]]), particularly all sorts of (royal) dress elements, such as [[Maya belt plaques|belt plaques]] - or celts - ear spools, pendants, and also masks. Celts (i.e., flat, celt-shaped ornaments) were sometimes engraved with a stela-like representation of the king (e.g., the Early-Classic 'Leyden Plate'). The best-known example of a mask is probably the death mask of the Palenque king [[Pakal]], covered with irregularly-shaped jade plaques and having eyes made from [[Nacre|mother-of-pearl]] and obsidian; another death mask, belonging to a Palenque queen, consists of malachite plaques. Similarly, certain cylindrical vases from Tikal have an outer layer of square jade discs. Many stone carvings had jade inlays.

Among other sculpted and engraved materials are flint, shell, and bone, often found in caches and burials. The so-called '[[eccentric flint]]s' are ceremonial objects of uncertain use, in their most elaborate forms of elongated shape with usually various heads extending on one or both sides, sometimes those of the [[God K|lightning deity]], but more often of an anthropomorphic lightning probably representing the [[Maya maize god|Tonsured Maize God]].&lt;ref&gt;Agurcia, Sheets, Taube 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Shell was worked into disks and other decorative elements showing human, possibly ancestral heads and deities; [[conch]] trumpets were similarly decorated.&lt;ref&gt;Finamore and Houston 2010: 124-131&lt;/ref&gt; Human and animal bones were decorated with incised symbols and scenes. A collection of small and modified, tubular bones from an 8th-century royal burial under [[Tikal Temple I]] contains some of the most subtle engravings known from the Maya, including several scenes with the [[Maya maize god|Tonsured maize god]] in a canoe.&lt;ref&gt;Trik 1963&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery widths="170px" heights="170px"&gt;
Flower-Shaped Earflares LACMA M.2007.85.1-.2.jpg|Flower-shaped jadeite earflares, Late Classic ([[Los Angeles County Museum of Art]])

Deity Face Pendant MET DP148420.jpg|Jadeite deity face pendant, 7th–8th century (Metropolitan Museum of Art)

Deity Figure MET h2 1979.206.1069.jpg|Jadeite rain deity with arms in royal posture, Early Classic (Metropolitan Museum of Art)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Applied arts and body decoration==
{{see also|Maya textiles}}
Textiles from the Classic period, made of cotton, have not survived, but Maya art provides detailed information about their appearance and, to a lesser extent, their social function.&lt;ref&gt;Looper 2000&lt;/ref&gt; They include delicate fabrics used as wrappings, curtains and canopies furnishing palaces, and garments. Among the dyeing techniques may have been [[ikat]]. Daily costume depended on social standing. Noblewomen usually wore long dresses, noblemen girdles and breechcloths, leaving legs and upper body more or less bare, unless jackets or mantles were worn. Both men and women could wear turbans. Costumes worn on ceremonial occasions and during the many festivities were highly expressive and exuberant; animal headdresses were common. The most elaborate costume was the formal apparel of the king, as depicted on the royal stelae, with numerous elements of symbolic meaning.&lt;ref&gt;E.g., Dillon and Christensen 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Wickerwork, only known from incidental depictions in sculptural and ceramic art,&lt;ref&gt;Reents-Budet 1994: 331&lt;/ref&gt; must once have been ubiquitous; the well-known ''pop'' ('mat') motif testifies to its importance.&lt;ref&gt;Robicsek 1975&lt;/ref&gt;

Body decorations often consisted of painted patterns on face and body, but could also be of a permanent character marking status and age differences. The latter type included artificial deformation of the skull, filing and incrustation of the teeth, and tattooing of the face.&lt;ref&gt;Houston et al. 2006: 18-25&lt;/ref&gt;

==Museum collections==
[[File:Nationalmuseum für Archäologie und Ethnologie, Guatemala-20.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología]], in [[Guatemala City]]]]
There are a great many museums across the world with Maya artifacts in their collections. The [[Foundation for the Advancement of Mesoamerican Studies]] lists over 250 museums in its Maya Museum database,&lt;ref&gt;Ros.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[European Association of Mayanists]] lists just under 50 museums in Europe alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wayeb.org/resources-links/museums-collections/|title=Museums &amp; Collections - Wayeb|author=|date=|website=wayeb.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[Mexico City]], the [[National Museum of Anthropology (Mexico)|Museo Nacional de Antropología]] contains an especially large selection of Maya artifacts.&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p451"&gt;Wagner 2011, p. 451.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of regional museums in Mexico hold important collections, including [[Museo Amparo]] in Puebla, with its beautiful throne back from Chiapas, the [[Museo de las Estelas "Román Piña Chan"]] in [[Campeche, Campeche|Campeche]],&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p450"/&gt; the [[Museo Regional de Yucatán "Palacio Cantón"]] in [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]], and the [[Museo Regional de Antropología "Carlos Pellicer Camera"]] in [[Villahermosa]], Tabasco.&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p452"&gt;Wagner 2011, p. 452.&lt;/ref&gt; The most important museum collections in Guatemala are those of the [[Museo Popol Vuh]] and the [[Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología]], both in [[Guatemala City]].&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p451"/&gt; 

In the United States, almost every major art museum has a collection of Maya artifacts. Among these museums are the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in [[New York City|New York]], the [[Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology]] in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]], [[Massachusetts]], and the [[University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology]].The [[Field Museum of Natural History]] in [[Chicago]] contains a notable selection of Maya ceramics,&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p450"/&gt; while the [[Cleveland Museum of Art]] in [[Ohio]] has one of the most extensive Maya collections in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p451"/&gt; 

In Europe, the [[British Museum]] in [[London]] exhibits a series of famous Yaxchilan lintels, and the [[Museum of Cultures (Basel)|Museum der Kulturen]] in [[Basel]], [[Switzerland]], a number of wooden lintels from Tikal. The [[Ethnological Museum of Berlin|Ethnologisches Museum]] in [[Berlin]] holds a broad selection of Maya artifacts. In [[Belgium]], the [[Royal Museums of Art and History|Musées royaux d'art et d'histoire]] in [[Brussels]] houses an important collection.&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p450"&gt;Wagner 2011, p. 450.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Museum of the Americas (Madrid)|Museo de América]] in [[Madrid]] hosts a large selection of artifacts from Palenque; it is also home to the Madrid Codex.&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p452"/&gt; Other notable European museums are the [[National Museum of Ethnology (Netherlands)|Rijksmuseum voor Volkenkunde]] in [[Leiden]], [[Netherlands]], home to the Leyden Plate, and the [[Rietberg Museum]] in [[Zürich]], Switzerland.&lt;ref name="Wagner2011p452"/&gt;

==Maya performative arts==
* [[Maya dance]]
* [[Maya dance drama]]
* [[Maya music]]

==See also==
* [[Ancient Maya graffiti]]
* [[Pre-Columbian art]]
* [[Painting in the Americas before Colonization]]
* [[Visual arts by indigenous peoples of the Americas]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
* {{cite book |author=Agurcia Fasquelle, Ricardo, Payson Sheets, and Karl Andreas Taube|year=2016|title=Protecting Sacred Space. Rosalila's Eccentric Chert Cache at Copan and Eccentrics among the Classic Maya|location=San Francisco|publisher=Precolumbia Mesoweb Press|series=Monograph 2}}
* Coe, Michael D., ''The Maya Scribe and His World''. New York: The Grolier Club 1973.
* Coe, Michael D., ''Classic Maya Pottery from Dumbarton Oaks''. Washington: Trustees of Harvard University 1975. 
* Coe, Michael D., ''Lords of the Underworld; Masterpieces of Classic Maya Ceramics''. New Jersey: Princeton University Press 1978.
* Coe, Michael D., ''Old Gods and Young Heroes; The Pearlman Collection of Maya Ceramics''. Jerusalem: The Israel Museum 1982.
* Coe, Michael D., and Justin Kerr, ''The Art of the Maya Scribe''. Thames and Hudson 1997.
* Coe, William R., Edwin M. Shook, and Linton Satterthwaite, 'The Carved Wooden Lintels of Tikal'. Tikal Report No. 6, ''Tikal Reports Numbers 5-10'', Museum Monographs, The University Museum, U. of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia 1961.
* Dillon, Brian D., and Wes Christensen, 'The Maya Jade Skull Bead: 700 Years as Military Insignia?'. In Brian D. Dillon and Matthew A. Boxt, ''Archaeology without Limits. Papers in Honor of Clement W. Meighan,'' pp.&amp;nbsp;369–388. Lancaster: Labyrinthos 2005.
* Doyle, James, and Stephen Houston, 'A Watery Tableau at El Mirador, Guatemala'. In ''Maya Decipherment'', April 9, 2012 (decipherment.wordpress.com.).
* Finamore, Daniel, and Stephen D. Houston, ''The Fiery Pool: The Maya and the Mythic Sea''. Peabody Essex Museum 2010. 
* Gann, Thomas, ''Mounds in Northern Honduras''. 19th Annual Report, Smithsonian Institution, Washington 1900.
* Gendrop, Paul, Los estilos Río Bec, Chenes y Puuc en la arquitectura maya. Mexico: UNAM (División de Estudios de Posgrado, Facultad de Arquitectura) 1983.
* Guernsey, Julia, ''Ritual and Power in Stone: The Performance of Rulership in Mesoamerican Izapan Style Art''. Austin: University of Texas Press 2006.
* Houston, Stephen, et al., ''The Memory of Bones. Body, Being, and Experience among the Classic Maya''. Austin: U. of Texas Press 2006.
* Houston, Stephen, et al., ''Veiled Brightness. A History of Ancient Maya Color''. Austin: U.of Texas Press 2009.
* Just, Bryan R., ''Dancing into Dreams. Maya Vase Painting of the Ik' Kingdom''. Yale University Press 2012.
* Kubler, George, ''Studies in Classic Maya Iconography''. Memoirs of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 28. New Haven: Connecticut 1969.
* Looper, Matthew, ''Gifts of the Moon: Huipil Designs of the Ancient Maya''. San Diego Museum Papers 38. San Diego: San Diego Museum of Man, 2000.
* Looper, Mathhew, ''Lightning Warrior. Maya Art and Kingship at Quirigua''. Austin: U. of Texas Press 2003.
* Love, Bruce, 'Authenticity of the Grolier Codex remains in doubt'. ''Mexicon'' Vol. XXXIX Nr. 4 (2017): 88-95.
* Lozoff Brittenham, Claudia, and María Teresa Uriarte, ''The Murals of Cacaxtla: The Power of Painting in Ancient Central Mexico.'' Austin: U. of Texas Press 2015. 
* Martin, Simon, and Nicolas Grube, ''Chronicle of the Maya Kings and Queens''. Thames&amp;Hudson 2000.
* Maudslay, A.P., ''Biologia Centrali-Americana''. Text and 4 Vols. of Illustrations. London 1889-1902.*
* Mayer, Karl Herbert, ''Classic Maya Relief Columns''. Acoma Books, Ramona, California 1981.
* McCampbell, Kathleen G., ''Highland Maya Effigy Funerary Urns. A Study of Genre, Iconography, and Function.'' MA Thesis, Florida State University 2010 (online). 
* Milbrath, Susan, ''Mayapán’s Effigy Censers: Iconography, Context, and External Connections''. www.famsi.org/reports (2007)
* Miller, Arthur G., ''On the Edge of the Sea. Mural Painting at Tancah-Tulum, Quintana Roo, Mexico''. Washington DC: Dumbarton Oaks 1982.
* Miller, M.E., 'The History of the Study of Maya Vase Painting'. In ''Maya Vase Book'' Vol. 1, ed. J. Kerr, New York: 128-145.
* Miller, M.E., and Megan O'Neil, ''Maya Art and Architecture''. New York and London: Thames and Hudson 2014.
* Miller, M.E., ''The Murals of Bonampak''. Princeton U.P. 1986.
* Miller, M.E., and Claudia Brittenham, ''The Spectacle of the Late Maya Court. Reflections on the Murals of Bonampak''. Austin: Texas U.P. 2013
* Miller, Mary, and Simon Martin, ''Courtly Art of the Ancient Maya''. Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco. Thames and Hudson 2004.
* Miller, Mary, and Karl Taube, ''The Gods and Symbols of Ancient Mexico and the Maya. An Illustrated Dictionary of Mesoamerican Religion.'' London: Thames and Hudson.
* Miller, Virginia E., ''The Frieze of the Palace of the Stuccoes, Acanceh, Yucatan, Mexico''. Studies in Pre-Columbian Art &amp; Archaeology, 39. Washington DC: Dumbarton Oaks 1991.
* O'Neil, Megan, ''Engaging Ancient Maya Sculpture at Piedras Negras, Guatemala''. Norman: U. of Oklahoma Press 2012.
* Proskouriakoff, Tatiana, ''A Study of Classic Maya Sculpture''. Carnegie Institute of Washington Publication No. 593, 1950
* Reents-Budet, Doreen, ''Painting the Maya Universe: Royal Ceramics of the Classic Period''. Duke U.P. 1994.
* Reyes-Valerio, Constantino, ''De Bonampak al Templo Mayor, Historia del Azul Maya en Mesoamerica''. Siglo XXI Editores, 1993.
* Robicsek, Francis, ''A study in Maya art and history : the mat symbol''. New York: Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation, 1975.
* Robicsek, Francis, and Donald Hales, ''The Maya Book of the Dead: The Corpus of Codex Style Ceramics of the Late Classic period''. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press 1981.
* {{cite web |author=Ros, Narin |title=Maya Museum Database |url=http://www.famsi.org/research/museum_database.html |publisher=Foundation for the Advancement of Mesoamerican Studies |accessdate=2015-06-08 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140708162851/http://www.famsi.org/research/museum_database.html |archivedate=2014-07-08}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20150608160339/http://research.famsi.org/museum_list.php?name=&amp;city=&amp;state=&amp;country=&amp;focus=&amp;x=13&amp;y=19 Full list from FAMSI] archived from [http://research.famsi.org/museum_list.php?name=&amp;city=&amp;state=&amp;country=&amp;focus=&amp;x=13&amp;y=19 the original] on 2015-06-08.
* Saturno, William; David Stuart and Karl Taube (2005). The Murals of San Bartolo, El Petén, Guatemala, Part I: The North Wall. ''Ancient America'' 7.
* Schele, Linda, and Mary Ellen Miller, ''The Blood of Kings. Dynasty and Ritual in Maya Art''. New York: George Braziller, Inc., in association with the Kimbell Art Museum.
* Schwerin, Jennifer von, 'The sacred mountain in social context. Symbolism and history in Maya Architecture: Temple 22 at Copan, Honduras.' ''Ancient Mesoamerica'' 22(2), September 2011: 271-300.
* Simmons Clancy, Flora, ''The Monuments of Piedras Negras, an Ancient Maya City''. Albuquerque: U. of New Mexico Press 2009.
* Spinden, Herbert, ''A Study of Maya Art: Its Subject Matter &amp; Historical Development''. New York: Dover Publ., 1975.
* Stierlin, Henri, ''Living Architecture: Mayan''. Architecture of the World, 10. Benedikt Taschen Verlag, 1994.
* Stone, Andrea J., ''Images from the Underworld. Naj Tunich and the Tradition of Maya Cave Painting''. 1995. {{ISBN|978-0-292-75552-9}}
* Stone, Andrea, and Marc Zender, ''Reading Maya Art: A Hieroglyphic Guide to Ancient Maya Painting and Sculpture''. Thames and Hudson 2011.
* Stuart, David, and George Stuart, ''Palenque, Eternal City of the Maya''. Thames and Hudson 2008.
* Tate, Carolyn E., The Carved Ceramics Called Chochola. In ''5th Palenque Round Table'', PARI, San Francisco 1985: 122-133. 
* Tate, Carolyn E., ''Yaxchilan: The Design of a Maya Ceremonial City''. Austin: U. of Texas Press 1992.
* Taube, Karl; David Stuart, William Saturno and Heather Hurst (2010). The Murals of San Bartolo, El Petén, Guatemala, Part 2: The West Wall. ''Ancient America'' 10.
* Thompson, J.E.S., Deities portrayed on censers at Mayapan. ''Carnegie Institution of Washington, Current Reports'', No. 40 (July 1957).
* Tozzer, Alfred M., ''Landa's Relación de las cosas de Yucatán. A Translation''. Peabody Museum, Cambridge MA 1941.
* Trik, Aubrey S., 'The Splendid Tomb of Temple I At Tikal, Guatemala'. ''Expedition'' (Fall 1963): 3-18.
* {{cite book |author=Wagner, Elisabeth |chapter=Una Selección de Colecciones y Museos |title=Los Mayas: Una Civilización Milenaria |pages=450–452 |year=2011 |origyear=2006 |publisher=Tandem Verlag GmbH |editor=Nikolai Grube |isbn=978-3-8331-6293-0 |oclc=828120761 |location=Potsdam, Germany |language=Spanish}}
* {{cite web |author=WAYEB |publisher=European Association of Mayanists (WAYEB) |title=Museums &amp; Collections |url=http://www.wayeb.org/resourceslinks/collections.php |accessdate=2015-06-08 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150511132259/http://www.wayeb.org/resourceslinks/collections.php |archivedate=2015-05-11}}
* Wren, Linnea, et al., eds. ''Landscapes of the Itza: Archeology and Art History at Chichen Itza and Neighboring Sites''. Gainesville: University of Florida Press 2018.
* Yadeun, Juan, ''Toniná''. Mexico: El Equilibrista / Madrid: Turner Libros 1993.

==External links==
{{commons category|Maya art}}
* [http://www.nmai.si.edu/searchcollections/results.aspx?regid=11 Maya art, National Museum of the American Indian]
* [http://www.azulmaya.com Azulmaya:Maya Blue Pigment]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071005004644/http://www.authenticmaya.com/maya_art.htm 'Authentic Maya']
* [http://www.mayavase.com/ Kerr Maya Vase Data Base &amp; Precolumbian Portfolio]
* [http://www.pinturamural.esteticas.unam.mx UNAM: Ancient Prehispanic Murals]

{{Clear}}
{{Maya}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Maya Art}}
[[Category:Maya art| ]]
[[Category:Maya Preclassic Period]]
[[Category:Maya Classic Period]]
[[Category:Mesoamerican art]]
[[Category:Pre-Columbian art]]</text>
      <sha1>686tvv4cmp5t1mvygjk790fr09efilu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
