<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Leda and the Swan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18461</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959456635</id>
      <parentid>955990147</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-28T21:41:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>85.212.89.198</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In modern and contemporary art */Added the link to sculptors</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="24825" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{About|the story and its depictions||Leda and the Swan (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:Leda - after Michelangelo Buonarroti.jpg|thumb|320px|right|''Leda and the Swan'', a 16th-century [[Leda and the Swan (Michelangelo)|copy after a lost painting]] by [[Michelangelo]] ([[National Gallery, London]])]]
[[File:Leda and the swan, terracotta Roman oil lamp 1st century AD, Staatliche Antikensammlungen, Munich (8958396304).jpg|thumb|[[Ancient Roman pottery#Lamps|Roman oil lamp]], 1st century AD]] 
'''Leda and the Swan''' is a story and subject in art from [[Greek mythology]] in which the god [[Zeus]], in the form of a [[swan]], seduces (or in some versions, rapes) [[Leda (mythology)|Leda]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Medlicott |first1=R. W. |title=Leda and the Swan—An Analysis of the Theme in Myth and Art |journal=Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry |volume=4 |issue=1 |publisher=Sage Journals |pages=15–23 |language=en |doi=10.3109/00048677009159303 |pmid=4107336 |date=1 March 1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to later Greek mythology, Leda bore [[Helen of Troy|Helen]] and [[Castor and Polydeuces|Polydeuces]], children of Zeus, while at the same time bearing [[Castor and Polydeuces|Castor]] and [[Clytemnestra]], children of her husband [[Tyndareus]], the King of [[Sparta]]. In the [[W. B. Yeats]] version, it is subtly suggested that Clytemnestra, although being the daughter of Tyndareus, has somehow been traumatized by what the swan has done to her mother (see below).  According to many versions of the story, Zeus took the form of a swan and seduced Leda on the same night she slept with her husband King [[Tyndareus]]. In some versions, she laid two eggs from which the children hatched.&lt;ref&gt;The idea that the semen of more than one male might influence pregnancy, a feature in the origin myth of [[Theseus]], is called [[Telegony (pregnancy)|telegony]]; it retained scientific followers until the late nineteenth century.&lt;/ref&gt; In other versions, Helen is a daughter of [[Nemesis (mythology)|Nemesis]], the goddess who personified the disaster that awaited those suffering from the pride of [[Hubris]].

The subject was rarely seen in the large-scale sculpture of antiquity, although a representation of Leda in sculpture has been attributed in modern times to [[Timotheus (sculptor)|Timotheus]] (''compare illustration, below left''); small-scale sculptures survive showing both reclining and standing poses,&lt;ref&gt;Bull p. 167. See for example a marble relief with the Swan, grasping the back of Leda's neck with his beak, excavated in Argos, [[Pelopennese]], Greece, from 50–100 AD [https://www.britishmuseum.org/collectionimages/AN00102/AN00102484_001_l.jpg in the British Museum]; See External links for other examples&lt;/ref&gt; in [[cameo (carving)|cameo]]s and [[engraved gem]]s, rings, and terracotta oil lamps. Thanks to the literary renditions of [[Ovid]] and [[Fabius Planciades Fulgentius|Fulgentius]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fulgentius|first1=Fabuis Planciades|authorlink1=The|title=The Fable of the Swan and Leda|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=73mJIuYfmzEC&amp;pg=PA78|publisher=Ohio State University Press|page=78|isbn=9780814201626|year=1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was a well-known myth through the Middle Ages, but emerged more prominently as a classicizing theme, with [[erotic art|erotic overtones]], in the Italian Renaissance.

==Eroticism==
[[Image:Leda and Zeus (Swan).jpg|thumb|left|230px|''Leda and the Swan'', Roman marble possibly reflecting a lost work by [[Timotheus (sculptor)|Timotheos]]; restored ([[Prado]])]]

The subject undoubtedly owed its sixteenth-century popularity to the paradox that it was considered more acceptable to depict a woman in the act of copulation with a swan than with a man.  The earliest depictions show the pair love-making with some explicitness—more so than in any depictions of a human pair made by artists of high quality in the same period.&lt;ref&gt;Bull p 167&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Leda mosaic crop.jpg|thumb|right|225px|A [[mosaic]] from [[Cyprus]] (c. 3rdC AD)]]The fate of the erotic album ''[[I Modi]]'' some years later shows why this was so. The theme remained a dangerous one in the Renaissance, as the fates of the three best known paintings on the subject demonstrate.  The earliest depictions were all in the more private medium of the [[old master print]], and mostly from Venice.  They were often based on the extremely brief account in the ''Metamorphoses'' of [[Ovid]] (who does not imply a rape), though [[Lorenzo de' Medici]] had both a Roman sarcophagus and an [[engraved gems|antique carved gem]] of the subject, both with reclining Ledas.&lt;ref&gt;Bull p167&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest known explicit Renaissance depiction is one of the many [[woodcut]] illustrations to ''[[Hypnerotomachia Poliphili]]'', a book published in [[Venice]] in 1499.  This shows Leda and the Swan making love with gusto, despite being on top of a triumphal car, being pulled along and surrounded by a considerable crowd.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mitpress2.mit.edu/e-books/HP/hyp166.htm Page 166 – Hypnerotomachia Poliphili&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; An engraving dating to 1503 at the latest, by [[Giovanni Battista Palumba]], also shows the couple in [[coitus]], but in deserted countryside.&lt;ref&gt;[[:File:Palumba leda swan.jpg|Photo of the print]]&lt;/ref&gt; Another engraving, certainly from Venice and attributed by many to [[Giulio Campagnola]], shows a love-making scene, but there Leda's attitude is highly ambiguous.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bodkinprints.co.uk/product.php?id=38 |title=Leda and the Swan |publisher=Bodkin Prints |first=Giulio |last=Campagnola |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130413192242/http://www.bodkinprints.co.uk/product.php?id=38 |archivedate=13 April 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Not a woodcut, as Bull (p169) wrongly says (see Hind BM catalogue, The Illustrated [[Bartsch]] etc); nor is his view of Leda's expression the only one.&lt;/ref&gt; Palumba made another engraving, perhaps in about 1512, presumably influenced by Leonardo's sketches for his earlier composition, showing Leda seated on the ground and playing with her children.&lt;ref&gt;[[:File:Palumba ledafamily.jpg|British Museum copy]]; [http://www.metmuseum.org/special/Poets_Lovers_Heroes/lovers_05_51.623.3.R.asp The Metropolitan Museum of Art – Special Exhibitions: Poets, Lovers, and Heroes in Italian Mythological Prints&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also significant depictions in the smaller decorative arts, also private media. [[Benvenuto Cellini]] made a medallion, now in Vienna, early in his career, and [[Antonio Abondio]] one on the [[obverse]] of a medal celebrating a Roman [[courtesan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nga.gov.au/international/Catalogue/Detail.cfm?IRN=66251&amp;Orient=Verso Abondio, NGA Washington]&lt;/ref&gt;

==In painting==
[[Image:Leda and the Swan 1505-1510.jpg|thumb|right|220px|[[Leda and the Swan (Wilton House)|''Leda and the Swan'']], copy by [[Cesare da Sesto]] after a lost original by [[Leonardo da Vinci|Leonardo]], 1515–1520, Oil on canvas, [[Wilton House]], England.]]
[[File:Correggio.jpg|thumb|left|250px|''Leda and the Swan'' by [[Correggio]]]]
[[Leonardo da Vinci]] began making studies in 1504 for a painting, apparently never executed, of Leda seated on the ground with her children. In 1508 he painted a [[Leda and the Swan (Leonardo)|different composition of the subject]], with a nude standing Leda cuddling the Swan, with the two sets of infant twins (also nude), and their huge broken egg-shells. The original of this is lost, probably deliberately destroyed, and was last recorded in the French royal [[Château de Fontainebleau]] in 1625 by [[Cassiano dal Pozzo]].  However it is known from many copies, of which the earliest are probably the [[Leda and the Swan (Uffizi)|''Spiridon Leda'']], perhaps by a studio assistant and now in the [[Uffizi]],&lt;ref&gt;[[:File:Leda Melzi Uffizi.jpg|image]]; Fossi, Gloria, pp. 402–3, ''Uffizi: art, history, collections'', Giunti Editore Firenze Italy, 2004, {{ISBN|88-09-03676-X}}, 9788809036765 [https://books.google.com/books?id=oNE3ofu8psMC&amp;pg=PA402&amp;dq=Spiridon+Leda&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=kcWYTOuCJoWUjAex24D9Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Spiridon%20Leda&amp;f=false google books]&lt;/ref&gt; and the one at [[Leda and the Swan (Wilton House)|Wilton House]] in the United Kingdom (illustrated).

Also lost, and probably deliberately destroyed, is [[Michelangelo]]'s tempera [[Leda and the Swan (Michelangelo)|painting of the pair]] making love, commissioned in 1529 by [[Alfonso d'Este]] for his palazzo in [[Ferrara]], and taken to France for the royal collection in 1532; it was at [[Château de Fontainebleau|Fontainebleau]] in 1536. Michelangelo's [[cartoon]] for the work—given to his assistant Antonio Mini, who used it for several copies for French patrons before his death in 1533—survived for over a century.  This composition is known from many copies, including an [[:commons:File:Cornelis Bos - Leda and the Swan - WGA2486.jpg|ambitious engraving]] by [[Cornelis Bos]], c. 1563; the marble sculpture by [[Bartolomeo Ammanati]] in the Bargello, Florence; two copies by the young [[Peter Paul Rubens|Rubens]] on his Italian voyage, and the painting after Michelangelo, ca. 1530, in the [[National Gallery, London]].&lt;ref&gt;Elfriede R. Knauer, "Leda." ''Jahrbuch der Berliner Museen 11'' (1969:5–35) illustrates several copies as well as an engraving of a Roman bas-relief and examples of antique engraved gems that seem to have provided Micelangelo's inspiration and gives a full bibliography of Michelangelo's ''Leda''.&lt;/ref&gt; The Michelangelo composition, of about 1530, shows [[Mannerism|Mannerist]] tendencies of elongation and twisted pose (the ''[[figura serpentinata]]'') that were popular at the time. In addition, a sculptural group, similar to the Prado Roman group illustrated, was believed until at least the 19th century to be by Michelangelo.&lt;ref&gt;It belonged to [[John Everett Millais]] and was included in his 2007 [[Tate Britain]] exhibition. Now London, attributed to a 16th-century "follower of Michelangelo".&lt;/ref&gt;

The last very famous Renaissance painting of the subject is [[Antonio da Correggio|Correggio]]'s elaborate composition of c. 1530 (Berlin); this too was damaged whilst in the [[Orléans collection|collection of Philippe II, Duke of Orléans]], the Regent of France in the minority of [[Louis XV]].  His son [[Louis of Bourbon, Duke of Orléans|Louis]], though a great lover of painting, had periodic crises of conscience about his way of life, in one of which he attacked the figure of Leda with a knife. The damage has been repaired, though full restoration to the original condition was not possible.  Both the Leonardo and Michelangelo paintings also disappeared when in the collection of the French Royal Family, and are believed to have been destroyed by more moralistic widows or successors of their owners.&lt;ref&gt;Bull 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

There were many other depictions in the Renaissance, including cycles of book illustrations to Ovid, but most were derivative of the compositions mentioned above.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/zino/ho_1982.60.11.htm Bacchiacca (Francesco d'Ubertino): Leda and the Swan | Work of Art | Timeline of Art History | The Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The subject remained largely confined to Italy, and sometimes France – Northern versions are rare.&lt;ref&gt;Bull 170.&lt;/ref&gt; After something of a hiatus in the 18th and early 19th centuries (apart from a very sensuous [[François Boucher|Boucher]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bc.edu/bc_org/avp/cas/his/CoreArt/art/anc_bou_leda.html Leda and the Swan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;), Leda and the Swan became again a popular motif in the later 19th and 20th centuries, with many [[Symbolist]] and [[Expressionist]] treatments.

Also from that era were sculptures of the theme by [[Antonin Mercié]] and [[Max Klinger]].&lt;ref&gt;Dijkstra, Bram, Idols of Perversity, Oxford University Press, New York, 1986 p.315&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Paul Cezanne Leda au cygne.jpg|thumb|right|265px|[[Paul Cézanne]]'s ''Leda and the Swan''&lt;ref&gt;Now in the [[Barnes Foundation|Barnes Foundation Collection]], [[Lower Merion Township, Montgomery County, Pennsylvania|Merion, Pennsylvania]] has been dated as early as 1868 and as late as 1886–1890; the best estimate is 1880–1882; ''Great French Paintings from the Barnes Foundation: Impressionist, Post-Impressionist, and Early Modern''. New York: Knopf, 1993. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

==In modern and contemporary art==
[[Cy Twombly]] executed an abstract version of ''Leda and the Swan'' in 1962. It was purchased by [[Larry Gagosian]] for $52.9&amp;nbsp;million at Christie's May 2017 Post-War and Contemporary Art Evening Sale.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.liveauctioneers.com/news/top-news/gagosian-pays-52-9m-twombly-fritz-cat-smashes-comic-art-record-fresh-news/ |title=Leda and the Swan |author=Cy Twombly}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Avant-garde filmmaker Kurt Kren along with other members of the [[Viennese Actionism|Viennese Actionist]] movement, including [[Otto Muehl]] and [[Hermann Nitsch]], made a film-performance called ''7/64 Leda mit der Schwan'' in 1964. The film retains the classical motif, portraying, for most of its duration, a young woman embracing a swan.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

There is a life-sized marble statue of ''Leda and the Swan'' at the [[Jai Vilas Palace|Jai Vilas Palace Museum]] in [[Gwalior]], Northern [[Madhya Pradesh]], India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jiwaji Rao Scindia Museum – Collection|url=http://jaivilasmuseum.org/Collection.html|accessdate=11 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150211184502/http://jaivilasmuseum.org/Collection.html|archive-date=11 February 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American artist and photographer [[Carole Harmel]] created the "Bird" series (1983), a Jean Cocteau-influenced collection of photographs that explored the "Leda and the Swan" myth in tightly cropped, voyeuristic images of a nude female and an undefinable birdlike creature hinting at intimacy.&lt;ref name="Pieszak2"&gt;Pieszak, Devonna. "Carole Harmel", Catalogue essay, Chicago: Galerija, 1983.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bone"&gt;Bone, James. "Art Facts: a mix of media on Wells Street", ''Chicago Reader'', 11 March 1983.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Bristol Museum and Art Gallery currently exhibits Karl Weschke's ''Leda and the Swan'', painted in 1986.  The [[Winnipeg Art Gallery]] in Canada has, in its permanent collection, a ceramic "Leda and the Swan" by Japanese-born American artist [[Akio Takamori]].  [[Genieve Figgis]] painted her version of Leda and the Swan in 2018 after an earlier work by [[François Boucher]]. Figgis’ contemporary version reinvents the idyllic romantic scene of lavish playfulness with a dark humor creating a scene of profanity and horror. There is a sculpture in neon lights depicting Leda and the Swan in Berlin, near Sonnenallee metro station and the Estrel hotel, designed by [[AES+F]].  Photographer [[Charlie White (artist)|Charlie White]] included a portrait of Leda in his "And Jeopardize the Integrity of the Hull" series. Zeus, as the swan, only appears metaphorically.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

==In poetry==
[[Ronsard]] wrote a poem on ''La Défloration de Lède'', perhaps inspired by the Michelangelo, which he may well have known. Like many artists, he imagines the beak penetrating Leda's vagina.&lt;ref&gt;Bull p.169&lt;/ref&gt;

"Leda and the Swan" is a sonnet by [[William Butler Yeats]] first published in the ''Dial'' in [[1923 in poetry|1923]].  Combining [[psychological realism]] with a mystic vision, it describes the swan's rape of [[Leda (mythology)|Leda]]. It also alludes to the [[Trojan war]], which will be provoked by the abduction of [[Helen of Troy|Helen]], who will be begotten by Zeus on Leda (along with [[Castor and Pollux]], in some versions of the myth). [[Clytaemnestra]], who killed her husband, [[Agamemnon]], leader of the Greeks at Troy, was also supposed to have hatched from one of Leda's eggs. The poem is regularly praised as one of Yeats's masterpieces.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Bloom|first=Harold|title=Yeats|publisher=Oxford UP|year=1972|pages=363–66|isbn=978-0-19-501603-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vqpspMiPWLgC&amp;pg=PA363}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Camille Paglia]], who called the poem "the greatest poem of the twentieth century," and said "all human beings, like Leda, are caught up moment by moment in the 'white rush' of experience. For Yeats, the only salvation is the shapeliness and stillness of art."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Paglia|first=Camille|title=Break, Blow, Burn|publisher=Random House|year=2006|pages=114–18|isbn=978-0-375-72539-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lNZ_LYCGSPsC&amp;pg=PA114}}&lt;/ref&gt;  See external links for a bas relief arranged in the position as described by Yeats.

Nicaraguan poet [[Rubén Darío]]'s 1892 poem "Leda" contains an oblique description of the rape, watched over by the god [[Pan (god)|Pan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Darío|first=Rubén|author2=Andrew Hurley |author3=Greg Simon |author4=Steven F. White |title=Selected Writings: Ruben Dario|editor=Ilan Stavans|publisher=Penguin|year=2005|pages=[https://archive.org/details/selectedwritings00dari/page/20 20]–21|isbn=978-0-14-303936-5|url=https://archive.org/details/selectedwritings00dari|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[H.D.]] (Hilda Doolittle) also wrote a poem called "Leda" in 1919, suggested to be from the perspective of Leda. The description of the sexual action going on makes it seem almost beautiful, as if Leda had given her consent.

In the song "Power and Glory" from [[Lou Reed]]'s 1992 album ''[[Magic and Loss]]'', Reed recalls the experience of seeing his friend dying of cancer and makes reference to the myth, "I saw [[isotope]]s introduced into his lungs / trying to stop the cancerous spread / And it made me think of Leda and The Swan / and gold being made from lead"

[[Sylvia Plath]] alludes to the myth in her [[radio play]] ''Three Women'' written for the [[BBC]] in 1962. The play features the voices of three women. The first is a married woman who keeps her baby. The second is a secretary who suffers a miscarriage. The third voice, a girl who is pregnant and leaves her baby, mentions "the great swan, with its terrible look,/ Coming at me," insinuating that the girl was raped. The play is about the disconnection of women in society and challenges societal expectations of childbirth.

==In literature==
Several references to the myth are presented in novels by [[Angela Carter]], including ''Nights at the Circus'' and ''The Magic Toyshop''. In the latter novel, the myth is brought to life in the form of a performance in which a frightened young girl is forced to act as Leda in accompaniment with a large mechanical swan.

There is a reference to Leda and the Swan in [[Dorothea Benton Frank]]'s book "All Summer Long" published in 2016.

The myth is also mentioned in [[Richard Yates (novelist)|Richard Yates]]' classic 1962 novel [[Revolutionary Road]]. The character Frank Wheeler, married to April Wheeler, after having had sex with an office secretary ponders what to say as he is leaving: "Did the swan apologize to Leda? Did an eagle apologize? Did a lion apologize? Hell no!"
&lt;ref&gt;Third Vintage Contemporaries Edition, 2008, pg106&lt;/ref&gt;

==In modern media==
A version of the Leda and the Swan story is the foundation myth in the Canadian futuristic thriller television series ''[[Orphan Black]]'' which aired over 5 seasons from 2013 to 2017. A corporation uses genetic engineering to create a series of female clones (Leda) and a series of male clones (Castor) who are also brothers and sisters clones as they derive from one mother who is a chimera with male and female genomes. 

==Modern censorship==
In April 2012 an art gallery in London, England, was instructed by the police to remove a modern exhibit of Leda and the Swan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/art/art-news/9232512/Mythical-swan-photo-taken-down-after-bestiality-fears.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Hannah | last=Furness | title='Mythical' swan photo taken down after 'bestiality' fears | date=28 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The law concerned was [[Section 63 of the Criminal Justice and Immigration Act 2008]], condemning 'violent pornography', brought in by the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] government of 2005–2010.

== Gallery ==

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="200px" perrow="4"&gt;
File:Cornelis Bos - Leda and the Swan - WGA2486.jpg|Drawing by [[Cornelis Bos]] after the lost original by [[Michelangelo]]
Image:Leda Melzi Uffizi.jpg|''Leda and the Swan'' copy by Giovanni Francesco Melzi after the lost painting by [[Leonardo da Vinci|Leonardo]], 1508–1515, oil on canvas, [[Uffizi|Galleria degli Uffizi]], [[Florence]], [[Italy]].
File:Leda y el cisne.jpg|''Leda and the Swan'', charcoal, gouache on paper. ([[Ulpiano Checa]])
File:Leda y el cisne (Pencz).jpg|''Leda and the Swan''. ([[Georg Pencz]])
File:La fábula de Leda (Cajés (copia de Correggio)).jpg|"The fable of Leda" ''(Leda and the Swan)'', Eugenio Cajés (copy of Correggio), Museo del Prado, Madrid, Spain.
File:0 Léda et Zeus métamorphosé en cygne - Musei Capitolini (1).JPG|''Leda and Zeus transformed into a swan'', Palazzo Nuovo (Capitoline Museums), Rome.
File:Benvenuto cellini, leda e il cigno.JPG|''Leda and the Swan'' by [[Benvenuto Cellini]]
File:Attribué à François Boucher, Léda et le Cygne (vers 1740).jpg|''Leda and the Swan'' by [[François Boucher]], 1740, oil on canvas.
File:Leda and the Swan by Jean-Leon Gerome.jpg|''Leda and the Swan'' by [[Jean-Léon Gérôme]]. Dated 1895
File:Genieve Figgis Leda and the Swan (after Boucher) 2018 23x31 inches Acrylic in canvas 37kB.JPEG|"Leda and the Swan (after Boucher)" by [[Genieve Figgis]] 2018, Acrylic on canvas, 23 x 31 inches
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==

{{Reflist}}

==References==
*Bull, Malcolm, ''The Mirror of the Gods, How Renaissance Artists Rediscovered the Pagan Gods'', Oxford UP, 2005, {{ISBN|0-19-521923-6}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Leda and the Swan}}
* [http://www.theoi.com/Text/HyginusFabulae2.html#77 Version of Leda and the Swan myth, in the "Fabulae" of Hyginus]
*[https://www.britishmuseum.org/collectionimages/AN00102/AN00102484_001_l.jpg Bas relief from the British Museum that appears as the scene does in the Yeats sonnet]
*[http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/latin/ovid/notes.html Ovid Illustrated – large site from the University of Virginia, where many depictions of Leda and the Swan from Renaissance and later editions of the Metamorphoses will (eventually) be found.]
*[http://d-sites.net/english/yeats.htm Yeats' "Leda and the Swan": an image's coming of age]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081226224628/http://www.getty.edu/art/gettyguide/artObjectDetails?artobj=14945&amp;handle=li Greek vase from the Getty]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090101133726/http://www.samuelson.co.uk/blog/?p=407 Samuelson blog with thoughts and pictures]
*[http://www.museiciviciveneziani.it/frame.asp?id=2341&amp;musid=112 16th century Venetian painting by Il Padovanino]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070228073059/http://www.theoi.com/Gallery/K1.11.html Alternative detail view of the Getty vase]
*[http://www.getty.edu/art/gettyguide/artObjectDetails?artobj=7639 Roman statue from the Getty]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081226224922/http://www.getty.edu/art/gettyguide/artObjectDetails?artobj=113647 Baroque bronze from the Getty]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070211115257/http://www.liverpoolmuseums.org.uk/ladylever/collections/ledaandtheswan.asp Sculpture c 1900]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090126022229/http://www.zeinalov.com/htm/e/erotic/leda_01.htm ''Leda and the swan'' – Bronze miniature]
*[http://beckydaroff.com/stories/details.php?recordID=186 ''Leda and the Swan'', by Tintoretto, from the Galleria degli Uffizi, Florence; explore other depictions of ''Leda and the Swan'' and compare to similar themes]
* {{Cite web
 |publisher   = [[Victoria and Albert Museum]]
 |url         = http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/sculpture/stories/leda/index.html
 |title       = Leda and the Hat Pin
 |work        = Sculpture
 |accessdate  = 24 July 2007
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20090310045155/http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/sculpture/stories/leda/index.html
 |archivedate = 10 March 2009
 |df          = dmy-all
}}
*[http://www.shunya.net/Pictures/NorthIndia/Gwalior/LedaSwan.jpg Jai Vilas Palace Museum, Gwalior, India]

{{Michelangelo|painting}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Leda and the Swan}}
[[Category:Irish poems]]
[[Category:1924 poems]]
[[Category:Greek mythology]]
[[Category:Iconography]]
[[Category:Swans]]
[[Category:Mythological rape victims]]
[[Category:Zoophilia in culture]]
[[Category:Paintings of Leda| ]]</text>
      <sha1>a56hpf86l3vpzx3dcw8ch4najso4fe7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
