<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Classic Maya collapse</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10443117</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962199229</id>
      <parentid>950783297</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-12T17:24:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Parkwells</username>
        <id>5326371</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Theories */ correct two typos (letters)  - spatial patters (patterns) and a plural that should be singular</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="40663" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|decline of classic Maya civilization}}
{{Use American English|date = March 2019}}
{{Maya civilization}}

In archaeology, the '''classic Maya collapse''' is the decline of the [[Classic Maya|Classic]] [[Maya civilization]] and the abandonment of [[Maya city|Maya cities]] in the [[Geography of Mesoamerica#Maya Region|southern Maya lowlands]] of [[Mesoamerica]] between the 8th and 9th&amp;nbsp;centuries, at the end of the Classic Maya Period. The [[Preclassic Maya]] experienced a similar collapse in the 2nd century.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.history.com/news/what-caused-the-maya-collapse-archaeologists-uncover-new-clues&lt;/ref&gt;

The Classic Period of [[Mesoamerican chronology]] is generally defined as the period from 250 to 900 CE, the last century of which is referred to as the '''Terminal Classic'''.&lt;ref&gt;See Stuart and Stuart (1993, p. 12), McKillop (2006, p. 90, pp. 339–340)&lt;/ref&gt; The Classic Maya collapse is one of the greatest unsolved mysteries in archaeology. Urban centers of the southern lowlands, among them [[Palenque]], [[Copán]], [[Tikal]], and [[Calakmul]], went into decline during the 8th and 9th&amp;nbsp;centuries and were abandoned shortly thereafter. Archaeologically, this decline is indicated by the cessation of monumental inscriptions&lt;ref name = "Knorozov"&gt;[http://bookfi.net/book/683367 Кнорозов, Ю. В. Письменность индейцев майя. — М.—Л.: Изд-во АН СССР, 1963. — 664 с.]&lt;/ref&gt; and the reduction of large-scale [[Mesoamerican architecture|architectural]] construction at the primary urban centers of the Classic Period.{{Citation needed|date=March 2018}}

Although termed a collapse, it did not mark the end of the Maya civilization but rather a shift away from the Southern Lowlands as a power center; the Northern [[Yucatán Peninsula|Yucatán]] in particular prospered afterwards, although with very different artistic and architectural styles, and with much less use of monumental hieroglyphic writing. In the Post-Classic Period following the collapse, the state of [[Chichén Itzá]] built an empire that briefly united much of the Maya region,&lt;ref name = "Knorozov"/&gt; and centers such as [[Mayapán]] and [[Uxmal]] flourished, as did the Highland states of the [[Kʼicheʼ Kingdom of Qʼumarkaj|Kʼicheʼ]] and [[Kaqchikel people|Kaqchikel]] Maya. Independent Maya civilization continued until 1697 when the Spanish conquered [[Nojpetén]], the last independent city-state. Millions of [[Maya people]] still inhabit the Yucatán peninsula today.&lt;ref name="total"&gt;{{cite book|language=es|author1=Lorenzo Ochoa|author2 = Patricia Martel(dir.)|title=Lengua y cultura mayas|publisher=UNAM|year=2002|isbn=978-9703200894|pages=170|quote=''El "Pueblo Maya" lo constituyen actualmente algo menos de 6 millones de hablantes de 25 idiomas''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because parts of Maya civilization unambiguously continued, a number of scholars strongly dislike the term collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Aimers, James J. "What Maya Collapse? Terminal Classic Variation in the Maya Lowlands." J Archaeol Res (2007) 15:329–377&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding the proposed collapse, E. W. Andrews IV went as far as to say, "in my belief no such thing happened."&lt;ref&gt;Andrews IV, E. W. (1973). The development of Maya civilization after the abandonment of the southern cities. In Culbert, T. P. (ed.), ''The Classic Maya Collapse'', University of New Mexico Press, Albuquerque, pp. 243–265&lt;/ref&gt;

== Progression of the decline ==
The Maya often recorded dates on monuments they built. Few dated monuments were being built circa 500 – around ten per year in 514, for example. The number steadily increased to twenty per year by 672 and forty by around 750. After this, the number of dated monuments begins to falter relatively quickly, collapsing back to ten by 800 and to zero by 900. Likewise, recorded lists of kings complement this analysis. [[Copán Altar Q|Altar Q]] at [[Copán]] shows a reign of kings from 426 to 763. One last king not recorded on Altar Q was [[Ukit Took]], "Patron of Flint", who was probably a usurper. The dynasty is believed to have collapsed entirely shortly thereafter. In [[Quirigua]], twenty miles north of Copán, the last king [[Jade Sky]] began his rule between 895 and 900, and throughout the Maya area all kingdoms similarly fell around that time.&lt;ref name="whyNationsFail"&gt;{{Cite book| last=Acemoglu, Robinson| first=Daron, James A.| title=Why Nations Fail|  year=2012| pages=143–149| isbn=978-1-84668-429-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A third piece of evidence of the progression of Maya decline, gathered by Ann Corinne Freter, Nancy Gonlin, and David Webster, uses a technique called [[obsidian hydration]]. The technique allowed them to map the spread and growth of settlements in the [[Copán|Copán Valley]] and estimate their populations. Between 400 and 450, the population was estimated at a peak of twenty-eight thousand, between 750 and 800 – larger than London at the time. Population then began to steadily decline. By 900 the population had fallen to fifteen thousand, and by 1200 the population was again less than 1000. {{Citation needed|date=March 2018}}

==Theories==
Over 80 different theories or variations of theories attempting to explain the Classic Maya collapse have been identified.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (2000, p. 371)&lt;/ref&gt; From [[Climate change (general concept)|climate change]] to deforestation to lack of action by Maya kings, there is no universally accepted collapse theory, although drought has gained momentum in the first quarter of the 21st century as the leading explanation, as more scientific studies are conducted.&lt;ref&gt;"Like most things, collapse explanations are subject to fashion, and the one most in the limelight today is climatic change, or more specifically, megadrought." Quote is from Webster (2002, p. 239); see also article by Diamond (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foreign invasion===
The archaeological evidence of the [[Toltec]] intrusion into  [[Seibal]], [[Petén Department|Peten]], suggests to some the theory of foreign invasion. The latest hypothesis states that the southern lowlands were invaded by a non-Maya group whose homelands were probably in the gulf coast lowlands. This invasion began in the 9th&amp;nbsp;century and set off, within 100&amp;nbsp;years, a group of events that destroyed the Classic Maya. It is believed that this invasion was somehow influenced by the Toltec people of central Mexico. However, most Mayanists do not believe that foreign invasion was the main cause of the Classic Maya collapse; they postulate that no military defeat can explain or be the cause of the protracted and complex Classic collapse process. [[Teotihuacan]] influence across the Maya region may have involved some form of military invasion; however, it is generally noted that significant Teotihuacan-Maya interactions date from at least the Early Classic period, well before the episodes of Late Classic collapse.&lt;ref&gt;See Braswell(2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

The foreign invasion theory does not answer the question of where the inhabitants went. David Webster believed that the population should have increased because of the lack of elite power. Further, it is not understood why the governmental institutions were not remade following the revolts, which happened under similar circumstances in places like [[China]]. A study by anthropologist Elliot M. Abrams came to the conclusion that buildings, specifically in [[Copan]], did not require an extensive amount of time and workers to construct.&lt;ref name=Abrams&gt;{{cite book|last1=Abrams|first1=Elliot M.|title=How the Maya Built Their World|date=1994|publisher=University of Texas|isbn=978-0-292-70462-6|url=https://archive.org/details/howmayabuiltthei00abra}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this theory was developed during a period when the archaeological evidence showed that there were fewer Maya people than there are now known to have been.&lt;ref&gt;Webster (2002 pp. 221–223)&lt;/ref&gt; Revolutions, peasant revolts, and social turmoil change circumstances, and are often followed by foreign wars, but they run their course. There are no documented revolutions that caused wholesale abandonment of entire regions.{{Citation needed|date=January 2017}}

===Collapse of trade routes===
It has been hypothesized that the decline of the Maya is related to the collapse of their intricate trade systems, especially those connected to the central Mexican city of [[Teotihuacán]]. Preceding improved knowledge of the chronology of Mesoamerica, Teotihuacan was believed to have fallen during 700–750, forcing the "restructuring of economic relations throughout highland Mesoamerica and the Gulf Coast".&lt;ref&gt;Webster (2002 pp. 231)&lt;/ref&gt;  This remaking of relationships between civilizations would have then given the collapse of the Classic Maya a slightly later date. However, after researchers learned more about the events and the periods when they occurred, it is believed that the strongest Teotihuacan influence was during the 4th and 5th&amp;nbsp;centuries. In addition, the civilization of Teotihuacan started to lose its power, and maybe abandoned the city, during 600–650. This differs greatly from the previous belief that Teotihuacano power decreased during 700–750.&lt;ref&gt;Webster (2002 pp. 231–234)&lt;/ref&gt; But since the new decline date of 600–650 has been accepted, the Maya civilizations are now thought to have lived on and prospered "for another century and more"&lt;ref name="Webster 2002 pp.232"&gt;Webster (2002 pp. 232)&lt;/ref&gt; than what was previously believed. Rather than the decline of Teotihuacan directly preceding the collapse of the Maya, their decline is now seen as contributing "to the 6th-century 'hiatus'".&lt;ref name="Webster 2002 pp.232"/&gt;

===Epidemic diseases===
The [[disease]] theory is also a contender as a factor in the Classic Maya collapse. Widespread disease could explain some rapid depopulation, both directly through the spread of infection itself and indirectly as an inhibition to recovery over the long run. According to Dunn (1968) and Shimkin (1973), infectious diseases spread by parasites are common in tropical rainforest regions, such as the Maya lowlands. Shimkin specifically suggests that the Maya may have encountered endemic infections related to American [[trypanosomiasis]], ''[[Ascaris]]'', and some [[enteropathogen]]s that cause acute diarrheal illness. Furthermore, some experts believe that, through development of their civilization (that is, development of agriculture and settlements), the Maya could have created a "disturbed environment", in which parasitic and pathogen-carrying insects often thrive.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson and May (1982); R. Anderson (1982); Lycett (1985).&lt;/ref&gt; Among the pathogens listed above, it is thought that those that cause the acute diarrheal illnesses would have been the most devastating to the Maya population, because such illness would have struck a victim at an early age, thereby hampering nutritional health and the natural growth and development of a child. This would have made them more susceptible to other diseases later in life,  and would have been exacerbated by an increasing dependence on carbohydrate-rich crops.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wright|first=Lori E|date=1997|title=Intertooth Patterns of Hypoplasia Expression: Implications for Childhood Health in the Classic Maya Collapse|url=|journal=American Journal of Physical Anthropology|volume=102|issue=2|pages=233–247|doi=10.1002/(SICI)1096-8644(199702)102:2&lt;233::AID-AJPA6&gt;3.0.CO;2-Z}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such ideas as this could explain the role of disease as at least a possible partial reason for the Classic Maya Collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Santley, Killion, and Lycett (1986, pp. 140–141)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Drought theory===
The drought theory holds that rapid [[Climate change (general concept)|climate change]] in the form of severe [[drought]] (a [[megadrought]]) brought about the Classic Maya collapse. [[Paleoclimatologists]] have discovered abundant evidence that prolonged droughts occurred in the [[Yucatán Peninsula]] and [[Petén Basin]] areas during the Terminal Classic. Large droughts likely caused a decline in agricultural fertility due to regular seasonal drought drying up surface waters,&lt;ref name="Webster 2002, p.239"&gt;Webster (2002, p. 239)&lt;/ref&gt; as well as causing thin tropical soils to erode when deprived of vegetation and forest cover.&lt;ref&gt;Coe (1999, pp. 26–27)&lt;/ref&gt;

Climatic factors were first implicated in the collapse as early as 1931 by Mayanists [[Thomas Gann]] and [[J. Eric S. Thompson|J. E. S. Thompson]].&lt;ref&gt;Gann &amp; Thompson, ''The History of the Maya'', 1931&lt;/ref&gt; In 1995, Hodell, Curtis and Brenner published a [[paleoclimate]] record from [[Lake Chichancanab]] on the [[Yucatán Peninsula]] that showed an intense, protracted drought occurred in the 9th century AD and coincided with the Classic Maya collapse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hodell |first=David A. |authorlink= |author2=Curtis, Jason H. |author3=Brenner, Mark  |year=1995 |title=Possible role of climate in the collapse of Classic Maya civilization |journal=Nature |volume=375 |issue=6530 |pages=391–394 |doi=10.1038/375391a0 |url= |access-date= |quote= |bibcode=1995Natur.375..391H }}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''The Great Maya Droughts'', Richardson Gill gathered and analyzed an array of climatic, historical, hydrologic, tree ring, volcanic, geologic, and archeological research, and suggested that a prolonged series of droughts likely caused the Classic Maya collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (2000, ''passim.'')&lt;/ref&gt; The drought theory provides a comprehensive explanation, because non-environmental and cultural factors (excessive warfare, foreign invasion, peasant revolt, less trade, etc.) can all be explained by the effects of prolonged drought on Classic Maya civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Webster (2002, p. 99)&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Gill in ''The Great Maya Droughts'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[Studies of] Yucatecan lake sediment cores ... provide unambiguous evidence for a severe 200-year drought from AD&amp;nbsp;800 to 1000 ... the most severe in the last 7,000&amp;nbsp;years ... precisely at the time of the Maya Collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (2000, p.276 )&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The role of drought in the collapse of Classic Maya civilization has remained controversial, however, largely because the majority of [[paleoclimate]] records only provide [[qualitative data]], for example whether conditions were simply "wetter" or "drier". The lack of [[quantitative data]] makes it difficult to predict how climatic changes would have affected human populations and the environment in which they lived. In 2012, a study attempted to quantify the drought using four detailed paleoclimate records of the drought event.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Collapse of Classic Maya Civilization Related to Modest Reduction in Precipitation|first1=Martín|last1=Medina-Elizalde|first2=Eelco J.|last2=Rohling|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |date=24 Feb 2012 |volume= 335 |issue= 6071 |pages=956–959 |bibcode=2012Sci...335..956M|doi=10.1126/science.1216629}}&lt;/ref&gt; Semi-quantitative rainfall estimates were achieved by correlating [[oxygen isotopes]] measurements in [[carbonate]] cave formations ([[speleothems]]) with modern seasonal rainfall amounts recorded in the nearby city of [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]], northern [[Yucatán]], which were extrapolated back to the time of the Terminal Classic Period. The authors suggest that modest rainfall reductions, amounting to only 25 to 40 percent of annual rainfall, may have been the tipping point to the Maya collapse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/02/120223142455.htm|title=Classic Maya Civilization Collapse Related to Modest Rainfall Reductions, Research Suggests|work=[[Science Daily]]|date=2012-02-23|access-date=2012-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-17149812|title=Mild drought caused Maya collapse in Mexico, Guatemala|work=[[BBC News]]|date=2012-02-25|access-date=2012-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although this analysis referred to the estimated decrease in rainfall as "modest", subsequent studies suggest that the same data could represent a 20 to 65 percent decrease in rainfall.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Impacts of Climate Change on the Collapse of Lowland Maya Civilization|first1=Peter M.J.|last1=Douglas|first2=Arthur A.|last2=Demarest|first3=Mark|last3=Brenner|first4=Marcello A.|last4=Canuto|journal=Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences |date=2 May 2016 |volume= 44 |pages=613–645 |doi=10.1146/annurev-earth-060115-012512|bibcode=2016AREPS..44..613D}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study published in the journal ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' in 2018 provides the most robust estimate of the magnitude of rainfall reduction to date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Quantification of drought during the collapse of the classic Maya civilization|first1=Nicholas P.|last1=Evans|first2=Thomas K.|last2=Bauska|first3=Fernando|last3=Gázquez-Sánchez|first4=Mark|last4=Brenner|first5=Jason H.|last5=Curtis|first6=David A.|last6=Hodell|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |date=3 Aug 2018 |volume= 361 |issue= 6401 |pages=498–501 |doi=10.1126/science.aas9871|pmid=30072537|bibcode=2018Sci...361..498E|hdl=10023/16993|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evans and co-authors developed a method to measure the different [[isotopes]] of water trapped in the [[hydrate]] mineral, [[gypsum]], a mineral that forms in lakes of the [[Yucatán Peninsula]] during times of drought when the water level is lowered. When gypsum forms, water molecules are incorporated directly into its crystalline structure, and this water records the different isotopes that were present in the ancient lake water at the time of its formation.&lt;ref name="University of Cambridge"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/scientists-measure-severity-of-drought-during-the-maya-collapse|title=Scientists measure severity of drought during the Maya collapse|work=[[University of Cambridge]]|date=2018-09-02|access-date=2019-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The "fossil water" inside the crystals allowed Evans and his co-authors to analyze the properties of the lake water during each drought period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://eos.org/articles/severe-drought-may-have-helped-hasten-ancient-mayas-collapse|title=Severe Drought May Have Helped Hasten Ancient Maya's Collapse|work=[[Eos (magazine)|Eos]]|date=2018-09-02|access-date=2019-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/speaking-of-science/wp/2018/08/02/an-ancient-lake-holds-secrets-to-the-mayan-civilizations-mysterious-collapse-study-finds/|title=Severe Drought May Have Helped Hasten Ancient Maya's Collapse|work=[[Washington Post]]|date=2018-09-02|access-date=2019-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on these measurements, the researchers found that annual precipitation decreased between 41 and 54 percent during the period of the Maya civilisation's collapse, with periods of up to 70 percent rainfall reduction during peak drought conditions, and that relative humidity declined by 2 to 7 percent compared to today. This quantitative climate data can be used to better predict how these drought conditions may have affected agriculture, including yields of the Maya's staple crops, such as maize.&lt;ref name="University of Cambridge"/&gt;

Critics of the drought theory question the spatial patterns of drought and its relation to the timing of the degradation of Maya city-states. Archaeological research demonstrates that while many regions of the Maya Lowlands were indeed abandoned during the eighth to eleventh centuries CE, other regions experienced only minor disruption, or even flourished.&lt;ref&gt;Mann (2006, p. 312)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; Although the spatial patterns of [[societal collapse]] are complex, population centers continued in many coastal regions and in the northern [[Yucatán Peninsula]], including as [[Chichen Itza]], [[Uxmal]], and [[Coba]], whereas most states in the central regions collapsed and landscapes were depopulated. The reasons for this spatial heterogeneity in societal disintegration are largely unknown, but researches have hypothesised that central regions may have been more affected because of a very deep water table (which would have exacerbated the effects of drought), or that the longevity of the northern regions was likely facilitated by access to the coast, and thus trade routes.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

Other critics of the [[megadrought]] theory, including David Webster, note that much of the evidence of drought comes from the northern Yucatán and not the southern part of the peninsula, where Classic Maya civilization flourished. Webster states that if water sources were to have dried up, then several city-states would have moved to other water sources. That Gill suggests that all water in the region would have dried up and destroyed Maya civilization is a stretch, according to Webster,&lt;ref&gt;Webster (2002, pp. 243–245)&lt;/ref&gt; although Webster does not have a precise competing theory explaining the Classic Maya Collapse. Since publication, further records from the more southerly states have strengthened the argument of a synchronous drought occurring across the Yucatán Peninsula.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

Climatic changes are, with increasing frequency, found to be major drivers in the rise and fall of civilizations all over the world.&lt;ref&gt;See for example papers by deMenocal (2001); Weiss (1997); Weiss and Bradley (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; Professors Harvey Weiss of Yale University and Raymond S. Bradley of the University of Massachusetts have written, "Many lines of evidence now point to climate forcing as the primary agent in repeated social collapse."&lt;ref&gt;Weiss and Bradley (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; In a separate publication, Weiss illustrates an emerging understanding of scientists:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Within the past five years new tools and new data for archaeologists, climatologists, and historians have brought us to the edge of a new era in the study of global and hemispheric climate change and its cultural impacts. The climate of the Holocene, previously assumed static, now displays a surprising dynamism, which has affected the agricultural bases of pre-industrial societies. The list of Holocene climate alterations and their socio-economic effects has rapidly become too complex for brief summary.&lt;ref&gt;Quote is from Weiss (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A number of causal mechanisms for droughts in the Maya area have been proposed, but there is no consensus among researchers regarding a single causal mechanism. Instead, it is likely that multiple mechanisms were involved,&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; including solar variability,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hodell |first=David A. |authorlink=David A. Hodell |author2=Brenner, Mark |author3=Curtis, Jason H. |author4= Guilderson, Thomas |date=18 May 2001 |title=Solar Forcing of Drought Frequency in the Maya Lowlands |url=http://mac01.eps.pitt.edu/Courses/GEOL3909/Hodell_et_al_2001.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=292 |issue=5520 |pages=1367–1370 |doi=10.1126/science.1057759 |citeseerx=10.1.1.586.6815 |bibcode=2001Sci...292.1367H |pmid=11359010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; shifts in the position of the Intertropical Convergence Zone,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Climate and the Collapse of Maya Civilization
|first1=Gerald H.|last1=Haug|first2=Detlef|last2=Günther|first3=Larry C.|last3= Peterson|first4=Daniel M.|last4= Sigman|first5=Konrad A.|last5=Hughen|first6=Beat|last6= Aeschlimann|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |date=14 Mar 2003 |volume= 299 |issue= 5613 |pages=1731–1735 |doi=10.1126/science.1080444|pmid=12637744|bibcode=2003Sci...299.1731H}}&lt;/ref&gt; changes in tropical cyclone frequency&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; and deforestation.

The Maya are often perceived as having lived in a rainforest, but technically, they lived in a seasonal desert without access to stable sources of drinking water.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (2000, p. 382); Webster (2002, p. 239)&lt;/ref&gt; The exceptional accomplishments of the Maya are even more remarkable because of their engineered response to the fundamental environmental difficulty of relying upon rainwater rather than permanent sources of water. "The Maya succeeded in creating a civilization in a seasonal desert by creating a system of water storage and management which was totally dependent on consistent rainfall."&lt;ref&gt;Gill (2000, p. 386)&lt;/ref&gt; The constant need for water kept the Maya on the edge of survival. "Given this precarious balance of wet and dry conditions, even a slight shift in the distribution of annual precipitation can have serious consequences."&lt;ref name="Webster 2002, p.239"/&gt; Water and civilization were vitally connected in ancient Mesoamerica. [[Vernon Scarborough]], an archaeologist and specialist in pre-industrial land and water usage practices, believes water management and access were critical to the development of Maya civilization.&lt;ref&gt;As reported in McKillop (2006, p. 89)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Systemic ecological collapse model===
Some ecological theories of Maya decline focus on the worsening agricultural and resource conditions in the [[late Classic]] period. It was originally thought that the majority of Maya agriculture was dependent on a simple [[slash-and-burn]] system. Based on this method, the hypothesis of soil exhaustion was advanced by [[Orator F. Cook]] in 1921. Similar soil exhaustion assumptions are associated with [[erosion]], intensive agricultural, and [[savanna]] grass competition.

More recent investigations have shown a complicated variety of intensive agricultural techniques utilized by the Maya, explaining the high population of the Classic Maya polities. Modern archaeologists now comprehend the sophisticated intensive and productive agricultural techniques of the ancient Maya, and several of the Maya agricultural methods have not yet been reproduced. Intensive agricultural methods were developed and utilized by all the Mesoamerican cultures to boost their food production and give them a competitive advantage over less skillful peoples.&lt;ref&gt;See synopsis in Dunning ''et al.''(2002)&lt;/ref&gt; These intensive agricultural methods included canals, terracing, raised fields, ridged fields, [[chinampa]]s, [[Night soil|the use of human feces as fertilizer]], seasonal swamps or ''bajos'', using muck from the ''bajos'' to create fertile fields, dikes, dams, irrigation, water reservoirs, several types of water storage systems, hydraulic systems, swamp reclamation, [[swidden]] systems, and other agricultural techniques that have not yet been fully understood.&lt;ref&gt;Demarest (2004, pp. 130–147); Sabloff (1994, pp. 81–84, 139–140)&lt;/ref&gt; Systemic [[ecological collapse]] is said to be evidenced by [[deforestation]], [[siltation]], and the decline of [[biological diversity]].

In addition to mountainous terrain, Mesoamericans successfully exploited the very problematic tropical rainforest for 1,500&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;ref&gt;Sabloff (1994, p. 171), citing Rice and Rice (1984)&lt;/ref&gt; The agricultural techniques utilized by the Maya were entirely dependent upon ample supplies of water, lending credit to the drought theory of collapse. The Maya thrived in territory that would be uninhabitable to most peoples. Their success over two millennia in this environment was "amazing."&lt;ref&gt;Demarest (2004, p. 129)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other explanations===
Anthropologist [[Joseph Tainter]] wrote extensively about the collapse of the Southern Lowland Maya in his 1988 study ''The Collapse of Complex Societies''. His theory about Maya collapse encompasses some of the above explanations, but focuses specifically on the development of and the declining marginal returns from the increasing social complexity of the competing Maya city-states.&lt;ref name="Tainter 1988"&gt;Tainter (1988, pp. 152–177)&lt;/ref&gt; Psychologist [[Julian Jaynes]] suggested that the collapse was due to a failure in the social control systems of religion and political authority, due to increasing socioeconomic complexity that overwhelmed the power of traditional rituals and the king's authority to compel obedience.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Jaynes | first=Julian | title=The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind | publisher=Houghton Mifflin | origyear=1976| year=2000 | isbn=978-0-618-05707-8 | page=197 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=3eQd-x-cxPwC&amp;pg=PT207}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Societal collapse]], the collapse of a complex human society
*[[Bronze Age collapse]], a similar collapse in the ancient Middle East

==Notes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin|indent=yes}}&lt;!--BEGIN biblio format.--&gt;
* {{cite book |author=Braswell, Geoffrey E.  |year=2003 |chapter=Introduction: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |title=The Maya and Teotihuacan: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |editor=Geoffrey E. Braswell|location=Austin |publisher=University of Texas Press |pages=1–44|isbn=978-0-292-70587-6 |oclc=49936017}}
* {{cite book |author=Coe, Michael D.  |authorlink=Michael D. Coe|year=1999|title=The Maya |edition=6th |location=New York |publisher=Thames and Hudson |isbn=978-0-500-28066-9 |oclc=15895415}}
* {{cite book |author=Colinvaux, Paul A.  |authorlink=Paul Colinvaux |year=1980 |title=The Fates of Nations: A Biological Theory of History |location=New York |publisher=Simon and Schuster |isbn=978-0-671-25204-5 |oclc=6143975}}
* {{cite book |author=Demarest, Arthur  |authorlink=Arthur Demarest|year=2004 |title=Ancient Maya: The Rise and Fall of a Rainforest Civilization |series=Case Studies in Early Societies, No. 3 |location=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-59224-6 |oclc=51438896}}
* {{cite journal |author=deMenocal, Peter B. |date=2001-04-27 |title=Cultural Responses to Climate Change During the Late Holocene |url=http://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/%7Epeter/Resources/Publications/deMenocal.2001.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=292 |issue=5517 |pages=667–673 |doi=10.1126/science.1059827 |pmid=11303088 |bibcode=2001Sci...292..667D |access-date=2007-10-17 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081217162859/http://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/%7Epeter/Resources/Publications/deMenocal.2001.pdf |archive-date=2008-12-17 |url-status=dead }}
* {{cite journal |author=Diamond, Jared M.  |authorlink=Jared Diamond | date=June 2003 |title=The Last Americans: Environmental Collapse and the End of Civilization |url=http://harpers.org/archive/2003/06/the-last-americans/ |format=online Reprint|journal=[[Harper's Magazine|Harper's]] |volume=306 |issue=1837 |pages=43–51 |issn=0017-789X |oclc=4532730}}
* {{cite journal |title=Impacts of Climate Change on the Collapse of Lowland Maya Civilization|first1=Peter M.J.|last1=Douglas|first2=Arthur A.|last2=Demarest|first3=Mark|last3=Brenner|first4=Marcello A.|last4=Canuto|journal=Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences |date=2 May 2016 |volume= 44 |pages=613–645 |doi=10.1146/annurev-earth-060115-012512|bibcode=2016AREPS..44..613D}}
* {{cite journal |author=Dunning, Nicholas P.   |author2=Sheryl Luzzadder-Beach |author3=Timothy Beach |author4=John G. Jones |author5-link=Vernon Scarborough |author5=Vernon Scarborough |author6=T. Patrick Culbert | date=June 2002 |title=Arising from the ''Bajos'': The Evolution of a Neotropical Landscape and the Rise of Maya Civilization |journal=Annals of the Association of American Geographers |volume=92 |issue=2 |pages=267–283 |doi=10.1111/1467-8306.00290 |oclc=89457939}}
* {{cite journal |title=Quantification of drought during the collapse of the classic Maya civilization|first1=Nicholas P.|last1=Evans|first2=Thomas K.|last2=Bauska|first3=Fernando|last3=Gázquez-Sánchez|first4=Mark|last4=Brenner|first5=Jason H.|last5=Curtis|first6=David A.|last6=Hodell|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |date=3 Aug 2018 |volume= 361 |issue= 6401 |pages=498–501 |doi=10.1126/science.aas9871|pmid=30072537|bibcode=2018Sci...361..498E|hdl=10023/16993|doi-access=free}}
* {{cite book |author=Favier, Jean |author2=Anik Blaise |author3=Serge Cosseron |author4=Jacques Legrand |year=c. 1989 |title=Chronicle of the French Revolution, 1788-1799 |edition=English translation of ''Chronique de la Révolution, 1788–1799'' (1988), Paris:Larousse.   |location=London/New York |publisher=Chronicle Publications, distributed in USA by Prentice Hall |others=Clifton Daniel (series general ed.) |isbn=978-0-13-133729-9 |oclc=19729759}}
* {{cite book |author=Gill, Richardson B.  |year=2000 |title=The Great Maya Droughts: Water, Life, and Death |location=Albuquerque |publisher=[[University of New Mexico Press]] |isbn=978-0-8263-2194-7 |oclc=43567384}}
* {{cite journal |author=Haug, Gerald H.   |author2=Detlef Günther |author3=Larry C. Peterson |author4=Daniel M. Sigman |author5=Konrad A. Hughen |author6=Beat Aeschlimann |date=2003-03-14 |title=Climate and the Collapse of Maya Civilization |url=http://www.climategeology.ethz.ch/people/ghaug/Haug_et_al_2003.pdf &lt;!--http://www.columbia.edu/itc/sipa/envp/louchouarn/courses/Clim-Wat/Wat/Drought-MayanCollapse(AmerSci05).pdf http://www.cornellcollege.edu/geology/courses/greenstein/earth_science/Haug-Collapse%20of%20the%20Maya.pdf http://www.gfz-potsdam.de/pb3/pg33/staff/haug/download/Haug_et_al_2003.pdf--&gt; |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=299 |issue=5613 |pages=1731–1735 |doi=10.1126/science.1080444 |pmid=12637744|bibcode = 2003Sci...299.1731H |author-link=:de:Gerald H. Haug }}
* {{cite journal |last=Hodell |first=David A. |authorlink=David A. Hodell |author2=Curtis, Jason H. |author3=Brenner, Mark  |year=1995 |title=Possible role of climate in the collapse of Classic Maya civilization |journal=Nature |volume=375 |issue=6530 |pages=391–394 |doi=10.1038/375391a0 |url= |accessdate= |quote= |bibcode=1995Natur.375..391H }}
* {{cite journal |last=Hodell |first=David A. |authorlink=David A. Hodell |author2=Brenner, Mark |author3=Curtis, Jason H. |author4= Guilderson, Thomas |date=18 May 2001 |title=Solar Forcing of Drought Frequency in the Maya Lowlands |url=http://mac01.eps.pitt.edu/Courses/GEOL3909/Hodell_et_al_2001.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=292 |issue=5520 |pages=1367–1370 |doi=10.1126/science.1057759 |pmid=11359010 |bibcode=2001Sci...292.1367H |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070813111332/http://mac01.eps.pitt.edu/Courses/GEOL3909/Hodell_et_al_2001.pdf |archivedate=13 August 2007 |citeseerx=10.1.1.586.6815 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Kerr, Richard A. |date=18 May 2001 |title=Paleoclimate: A Variable Sun and the Maya Collapse |url=http://www.geology.ucdavis.edu/~gel108/examples/Example%234.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=292 |issue=5520 |pages=1293 |doi=10.1126/science.292.5520.1293 |pmid=11360980 |access-date=17 October 2007 }}{{dead link|date=October 2019|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}
* {{cite book |author=Longhena, Maria |year=2006 |title=Ancient Mexico: The History and Culture of the Maya, Aztecs, and Other Pre-Columbian Peoples |others=Neil Davenport (trans.) |location=New York |publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble |isbn=978-0-7607-8381-8 |oclc=76818561 |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780760783818 }}
* {{cite book |author=Lucero, Lisa J. |year=2006 |title=Water and Ritual: The Rise and Fall of Classic Maya Rulers |location=Austin |publisher=University of Texas Press |isbn=978-0-292-70999-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/waterritualrisef00luce }}
* {{cite book |author=Mann, Charles C. |authorlink=Charles C. Mann |year=2006 |title=1491: New Revelations of the Americas Before Columbus |location=New York |publisher=Vintage Books |isbn=978-1-4000-3205-1 |oclc=72680543 |url=https://archive.org/details/149100char }}
* {{cite journal |author=Martin, Simon  |authorlink=Simon Martin (Mayanist) |author2=Nikolai Grube |year= 1995 |title=Maya Superstates |journal=[[Archaeology (journal)|Archaeology]] |volume=48 |pages=41–46|location=New York |issue=46}}
* {{cite book |author=McKillop, Heather I. |authorlink=Heather McKillop |year=2006 |title=The Ancient Maya: New Perspectives |location=New York |publisher=[[W.W. Norton]] |isbn=978-0-393-32890-5 |oclc=70170414 |url=https://archive.org/details/ancientmaya00heat }}
* {{cite book |author=Montgomery, John  |year=2002 |title=How to Read Maya Hieroglyphs |location=New York |publisher=Hippocrene Books |isbn=978-0-7818-0861-3 |oclc=47764291}}
* {{cite book |author=Morley, Sylvanus G.  |authorlink=Sylvanus Morley |year=1956 |title=The Ancient Maya |url=https://archive.org/details/ancientmaya0000morl  |url-access=registration  |edition=3rd |location=Stanford, CA |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]] |oclc=484868}}
* {{cite book |author=Olson, Mancur  |year=1982 |title=The Rise and Decline of Nations: Economic Growth, Stagflation, and Social Rigidities |url=https://archive.org/details/risedeclineofn00olso  |url-access=registration  |location=New Haven, CT |publisher=[[Yale University Press]] |isbn=978-0-300-02307-7 |oclc=8451838}}
* {{cite book |author=Prescott, William H.  |authorlink=William H. Prescott |year=1843 |title=History of the Conquest of Mexico, with a Preliminary View of Ancient Mexican Civilization, and the Life of the Conqueror, Hernando Cortes |url=http://etext.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/PreConq.html |format=online reproduction, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Library |location=New York |publisher=Harper and Brothers |oclc=2458166}}
* {{cite book |author=Sabloff, Jeremy A. |authorlink=Jeremy Sabloff |year=1990 |title=The New Archaeology and the Ancient Maya |location=New York |publisher=Scientific American Library, distributed by W.H. Freeman |isbn=978-0-7167-5054-3 |oclc=60170399 |url=https://archive.org/details/newarchaeologyan00sabl }}
* {{cite book |author=Stuart, Gene S. |author2=George E. Stuart |year=1993 |title=Lost Kingdoms of the Maya |location=Washington, DC |publisher=[[National Geographic Society]] |isbn=978-0-87044-928-4 |oclc=27012239 |url=https://archive.org/details/lostkingdomsofma00stua }}
* {{cite book |author=Tainter, Joseph A |authorlink=Joseph A. Tainter |year=2003 |title=The Collapse of Complex Societies |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=M4H-02d9oE0C|place=New York &amp; Cambridge, UK |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-38673-9 |accessdate=11 October 2011}}
* {{cite book |author=Thompson, J. Eric S.  |authorlink=J. Eric S. Thompson|author2=Elizabeth Graham |year=1970 |chapter= Trade Relations Between Maya Highlands and Lowlands |title=Maya History and Religion |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/mayahistoryrelig00thom  |chapter-url-access=registration  |publisher=[[University of Oklahoma Press]] |location=Norman |isbn=978-0-8061-2247-2}}
* {{cite book |author=Toynbee, Arnold J.  |authorlink=Arnold Toynbee |year=1947 |title=A Study of History |edition=1st American, Somervell abridgement |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=New York |oclc=1151071}}
* {{cite book |author=Webster, David L. |year=2002 |title=The Fall of the Ancient Maya: Solving the Mystery of the Maya Collapse |location=London |publisher=Thames and Hudson |isbn=978-0-500-05113-9 |oclc=48753878 |url=https://archive.org/details/fallofancientmay0000webs }}
* {{cite book |author=Weiss, Harvey  |year=1997 |chapter=Late Third Millennium Abrupt Climate Change and Social Collapse in West Asia and Egypt |chapterurl=http://www.zetatalk.com/theword/tword04m.htm |editor=H. Nüzhet Dalfes |editor2=G. Kukla |editor3=Harvey Weiss|title=Third Millennium BC Climate Change and Old World Collapse |location= Heidelberg/Berlin |publisher=Springer Verlag |pages=718–720 |isbn=978-3-540-61892-8 |oclc=35741821}}
* {{cite journal |author=Weiss, Harvey  |author2=Raymond S. Bradley |date=2001-01-26 |title=What Drives Societal Collapse? |url=http://www.geo.umass.edu/faculty/bradley/weiss2001.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprint |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=291 |issue=5504 |pages=609–610 |doi=10.1126/science.1058775 |pmid=11158667}}
* {{cite journal |author=Wilk, Richard R.  |year=1985 |title=The Ancient Maya and the Political Present |journal=Journal of Anthropological Research |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=307–326 |issn=0091-7710 |oclc=1787802 |jstor=3630596|doi=10.1086/jar.41.3.3630596 }}

{{refend}}&lt;!-- END biblio format style --&gt;

{{Maya}}
{{population}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Classic Maya Collapse}}
[[Category:Maya civilization|Collapse]]
[[Category:Maya society|Collapse]]
[[Category:History of Mesoamerica]]
[[Category:History of the Yucatán Peninsula]]
[[Category:Classic period in Mesoamerica]]
[[Category:8th century in the Maya civilization]]
[[Category:9th century in the Maya civilization]]
[[Category:Societal collapse|Maya]]</text>
      <sha1>5dzvsdfoshj7ambioiev5y2e5fo32j3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
