<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>959454807</id>
      <parentid>959424099</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-05-28T21:28:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SMP0328.</username>
        <id>6129137</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Legal challenges */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="101761" xml:space="preserve">{{good article}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Use American English|date = March 2019}}
{{Short description|Grants women the right to vote; prohibiting denial of voting rights on the basis of sex}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2018}}
{{US Constitution article series}}
The '''Nineteenth Amendment''' ('''Amendment XIX''') to the [[United States Constitution]] prohibits the states and the federal government from denying the [[Suffrage|right to vote]] to citizens of the United States on the basis of sex. Initially introduced to [[United States Congress|Congress]] in 1878, several attempts to pass a women's suffrage amendment failed until passing the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] on May 21, 1919, followed by the [[United States Senate|Senate]] on June 4, 1919. It was then submitted to the states for ratification. On August 18, 1920, [[Tennessee]] was the last of the necessary 36 states to secure ratification. The Nineteenth Amendment was officially [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Ratification of amendments|adopted]] on August 26, 1920: the culmination of a decades-long movement for [[Women's suffrage in the United States|women's suffrage]] at both state and national levels.

Prior to 1776, women had the right to vote in several of the [[Thirteen Colonies|colonies]] in what would become the United States, but by 1807 every state constitution denied even limited suffrage. Organizations supporting [[women's rights]] became more active in the mid-nineteenth century and, in 1848, the [[Seneca Falls Convention|Seneca Falls convention]] adopted the [[Declaration of Sentiments]], which called for equality between the sexes and included a resolution urging women to secure the vote. Pro-suffrage organizations used a variety of tactics including legal arguments that relied on existing amendments. After those arguments were struck down by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]], suffrage organizations, with activists like [[Susan B. Anthony]] and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], called for a new constitutional amendment that would guarantee women the right to vote.

By the late nineteenth century, new states and territories, particularly in the [[Western United States|West]], began to grant women the right to vote. In 1878, a suffrage proposal that would eventually become the Nineteenth Amendment was introduced to Congress, but it was rejected in 1887. In the 1890s, suffrage organizations focused on a national amendment while still working at the state and local levels. [[Lucy Burns]] and [[Alice Paul]] emerged as important leaders whose different strategies helped move the Nineteenth Amendment forward. Entry of the United States into [[World War I]] helped to shift public perception of women's suffrage. The [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]], led by [[Carrie Chapman Catt]], supported the war effort, making the case that women should be rewarded with enfranchisement for their patriotic wartime service. The [[National Woman's Party]] staged marches, demonstrations, and hunger strikes while pointing out the contradictions of fighting abroad for democracy while limiting it at home by denying women the right to vote. The work of both organizations swayed public opinion, prompting President Wilson to announce his support of the suffrage amendment in 1918. It passed in 1919 and was adopted in 1920, withstanding two legal challenges, ''[[Leser v. Garnett]]'' and ''[[Fairchild v. Hughes]]''.

The Nineteenth Amendment enfranchised 26 million American women in time for the [[1920 U.S. Presidential election|1920 U.S. presidential election]], but the powerful women's voting bloc that many politicians feared failed to fully materialize until decades later. As well, the Nineteenth Amendment failed to fully enfranchise African American, Asian American, Hispanic American, and Native American women. Shortly after the amendment's adoption, Alice Paul and the National Woman's Party began work on the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], which they believed a necessary additional step to ensure equality.

==Text==
[[File:19th Amendment Pg1of1 AC.jpg|upright=0.8|thumb|The Nineteenth Amendment in the [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]]]]
{{quote|The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex.&lt;br/&gt;
Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/amendmentxix|title=19th Amendment|website=LII / Legal Information Institute|language=en|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Background==
=== Early woman suffrage efforts (1776&amp;ndash;1865) ===
{{main|Women's suffrage in the United States}}
[[File:Women's Rights Convention -WomensMarch -WomensMarch2018 -SenecaFalls -NY (28029155839).jpg|thumb|left|Text of the small ad that attracted a wide and diverse meeting of women and men at the first Women's Rights Convention, held in Seneca Falls, NY during July 1848|alt=]]
The [[United States Constitution]], adopted in 1789, left the boundaries of [[suffrage]] undefined. The only directly elected body created under the original Constitution was the [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. House of Representatives]], for which voter qualifications were explicitly delegated to the individual states.{{refn|group="note"|name="Article1"|1=U.S. Constitution, Article I, Section 2, states, in part: "the electors in each state shall have the qualifications requisite for electors of the most numerous branch of the state legislature"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title =1st Amendment|publisher =Legal Information Institute, Cornell University School of Law|url =https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/articlei|accessdate =May 31, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} While women had the right to vote in several of the pre-revolutionary colonies in what would become the United States, after 1776, with the exception of [[New Jersey]], all states adopted constitutions that denied voting rights to women. New Jersey's constitution initially granted suffrage to property-holding residents, including single and married women, but the state rescinded women's voting rights in 1807 and did not restore them until New Jersey ratified the Nineteenth Amendment in 1920.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| author=Nenadic, Susan L. | title =Votes for Women: Suffrage in Michigan | journal =Michigan History | volume =103 | issue =3 | page =18 | publisher =Historical Society of Michigan | location =Lansing, Michigan | date = May 2019| url =| accessdate =}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While scattered movements and organizations dedicated to women's rights existed previously, the 1848 [[Seneca Falls Convention]] in [[New York (state)|New York]] is traditionally held as the start of the American women's rights movement. Attended by nearly 300 women and men, the convention was designed to "discuss the social, civil, and religious rights of women", and culminated in the adoption of the [[Declaration of Sentiments]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Right to Vote: The Contested History of Democracy in the United States |last=Keyssar |first=Alexander |publisher=Basic Books|year=2000|isbn=|location=New York|pages=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; Signed by 68 women and 32 men, the ninth of the document's twelve resolved clauses reads, "Resolved, That it is the duty of the women of this country to secure to themselves their sacred right to the elective franchise."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/resource/rbcmil.scrp4006702/?sp=8|title=Image 8 of Report of the Woman's Rights Convention, held at Seneca Falls, New York, July 19th and 20th, 1848. Proceedings and Declaration of Sentiments|website=Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540 USA|access-date=2019-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conveners [[Lucretia Mott]] and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] became key early leaders in the U.S. women's suffrage movement, often referred to at the time as the "woman suffrage movement".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Woman Suffrage and Women's Rights|last=DuBois|first=Ellen Carol|date=1998|publisher=New York University Press|isbn=978-0585434711|location=New York|oclc=51232208}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/history/2019/06/03/women-color-were-cut-out-suffragist-story-historians-say-its-time-reckoning/|title=Women of color were cut out of the suffragist story. Historians say it's time for a reckoning|last=Weber|first=Liz|date=June 3, 2019|website=The Washington Post|access-date=June 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mott's support of women's suffrage stemmed from as summer spent with the Seneca Nation, one of the six tribes in the Iroquois Confederacy, where women had significant political power, including the right to choose and remove chiefs and veto acts of war.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2016/11/24/millions-of-women-voted-for-hillary-clinton-they-have-the-iroquois-to-thank/|title=Millions of women voted this election. They have the Iroquois to thank.|last=Nordell|first=Jessica|date=November 24, 2016|website=Washington Post|access-date=June 5, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Activism addressing federal women's suffrage was minimal during the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]. In 1865, at the conclusion of the war, a "Petition for Universal Suffrage", signed by Elizabeth Cady Stanton and [[Susan B. Anthony]], among others, called for a national constitutional amendment to "prohibit the several states from disenfranchising any of their citizens on the ground of sex".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://catalog.archives.gov/id/26081744|title=Petition for Universal Suffrage which Asks for an Amendment to the Constitution that Shall Prohibit the Several States from Disenfranchising Any of Their Citizens on the Ground of Sex|author=United States Senate|website=National Archives Catalog|publisher=National Archives and Records Administration|accessdate=July 29, 2016|year=1865|series=File Unit: Petitions and Memorials, Resolutions of State Legislatures which were Presented, Read, or Tabled during the 39th Congress, 1865 - 1867}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign was the first national petition drive to feature woman suffrage among its demands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/legislative/features/suffrage|title=Universal Suffrage|date=2016-08-15|website=National Archives|language=en|access-date=2019-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; While suffrage bills were introduced into many state legislatures during this period, they were generally disregarded and few came to a vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Banaszak|1996|pp=5–6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Reconstruction Amendments and woman suffrage (1865&amp;ndash;1877) ===
[[File:Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony.jpg|thumb|upright=.8|[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] (seated) with [[Susan B. Anthony]] (standing)|alt=]]
The women's suffrage movement, delayed by the American Civil War, resumed activities during the [[Reconstruction era]] (1865–1877). Two rival suffrage organizations formed in 1869: the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]] (NWSA), led by suffrage leaders Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony, and the [[American Woman Suffrage Association]] (AWSA), led by [[Lucy Stone]].&lt;ref name="banaszak-6-7" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mintz-47"&gt;{{cite journal| author=Mintz, Steven | title =The Passage of the Nineteenth Amendment | journal =OAH Magazine of History | volume =21 | issue =3 | page =47 | publisher = Organization of American Historians | date =July 2007| url =| accessdate =| doi =10.1093/maghis/21.3.47 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The NWSA's main effort was lobbying Congress for a women's suffrage amendment to the U.S. Constitution. The AWSA generally focused on a long-term effort of state campaigns to achieve women's suffrage on a state-by-state basis.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=307}}

During the Reconstruction era, women's rights leaders advocated for inclusion of universal suffrage as a civil right in the [[Reconstruction Amendments]] (the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth]], [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]], and [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifteenth]] Amendments). Some unsuccessfully argued that the Fifteenth Amendment, which prohibited denying voting rights "on account of race, color, or previous condition of servitude",&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/founding-docs|title=America's Founding Documents|date=2015-10-30|website=National Archives|language=en|access-date=2019-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; implied suffrage for women.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Despite their efforts, these amendments did not enfranchise women.&lt;ref name="banaszak-6-7"&gt;{{harvnb|Banaszak|1996|pp=6–7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="mead-2"&gt;{{harvnb|Mead|2004|p=2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Section 2 of the Fourteenth Amendment explicitly discriminated between men and women by only penalizing states which deprived adult male citizens of the vote.{{refn|group="note"|name="14thAmendment"|1=U.S. Constitution, Fourteenth Amendment, Section 2, states, in part: "But when the right to vote at any election for the choice of electors for President and Vice President of the United States, Representatives in Congress, the Executive and Judicial officers of a State, or the members of the Legislature thereof, is denied to any of the '''male''' inhabitants of such State, being twenty-one years of age, and citizens of the United States, or in any way abridged, except for participation in rebellion, or other crime, the basis of representation therein shall be reduced in the proportion which the number of such male citizens shall bear to the whole number of male citizens twenty-one years of age in such State." (emphasis added)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| author=| title =14th Amendment | publisher = Legal Information Institute, Cornell University School of Law  | date = | url =https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/amendmentxiv | format = | accessdate =May 31, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The NWSA attempted several unsuccessful court challenges in the mid-1870s.&lt;ref name="banaszak-8"&gt;{{harvnb|Banaszak|1996|p=8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Their legal argument, known as the "New Departure" strategy, contended that the Fourteenth Amendment (granting universal citizenship) and Fifteenth Amendment (granting the vote irrespective of race) together guaranteed voting rights to women.&lt;ref name=Mead-35-38&gt;{{harvnb|Mead|2004|pp=35–38}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] rejected this argument. In ''[[Bradwell v. Illinois]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|83|130|1873}}&lt;/ref&gt; the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that the [[Supreme Court of Illinois]]'s refusal to grant [[Myra Bradwell]] a license to practice law was not a violation of the U.S. Constitution and refused to extend federal authority in support of women's citizenship rights.{{refn|group="note"|name="Bradwell"|1=Illinois courts denied Myra Bradwell's application to practice law in that state because she was a married women and due to her marital status she could not be bound by legal contracts she made with her clients.{{sfn|Baker|2009|p=3}}}} In ''[[Minor v. Happersett]]'' &lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|88|162|1874}}&lt;/ref&gt; the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that the [[Privileges or Immunities Clause]] of the Fourteenth Amendment did not provide voting rights to U.S. citizens; it only guaranteed additional protection of privileges to citizens who already had them. If a state constitution limited suffrage to male citizens of the United States, then women in that state did not have voting rights.{{sfn|Baker|2009|p=3}} After U.S. Supreme Court decisions between 1873 and 1875 denied voting rights to women in connection with the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments, suffrage groups shifted their efforts to advocating for a new constitutional amendment.&lt;ref name=Mead-35-38/&gt;

Continued settlement of the [[American Old West|western frontier]], along with the [[Territorial evolution of the United States|establishment of territorial constitutions]], allowed the women's suffrage issue to be raised as the western territories progressed toward statehood. Through the activism of suffrage organizations and independent political parties, women's suffrage was included in the constitutions of [[Wyoming Territory]] (1869) and [[Utah Territory]] (1870).&lt;ref name="mead-2"/&gt;{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=333}} Women's suffrage in Utah was revoked in 1887, when Congress passed the [[Edmunds-Tucker Act]] in 1887 that also prohibited [[polygamy]]; it was not restored in [[Utah]] until it achieved statehood in 1896.&lt;ref name=Mintz-47/&gt;{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=333}}

=== Post-Reconstruction (1878&amp;ndash;1910) ===
[[File:Elizabeth Cady Stanton before the Senate Committee on Privileges and Elections cph.3b08655.jpg|thumb|left|[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] before the Senate Committee on Privileges and Elections. ''New York Daily Graphic'', January 16, 1878, p. 501|alt=]]
Existing state legislatures in the West, as well as those east of the [[Mississippi River]], began to consider suffrage bills in the 1870s and 1880s. Several held voter referendums, but they were unsuccessful&lt;ref name="banaszak-8"/&gt; until the suffrage movement was revived in the 1890s. Full women's suffrage continued in [[Wyoming]] after it became a state in 1890. [[Colorado]] granted partial voting rights that allowed women to vote in school board elections in 1893 and Idaho granted women suffrage in 1896. Beginning with [[Washington (state)|Washington]] in 1910, seven more western states passed women's suffrage legislation, including [[California]] in 1911, [[Oregon]], [[Arizona]], and [[Kansas]] in 1912, [[Territory of Alaska|Alaska Territory]] in 1913, and [[Montana]] and [[Nevada]] in 1914. All states that were successful in securing full voting rights for women before 1920 were located in the West.&lt;ref name=Mintz-47/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author =Myres, Sandra L. | title =Westering Women and the Frontier Experience | publisher =University of New Mexico Press | series = | volume = | edition = | year =1982 | location =Albuquerque | pages =[https://archive.org/details/westeringwomenfr00myre/page/227 227]–30 | url =https://archive.org/details/westeringwomenfr00myre | url-access =registration | isbn =9780826306258 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A federal amendment intended to grant women the right to vote was introduced in the [[United States Senate|U.S. Senate]] for the first time in 1878 by [[Aaron A. Sargent]], a Senator from California who was a women's suffrage advocate.&lt;ref name="mead-38"&gt;{{Harvnb|Mead|2004|p=38}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Stanton and other women testified before the Senate in support of the amendment.&lt;ref name="Amar 2005"&gt;{{Harvnb|Amar|2005|pp=421}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The proposal sat in a committee until it was considered by the full Senate and rejected in a 16-to-34 vote in 1887.&lt;ref name="Kobach 94"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/conlaw/nineteenthkobach.html|title=Woman suffrage and the Nineteenth Amendment|last=Kobach|first=Kris|date=May 1994|publisher=[[University of Missouri–Kansas City School of Law]]|access-date=February 2, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101110051358/http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/conlaw/nineteenthkobach.html|archive-date=November 10, 2010|url-status=dead}} See also: Excerpt from {{cite journal|last=Kobach|first=Kris|date=May 1994|title=Rethinking Article V: term limits and the Seventeenth and Nineteenth Amendments|journal=[[Yale Law Journal]]|publisher=[[Yale Law School]]|volume=103|issue=7|pages=1971–2007|doi=10.2307/797019|jstor=797019|url=https://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7556&amp;context=ylj}}&lt;/ref&gt; An amendment proposed in 1888 in the U.S. House of Representatives called for limited suffrage for women who were spinsters or widows who owned property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=United States House of Representatives|title=House Joint Resolution (H.J. Res.) 159, Proposing an Amendment to the Constitution to Extend the Right to Vote to Widows and Spinsters who are Property Holders|url=https://catalog.archives.gov/id/25466157|website=National Archives Catalog|publisher=National Archives and Records Administration|accessdate=July 25, 2016|date=April 30, 1888|series=File Unit: Bills and Resolutions Originating in the House of Representatives during the 50th Congress, 1885 - 1887}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 1890s, suffrage leaders began to recognize the need to broaden their base of support to achieve success in passing suffrage legislation at the national, state, and local levels. While western women, state suffrage organizations, and the AWSA concentrated on securing women's voting rights for specific states, efforts at the national level persisted through a strategy of congressional testimony, petitioning, and lobbying.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|pp=325-326}}{{sfn|Banaszak|1996|pp=133–134}} After the AWSA and NWSA merged in 1890 to form the [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]] (NAWSA), the group directed its efforts to win state-level support for suffrage.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=334}} Suffragists had to campaign publicly for the vote in order to convince male voters, state legislators, and members of Congress that American women wanted to be enfranchised and that women voters would benefit American society. Suffrage supporters also had to convince American women, many of whom were indifferent to the issue, that suffrage was something they wanted. Apathy among women was an ongoing obstacle that the suffragists had to overcome through organized grassroots efforts.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=327}} Despite the suffragists' efforts, no state granted women suffrage between 1896 and 1910, and the NAWSA shifted its focus toward passage of a national constitutional amendment.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=334}} Suffragists also continued to press for the right to vote in individual states and territories while retaining the goal of federal recognition.&lt;ref name="Kobach 94" /&gt;

=== African-American woman suffrage efforts ===
[[File:Mary church terrell.jpg|thumb|upright=.8|Suffragist and civil rights activist [[Mary Church Terrell]]|alt=]]
{{Main|African-American women's suffrage movement}}
Thousands of African-American women were active in the suffrage movement, addressing issues of race, gender, and class, as well as enfranchisement,&lt;ref name=":18"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2019/04/23/its-time-return-black-women-center-history-womens-suffrage/|title=Perspective {{!}} It's time to return black women to the center of the history of women's suffrage|website=Washington Post|language=en|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; often through the church but eventually through organizations devoted to specific causes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.blacksuffragette.com/the-church|title=The Black Church|website=The Black Suffragist}}&lt;/ref&gt; While white women sought the vote to gain an equal voice in the political process, African-American women often sought the vote as a means of racial uplift and as a way to effect change in the post-Reconstruction era.&lt;ref name=":19" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Goodier|first=S.|last2=Pastorello|first2=K.|date=2017|chapter=A Fundamental Component: Suffrage for African American Women|title=Women Will Vote: Winning Suffrage in New York State|pp=71–91|location=ITHACA; LONDON|publisher=Cornell University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable African-American suffragists such as [[Mary Church Terrell]], [[Sojourner Truth]], [[Frances Harper|Frances Ellen Watkins Harper]], [[Fannie Barrier Williams]], and [[Ida B. Wells|Ida B. Wells-Barnett]] advocated for suffrage in tandem with civil rights for African-Americans.&lt;ref name=":18" /&gt;

As early as 1866, in Philadelphia, [[Margaretta Forten]] and [[Harriet Forten Purvis]] helped to found the [[Philadelphia Suffrage Association]]; Purvis would go on to serve on the executive committee of the [[American Equal Rights Association]] (AERA), an organization that supported suffrage for women and for African-American men.&lt;ref name=":21"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nps.gov/articles/african-american-women-and-the-nineteenth-amendment.htm|title=African American Women and the Nineteenth Amendment (U.S. National Park Service)|website=nps.gov|language=en|access-date=2019-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; A national movement in support of suffrage for African-American women began in earnest with the rise of the black women's club movement.&lt;ref name=":19" /&gt; In 1896, club women belonging to various organizations promoting women's suffrage met in Washington, D.C. to form the [[National Association of Colored Women]], of which [[Frances E.W. Harper]], [[Josephine St. Pierre Ruffin|Josephine St. Pierre]], [[Harriet Tubman]], and Ida B. Wells Barnett were founding members.&lt;ref name=":24"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.blacksuffragette.com/nacwc-2|title=A National Association for Colored Women|website=The Black Suffragist}}&lt;/ref&gt; Led by [[Mary Church Terrell]], it was the largest federation of African-American women's clubs in the nation.&lt;ref name=":19" /&gt; After 1914 it became the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/National-Association-of-Colored-Womens-Clubs|title=National Association of Colored Women's Clubs|website=Britannica.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Nannie Burroughs, Woman's National Baptist Convention.jpg|thumb|left|Nannie Helen Burroughs holding a Woman's National Baptist Convention banner]]
When the Fifteenth Amendment enfranchised African-American men, Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony abandoned the AERA, which supported universal suffrage, to found the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]] in 1869, stating that black men should not receive the vote before white women.&lt;ref name=":21" /&gt; In response, African-American suffragist [[Frances Harper|Frances Ellen Watkins Harper]] and others joined the [[American Woman Suffrage Association]], which supported suffrage for women and for black men. [[Mary Ann Shadd Cary]], the second African-American woman to receive a degree from Howard University Law School, joined the National Woman Suffrage Association in 1878 when she delivered their convention's keynote address.&lt;ref name=":23"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.blacksuffragette.com|title=SISTERHOOD: The Black Suffragist: Trailblazers of Social Justice -- A Documentary Film|website=The Black Suffragist}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tensions between African-American and white suffragists persisted, even after the NWSA and AWSA merged to form the [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]] in 1890.&lt;ref name=":21" /&gt; By the early 1900s, white suffragists often adopted strategies designed to appease the Southern states at the expense of African-American women.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; At conventions in 1901 and 1903, in Atlanta and New Orleans, NAWSA prevented African Americans from attending. At the 1911 national NAWSA conference, [[Martha Gruening]] asked the organization to formally denounce white supremacy. NAWSA president [[Anna Howard Shaw]] refused, saying that she was “in favor of colored people voting,” but did not want to alienate others in the suffrage movement.&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.womenshistory.org/articles/votes-women-means-votes-black-women|title=Votes for Women means Votes for Black Women|website=National Women's History Museum|language=en|access-date=2019-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even NAWSA's more radical Congressional Committee, which would become the [[National Woman's Party]], failed African-American women, most visibly by refusing to allow them to march in the nation's first suffrage parade in Washington, D.C.  While the NAWSA directed Paul not to exclude African-American participants, 72 hours before the parade African-American women were directed to the back of the parade; [[Ida B. Wells]] defied these instructions and joined the Illinois unit, prompting telegrams of support.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;

[[Mary Burnett Talbert|Mary B. Talbert]], a leader in both the NACW and [[NAACP]], and [[Nannie Helen Burroughs]], an educator and activist, contributed to an issue of the ''Crisis'', published by [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] in August, 1915.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt; They wrote passionately about African-American women's need for the vote. Burroughs, asked what women could do with the ballot, responded pointedly: “What can she do without it?” &lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;

==Proposal and ratification==
=== A new focus on a federal amendment ===
[[File:Carrie Chapman Catt - National Woman's Party Records.jpg|thumb|upright=.8|[[Carrie Chapman Catt]], President of the National American Woman Suffrage Association, organized the "Winning Plan" that helped secure passage of the Nineteenth Amendment.]]
In 1900, [[Carrie Chapman Catt]] succeeded Susan B. Anthony as the president of the National American Woman Suffrage Association. Catt revitalized NAWSA, turning the focus of the organization to the passage of the federal amendment while simultaneously supporting women who wanted to pressure their states to pass suffrage legislation. The strategy, which she later called "The Winning Plan", had several goals: women in states that had already granted presidential suffrage (the right to vote for the [[President of the United States|President]]) would focus on passing a federal suffrage amendment; women who believed they could influence their state legislatures would focus on amending their state constitutions and Southern states would focus on gaining primary suffrage (the right to vote in state primaries).&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Simultaneously, the NAWSA worked to elect congressmen who supported suffrage for women.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Embattled Vote in America: From the Founding to the Present|last=Lichtman|first=Allan J.|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=2018|isbn=9780674972360|location=Cambridge, MA|pages=120}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1915, NAWSA was a large, powerful organization, with 44 state chapters and over 2 million members.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://suffragistmemorial.org/carrie-chapman-catt-1859-1947/|title=Carrie Chapman Catt (1859-1947) {{!}} Turning Point Suffragist Memorial|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a break with NAWSA, [[Alice Paul]] and [[Lucy Burns]] founded the Congressional Union for Women Suffrage in 1913 to pressure the federal government to take legislative action. One of their first acts was to organize a [[Woman suffrage parade of 1913|women's suffrage parade]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] on March 3, 1913, the day before [[Woodrow Wilson]]'s inauguration. The procession of more than 5,000 participants, the first of its kind, attracted a crowd of an estimated 500,000, as well as national media attention, but Wilson took no immediate action. In March 1917, the Congressional Union joined with Women's Party of Western Voters to form the [[National Woman's Party]] (NWP), whose aggressive tactics included staging more radical acts of civil disobedience and controversial demonstrations to draw more attention to the women's suffrage issue.&lt;ref name="Ault"&gt;{{cite web| author=Ault, Alicia | title =How Women Got the Vote Is a Far More Complex Story Than the History Textbooks Reveal | website = | publisher =Smithsonian.com | date =April 9, 2019 | url = https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/how-women-got-vote-far-more-complex-story-history-textbooks-reveal-180971869/ | format = | accessdate =May 15, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Woman suffrage and World War I patriotism===
[[File:Women suffragists picketing in front of the White house.jpg|thumb|left|"Silent sentinels" begin a 2 1/2 year campaign in front of the White House (1917)]]
When [[World War I]] started in 1914, women in eight states had already won the right to vote, but support for a federal amendment was still tepid. The war provided a new urgency to the fight for the vote. When the U.S. entered World War I, Catt made the controversial decision to support the war effort, despite the widespread pacifist sentiment of many of her colleagues and supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Evans, Sara M. | title =Born for Liberty: A History of Women in America | publisher =The Free Press | series = | volume = | edition = | year =1989 | location =New York | pages =164–72 | url =  | isbn =| author-link =Sara M. Evans }}&lt;/ref&gt; As women joined the labor force to replace men serving in the military and took visible positions as nurses, relief workers, and ambulance drivers&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.army.mil/article/192727/how_world_war_i_helped_give_us_women_the_right_to_vote |title=How World War I helped give US women the right to vote |website=army.mil |language=en |access-date=2019-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; to support the war effort, NAWSA organizers argued that women's sacrifices made them deserving of the vote. By contrast, the NWP used the war to point out the contradictions of fighting for democracy abroad while restricting it at home.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; In 1917, the NWP began picketing the White House to bring attention to the cause of women's suffrage.

In 1914 the constitutional amendment proposed by Sargent, which was nicknamed the "Susan B. Anthony Amendment", was once again considered by the Senate, where it was again rejected.&lt;ref name="Kobach 94" /&gt; In April 1917 the "Anthony Amendment," which eventually became the Nineteenth Amendment, was reintroduced in the U.S. House and Senate. Picketing NWP members, nicknamed the "Silent Sentinels", continued their protests on the sidewalks outside the White House. On July 4, 1917, police arrested 168 of the protesters, who were sent to prison in Lorton, Virginia. Some of these women, including Lucy Burns and Alice Paul, went on hunger strikes; some were force fed while others were otherwise harshly treated by prison guards. The release of the women a few months later was largely due to increasing public pressure.&lt;ref name="Ault" /&gt;

===Final congressional challenges===
[[File:Allender President Wilson says 1917 (cropped).jpg|thumb|upright=.8|[[Nina E. Allender|Nina Allender]] political cartoon aimed at President Wilson published in ''[[The Suffragist]]'' on October 3, 1917|alt=]]
In 1918, President Wilson faced a difficult midterm election and would have to confront the issue of women's suffrage directly.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; Fifteen states had extended equal voting rights to women and, by this time, the President fully supported the federal amendment.&lt;ref name="Christine Stansell 2011, pp 171-174"&gt;[[Christine Stansell]]. ''The Feminist Promise''. New York: The Modern Library, 2011, pp. 171–174.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Nineteenth-Amendment|title=Nineteenth Amendment {{!}} History &amp; Facts|website=Encyclopedia Britannica|language=en|access-date=2019-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; A proposal brought before the House in January 1918 passed by only one vote. The vote was then carried into the Senate where Wilson made an appeal on the Senate floor, an unprecedented action at the time.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lunardini|first=C.|last2=Knock|first2=T.|date=1980|title=Woodrow Wilson and Woman Suffrage: A New Look|journal=Political Science Quarterly|volume=95|issue=4|pages=655–671|doi=10.2307/2150609|jstor=2150609}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a short speech, the President tied women's right to vote directly to the war, asking, "Shall we admit them only to a partnership of suffering and sacrifice and toil and not to a partnership of privilege and right?"&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; On September 30, 1918, the proposal fell two votes short of passage, prompting the NWP to direct campaigning against senators who had voted against the amendment.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt;

Between January 1918 and June 1919, the House and Senate voted on the federal amendment five times.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://history.house.gov/Historical-Highlights/1901-1950/The-House-s-1918-passage-of-a-constitutional-amendment-granting-women-the-right-to-vote/|title=The House's 1918 Passage of a Constitutional Amendment Granting Women the Right to Vote {{!}} US House of Representatives: History, Art &amp; Archives|website=history.house.gov|language=en|access-date=2019-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each vote was extremely close and [[Southern Democrats]] continued to oppose giving women the vote.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; Suffragists pressured President Wilson to call a special session of Congress and he agreed to schedule one for May 19, 1919. On May 21, 1919, the amendment passed the House 304 to 89, with 42 votes more than was necessary.&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Winning the Vote: the Triumph of the American Woman Suffrage Movement|last=Cooney, Jr.|first=Robert P. J.|publisher=American Graphic Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0977009503|location=Santa Cruz, CA|pages=408–427}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 4, 1919, it was brought before the Senate and, after Southern Democrats abandoned a [[filibuster]],&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; 37 Republican Senators were joined by 19 Democrats to pass the amendment with 56 ayes and 25 nays.  Ultimately, 76% of Republican Senators voted in favor, while 60% of Democrat Senators voted against.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/minute/Senate_Passes_Woman_Suffrage_Amendment.htm|title=U.S. Senate: The Senate Passes the Woman Suffrage Amendment|website=senate.gov|access-date=2019-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ratification ===
[[File:JudgeMagazine25Oct1919.jpg|thumb|left|''"The Big Issue At The Polls"'' (''[[Judge (magazine)|Judge]]'', 25 Oct 1919)]]
[[File:Map of US Suffrage, 1920.svg|thumb|upright=1.6|Highest level of women's suffrage laws just before adoption of the Nineteenth Amendment:&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://idserver.utk.edu/?id=200700000001602|title=Out of Subjection Into Freedom|first=Marjorie|last=Shuler|journal=The Woman Citizen|page=360|date=September 4, 1920}}{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Right to Vote|first=Alexander|last=Keyssar|isbn=978-0-465-02969-3|date=August 15, 2001|url=https://archive.org/details/righttovote00alex}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{legend|#4575b4|Full suffrage}}
{{legend|#74add1|Presidential suffrage}}
{{legend|#abd9e9|Primary suffrage}}
{{legend|#e0f3f8|Municipal suffrage}}
{{legend|#fee090|School, bond, or tax suffrage}}
{{legend|#fdae61|Municipal suffrage in some cities}}
{{legend|#f46d43|Primary suffrage in some cities}}
{{legend|#d73027|No suffrage}}]]

Carrie Chapman Catt and Alice Paul immediately mobilized members of the NAWSA and NWP to pressure states to ratify the amendment. Within a few days, [[Illinois]], [[Wisconsin]], and [[Michigan]] did so, their legislatures being in session. By July, [[Montana]], [[Arkansas]], and [[Nebraska]] had approved ratification.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt; In other states support proved more difficult to secure. Much of the opposition to the amendment came from Southern Democrats; only one southern state ([[Texas]]) and four border states had voted for ratification.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; [[Alabama]] and [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] were the first states to defeat ratification. The governor of [[Louisiana]] worked to organize 13 states to resist ratifying the amendment. The [[Maryland]] legislature refused to ratify the amendment and attempted to prevent other states from doing so. Carrie Catt began appealing to Western governors, encouraging them to act swiftly. By the end of 1919, a total of 22 states had ratified the amendment.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt;
[[File:Anti-suffrage postcard- Suffragists on the warpath.jpg|thumb|left|Anti-suffrage postcard: ''Suffragists on the War Path'']]
Resistance to ratification took many forms: [[Anti-suffragism|anti-suffragists]] continued to state that the amendment would never be approved by the November, 1920 elections and that special sessions were a waste of time and effort. Other opponents to ratification filed lawsuits requiring the federal amendment to be approved by state referendums. By June, 1920, after intense lobbying by both the NAWSA and the NWP, the amendment was ratified by 35 of the necessary 36 state legislatures.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt; Ratification would be determined by [[Tennessee]].
In the middle of July, 1919, both opponents and supporters of the Anthony Amendment arrived in Nashville to lobby the General Assembly. Carrie Catt, representing the NAWSA, worked with state suffragist leaders, including [[Anne Dallas Dudley]] and [[Abby Crawford Milton]]. [[Sue Shelton White]], a Tennessee native who had participated in protests at the White House and toured with the [[Prison Special]], represented the NWP.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jones|first=Robert B., and Mark E. Byrnes|date=Fall 2009|title=The "Bitterest Fight": The Tennessee General Assembly and the Nineteenth Amendment|journal=Tennessee Historical Quarterly|volume=68|issue=3|pages=270–295|jstor=42628623}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opposing them were the "Antis", in particular, [[Josephine Pearson]], state president of the Southern Women's Rejection League of the Susan. B. Anthony Amendment, who had served as dean and chair of philosophy at Christian College in Columbia.&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Woman's Hour: The Great Fight to Win the Vote|last=Weiss|first=Elaine|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2018|isbn=9780143128991|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pearson was assisted by [[Anne Ector Pleasant|Anne Pleasant]], president of the Louisiana Women's Rejection League and the wife of a former Louisiana governor. Especially in the South, the question of women's suffrage was closely tied to issues of race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| author=Goodstein, A.| title =A Rare Alliance: African American and White Women in the Tennessee Elections of 1919 and 1920 | journal =The Journal of Southern History | volume =64 | issue =2 | pages =219–46 | year=1998| url =| accessdate = |doi=10.2307/2587945| jstor =2587945 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; While both white and African-American women worked toward women's suffrage, some white suffragists tried to appease southern states by arguing that votes for women could counter the black vote, strengthening white supremacy.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; For the anti-suffragists in the south (the "Antis"), the federal amendment was viewed as a "Force Bill", one that Congress could use to enforce voting provisions not only for women, but for African-American men who were still effectively disenfranchised even after passage of the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments. Carrie Catt warned suffrage leaders in Tennessee that the "Anti-Suffs" would rely on "lies, innuendoes, and near truths", raising the issue of race as a powerful factor in their arguments.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;
[[File:Opposed to suffrage.jpg|left|thumb|Headquarters of the anti-suffragist [[National Association Opposed to Woman Suffrage]]]]
Prior to the start of the General Assembly session on August 9, both supporters and opponents had lobbied members of the Tennessee Senate and House of Representatives. Though the Democratic governor of Tennessee, [[Albert H. Roberts]], supported ratification, most lawmakers were still undecided. Anti-suffragists targeted members, meeting their trains as they arrived in Nashville to make their case. When the General Assembly convened on August 9, both supporters and opponents set up stations outside of chambers, handing out yellow roses to suffrage supporters and red roses to the "Antis". On August 12, the legislature held hearings on the suffrage proposal; the next day the Senate voted 24-5 in favor of ratification. As the House prepared to take up the issue of ratification on August 18, lobbying intensified.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; House Speaker [[Seth M. Walker]] attempted to table the ratification resolution, but was defeated twice with a vote of 48-48. The vote on the resolution would be close. Representative [[Harry T. Burn|Harry Burn]], a Republican, had voted to table the resolution both times. When the vote was held again, Burn voted yes. The 24-year-old said he supported women's suffrage as a "moral right", but had voted against it because he believed his constituents opposed it. In the final minutes before the vote, he received a note from his mother, urging him to vote yes. Rumors immediately circulated that Burn and other lawmakers had been bribed, but newspaper reporters found no evidence of this.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt;

The same day that ratification passed in the General Assembly, Speaker Walker filed a motion to reconsider. When it became clear that he did not have enough votes to carry the motion, representatives opposing suffrage boarded a train, fleeing Nashville for Decatur, Alabama to block the House from taking action on the reconsideration motion by preventing a quorum. Thirty-seven legislators fled to Decatur, issuing a statement that ratifying the amendment would violate their oath to defend the state constitution.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; The ploy failed. Speaker Walker was unable to muster any additional votes in the allotted time. When the House reconvened to take the final procedural steps that would reaffirm ratification, Tennessee suffragists seized an opportunity to taunt the missing Anti delegates by sitting at their empty desks. When ratification was finally confirmed, a suffragist on the floor of the House rang a miniature Liberty Bell.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;

On August 18, 1920, Tennessee narrowly approved the Nineteenth Amendment, with 50 of 99 members of the [[Tennessee House of Representatives]] voting yes.&lt;ref name="Christine Stansell 2011, pp 171-174" /&gt;&lt;ref name="VanWest 1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Van West|1998}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon signing the ratification certificate, the Governor of Tennessee sent it by registered mail to the U.S. Secretary of State [[Bainbridge Colby]], whose office received it at 4:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. on August 26, 1920. Once certified as correct, Colby signed the Proclamation of the Women's Suffrage Amendment to the U.S. Constitution in the presence of his secretary only, making the Nineteenth Amendment officially law as of that date.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Nineteenth Amendment: Women's Right to Vote|last=Monroe|first=Judy|publisher=Ensloe Publishers, Inc.|year=1998|isbn=978-0-89490-922-1|location=Berkeley Heights, NJ|pages=[https://archive.org/details/nineteenthamendm00monr/page/77 77]|url=https://archive.org/details/nineteenthamendm00monr/page/77}}&lt;/ref&gt; This provided the final ratification necessary to add the amendment to the Constitution,&lt;ref name="Hakim 1995"&gt;{{Harvnb|Hakim|1995|pp=29–33}}.&lt;/ref&gt; making the United States the twenty-seventh country in the world to give women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="Mintz-47" /&gt;

===Ratification timeline===
[[File:Sewing stars on suffrage flag LCCN2016827559.jpg|thumb|upright=1.1|[[Alice Paul]] and other suffragists sewing stars on suffrage flag for each state as the Nineteenth Amendment is ratified]]
Congress proposed the Nineteenth Amendment on June 4, 1919, and the following states ratified the amendment.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usconstitution.net/constamrat.html|title=Ratification of Constitutional Amendments|accessdate=February 24, 2007|last=Mount|first=Steve|date=January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/turningpoints/search.asp?id=1484|title=Claim Wisconsin First to O.K. Suffrage|newspaper=Milwaukee Journal|accessdate=November 16, 2010|date=November 2, 1919}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
# [[Illinois]] (June 10, 1919)&lt;ref name="The Ottawa Herald"&gt;{{cite news|title=Two States Ratify Votes for Women|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26296631/two_states_ratify_votes_for_women_the/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The Ottawa Herald]]|date=June 10, 1919|location=Ottawa, Kansas|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Capital Times"&gt;{{cite news|title=Wisconsin O.K.'s Suffrage; Illinois First|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26296679/the_capital_times/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The Capital Times]]|date=June 10, 1919|location=Madison, Wisconsin|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|group="note"|name="Illinois"|1=Because of a mistake in wording in the introduction of the bill, but not the amendment itself, Illinois reaffirmed passage of the amendment on June 17 and submitted a brief to confirm that the second vote was merely a legal formality. Illinois was acknowledged by the U.S. Secretary of State as the first state to ratify the amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Harper|editor1-first=Ida Husted|editor-link=Ida Husted Harper|title=History of Woman Suffrage|date=1922|volume=6: 1900-1920|publisher=J. J. Little &amp; Ives Company for the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]]|location=Rochester, New York|oclc=963795738|page=[https://archive.org/details/historyofwomansu06stanuoft/page/164 164]|url=https://archive.org/details/historyofwomansu06stanuoft}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
# [[Wisconsin]] (June 10, 1919)&lt;ref name="The Ottawa Herald" /&gt;&lt;ref name="The Capital Times" /&gt;
# [[Michigan]] (June 10, 1919)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Michigan Third to Put O.K. on Suffrage Act|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26296916/detroit_free_press/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The Detroit Free Press]]|date=June 10, 1919|location=Detroit, Michigan|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Kansas]] (June 16, 1919)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Suffrage is Ratified|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26304314/suffrage_is_ratified_the_independence/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=The Independence Daily Reporter|date=June 16, 1919|location=Independence, Kansas|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Ohio]] (June 16, 1919)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Assembly to O. K. Suffrage with Dispatch|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26304891/assembly_to_o_k_suffrage_with/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The Dayton Daily News]]|date=June 16, 1919|location=Dayton, Ohio|page=9|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ohio Legislature Favors Suffrage|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26304946/ohio_legislature_favors_suffrage_the/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=The Fremont Daily Messenger|date=June 17, 1919|location=Fremont, Ohio|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=231}}
# [[New York (state)|New York]] (June 16, 1919)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Women Suffrage Amendment Wins in Legislature (pt. 1)|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26304458/the_new_york_times/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=June 17, 1919|location=New York, New York|page=1|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}} and {{cite news|title=Women Suffrage Amendment Wins in Legislature (pt. 2)|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26304613/the_new_york_times/|accessdate=December 17, 2018|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=June 17, 1919|location=New York, New York|page=9|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Pennsylvania]] (June 24, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=231}}
# [[Massachusetts]] (June 25, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=231}}
# [[Texas]] (June 28, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=231}}
# [[Iowa]] (July 2, 1919){{refn|group="note"|name="governor"|1=Date on which approved by governor}}
# [[Missouri]] (July 3, 1919)
# [[Arkansas]] (July 28, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[Montana]] (July 30, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}} (August 2, 1919);{{refn|group="note"|name="governor"}}{{refn|group="note"|name="Montana"|1=Montana was not only the first Western state to ratify, it was also the first state to elect a woman to Congress.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}}}
# [[Nebraska]] (August 2, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[Minnesota]] (September 8, 1919)
# [[New Hampshire]] (September 10, 1919){{refn|group="note"|name="governor"}}
# [[Utah]] (September 30, 1919)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Utah Ratifies the Suffrage Amendment|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26332255/utah_ratifies_the_suffrage_amendment/|accessdate=December 18, 2018|newspaper=[[The Ogden Standard]]|date=September 30, 1919|location=Ogden, Utah|page=6|via=[[Newspapers.com]]}} {{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
# [[California]] (November 1, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[Maine]] (November 5, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=231-233}}
# [[North Dakota]] (December 1, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[South Dakota]] (December 4, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=231-233}}
# [[Colorado]] (December 12, 1919){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}} (December 15, 1919){{refn|group="note"|name="governor"}}
# [[Kentucky]] (January 6, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[Rhode Island]] (January 6, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[Oregon]] (January 12, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=231-233}}
# [[Indiana]] (January 16, 1920)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| author=Morgan, Anita | title ='An Act of Tardy Justice': The Story of Women's Suffrage in Indiana | website = | publisher =Indiana Women's Suffrage Centennial  | date =2019 | url =http://indianasuffrage100.org/indiana-womens-suffrage-history/ | format = | accessdate =May 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=232-233}}
# [[Wyoming]] (January 26, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}{{refn|group="note"|name="Wyoming"|1=Wyoming as a territory was the first globally to grant women full voting rights in 1869. In 1892, Wyoming's Theresa Jenkins was the first woman to serve as a national party convention delegate; now in 1919 she thanked Wyoming legislators for their unanimous decision to support the Nineteenth Amendment.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}}}
# [[Nevada]] (February 7, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=232}}
# [[New Jersey]] (February 9, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}{{refn|group="note"|name="New Jersey"|1=New Jersey ratified following a rally producing a petition of over 140,000 signatures supporting the state's ratification of the amendment.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}}}
# [[Idaho]] (February 11, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}
# [[Arizona]] (February 12, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}
# [[New Mexico]] (February 16, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}{{refn|group="note"|name="NewMexico"|1=New Mexico's ratification came a day after the hundredth anniversary of Susan B. Anthony's birth; suffragists used this centennial to lament that ratification had not yet been achieved.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=233}}}}
# [[Oklahoma]] (February 23, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=237}}{{refn|group="note"|name="Oklahoma"|1=Oklahoma's ratification followed a Presidential intervention urging legislators to ratify.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=237}}}}
# [[West Virginia]] (March 10, 1920, confirmed on September 21, 1920){{refn|group="note"|name="West Virginia"|1=West Virginia's ratification followed the dramatic turnaround of a voting block instigated by state Senator Jesse A. Bloch demonstrated against by suffragists from around the nation who had descended upon the state capitol.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=237-238}}}}
# [[Washington (state)|Washington]] (March 22, 1920){{refn|group="note"|name="Washington"|1=Washington was holding out to have the honor of being the last state to ratify but, in the end, a female legislator brought the matter to the floor and ratification was unanimously approved in both houses.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|p=238}}}}
# [[Tennessee]] (August 18, 1920){{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=242-243|p=}}{{refn|group="note"|name="Tennessee"|1=Breaking a 48-48 vote tie, Tennessee's ratification passed when 24-year old Representative Harry T. Burn remembered his mother writing him to "help Mrs. [Carrie Chapman] Catt put the rat in ratification" by supporting suffrage.{{sfn|Weatherford|1998|pp=232-233}}}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Monroe|first=Judy|title=The Nineteenth Amendment: Women's Right to Vote|publisher=Ensloe Publishers, Inc.|location=Berkeley Heights, NJ|page=75}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}&lt;/small&gt;

The ratification process required 36 states, and completed with the approval by Tennessee. Though not necessary for adoption, the following states subsequently ratified the amendment. Some states did not call a legislative session to hold a vote until later, others rejected it when it was proposed and then reversed their decisions years later, with the last taking place in 1984.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Women of the American South: A Multicultural Reader|editor=Farnham, Christie Anne|chapter=Black Women's Culture of Resistance and the Right to Vote|last1=Hine|first1=Darlene Clark|last2=Farnham|first2=Christie Anne|pages=[https://archive.org/details/womenofamericans0000unse/page/204 204–219]|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York|date=1997|isbn=9780814726549|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/womenofamericans0000unse/page/204}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
{{ordered list|start=37
| [[Connecticut]] (September 14, 1920, reaffirmed on September 21, 1920)
| [[Vermont]] (February 8, 1921)
| [[Delaware]] (March 6, 1923, after being rejected on June 2, 1920)
| [[Maryland]] (March 29, 1941, after being rejected on February 24, 1920; not certified until February 25, 1958)
| [[Virginia]] (February 21, 1952, after being rejected on February 12, 1920)
| [[Alabama]] (September 8, 1953, after being rejected on September 22, 1919)
| [[Florida]] (May 13, 1969)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.floridamemory.com/exhibits/floridahighlights/19th_amendment/|title=Ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment by the Florida Legislature, 1969|publisher=Institute of Museum and Library Services|accessdate=February 2, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111013142854/http://www.floridamemory.com/exhibits/floridahighlights/19th_amendment/|archive-date=October 13, 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[South Carolina]] (July 1, 1969, after being rejected on January 28, 1920; not certified until August 22, 1973)
| [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] (February 20, 1970, after being rejected on July 24, 1919)
| [[Louisiana]] (June 11, 1970, after being rejected on July 1, 1920)
| [[North Carolina]] (May 6, 1971)
| [[Mississippi]] (March 22, 1984, after being rejected on March 29, 1920)}}
{{div col end}}
&lt;/small&gt;

==Legal challenges==
[[File:19th Amendment Voting Badge-Harding Coolidge Ticket 1920.png|thumb|upright=.8|"I Cast My First Vote" Nineteenth Amendment Women's Suffrage Badge, Nov. 2, 1920]]

The U.S. Supreme Court unanimously upheld the amendment's validity in ''[[Leser v. Garnett]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|258|130|1922}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Anzalone 2002"&gt;{{Harvnb|Anzalone|2002|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Maryland citizens Mary D. Randolph, "'a colored female citizen' of 331 West Biddle Street,"&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite magazine|last=Bronson|first=Minnie|date=November 6, 1920|title=Maryland League for State Defense Starts Great Suit|url=https://books.google.com/?id=J9NBAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA8-IA138|magazine=The Woman Patriot|volume=4|issue=45|page=2|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Cecilia Street Waters, "a white woman, of 824 North Eutaw Street",&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; applied for and were granted registration as qualified Baltimore voters on October 12, 1920. To have their names removed from the list of qualified voters, Oscar Leser and others brought suit against the two women on the sole grounds that they were women, arguing that they were not eligible to vote because the Constitution of Maryland limited suffrage to men&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://i2i.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/1922-Leser-v.-Garnett-USSC.pdf|title=Leser v. Garnett page 217|date=October 1921|work=Independence Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Maryland legislature had refused to vote to ratify the Nineteenth Amendment. Two months before, on August 26, 1920, the federal government had proclaimed the amendment incorporated into the Constitution.&lt;ref name="Anzalone 2002"/&gt;

Leser stated that the amendment "destroyed State autonomy" because it increased Maryland's electorate without the state's consent. The Supreme Court answered that the Nineteenth Amendment had similar wording to the Fifteenth Amendment, which had expanded state electorates without regard to race for more than 50 years by that time despite being rejected by six states, including Maryland.&lt;ref name="Anzalone 2002"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leser v. Garnett"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://openjurist.org/258/us/130/leser-v-garnett|title=258 U.S. 130 - Leser v. Garnett|work=OpenJurist|accessdate=February 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leser further argued that the state constitutions in some ratifying states did not allow their legislatures to ratify. The Court replied that state ratification was a federal function granted under [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Ratification of amendments|Article V of the U.S. Constitution]] and not subject to a state constitution's limitations. Finally, those bringing suit asserted the Nineteenth Amendment was not adopted because Tennessee and West Virginia violated their own rules of procedure. The Court ruled that the point was moot because Connecticut and Vermont had subsequently ratified the amendment, providing a sufficient number of state ratifications to adopt the Nineteenth Amendment even without Tennessee and West Virginia. The Court also ruled that Tennessee's and West Virginia's certifications of their state ratifications was binding and had been duly authenticated by their respective [[Secretary of state (U.S. state government)|Secretaries of State]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Maryland and the 19th Amendment|url=https://www.nps.gov/articles/maryland-and-the-19th-amendment.htm|publisher=[[National Park Service]]|accessdate=May 4, 2020|language=English|date=September 12, 2019|quote=The court also said that, since the Secretaries of State of Tennessee and West Virginia had accepted the ratifications, that they were necessarily valid.}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the Court's ruling, Randolph and Waters were permitted to become registered voters in Baltimore.&lt;ref name="Anzalone 2002"/&gt;

Another challenge to the Nineteenth Amendment's adoption was dismissed by the Supreme Court in ''[[Fairchild v. Hughes]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|258|126|1922}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fairchildvhughes&gt;{{ussc|name=Fairchild v. Hughes|volume=258|page=126|year=1922}}&lt;/ref&gt; because the party bringing the suit, [[Charles S. Fairchild]], came from a state that already allowed women to vote and so Fairchild lacked [[Standing (law)|standing]].

==Effects==
[[File:VOTE poster - Citation Acc 22002 - Archives and Manuscripts - Library of Virginia.jpg|thumb|upright=.8|VOTE poster, League of Women Voters.  c.1920]]
[[File:Ad targeting female votes for 1920 presidential election.jpg|thumb|upright=.8|Ladies Home Journal ad targeting female votes for 1920 presidential election]]

=== Women's voting behavior ===
Ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment enfranchised 26 million American women in time for the 1920 U.S. presidential election.{{sfn|Woloch|1984|p=354}} Many legislators feared that a powerful women's [[Voting bloc|bloc]] would emerge in American politics. This fear led to the passage of such laws as the [[Sheppard–Towner Act|Sheppard–Towner Maternity and Infancy Protection Act]] of 1921, which expanded maternity care during the 1920s.&lt;ref name="Dumenil 1995"&gt;{{Harvnb|Dumenil|1995|pp=23–30}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Newly enfranchised women and women's groups prioritized a reform agenda rather than party loyalty and their first goal was the Sheppard-Towner Act. It was the first federal social security law and made a dramatic difference before it was allowed to lapse in 1929.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lemons|first=J. Stanley|date=1969|title=The Sheppard-Towner Act: Progressivism in the 1920s|journal=The Journal of American History|volume=55|issue=4|pages=776–786|doi=10.2307/1900152|issn=0021-8723|jstor=1900152}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other efforts at the federal level in the early 1920s that related to women labor and women's citizenship rights included the establishment of a Women's Bureau in the [[United States Department of Labor|U.S. Department of Labor]] in 1920 and passage of the [[Cable Act]] in 1922.{{sfn|Baker|2009|p=43}} After the [[1924 United States presidential election|U.S. presidential election in 1924]], politicians realized that the women's bloc they had feared did not actually exist and they did not need to cater to what they considered as "women's issues" after all.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VKGCbw5_P-wC&amp;lpg=PA210&amp;vq=bloc&amp;pg=PA157#v=onepage&amp;q=bloc&amp;f=false|title=Votes Without Leverage: Women in American Electoral Politics, 1920-1970|last=Harvey|first=Anna L.|date=1998-07-13|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521597432|location=|pages=157|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The eventual appearance of an American women's voting bloc has been tracked to various dates, depending on the source, from the 1950s&lt;ref name="Moses 1995"&gt;{{Harvnb|Moses|Hartmann|1995|pp=xx-xxi}}.&lt;/ref&gt; to 1970.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VKGCbw5_P-wC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA10#v=onepage&amp;q=bloc&amp;f=false|title=Votes Without Leverage: Women in American Electoral Politics, 1920-1970|last=Harvey|first=Anna L.|date=1998-07-13|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521597432|location=|pages=10, 210|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 1980, a nationwide [[Voting gender gap in the United States|gender gap in voting]] had emerged, with women usually favoring the Democratic candidate in presidential elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cawp.rutgers.edu/sites/default/files/resources/ggpresvote.pdf|title=THE GENDER GAP, Voting Choices In Presidential Elections; Fact Sheet|date=2017|website=Center for American Women and Politics (CAWP), Eagleton Institute of Politics, Rutgers University.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to political scientists J. Kevin Corder and [[Christina Wolbrecht]], few women turned out to vote in the first national elections after the Nineteenth Amendment gave them the right to do so. In 1920, 36 percent of eligible women turned out to vote (compared with 68 percent of men). The low turnout among women was partly due to other barriers to voting, such as literacy tests, long residency requirements and poll taxes. Inexperience with voting and persistent beliefs that voting was inappropriate for women may also have kept turnout low. The participation gap was lowest between men and women in swing states at the time, in states that had closer races such as Missouri and Kentucky, and where barriers to voting were lower.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/08/26/was-womens-suffrage-a-failure-what-new-evidence-tells-us-about-the-first-women-voters/|title=Was women's suffrage a failure? What new evidence tells us about the first women voters|website=Washington Post|access-date=August 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cambridge.org/us/academic/subjects/politics-international-relations/american-government-politics-and-policy/counting-womens-ballots-female-voters-suffrage-through-new-deal?format=PB|title=Counting Women's Ballots|website=Cambridge University Press|access-date=August 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1960, women were turning out to vote in presidential elections in greater numbers than men and a trend of higher female voting engagement has continued into 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/2010/0818/19th-Amendment-How-far-have-women-in-politics-come-since-1920|title=19th Amendment: How far have women in politics come since 1920?|date=2010-08-18|work=Christian Science Monitor|access-date=2019-05-24|issn=0882-7729}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Limitations ===
====African-American women====
African-Americans had gained the right to vote, but for 75 percent of them it was granted in name only, as state constitutional loopholes kept them from exercising that right.&lt;ref name=":19"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780253211767|url-access=registration|quote=rosalyn terborg-penn african american women in the struggle for the vote.|title=African American Women in the Struggle for the Vote, 1850-1920|last=Terborg-Penn|first=Rosalyn|date=1998|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=9780253211767|location=|pages=|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the passage of the amendment, southern politicians held firm in their convictions not to allow African-American women to vote.&lt;ref name=":14"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nelson|first=Marjory|date=1979|title=women suffrage and race|journal=Off Our Backs|volume=9|issue=10|pages=6–22|issn=0030-0071|jstor=25793145}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had to fight to not only secure their own right to vote, but the right of African-American men as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nps.gov/articles/african-american-women-and-the-nineteenth-amendment.htm|title=African American Women and the Nineteenth Amendment (U.S. National Park Service)|website=nps.gov|language=en|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three million women south of the [[Mason–Dixon line|Mason-Dixon line]] remained disfranchised after the passage of the amendment.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Paul|first=Alice|date=February 16, 1921|title=The White Woman's Burden|url=|journal=The Nation|volume=112|issue=2902|pages=257|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Election officials regularly obstructed access to the ballot box.&lt;ref name=":26"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nps.gov/subjects/tellingallamericansstories/upload/CivilRights_VotingRights.pdf|title=Civil Rights in America: Racial Voting Rights|last=Salvatore|first=Susan Cianci|date=June 7, 2019|website=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; As newly enfranchised African-American women attempted to register, officials increased methods of what [[Brent Staples]], in an opinion piece for the ''New York Times'', described as fraud, intimidation, poll taxes, and state violence.&lt;ref name=":15"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/07/28/opinion/sunday/suffrage-movement-racism-black-women.html|title=Opinion {{!}} How the Suffrage Movement Betrayed Black Women|last=Staples|first=Brent|date=2018-07-28|work=[[The New York Times]]|access-date=2019-05-24|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1926, a group of women attempting to register in [[Birmingham, Alabama]] were beaten by officials.&lt;ref name=":16"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.greatfallstribune.com/story/news/2018/11/01/how-native-american-vote-evolved/1852110002/|title=How the Native American Vote Evolved|last=Contreras|first=Russell|date=2018-11-01|website=Great Falls Tribune|language=en|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Incidents such as this, threats of violence and job losses, and legalized prejudicial practices blocked women of color from voting.&lt;ref name=":17"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thelily.com/womens-equality-day-celebrates-the-19th-amendment-for-non-white-women-the-fight-to-vote-continued-for-decades/|title=Women's Equality Day celebrates the 19th Amendment. For nonwhite women, the fight to vote continued for decades|last=Williams|first=Sherri|website=The Lily|publisher=The Washington Post|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not until the [[Twenty-fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Twenty-fourth Amendment]] was adopted in 1962, were Congress and the states prohibited from making voting conditional on poll or other taxes, paving the way to more reforms with the [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]].

African-Americans continued to face barriers preventing them from exercising their vote until a new movement arose in the 1950s and 1960s, which posited voting rights as civil rights.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt; Nearly a thousand civil rights workers converged on the South to support voting rights as part of Freedom Summer. However, state officials continued to refuse registration until the passage of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, which prohibited racial discrimination in voting.&lt;ref name=":26" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt; For the first time, states were forbidden from imposing discriminatory restrictions on voting eligibility, and mechanisms were placed allowing the federal government to enforce its provisions.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;

==== Other minority groups ====
Native Americans were granted citizenship by an Act of Congress in 1924,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://constitutioncenter.org/blog/on-this-day-in-1924-all-indians-made-united-states-citizens|title=On this day, all Indians made United States citizens - National Constitution Center|website=National Constitution Center – constitutioncenter.org|language=en|access-date=2019-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; but state policies prohibited them from voting. In 1948, a suit brought by World War II veteran [[Miguel Trujillo]] resulted in Native Americans gaining the right to vote in New Mexico and Arizona,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.santafenewmexican.com/news/local_news/it-s-been-years-since-court-ruled-native-americans-could/article_d0544a48-ef37-56ef-958f-eb81dcf01344.html|title=It's been 70 years since court ruled Native Americans could vote in New Mexico|last=Oxford|first=Andrew|date=2 August 2018|website=Santa Fe New Mexican|access-date=5 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; but some states continued to bar them from voting until 1957.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;

Poll taxes and literacy tests kept Latina women from voting. In Puerto Rico, for example, women did not receive the right to vote until 1929, but was limited to literate women until 1935.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nps.gov/articles/puerto-rico-women-s-history.htm|title=Puerto Rico and the 19th Amendment (U.S. National Park Service)|last=|first=|date=|website=National Park Service|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, the 1975 extensions of the Voting Rights Act included requiring bilingual ballots and voting materials in certain regions, making it easier for Latina women to vote.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt;

National immigration laws prevented Asians from gaining citizenship until 1952.&lt;ref name="Ault" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt;

====Other limitations====
After passage of the Nineteenth Amendment, women still faced political limitations. Women had to lobby their state legislators, bring lawsuits, and engage in letter-writing campaigns to earn the right to sit on [[Women in United States juries|juries]]. In California, women won the right to serve on juries four years after passage of the Nineteenth Amendment. In Colorado, it took 33 years. Women continue to face obstacles when running for elective offices, and the Equal Rights Amendment, which would grant women equal rights under the law, has yet to be realized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McCammon|first=H.|last2=Chaudhuri|first2=S.|last3=Hewitt|first3=L.|last4=Muse|first4=C.|last5=Newman|first5=H.|last6=Smith|first6=C.|last7=Terrell|first7=T.|date=2008|title=Becoming Full Citizens: The U.S. Women's Jury Rights Campaigns, the Pace of Reform, and Strategic Adaptation|journal=American Journal of Sociology|volume=113|issue=4|pages=1104–1147|doi=10.1086/522805}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brown|first=J.|date=1993|title=The Nineteenth Amendment and Women's Equality|journal=The Yale Law Journal|volume=102|issue=8|pages=2175–2204| doi=10.2307/796863|jstor=796863}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cawp.rutgers.edu/current-numbers|title=Current Numbers|date=2015-06-12|website=CAWP|language=en|access-date=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theconversation.com/in-2019-womens-rights-are-still-not-explicitly-recognized-in-us-constitution-108150|title=In 2019, women's rights are still not explicitly recognized in US Constitution|last=Rohlinger|first=Deana|website=The Conversation|language=en|access-date=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
=== League of Women Voters ===
In 1920, about six months before the Nineteenth Amendment was ratified, [[Emma Smith DeVoe]] and Carrie Chapman Catt agreed to merge the [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]] and the [[League of Women Voters|National Council of Women Voters]] to help newly enfranchised women exercise their responsibilities as voters. Originally, only women could join the league; but in 1973 the charter was modified to include men. Today, the [[League of Women Voters]] operates at the local, state, and national level, with over 1,000 local and 50 state leagues, and one territory league in the U.S. Virgin Islands. Some critics and historians question whether creating an organization dedicated to political education rather than political action made sense in the first few years after ratification, suggesting that the League of Women Voters diverted the energy of activists.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;

=== Equal Rights Amendment ===
{{main|Equal Rights Amendment}}
[[Alice Paul]] and the NWP did not believe the Nineteenth Amendment would be enough to ensure men and women were treated equally, and in 1921 the NWP announced plans to campaign for another amendment which would guarantee equal rights not limited to voting. The first draft of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], written by Paul and [[Crystal Eastman]] and first named "the [[Lucretia Mott]] Amendment," stated: "No political, civil, or legal disabilities or inequalities on account of sex or on account of marriage, unless applying equally to both sexes, shall exist within the United States or any territory subject to the jurisdiction thereof."&lt;ref name=BaltSun&gt;{{cite news|title=WOMAN'S PARTY ALL READY FOR EQUALITY FIGHT; Removal Of All National and State Discriminations Is Aim. SENATE AND HOUSE TO GET AMENDMENT; A Proposed Constitutional Change To Be Introduced On October 1|last=Henning|first=Arthur Sears|date=September 26, 1921|work=[[The Baltimore Sun]]|page=1|title-link=:File:Equal Rights Amendment proposed in Congress 1921.jpg}}&lt;/ref&gt; Senator [[Charles Curtis]] brought it to Congress that year, but it did not make it to the floor for a vote. It was introduced in every congressional session from 1921 to 1971, usually not making it out of committee.&lt;ref name=crsreport&gt;{{cite web|title=The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary Ratification Issues|date=July 18, 2018|access-date=September 22, 2019|url=https://www.everycrsreport.com/reports/R42979.html|website=EveryCRSReport.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The amendment did not have the full support of women's rights activists, and was opposed by Carrie Catt and the League of Women Voters. Whereas the NWP believed in total equality, even if that meant sacrificing benefits given to women through protective legislation, some groups like the [[Women's Joint Congressional Committee]] and the [[Women's Bureau]] believed that the loss of benefits relating to safety regulations, working conditions, lunch breaks, maternity provisions, and other labor protections would outweigh what would be gained. Labor leaders like Alice Hamilton and [[Mary Anderson (labor leader)|Mary Anderson]] argued that it would set their efforts back and make sacrifices of what progress they had made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Nancy|last=Cott|title=Feminist Politics in the 1920s: The National Woman's Party |journal=[[Journal of American History]]|year=1984|volume=71|issue=1|pages=43–68|jstor=1899833|doi=10.2307/1899833}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Genora Johnson|last=Dollinger|chapter=Women and Labor Militancy|editor-first=Susan|editor-last=Ware|title=Modern American Women: A Documentary History|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/modernamericanwo00susa_1|chapter-url-access=registration|publisher=McGraw-Hill Higher Education|year=1997|isbn=0-07-071527-0|pages=[https://archive.org/details/modernamericanwo00susa_1/page/125 125–126]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these concerns, a provision known as "the Hayden rider" was added to the ERA to retain special labor protections for women, and passed the Senate in 1950 and 1953, but failed in the House. In 1958, President [[Dwight Eisenhower|Eisenhower]] called on Congress to pass the amendment, but the Hayden rider was controversial, meeting with opposition from the NWP and others who felt that it undermined its original purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.cdlib.org/view?docId=kt6f59n89c&amp;brand=calisphere&amp;doc.view=entire_text|title=Conversations with Alice Paul: Woman Suffrage and the Equal Rights Amendment.|website=cdlib.org|publisher=Suffragists Oral History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite book|last=Harrison|first=Cynthia Ellen|title=On Account of Sex: The Politics of Women's Issues, 1945–1968|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AXlSB6-WpKUC&amp;pg=PA31|year=1989|publisher=University of California Press|pages=31–32|isbn=9780520909304}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The growing, productive women's movements of the 1960s and 1970s renewed support for the amendment. U.S. Representative [[Martha Griffiths]] of Michigan reintroduced it in 1971, leading to its approval by the House of Representatives that year. After it passed in the Senate on March 22, 1972, it went to state legislatures for ratification. Congress originally set a deadline of March 22, 1979, by which point at least 38 states needed to ratify the amendment. It reached 35 by 1977, with broad bipartisan support including both major political parties and Presidents [[Richard Nixon|Nixon]], [[Gerald Ford|Ford]], and [[Jimmy Carter|Carter]]. However, when [[Phyllis Schlafly]] mobilized conservative women in opposition, four states rescinded their ratification, although whether a state may do so is disputed.&lt;ref name=chicagotribune31may2018&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.chicagotribune.com/politics/ct-met-equal-rights-amendment-illinois-20180530-story.html|title=Illinois approves Equal Rights Amendment, 36 years after deadline|author1=Rick Pearson|author2=Bill Lukitsch|date=May 31, 2018|work=[[Chicago Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The amendment did not reach the necessary 38 states by the deadline.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; President Carter signed a controversial extension of the deadline to 1982, but that time saw no additional ratifications.

In the 1990s, ERA supporters resumed efforts for ratification, arguing that the pre-deadline ratifications still applied, that the deadline itself can be lifted, and that only three states were needed. Whether the amendment is still before the states for ratification remains disputed, but in 2014 both Virginia and Illinois state senates voted to ratify, although both were blocked in the house chambers. In 2017, 45 years after the amendment was originally submitted to states, the Nevada legislature became the first to ratify it following expiration of the deadlines. Illinois lawmakers followed in 2018.&lt;ref name=chicagotribune31may2018/&gt; Another attempt in Virginia passed the Assembly but was defeated on the state senate floor by one vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=WHSV|url=https://www.whsv.com/content/news/Virginia-Senate-panel-passes-Equal-Rights-Amendment-504158291.html|title=Bid to revive Equal Rights Amendment in Virginia fails by 1 vote|date=February 21, 2019|access-date=September 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most recent effort to remove the deadline was in early 2019, with proposed legislation from [[Jackie Speier]], accumulating 188 co-sponsors and pending in Congress {{as of|2019|08|lc=yes}}.&lt;ref name=miamiherald26august2019&gt;{{cite web|work=[[Miami Herald]]|date=August 26, 2019|last=Gross|first=Samantha J.|title=99 years ago Florida led in women's suffrage. Are equal rights still a priority?|url=https://www.miamiherald.com/news/politics-government/state-politics/article234323672.html|access-date=September 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Commemorations ===
[[File:Portrait Monument Video 01.webmhd.webm|thumb|"The Portrait Monument" (originally "Woman's Movement") by sculptress [[Adelaide Johnson]] in the U.S. Capitol Rotunda]]A 7-and-one-half ton marble slab from a [[Carrara|Carrara, Italy]], quarry carved into statue called the "Portrait Monument"&lt;ref name=":20"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.desertsun.com/story/news/nation/2016/09/19/suffrage-movement-susan-b-anthony-portrait-monument-us-capitol-hillary-clinton/88317362/|title=No room for fourth bust on suffragist statue?|last=Goolsby|first=Denise|date=September 19, 2016|website=Desert Sun}}&lt;/ref&gt; (originally known as the "Woman's Movement"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/the-portrait-monument-washington-dc|title=The Portrait Monument|website=Atlas Obscura}}&lt;/ref&gt;) by sculptress [[Adelaide Johnson]] was unveiled at the [[United States Capitol rotunda|U.S. Capitol Rotunda]] on February 15, 1921, six months after the ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment, on the 101st anniversary of [[Susan B. Anthony]]'s birth, and during the [[National Woman's Party]]'s first post-ratification national convention in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name=":20" /&gt; The Party presented it as a gift "from the women of the U.S." The monument is installed in the Capitol Rotunda and features busts of Susan B. Anthony, [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Lucretia Mott]]. Over 50 woman's groups with delegates from every state were represented at the dedication ceremony in 1921 that was presided over by [[Jane Addams]]. After the ceremony, the statue was moved temporarily to the Capitol Crypt, where it stood for less than a month until Johnson discovered that an inscription stenciled in gold lettering on the back of the monument had been removed. The inscription read, in part: "Woman, first denied a soul, then called mindless, now arisen declares herself an entity to be reckoned. Spiritually, the woman movement...represents the emancipation of womanhood. The release of the feminine principal in humanity, the moral integration of human evolution come to rescue torn and struggling humanity from its savage self."&lt;ref name=":20" /&gt; Congress denied passage of several bills to move the statue, whose place in the Crypt also held brooms and mops. In 1963, the Crypt was cleaned for an exhibition of several statues including this one, which had been dubbed "The Women in the Bathtub." In 1995 on the 75th anniversary of the Nineteenth Amendment, women's groups renewed congressional interest in the monument and on May 14, 1997, the statue was finally returned to the Rotunda.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/suffragist-statue-trapped-broom-closet-75-years-180963274/|title=The Suffragist Statue Trapped in a Broom Closet for 75 Years: The Portrait Monument was a testament to women's struggle for the vote that remained hidden till 1997|last=Boissoneault|first=Lorraine|date=May 13, 2017|website=Smithsonian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 26, 2016, a monument commemorating Tennessee's role in providing the required 36th state ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment was unveiled in [[Centennial Park (Nashville)]] in [[Nashville, Tennessee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Bliss|first1=Jessica|title=Alan LeQuire's Women Suffrage Monument unveiled in Nashville's Centennial Park|url=http://www.tennessean.com/story/news/2016/08/24/alan-lequires-women-suffrage-monument-unveiled-centennial-park/87150580/|accessdate=August 27, 2016|publisher=Nashville Tennessean|date=August 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The memorial, erected by the Tennessee Suffrage Monument, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Too Few Statues of Women|url=http://tnsuffragemonument.org/too-few-statues-of-women/|website=Tennessee Suffrage Monument, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and created by [[Alan LeQuire]], features likenesses of suffragists who were particularly involved in securing Tennessee's ratification: Carrie Chapman Catt; [[Anne Dallas Dudley]]; Abby Crawford Milton; [[Juno Frankie Pierce]]; and Sue Shelton White.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://tennesseeencyclopedia.net/entries/woman-suffrage-movement/|title=Woman Suffrage Movement|last=Randal Rust|website=Tennessee Encyclopedia|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2018, the city of [[Knoxville, Tennessee]], unveiled another sculpture by LeQuire, this one depicting 24-year-old freshman state representative Harry T. Burn and his mother. Representative Burn, at the urging of his mother, cast the deciding vote on August 18, 1920, making Tennessee the final state needed for the ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.roadsideamerica.com/story/62837|title=Listen to your Mother: a Mom-ument|website=RoadsideAmerica.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, Utah launched a campaign called Better Days 2020 to "popularize Utah women's history." One of its first projects was the unveiling on the [[Salt Lake City]] capitol steps of the design for a license plate in recognition of women's suffrage. The commemorative license plate would be available for new or existing car registrations in the state. The year 2020 marks the centennial of the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment, as well as the 150th anniversary of the first women voting in Utah, which was the first state in the nation where women cast a ballot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.deseretnews.com/article/900034928/new-utah-license-plates-celebrating-utah-womens-suffrage-now-available.html|title=New Utah license plates celebrating Utah women's suffrage now available|last=Burt|first=Spencer|date=October 3, 2018|website=Deseretnews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An annual celebration of the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment, known as [[Women's Equality Day]], began on August 26, 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.womenshistory.org/articles/womens-equality-day|title=Women's Equality Day|website=National Women's History Museum|language=en|access-date=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; There usually is heightened attention and news media coverage during momentous anniversaries such as the 75th (1995) and 100th (2020), as well as in 2016 because of the presidential election.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Womens-Equality-Day|title=Women's Equality Day {{!}} American holiday|website=Encyclopedia Britannica|language=en|access-date=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the amendment's centennial, several organizations announced large events or exhibits, including the [[National Constitution Center]] and [[National Archives and Records Administration]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/arts/5-things-you-might-not-know-about-the-19th-amendment|title=5 things you might not know about the 19th Amendment|last=Flock|first=Elizabeth|date=2019-09-10|website=PBS NewsHour|language=en-us|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/15/arts/design/womens-suffrage-movement.html|title=The Complex History of the Women's Suffrage Movement|last=Schuessler|first=Jennifer|date=2019-08-15|work=The New York Times|access-date=2019-12-16|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Popular culture ===
{{multiple image
|total_width=330
|align=right
|direction=horizontal
|footer=[[Lucy Burns]] (left, while in jail) and [[Alice Paul]] (right) of the [[Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage]] were subjects of the film ''[[Iron Jawed Angels]]''.
|image1=BURNS, MISS LUCY, OF C.U.W.S. IN JAIL LCCN2016868634.jpg
|image2=Alice Paul (1915) by Harris &amp; Ewing.jpg
}}
{{See also|Women's suffrage in film}}
The Nineteenth Amendment has been featured in a number of songs, films, and television programs. The 1976 song "Sufferin' Till Suffrage" from [[Schoolhouse Rock!]], performed by [[Essra Mohawk]] and written by [[Bob Dorough]] and Tom Yohe, states, in part, "Not a woman here could vote, no matter what age, Then the Nineteenth Amendment struck down that restrictive rule ... Yes the Nineteenth Amendment Struck down that restrictive rule."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Litman |first=Kevin |url=https://www.inverse.com/article/44125-best-bob-dorough-schoolhouse-rock-songs |title=Bob Dorough: 9 Best 'Schoolhouse Rock!' Songs from the Composer |publisher=Inverse |date=2018-04-25 |accessdate=2018-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.schoolhouserock.tv/Sufferin.html |title=Schoolhouse Rock - Sufferin' 'til Suffrage |publisher=Schoolhouserock.tv |date= |accessdate=2018-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, various recording artists released an album called ''27: The Most Perfect Album'', featuring songs inspired by the 27 amendments to the U.S. Constitution; [[Dolly Parton]]'s song inspired by the Nineteenth Amendment is called "A Woman's Right".&lt;ref name="wnycstudios1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wnycstudios.org/story/27-most-perfect-album |title=27: The Most Perfect Album &amp;#124; Radiolab |publisher=WNYC Studios |date=2018-09-19 |accessdate=2018-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nashcountrydaily.com/2018/09/18/dolly-parton-hopes-to-uplift-women-in-new-song-that-highlights-19th-amendment-womens-right-to-vote-listen/ |title=Dolly Parton Hopes to "Uplift Women" in New Song That Highlights 19th Amendment: Women's Right to Vote [Listen] |publisher=Nash Country Daily |date=2018-09-18 |accessdate=2018-11-12 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181112223521/http://www.nashcountrydaily.com/2018/09/18/dolly-parton-hopes-to-uplift-women-in-new-song-that-highlights-19th-amendment-womens-right-to-vote-listen/ |archive-date=November 12, 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''One Woman, One Vote'' is a 1995 PBS documentary narrated by actor [[Susan Sarandon]] chronicling the Seneca Falls Convention through the ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://suffrageandthemedia.org/source/one-woman-one-vote-pbs-documentary/|title=SECONDARY SOURCE - One Woman, One Vote: A PBS Documentary|website=Women's Suffrage and the Media|access-date=May 17, 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190517195129/http://suffrageandthemedia.org/source/one-woman-one-vote-pbs-documentary/|archive-date=May 17, 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.btchflcks.com/2008/11/one-woman-one-vote-a-documentary-review.html#.XORqKy-ZOqA|title='One Woman, One Vote': A Documentary Review|last=Leab|first=Amber|date=November 4, 2008|website=Bitch Flicks}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another documentary was released in 1999 by filmmaker [[Ken Burns]], ''Not For Ourselves Alone: The Story of Elizabeth Cady Stanton &amp; Susan B. Anthony''. It used archival footage and commentary by actors [[Ann Dowd]], [[Julie Harris (actress)|Julie Harris]], [[Sally Kellerman]] and [[Amy Madigan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/kenburns/not-for-ourselves-alone/|title=Not For Ourselves Alone|last=Burns|first=Ken|website=PBS}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0220253/|title=Not for Ourselves Alone: The Story of Elizabeth Cady Stanton &amp; Susan B. Anthony|website=IMBd}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, [[John Green (author)|John Green]], the best-selling author of ''[[The Fault in Our Stars]]'', produced a video entitled ''Women in the 19th Century: Crash Course US History #31'', providing an overview of the women's movement leading to the Nineteenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HGEMscZE5dY|title=Women's Suffrage: Crash Course US History #31|last=Green|first=John|website=CrashCourse on YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3957702/|title=Women in the 19th Century|website=IMBd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2004 drama ''[[Iron Jawed Angels]]'' depicting suffragists Alice Paul and Lucy Burns, played by actors [[Hilary Swank]] and Frances O’Connor, respectively, as they help secure the Nineteenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rightsinfo.org/suffrage-screen-five-films-watch-100-years-since-uk-women-got-vote/|title=Suffrage On Screen: Five Vital Films About How Women Won the Vote|last=McNeil-Walsh|first=Gemma|date=February 6, 2018|website=Rights Info: Human Rights News, Views &amp; Info}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/iron_jawed_angels|title=Iron Jawed Angels|website=Rotten Tomatoes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2018, former U.S. Secretary of State [[Hillary Clinton]] and Academy Award-winning director/producer [[Steven Spielberg]] announced plans to make a television series based on Elaine Weiss's best-selling book, ''The Woman's Hour: The Great Fight to Win the Vote''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2018/aug/01/hillary-clinton-steven-spielberg-the-womans-hour|title=Hillary Clinton and Steven Spielberg to make TV series on women's suffrage|last=Nevins|first=Jake|date=August 1, 2018|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://fortune.com/2018/08/01/hillary-clinton-steven-spielberg-amblin-tv-series-suffrage-women-vote/|title=Hillary Clinton Is Producing a Television Series on Women's Fight to Win Voting Rights|last=Shoot|first=Brittany|date=August 1, 2018|website=Fortune}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|United States|Feminism}}
{{div col start}}
*[[Feminism in the United States]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[List of female United States presidential and vice-presidential candidates]]
*[[List of suffragists and suffragettes]]
*[[List of women's rights activists]]
*[[Timeline of women's suffrage]]

{{end div col}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="note"}}

==References==
===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/americasconstitu00akhi|url-access=registration|title=America's Constitution: A Biography|first=Akhil Reed|last=Amar|authorlink=Akhil Reed Amar|publisher=[[Random House]] trade pbk. ed|year=2005|isbn=978-0-8129-7272-6}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mf2mstr5F58C|title=Supreme Court Cases on Gender and Sexual Equality, 1787–2001|publisher=United States Supreme Court (Sharpe)|year=2002|first=Christopher A|last=Anzalone|isbn=978-0-7656-0683-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Baker|first=Jean H. | title =Women and the U.S. Constitution, 1776–1920 | publisher =American Historical Association | series =New Essays in American Constitutional History | volume = | edition = | year =2009 | location =Washington, D.C. | pages = | url = | isbn =9780872291638|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jA52Fdb_V5sC|title=Why Movements Succeed or Fail: Opportunity, Culture, and the Struggle for Woman Suffrage|first=Lee A.|last=Banaszak|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|year=1996|isbn=978-1-4008-2207-2}}
* DuBois, Ellen Carol, et al. "Interchange: Women's Suffrage, the Nineteenth Amendment, and the Right to Vote." ''Journal of American History'' 106.3 (2019): 662-694.
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/moderntemperamer00dume|url-access=registration|title=The Modern Temper: American Culture and Society in the 1920s|last=Dumenil|first=Lynn|year=1995|publisher=Hill and Wang|isbn=978-0-8090-6978-1}}
* Gidlow, Liette. "The Sequel: The Fifteenth Amendment, the Nineteenth Amendment, and Southern Black Women's Struggle to Vote." ''Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era'' 17.3 (2018): 433-449.
*{{Cite encyclopedia|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5VzIRwAACAAJ|last=Hakim|first=Joy|authorlink=Joy Hakim|title=Book 9: War, Peace, and All That Jazz|encyclopedia=[[A History of US]]|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=1995|location=New York, New York|isbn=978-0-19-509514-2}}
* Hasen, Richard L., and Leah Litman. "Thin and Thick Conceptions of the Nineteenth Amendment Right to Vote and Congress's Power to Enforce It." ''Georgetown Law Journal'' (2020): 2019-63. [https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3501114 online]
* McCammon, Holly J., and Lee Ann Banaszak, eds. ''100 Years of the Nineteenth Amendment: An Appraisal of Women's Political Activism'' (Oxford UP, 2018).
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/howvotewaswonwom00mead|url-access=registration|title=How the Vote Was Won: Woman Suffrage in the Western United States, 1868–1914|first=Rebecca J.|last=Mead|publisher=[[NYU Press]]|year=2004|isbn=978-0-8147-5676-8}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UjcRujK-NmcC|title=U.S. Women in Struggle: A Feminist Studies Anthology|first1=Claire Goldberg|last1=Moses|first2=Heidi I.|last2=Hartmann|authorlink2=Heidi Hartmann|publisher=University of Illinois Press|year=1995|isbn=978-0-252-02166-4}}
* Teele, Dawn Langan. ''Forging the Franchise: The Political Origins of the Women's Vote'' (2018) [http://www.h-net.msu.edu/reviews/showrev.php?id=53857 Online review]
*{{Cite encyclopedia|ref=harv|title=Woman Suffrage Movement|encyclopedia=Tennessee Encyclopedia of History and Culture|year=1998|editor-last=Van West|editor-first=Carroll|publisher=Thomas Nelson|url=http://tennesseeencyclopedia.net/imagegallery.php?EntryID=W081|isbn=1558535993|accessdate=February 8, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100810133403/http://tennesseeencyclopedia.net/imagegallery.php?EntryID=W081|archivedate=August 10, 2010|url-status=dead}}
*{{cite book|last=Weatherford|first=Doris|title=A History of the American Suffragist Movement|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|location=Santa Barbara, CA|date=1998|isbn=9781576070659|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/historyofamerica0000weat}}
*{{cite book | last =Woloch | first =Nancy | title =Women and the American Experience | publisher =Knopf | date =1984 | location =New York | isbn =9780394535159 | ref =harv | url-access =registration | url =https://archive.org/details/womenamericanexp00wolo }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution}}
*[https://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/19thamendment.html 19th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution] from the Library of Congress
*[https://www.ourdocuments.gov/doc.php?flash=true&amp;doc=63 Our Documents: Nineteenth Amendment]
*[https://www.law.cornell.edu/anncon/html/amdt19toc_user.html CRS Annotated Constitution: Nineteenth Amendment]
*[https://www.archives.gov/education/lessons/woman-suffrage Woman Suffrage and the 19th Amendment] from the National Archives

{{US Constitution}}
{{Voting rights in the United States}}
{{Suffrage}}
{{Susan B. Anthony}}
{{Elizabeth Cady Stanton}}
{{Alice Paul}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19}}
[[Category:1920 in American law|Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:1920 in American politics]]
[[Category:Amendments to the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1918–1945)]]
[[Category:History of voting rights in the United States]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Presidency of Woodrow Wilson|Nineteenth Amendment]]
[[Category:Progressive Era in the United States]]
[[Category:Women's suffrage in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>c8b04b49wccce6sullumxsanzf83br6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
