<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epigenetic clock</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40854066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961649356</id>
      <parentid>961503014</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-09T17:26:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pengortm</username>
        <id>13707340</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Biological mechanism behind the epigenetic clock */ again, pre-prints are not good sources for wikipedia.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="66624" xml:space="preserve">An '''epigenetic clock''' is a [[Biomarkers of aging|biochemical test]] that can be used to measure age. The test is based on [[DNA methylation]] levels.

==History==
The strong effects of age on DNA methylation levels have been known since the late 1960s.&lt;ref name="Berdyshev1967"/&gt; A vast literature describes sets of [[CpG site|CpGs]] whose DNA methylation levels correlate with age, e.g.&lt;ref name="Rakyan2010"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Teschendorff2010"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Koch2011"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Horvath2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bell2012"/&gt; The first robust demonstration that DNA methylation levels in saliva could generate age predictors with an average accuracy of 5.2 years was published by a [[UCLA]] team including Sven Bocklandt, [[Steve Horvath]], and [[Eric Vilain]] in 2011 (Bocklandt et al. 2011).&lt;ref name="Forbes"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bocklandt2011" /&gt; The labs of [[Trey Ideker]] and [[Kang Zhang]] at the [[University of California, San Diego]] published the Hannum epigenetic clock (Hannum 2013),&lt;ref name="Hannum2013" /&gt; which consisted of 71 markers that accurately estimate age based on blood methylation levels. 
The first multi-tissue epigenetic clock, Horvath's epigenetic clock, was developed by [[Steve Horvath]], a professor of [[human genetics]]  and of [[biostatistics]] at [[UCLA]] (Horvath 2013).&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ScienceDaily"/&gt; Horvath spent over 4 years collecting publicly available [[Illumina (company)|Illumina]] DNA methylation data and identifying suitable statistical methods.&lt;ref name="Biome2013"/&gt; The personal story behind the discovery was featured in Nature.&lt;ref name="Gibbs2014"/&gt; The age estimator was developed using 8,000 samples from 82 Illumina DNA methylation array datasets, encompassing 51 healthy tissues and cell types. The major innovation of Horvath's epigenetic clock lies in its wide applicability: the same set of 353 CpGs and the same prediction algorithm is used irrespective of the DNA source within the organism, i.e. it does not require any adjustments or offsets.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; This property allows one to compare the ages of different areas of the human body using the same aging clock.

==Relationship to a cause of biological aging==
It is not yet known what exactly is measured by DNA methylation age. Horvath hypothesized that DNA methylation age measures the cumulative effect of an epigenetic maintenance system but details are unknown. The fact that DNA methylation age of blood predicts all-cause mortality in later life&lt;ref name="Chen2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Marioni2015mortality"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Christiansen2015"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Horvath2015centenarian"/&gt; has been used to argue that it relates to a process that causes aging.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|date=2016|title=DNA methylation-based measures of biological age: meta-analysis predicting time to death|journal=Aging|volume=8|issue=9|pages=1844–1865|doi=10.18632/aging.101020|pmc=5076441|pmid=27690265|doi-access=free|vauthors=Chen B, Marioni R, Colicino E, Peters M, Ward-Caviness C, Tsai P, Roetker N, Just A, Demerath E, Guan W|displayauthors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, if a particular CpG played a direct causal role in the aging process, the mortality it created would make it less likely to be observed in older individuals, making the site less likely to have been chosen as a predictor; the 353 clock CpGs therefore likely have no causal effect whatsoever.&lt;ref name="Nelson2019"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Nelson |first1=Paul G |last2=Promislow |first2=Daniel E L |last3=Masel |first3=Joanna |title=Biomarkers for Aging Identified in Cross-sectional Studies Tend to Be Non-causative |journal=The Journals of Gerontology: Series A |date=29 July 2019 |doi=10.1093/gerona/glz174|pmid=31353411 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather, the epigenetic clock captures an [[Emergence|emergent property]] of the epigenome.

===Epigenetic clock theory of aging===
Horvath and Raj&lt;ref name="HorvathRaj2018"/&gt; proposed an epigenetic clock theory of aging with the following tenets:
* Biological aging results as an unintended consequence of both developmental programs and maintenance program, the molecular footprints of which give rise to DNA methylation age estimators. 
* The precise mechanisms linking the innate molecular processes (underlying DNAm age) to the decline in tissue function probably relate to both intracellular changes (leading to a loss of cellular identity) and subtle changes in cell composition, for example, fully functioning somatic stem cells. 
* At the molecular level, DNAm age is a proximal readout of a collection of innate aging processes that conspire with other, independent root causes of ageing to the detriment of tissue function.

==Motivation for biological clocks==
In general, biological aging clocks and [[biomarkers of aging]]  are expected to find many uses in biological research since age is a fundamental characteristic of most [[organisms]]. Accurate measures of biological age ('''biological aging clocks''') could be useful for
* testing the validity of various [[theories of biological aging]],
* diagnosing various age related [[disease]]s and for defining [[cancer]] subtypes,
* predicting/prognosticating  the onset of various diseases,
* serving as [[surrogate marker]]s for evaluating therapeutic interventions including  [[Rejuvenation (aging)|rejuvenation]]  approaches,
* studying [[developmental biology]] and [[cell differentiation]],
* [[forensic]] applications, for example to estimate the age of a suspect based on blood left on a crime scene.
Overall, biological clocks are expected to be useful for studying what causes aging and what can be done against it. However, they can only capture the effects of interventions that affect the rate of future aging, i.e. the slope of the [[Gompertz–Makeham law of mortality|Gompertz curve]] by which mortality increases with age, and not that of interventions that act at one moment in time, e.g. to lower mortality across all ages, i.e. the intercept of the Gompertz curve.&lt;ref name="Nelson2019"/&gt;

==Properties of Horvath's clock==
The clock is defined as an age estimation method based on 353 [[epigenetics|epigenetic]] markers on the DNA. The 353 markers measure [[DNA methylation]] of [[CpG dinucleotide]]s. Estimated age ("predicted age" in mathematical usage), also referred to as DNA methylation age, has the following properties: first, it is close to zero for embryonic and [[induced pluripotent stem cell]]s; second, it correlates with cell [[Subculture (biology)#Passage number|passage number]]; third, it gives rise to a highly heritable measure of age acceleration; and, fourth, it is applicable to chimpanzee tissues (which are used as human analogs for biological testing purposes). Organismal growth (and concomitant cell division) leads to a high ticking rate of the epigenetic clock that slows down to a constant ticking rate (linear dependence) after adulthood (age 20).&lt;ref name="Horvath2013" /&gt;
The fact that DNA methylation age of blood predicts all-cause mortality in later life even after adjusting for known risk factors&lt;ref name="Chen2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Marioni2015mortality"/&gt; is compatible with a variety of causal relationships, e.g. a common cause for both. Similarly, markers of physical and mental fitness are associated with the epigenetic clock (lower abilities associated with age acceleration).&lt;ref name="Marioni2015fitness"/&gt; It systematically underestimates age from older individuals.&lt;ref name="elkhoury2019"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=El Khoury |first1=Louis Y. |last2=Gorrie-Stone |first2=Tyler |last3=Smart |first3=Melissa |last4=Hughes |first4=Amanda |last5=Bao |first5=Yanchun |last6=Andrayas |first6=Alexandria |last7=Burrage |first7=Joe |last8=Hannon |first8=Eilis |last9=Kumari |first9=Meena |last10=Mill |first10=Jonathan |last11=Schalkwyk |first11=Leonard C. |title=Systematic underestimation of the epigenetic clock and age acceleration in older subjects |journal=Genome Biology |date=17 December 2019 |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=283 |doi=10.1186/s13059-019-1810-4 |url=https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-019-1810-4 |issn=1474-760X|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Salient features of Horvath's epigenetic clock include its applicability to a broad spectrum of tissues and cell types. Since it allows one to contrast the ages of different tissues from the same subject, it can be used to identify tissues that show evidence of accelerated age due to disease.

===Statistical approach===
The basic approach is to form a weighted average of the 353 clock CpGs, which is then transformed to DNAm age using a calibration function. The calibration function reveals that the epigenetic clock has a high ticking rate until adulthood, after which it slows to a constant ticking rate. Using the training data sets, Horvath used a penalized regression model ([[Elastic net regularization]]) to regress a calibrated version of chronological age on 21,369 CpG probes that were present both on the Illumina 450K and 27K platform and had fewer than 10 missing values. DNAm age is defined as estimated ("predicted") age. The elastic net predictor automatically selected 353 CpGs. 193 of the 353 CpGs correlate positively with age while the remaining 160 CpGs correlate negatively with age. R software and a freely available web-based tool can be found  at the following webpage.&lt;ref name="DNAmAgeSoftware"/&gt;

===Accuracy===
The median error of estimated age is 3.6 years across a wide spectrum of tissues and cell types
&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;, although this increases for older individuals&lt;ref name="elkhoury2019"/&gt;  The epigenetic clock performs well in heterogeneous tissues (for example, whole blood, peripheral blood mononuclear cells, cerebellar samples, occipital cortex, buccal epithelium, colon, adipose, kidney, liver, lung, saliva, uterine cervix, epidermis, muscle) as well as in individual cell types such as CD4 T cells, CD14 monocytes, glial cells, neurons, immortalized B cells, mesenchymal stromal cells.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; However, accuracy depends to some extent on the source of the DNA.

=== Comparison with other biological clocks ===
{{Synthesis|section|date=December 2016}}
The epigenetic clock leads to a chronological age prediction that has a [[Pearson product-moment correlation coefficient|Pearson correlation coefficient]] of r=0.96 with chronological age (Figure 2 in&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;). Thus the age correlation is close to its maximum possible correlation value of 1.  Other biological clocks are based on a) [[telomere]] length, b) [[P16 (gene)|p16INK4a]] expression levels (also known as INK4a/ARF locus),&lt;ref name="Collado2007"/&gt; and c) [[microsatellite]] mutations.&lt;ref name="Forster2015"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Forster | first1 = P | last2 = Hohoff | first2 = C | last3 = Dunkelmann | first3 = B | last4 = Schürenkamp | first4 = M | last5 = Pfeiffer | first5 = H | last6 = Neuhuber | first6 = F | last7 = Brinkmann | first7 = B | year = 2015 | title = Elevated germline mutation rate in teenage fathers | journal = Proc Biol Sci | volume = 282 | issue = 1803| page = 20142898 | doi=10.1098/rspb.2014.2898 | pmid=25694621 | pmc=4345458}}&lt;/ref&gt; The correlation between chronological age and [[telomere]] length is r=−0.51 in women and r=−0.55 in men.&lt;ref name="Nordfjall2010"/&gt; The correlation between chronological age and expression levels of [[P16 (gene)|p16INK4a]] in T cells is r=0.56.&lt;ref name="Wang2012"/&gt; {{citation needed span|text=[[P16 (gene)|p16INK4a]] expression levels only relate to age in [[T cell]]s, a type of white blood cells.|date=December 2016}} {{citation needed span|text=The microsatellite clock measures not chronological age but age in terms of elapsed cell divisions within a tissue.|date=December 2016}}

==Applications of Horvath's clock==
By contrasting DNA methylation age (estimated age) with chronological age, one can define measures of age acceleration. Age acceleration can be defined as the difference between DNA methylation age and chronological age. Alternatively, it can be defined as the residual that results from regressing DNAm age on chronological age. The latter measure is attractive because it does not correlate with chronological age.
A positive/negative value of epigenetic age acceleration suggests that the underlying tissue ages faster/slower than expected.

===Genetic studies of epigenetic age acceleration===
The broad sense heritability (defined via [[Falconer's formula]]) of age acceleration of blood from older subjects is around 40% but it appears to be much higher in newborns.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;
Similarly, the age acceleration of brain tissue (prefrontal cortex) was found to be 41% in older subjects.&lt;ref name="Levine2015"/&gt;
Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of epigenetic age acceleration in postmortem brain samples have identified
several [[Single nucleotide polymorphism|SNPs]] at a genomewide significance level.&lt;ref name="Lu2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lu2017"/&gt;
GWAS of age acceleration in blood have identified several genome-wide significant genetic loci including the telomerase reverse transcriptase gene ([[Telomerase reverse transcriptase|TERT]]) locus.&lt;ref name="LuGWAS2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lu |first1=Ake T. |last2=Xue |first2=Luting |last3=Salfati |first3=Elias L. |last4=Chen |first4=Brian H. |last5=Ferrucci |first5=Luigi |last6=Levy |first6=Daniel |last7=Joehanes |first7=Roby |last8=Murabito |first8=Joanne M. |last9=Kiel |first9=Douglas P. |last10=Tsai |first10=Pei-Chien |last11=Yet |first11=Idil |last12=Bell |first12=Jordana T. |last13=Mangino |first13=Massimo |last14=Tanaka |first14=Toshiko |last15=McRae |first15=Allan F. |last16=Marioni |first16=Riccardo E. |last17=Visscher |first17=Peter M. |last18=Wray |first18=Naomi R. |last19=Deary |first19=Ian J. |last20=Levine |first20=Morgan E. |last21=Quach |first21=Austin |last22=Assimes |first22=Themistocles |last23=Tsao |first23=Philip S. |last24=Absher |first24=Devin |last25=Stewart |first25=James D. |last26=Li |first26=Yun |last27=Reiner |first27=Alex P. |last28=Hou |first28=Lifang |last29=Baccarelli |first29=Andrea A. |last30=Whitsel |first30=Eric A. |last31=Aviv |first31=Abraham |last32=Cardona |first32=Alexia |last33=Day |first33=Felix R. |last34=Wareham |first34=Nicholas J. |last35=Perry |first35=John R. B. |last36=Ong |first36=Ken K. |last37=Raj |first37=Kenneth |last38=Lunetta |first38=Kathryn L. |last39=Horvath |first39=Steve |title=GWAS of epigenetic aging rates in blood reveals a critical role for TERT |journal=Nature Communications |date=26 January 2018 |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=387 |doi=10.1038/s41467-017-02697-5 |pmid=29374233 |pmc=5786029 |bibcode=2018NatCo...9..387L }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Genetic variants associated with longer leukocyte telomere length in TERT gene paradoxically confer higher epigenetic age acceleration in blood.&lt;ref name="LuGWAS2018"/&gt;

===Lifestyle factors===
In general, lifestyle factors have only weak effects on epigenetic age acceleration in blood.&lt;ref name="Quach2017"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Quach |first1=Austin |last2=Levine |first2=Morgan E. |last3=Tanaka |first3=Toshiko |last4=Lu |first4=Ake T. |last5=Chen |first5=Brian H. |last6=Ferrucci |first6=Luigi |last7=Ritz |first7=Beate |last8=Bandinelli |first8=Stefania |last9=Neuhouser |first9=Marian L. |last10=Beasley |first10=Jeannette M. |last11=Snetselaar |first11=Linda |last12=Wallace |first12=Robert B. |last13=Tsao |first13=Philip S. |last14=Absher |first14=Devin |last15=Assimes |first15=Themistocles L. |last16=Stewart |first16=James D. |last17=Li |first17=Yun |last18=Hou |first18=Lifang |last19=Baccarelli |first19=Andrea A. |last20=Whitsel |first20=Eric A. |last21=Horvath |first21=Steve |title=Epigenetic clock analysis of diet, exercise, education, and lifestyle factors |journal=Aging |date=14 February 2017 |volume=9 |issue=2 |pages=419–446 |doi=10.18632/aging.101168 |pmid=28198702 |pmc=5361673 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, cross sectional studies of extrinsic epigenetic aging rates in blood confirm the conventional wisdom regarding the benefits of education, eating a high plant diet with lean meats, moderate alcohol consumption, physical activity and the risks associated with [[metabolic syndrome]].

===Obesity and metabolic syndrome===
The epigenetic clock was used to study the relationship between high [[body mass index]] (BMI) and the DNA methylation ages of human blood, liver, muscle and adipose tissue.&lt;ref name="Horvath2014obesity"/&gt; A significant correlation (r=0.42) between BMI and epigenetic age acceleration could be observed for the liver. A much larger sample size (n=4200 blood samples) revealed a weak but statistically significant correlation (r=0.09) between BMI and intrinsic age acceleration of blood.&lt;ref name="Quach2017"/&gt; The same large study found that various biomarkers of [[metabolic syndrome]] (glucose-, insulin-, triglyceride levels, C-reactive protein, [[Waist–hip ratio|waist-to-hip ratio]]) were associated with epigenetic age acceleration in blood.&lt;ref name="Quach2017"/&gt; Conversely, high levels of the good cholesterol [[High-density lipoprotein|HDL]] were associated with a lower epigenetic aging rate of blood.&lt;ref name="Quach2017"/&gt;

===Female breast tissue is older than expected===
DNAm age is higher than chronological age in female breast tissue that is adjacent to breast cancer tissue.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; Since normal tissue which is adjacent to other cancer types does not exhibit a similar age acceleration effect, this finding suggests that normal female breast tissue ages faster than other parts of the body.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; Similarly, normal breast tissue samples from women without cancer have been found to be substantially older than blood samples collected from the same women at the same time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sehl |first1=Mary E. |last2=Henry |first2=Jill E. |last3=Storniolo |first3=Anna Maria |last4=Ganz |first4=Patricia A. |last5=Horvath |first5=Steve |title=DNA methylation age is elevated in breast tissue of healthy women |journal=Breast Cancer Research and Treatment |date=2017 |volume=164 |issue=1 |pages=209–219 |doi=10.1007/s10549-017-4218-4 |pmid=28364215 |pmc=5487725 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female breast cancer===
In a study of three epigenetic clocks and breast cancer risk, DNAm age was found to be accelerated in blood samples of cancer-free women, years before diagnosis.&lt;ref name="Kresovich2019"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kresovich |first1=Jacob K. |last2=Xu |first2=Zongli |last3=O'Brien |first3=Katie M. |last4=Weinberg |first4=Clarice R. |last5=Sandler |first5=Dale P. |last6=Taylor |first6=Jack A. |title=Methylation-based biological age and breast cancer risk |journal=Journal of the National Cancer Institute |volume=111 |issue=10 |pages=1051–1058 |date=22 February 2019 |doi=10.1093/jnci/djz020 |pmid=30794318 |pmc=6792078 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cancer tissue===
Cancer tissues show both positive and negative age acceleration effects. For most tumor types, no significant relationship can be observed between age acceleration and tumor morphology (grade/stage).&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Horvath2015erratum"/&gt; On average, cancer tissues with mutated [[P53|TP53]] have a lower age acceleration than those without it.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; Further, cancer tissues  with high age acceleration tend to have fewer somatic mutations than those with low age acceleration.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Horvath2015erratum"/&gt;
Age acceleration is highly related to various genomic aberrations in cancer tissues. Somatic mutations in [[estrogen receptor]]s or [[progesterone receptor]]s are associated with accelerated DNAm age in breast cancer.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; Colorectal cancer samples with a [[BRAF (gene)|BRAF]] (V600E) mutation or promoter hypermethylation of the mismatch repair gene [[MLH1]] are associated with an increased age acceleration.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; Age acceleration in [[glioblastoma multiforme]] samples is highly significantly associated with certain mutations in [[H3F3A]].&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;
One study suggests that the epigenetic age of blood tissue may be prognostic of lung cancer incidence.&lt;ref name="Levine2015lungcancer"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Levine |first1=Morgan E. |last2=Hosgood |first2=H. Dean |last3=Chen |first3=Brian |last4=Absher |first4=Devin |last5=Assimes |first5=Themistocles |last6=Horvath |first6=Steve |title=DNA methylation age of blood predicts future onset of lung cancer in the women's health initiative |journal=Aging |date=24 September 2015 |volume=7 |issue=9 |pages=690–700 |doi=10.18632/aging.100809 |pmid=26411804 |pmc=4600626 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trisomy 21 (Down syndrome)===
[[Down syndrome|Down Syndrome (DS)]] entails an increased risk of many chronic diseases that are typically associated with older age. The clinical manifestations of accelerated aging suggest that trisomy 21 increases the biological age of tissues, but molecular evidence for this hypothesis has been sparse. According to the epigenetic clock, trisomy 21 significantly increases the age of blood and brain tissue (on average by 6.6 years).&lt;ref name="Horvath2015DownSyndrome"/&gt;

===Alzheimer's disease related neuropathology===
Epigenetic age acceleration of the human prefrontal cortex was found to be correlated with several neuropathological measurements that play a role in Alzheimer's disease&lt;ref name="Levine2015" /&gt;  Further, it was found to be associated with a decline in global cognitive functioning, and memory functioning among individuals with Alzheimer's disease.&lt;ref name="Levine2015" /&gt;
The epigenetic age of '''blood''' relates to cognitive functioning in the elderly.&lt;ref name="Marioni2015fitness"/&gt; Overall, these results strongly suggest that the epigenetic clock lends itself for measuring the biological age of the brain.

===Cerebellum ages slowly===
It has been difficult to identify tissues that seem to evade aging due to the lack of biomarkers of tissue age that allow one to contrast compare the ages of different tissues. An application of epigenetic clock to 30 anatomic sites from six centenarians and younger subjects revealed that the [[cerebellum]] ages slowly: it is about 15 years younger than expected in a centenarian.&lt;ref name="Horvath2015cerebellum"/&gt; This finding might explain why the cerebellum exhibits fewer neuropathological hallmarks of age related dementias compared to other brain regions. In younger subjects (e.g. younger than 70), brain regions and brain cells appear to have roughly the same age.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Horvath2015cerebellum"/&gt; Several SNPs and genes have been identified that relate to the epigenetic age of the cerebellum.&lt;ref name="Lu2016"/&gt;

===Huntington's disease===
[[Huntington's disease]] has been found to increase the epigenetic aging rates of several human brain regions.&lt;ref name="Horvath2016HD"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Horvath |first1=Steve |last2=Langfelder |first2=Peter |last3=Kwak |first3=Seung |last4=Aaronson |first4=Jeff |last5=Rosinski |first5=Jim |last6=Vogt |first6=Thomas F. |last7=Eszes |first7=Marika |last8=Faull |first8=Richard L.M. |last9=Curtis |first9=Maurice A. |last10=Waldvogel |first10=Henry J. |last11=Choi |first11=Oi-Wa |last12=Tung |first12=Spencer |last13=Vinters |first13=Harry V. |last14=Coppola |first14=Giovanni |last15=Yang |first15=X. William |title=Huntington's disease accelerates epigenetic aging of human brain and disrupts DNA methylation levels |journal=Aging |date=27 July 2016 |volume=8 |issue=7 |pages=1485–1512 |doi=10.18632/aging.101005 |pmid=27479945 |pmc=4993344 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Centenarians age slowly===
The offspring of semi-supercentenarians (subjects who reached an age of 105–109 years) have a lower epigenetic age than age-matched controls (age difference=5.1 years in blood) and centenarians are younger (8.6 years) than expected based on their chronological age.&lt;ref name="Horvath2015centenarian"/&gt;

===HIV infection===
Infection with the Human Immunodeficiency Virus-1 ([[HIV]]) is associated with clinical symptoms of accelerated aging, as evidenced by increased incidence and diversity of age-related illnesses at relatively young ages. But it has been difficult to detect an accelerated aging effect on a molecular level. An epigenetic clock analysis of human DNA from HIV+ subjects and controls detected a significant age acceleration effect in brain (7.4 years) and blood (5.2 years) tissue due to HIV-1 infection.&lt;ref name="Horvath2015HIV"/&gt; These results are consistent with an independent study that also found an age advancement of 5 years in blood of HIV patients and a strong effect of the HLA locus.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gross |first1=Andrew M. |last2=Jaeger |first2=Philipp A. |last3=Kreisberg |first3=Jason F. |last4=Licon |first4=Katherine |last5=Jepsen |first5=Kristen L. |last6=Khosroheidari |first6=Mahdieh |last7=Morsey |first7=Brenda M. |last8=Swindells |first8=Susan |last9=Shen |first9=Hui |last10=Ng |first10=Cherie T. |last11=Flagg |first11=Ken |last12=Chen |first12=Daniel |last13=Zhang |first13=Kang |last14=Fox |first14=Howard S. |last15=Ideker |first15=Trey |title=Methylome-wide Analysis of Chronic HIV Infection Reveals Five-Year Increase in Biological Age and Epigenetic Targeting of HLA |journal=Molecular Cell |date=April 2016 |volume=62 |issue=2 |pages=157–168 |doi=10.1016/j.molcel.2016.03.019 |pmc=4995115 |pmid=27105112 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parkinson's disease===
A large-scale study suggests that the blood of Parkinson's disease subjects exhibits (relatively weak) accelerated aging effects.&lt;ref name="Horvath2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Horvath |first1=Steve |last2=Ritz |first2=Beate R |title=Increased epigenetic age and granulocyte counts in the blood of Parkinson's disease patients |journal=Aging |date=9 December 2015 |volume=7 |issue=12 |pages=1130–1142 |doi=10.18632/aging.100859 |pmid=26655927 |pmc=4712337 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Developmental disorder: syndrome X===
Children with a very rare disorder known as [[Brooke Greenberg|syndrome X]] maintain the façade of persistent toddler-like features while aging from birth to adulthood. Since the physical development of these children is dramatically delayed, these children appear to be a toddler or at best a preschooler. According to an epigenetic clock analysis, blood tissue from syndrome X cases is not younger than expected.&lt;ref name="Horvath2015syndromeX"/&gt;

===Menopause accelerates epigenetic aging===
The following results strongly suggest that the loss of female hormones resulting from menopause accelerates the epigenetic aging rate of blood and possibly that of other tissues.&lt;ref name="Levine2016menopause"/&gt; First, early [[menopause]] has been found to be associated with an increased epigenetic age acceleration of blood.&lt;ref name="Levine2016menopause"/&gt; Second, surgical menopause (due to bilateral
[[oophorectomy]]) is associated with epigenetic age acceleration in blood and saliva. Third, [[Hormone replacement therapy (menopause)|menopausal hormone therapy]], which mitigates hormonal loss, is associated with a negative age acceleration of buccal cells (but not of blood cells).&lt;ref name="Levine2016menopause"/&gt; Fourth, genetic markers that are associated with early menopause are also associated with increased epigenetic age acceleration in blood.&lt;ref name="Levine2016menopause"/&gt;

===Cellular senescence versus epigenetic aging===
A confounding aspect of biological aging is the nature and role of senescent cells. It is unclear whether the three major types of cellular senescence, namely replicative senescence, oncogene-induced senescence and DNA damage-induced senescence are descriptions of the same phenomenon instigated by different sources, or if each of these is distinct, and how they are associated with epigenetic aging.
Induction of replicative senescence (RS) and oncogene-induced senescence (OIS) were found to be accompanied by epigenetic aging of primary cells but senescence induced by DNA damage was not, even though RS and OIS activate the cellular DNA damage response pathway.&lt;ref name="Lowe2016"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lowe |first1=Donna |last2=Horvath |first2=Steve |last3=Raj |first3=Kenneth |title=Epigenetic clock analyses of cellular senescence and ageing |journal=Oncotarget |date=14 February 2016 |volume=7 |issue=8 |pages=8524–31 |doi=10.18632/oncotarget.7383 |pmid=26885756 |pmc=4890984 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These results highlight the independence of cellular senescence from epigenetic aging. Consistent with this, telomerase-immortalised cells continued to age (according to the epigenetic clock) without having been treated with any senescence inducers or DNA-damaging agents, re-affirming the independence of the process of epigenetic ageing from telomeres, cellular senescence, and the DNA damage response pathway.
Although the uncoupling of senescence from cellular aging appears at first sight to be inconsistent with the fact that senescent cells contribute to the physical manifestation of organism ageing, as demonstrated by Baker et al., where removal of senescent cells slowed down aging.&lt;ref name="Baker2011"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Baker | first1 =DJ | year = 2011 | title = Clearance of p16Ink4a-positive senescent cells delays ageing-associated disorders. | journal = Nature | volume=479| issue =7372| pages = 232–36 | doi = 10.1038/nature10600| pmid= 22048312 | pmc=3468323| bibcode =2011Natur.479..232B }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the epigenetic clock analysis of senescence suggests that cellular senescence is a state that cells are forced into as a result of external pressures such as DNA damage, ectopic oncogene expression and exhaustive proliferation of cells to replenish those eliminated by external/environmental factors.&lt;ref name="Lowe2016"/&gt; These senescent cells, in sufficient numbers, will probably cause the deterioration of tissues, which is interpreted as organism ageing. However, at the cellular level, aging, as measured by the epigenetic clock, is distinct from senescence. It is an intrinsic mechanism that exists from the birth of the cell and continues. This implies that if cells are not shunted into senescence by the external pressures described above, they would still continue to age. This is consistent with the fact that mice with naturally long telomeres still age and eventually die even though their telomere lengths are far longer than the critical limit, and they age prematurely when their telomeres are forcibly shortened, due to replicative senescence. Therefore, cellular senescence is a route by which cells exit prematurely from the natural course of cellular aging.&lt;ref name="Lowe2016"/&gt;

===Effect of sex and race/ethnicity===
Men age faster than women according to epigenetic age acceleration in blood, brain, saliva, and many other tissues.
&lt;ref name="Horvath2016Race"&gt;{{Cite journal| title = An epigenetic clock analysis of race/ethnicity, sex, and coronary heart disease.| journal = [[Genome Biol]]| volume =17 | issue = 1| year = 2016| pmid = 27511193 |pmc= 4980791|vauthors= Horvath S, Gurven M, Levine ME, Trumble BC, Kaplan H, Allayee H, Ritz BR, Chen B, Lu AT, Rickabaugh TM, Jamieson BD, Sun D, Li S, Chen W, Quintana-Murci L, Fagny M, Kobor MS, Tsao PS, Reiner AP, Edlefsen KL, Absher D, Assimes TL | doi=10.1186/s13059-016-1030-0| pages=171}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The epigenetic clock method applies to all examined racial/ethnic groups in the sense that DNAm age is highly correlated with chronological age. But ethnicity can be associated with epigenetic age acceleration.&lt;ref name="Horvath2016Race"/&gt; For example, the blood of Hispanics and the [[Tsimané people|Tsimané]] ages more slowly than that of other populations which might explain the [[Hispanic paradox|Hispanic mortality paradox]].&lt;ref name="Horvath2016Race"/&gt;

===Rejuvenation effect due to stem cell transplantation in blood===
[[Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation]], which transplants these cells from a young donor to an older recipient, rejuvenates the epigenetic age of blood to that of the donor. However, [[graft-versus-host disease]] is associated with increased DNA methylation age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Stölzel |first1=Friedrich |last2=Brosch |first2=Mario |last3=Horvath |first3=Steve |last4=Kramer |first4=Michael |last5=Thiede |first5=Christian |last6=von Bonin |first6=Malte |last7=Ammerpohl |first7=Ole |last8=Middeke |first8=Moritz |last9=Schetelig |first9=Johannes |last10=Ehninger |first10=Gerhard |last11=Hampe |first11=Jochen |last12=Bornhäuser |first12=Martin |title=Dynamics of epigenetic age following hematopoietic stem cell transplantation |journal=Haematologica |date=August 2017 |volume=102 |issue=8 |pages=e321–e323 |doi=10.3324/haematol.2016.160481 |pmc=5541887 |pmid=28550187 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Progeria===
Adult progeria also known as [[Werner syndrome]] is associated with epigenetic age acceleration in blood.&lt;ref name="Maierhofer2017Werner"/&gt;
Fibroblast samples from children with Hutchinson-Gilford [[Progeria]] exhibit accelerated epigenetic aging effects according to the "skin &amp; blood" epigenetic clock but not according to the original pan tissue clock from Horvath.&lt;ref name="Horvath2018HGP"&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Epigenetic clock for skin and blood cells applied to Hutchinson Gilford Progeria Syndrome and ''ex vivo'' studies |journal=[[Aging (Albany NY)]] |volume=10 |issue=7 |year=2018 |pmid=30048243 |pmc=6075434|vauthors= Horvath S, Oshima J, Martin GM, Lu AT, Quach A, Cohen H, Felton S, Matsuyama M, Lowe D, Kabacik S, Wilson JG, Reiner AP, Maierhofer A, Flunkert J, Aviv A, Hou L, Baccarelli AA, Li Y, Stewart JD, Whitsel EA, Ferrucci L, Matsuyama S, Raj K |doi=10.18632/aging.101508 |doi-access=free |pages=1758–1775}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biological mechanism behind the epigenetic clock==
Despite the fact that biomarkers of ageing based on DNA methylation data have enabled accurate age estimates for any tissue across the entire life course, the precise biological mechanism behind the epigenetic clock is currently unknown.&lt;ref name="HorvathRaj2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Horvath |first1=Steve |last2=Raj |first2=Kenneth |title=DNA methylation-based biomarkers and the epigenetic clock theory of ageing |journal=Nature Reviews Genetics |date=11 April 2018 |volume=19 |issue=6 |pages=371–384 |doi=10.1038/s41576-018-0004-3 |pmid=29643443 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, epigenetic biomarkers may help to address long-standing questions in many fields, including the central question: why do we age?  To understand the essence of mechanisms behind the epigenetic clock, it would be advisable to make a comparison and find the relationship between the readings of the epigenetic clock and the [[transcriptome]] aging clock&lt;ref&gt;Fleischer, J. G., Schulte, R., Tsai, H. H., Tyagi, S., Ibarra, A., Shokhirev, M. N., ... &amp; Navlakha, S. (2018). Predicting age from the transcriptome of human dermal fibroblasts. Genome biology, 19(1), 221.  {{doi|10.1186/s13059-018-1599-6}}  {{PMC|6300908}}  {{PMID|30567591}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following explanations have been proposed for now in the literature.

===Possible explanation 1: Epigenomic maintenance system===
Horvath hypothesized that his clock arises from a methylation footprint left by an epigenomic maintenance system.&lt;ref name="Horvath2013" /&gt;

===Possible explanation 2: Unrepaired DNA damages===
{{Synthesis|section|date=December 2016}}
Endogenous DNA damages occur frequently including about 50 double-strand DNA breaks per cell cycle&lt;ref name="pmid14566050"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Vilenchik MM, Knudson AG |title=Endogenous DNA double-strand breaks: production, fidelity of repair, and induction of cancer |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=100 |issue=22 |pages=12871–76 |year=2003 |pmid=14566050 |pmc=240711 |doi=10.1073/pnas.2135498100 |url=|bibcode=2003PNAS..10012871V }}&lt;/ref&gt; and about 10,000 oxidative damages per day (see [[DNA damage (naturally occurring)]]).  During repair of double-strand breaks many epigenetic alterations are introduced, and in a percentage of cases epigenetic alterations remain after repair is completed, including increased methylation of CpG island promoters.&lt;ref name="pmid17616978"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Cuozzo C, Porcellini A, Angrisano T, Morano A, Lee B, Di Pardo A, Messina S, Iuliano R, Fusco A, Santillo MR, Muller MT, Chiariotti L, Gottesman ME, Avvedimento EV |title=DNA damage, homology-directed repair, and DNA methylation |journal=PLoS Genet. |volume=3 |issue=7 |pages=e110 |year=2007 |pmid=17616978 |pmc=1913100 |doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.0030110 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid18704159"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=O'Hagan HM, Mohammad HP, Baylin SB |title=Double strand breaks can initiate gene silencing and SIRT1-dependent onset of DNA methylation in an exogenous promoter CpG island |journal=PLoS Genet. |volume=4 |issue=8 |pages=e1000155 |year=2008 |pmid=18704159 |pmc=2491723 |doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.1000155 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid24137009"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Morano A, Angrisano T, Russo G, Landi R, Pezone A, Bartollino S, Zuchegna C, Babbio F, Bonapace IM, Allen B, Muller MT, Chiariotti L, Gottesman ME, Porcellini A, Avvedimento EV |title=Targeted DNA methylation by homology-directed repair in mammalian cells. Transcription reshapes methylation on the repaired gene |journal=Nucleic Acids Res. |volume=42 |issue=2 |pages=804–21 |year=2014 |pmid=24137009 |pmc=3902918 |doi=10.1093/nar/gkt920 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Similar, but usually transient epigenetic alterations were recently found during repair of oxidative damages caused by H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, and it was suggested that occasionally these epigenetic alterations may also remain after repair.&lt;ref name="pmid26186941"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ding |first1=Ning |last2=Bonham |first2=Emily M. |last3=Hannon |first3=Brooke E. |last4=Amick |first4=Thomas R. |last5=Baylin |first5=Stephen B. |last6=O'Hagan |first6=Heather M. |title=Mismatch repair proteins recruit DNA methyltransferase 1 to sites of oxidative DNA damage |journal=Journal of Molecular Cell Biology |date=July 2016 |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=244–254 |doi=10.1093/jmcb/mjv050 |pmid=26186941 |pmc=4937888 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These accumulated epigenetic alterations may contribute to the epigenetic clock.  Accumulation of epigenetic alterations may parallel the accumulation of un-repaired DNA damages that are proposed to cause aging (see [[DNA damage theory of aging]]).

==Other age estimators based on DNA methylation levels==
{{Synthesis|section|date=December 2016}}
Several other age estimators have been described in the literature.

1) Weidner et al. (2014) describe an age estimator for DNA from blood that uses only three CpG sites of genes hardly affected by aging (cg25809905 in integrin, alpha 2b (ITGA2B); cg02228185 in aspartoacylase (ASPA) and cg17861230 in phosphodiesterase 4C, cAMP specific (PDE4C)).&lt;ref name=pmid24490752/&gt;
The age estimator by Weidener et al. (2014) applies only to blood. Even in blood this sparse estimator is far less accurate than Horvath's epigenetic clock (Horvath 2014) when applied to data generated by the Illumina 27K or 450K platforms.
&lt;ref&gt;Horvath S (2014-02-18 16:34) Comparison with the epigenetic clock (2014). Reader Comment.[http://genomebiology.com/2014/15/2/R24/comments#1964698]
&lt;/ref&gt; But the sparse estimator was developed for pyrosequencing data and is highly cost effective.
&lt;ref&gt;Wagner W (2014) Response to comment "comparison with the epigenetic clock by Horvath 2013" [http://genomebiology.com/2014/15/2/R24/comments#1977698]
&lt;/ref&gt;

2) Hannum et al. (2013)&lt;ref name="Hannum2013"/&gt; report several age estimators: one for each tissue type. Each of these estimators requires covariate information (e.g. gender, body mass index, batch). The authors mention that each tissue led to a clear linear offset (intercept and slope). Therefore, the authors had to adjust the blood-based age estimator for each tissue type using a linear model. When the Hannum estimator is applied to other tissues, it leads to a high error (due to poor calibration) as can be seen from Figure 4A in Hannum et al. (2013). Hannum et al. adjusted their blood-based age estimator (by adjusting the slope and the intercept term) in order to apply it to other tissue types. Since this adjustment step removes differences between tissue, the blood-based estimator from Hannum et al. cannot be used to compare the ages of different tissues/organs. In contrast, a salient characteristic of the epigenetic clock  is that one does not have to carry out such a calibration step:&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"/&gt; it always uses the same CpGs and the same coefficient values. Therefore, Horvath's epigenetic clock can be used to compare the ages of different tissues/cells/organs from the same individual. While the age estimators from Hannum et al. cannot be used to compare the ages of different normal tissues, they can be used to compare the age of a cancerous tissue with that of a corresponding normal (non-cancerous) tissue. Hannum et al. reported pronounced age acceleration effects in all cancers. In contrast, Horvath's epigenetic clock&lt;ref name="Horvath2015erratum"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://genomebiology.com/2013/14/10/R115/comments |title=Horvath S (2013-11-04 11:00) Erratum in cancer tissues Reader Comment |access-date=2014-04-14 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140413132011/http://genomebiology.com/2013/14/10/R115/comments |archive-date=2014-04-13 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; reveals that some cancer types (e.g. triple negative breast cancers or uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma) exhibit negative age acceleration, i.e. cancer tissue can be much younger than expected.
An important difference relates to additional covariates. Hannum's age estimators make use of covariates such as gender, body mass index, diabetes status, ethnicity, and batch. Since new data involve different batches, one cannot apply it directly to new data. However, the authors present coefficient values for their CpGs in Supplementary Tables which can be used to define an aggregate measure that tends to be strongly correlated with chronological age but may be poorly calibrated (i.e. lead to high errors).

[[File:Comparison of epigenetic age predictors.pdf|center|700px|Comparison of the 3 age predictors described in A) Horvath (2013),&lt;ref name="Horvath2013" /&gt; B) Hannum (2013),&lt;ref name="Hannum2013"/&gt; and C) Weidener (2014),&lt;ref name=pmid24490752/&gt; respectively. The x-axis depicts the chronological age in years whereas the y-axis shows the predicted age. The solid black line corresponds to y=x. These results were generated in an independent blood methylation data set that was not used in the construction of these predictors (data generated in Nov 2014).]]

3.) Giuliani et al. identify genomic regions whose DNA methylation level correlates with age in human teeth. They propose the evaluation of DNA methylation at ELOVL2, FHL2, and PENK genes in DNA recovered from both cementum and pulp of the same modern teeth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Giuliani | first1 = C. | last2 = Cilli | first2 = E. | last3 = Bacalini | first3 = M. G. | last4 = Pirazzini | first4 = C. | last5 = Sazzini | first5 = M. | last6 = Gruppioni | first6 = G. | last7 = Franceschi | first7 = C. | last8 = Garagnani | first8 = P. | last9 = Luiselli | first9 = D. | year = 2016 | title = Inferring chronological age from DNA methylation patterns of human teeth | url = | journal = Am. J. Phys. Anthropol. | volume = 159 | issue = 4| pages = 585–595 | doi = 10.1002/ajpa.22921 | pmid = 26667772 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  They wish to apply this method also to historical and relatively ancient human teeth.

In a multicenter benchmarking study 18 research groups from three continents compared all promising methods for analyzing DNA methylation in the clinic and identified the most accurate methods, having concluded that epigenetic tests based on DNA methylation are a mature technology ready for broad clinical use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Quantitative comparison of DNA methylation assays for biomarker development and clinical applications |journal=Nature Biotechnology |date=27 June 2016 |volume=34 |issue=7 |pages=726–737 |doi=10.1038/nbt.3605 |pmid=27347756 |author1=BLUEPRINT consortium |hdl=10261/173638 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other species ===
Wang et al., (in mice livers)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wang |first1=Tina |last2=Tsui |first2=Brian |last3=Kreisberg |first3=Jason F. |last4=Robertson |first4=Neil A. |last5=Gross |first5=Andrew M. |last6=Yu |first6=Michael Ku |last7=Carter |first7=Hannah |last8=Brown-Borg |first8=Holly M. |last9=Adams |first9=Peter D. |last10=Ideker |first10=Trey |title=Epigenetic aging signatures in mice livers are slowed by dwarfism, calorie restriction and rapamycin treatment |journal=Genome Biology |date=28 March 2017 |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=57 |doi=10.1186/s13059-017-1186-2 |pmid=28351423 |pmc=5371228 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Petkovich et al.,(based on mice blood DNA methylation profiles)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Petkovich |first1=Daniel A. |last2=Podolskiy |first2=Dmitriy I. |last3=Lobanov |first3=Alexei V. |last4=Lee |first4=Sang-Goo |last5=Miller |first5=Richard A. |last6=Gladyshev |first6=Vadim N. |title=Using DNA Methylation Profiling to Evaluate Biological Age and Longevity Interventions |journal=Cell Metabolism |date=April 2017 |volume=25 |issue=4 |pages=954–960.e6 |doi=10.1016/j.cmet.2017.03.016 |pmid=28380383 |pmc=5578459 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  examined whether mice and humans experience similar patterns of change in the methylome with age. They found that mice treated with lifespan-extending interventions (such as calorie restriction or dietary rapamycin) were significantly younger in epigenetic age than their untreated, wild-type age-matched controls. Mice age predictors also detects the longevity effects of gene knockouts, and rejuvenation of fibroblast-derived [[induced pluripotent stem cell|iPSCs]].

Mice multi-tissue age predictor based on DNA methylation at 329 unique CpG sites reached a median absolute error of less than four weeks (~5 percent of lifespan). 
An attempt to use the human clock sites in mouse for age predictions showed that human clock  is not fully conserved in mouse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Stubbs |first1=Thomas M. |last2=Bonder |first2=Marc Jan |last3=Stark |first3=Anne-Katrien |last4=Krueger |first4=Felix |last5=von Meyenn |first5=Ferdinand |last6=Stegle |first6=Oliver |last7=Reik |first7=Wolf |title=Multi-tissue DNA methylation age predictor in mouse |journal=Genome Biology |date=11 April 2017 |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=68 |doi=10.1186/s13059-017-1203-5 |pmid=28399939 |pmc=5389178 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Differences between human and mouse clocks suggests that epigenetic clocks need to be trained specifically for different species.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wagner |first1=Wolfgang |title=Epigenetic aging clocks in mice and men |journal=Genome Biology |date=14 June 2017 |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=107 |doi=10.1186/s13059-017-1245-8 |pmid=28615041 |pmc=5470213 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Changes to DNA methylation patterns have great potential for age estimation and biomarker search in domestic and wild animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=De Paoli-Iseppi |first1=Ricardo |last2=Deagle |first2=Bruce E. |last3=McMahon |first3=Clive R. |last4=Hindell |first4=Mark A. |last5=Dickinson |first5=Joanne L. |last6=Jarman |first6=Simon N. |title=Measuring Animal Age with DNA Methylation: From Humans to Wild Animals |journal=Frontiers in Genetics |date=17 August 2017 |volume=8 |doi=10.3389/fgene.2017.00106 |pmid=28878806 |pmc=5572392 |page=106 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name="Horvath2013"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | year = 2013 | title = DNA methylation age of human tissues and cell types | url = | journal = Genome Biology | volume = 14| issue = 10 | page = R115 | doi = 10.1186/gb-2013-14-10-r115 | pmid=24138928 | pmc=4015143}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2015erratum"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | year = 2015 | title = Erratum to: DNA methylation age of human tissues and cell types | journal = Genome Biology | volume = 16 | issue = 1| page = 96 | doi = 10.1186/s13059-015-0649-6 | pmid = 25968125 | pmc=4427927}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Christiansen2015"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Christiansen | first1 = L | date = 2015 | title = DNA methylation age is associated with mortality in a longitudinal Danish twin study| journal = Aging Cell | volume =15 | issue =1| pages = 149–154| doi=10.1111/acel.12421 | pmid=26594032 | pmc=4717264}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Horvath2015centenarian"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Horvath |first1=Steve |last2=Pirazzini |first2=Chiara |last3=Bacalini |first3=Maria Giulia |last4=Gentilini |first4=Davide |last5=Di Blasio |first5=Anna Maria |last6=Delledonne |first6=Massimo |last7=Mari |first7=Daniela |last8=Arosio |first8=Beatrice |last9=Monti |first9=Daniela |last10=Passarino |first10=Giuseppe |last11=De Rango |first11=Francesco |last12=D'Aquila |first12=Patrizia |last13=Giuliani |first13=Cristina |last14=Marasco |first14=Elena |last15=Collino |first15=Sebastiano |last16=Descombes |first16=Patrick |last17=Garagnani |first17=Paolo |last18=Franceschi |first18=Claudio |title=Decreased epigenetic age of PBMCs from Italian semi-supercentenarians and their offspring |journal=Aging |date=15 December 2015 |volume=7 |issue=12 |pages=1159–1170 |doi=10.18632/aging.100861 |pmid=26678252 |pmc=4712339 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Horvath2015cerebellum"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Horvath |first1=Steve |last2=Mah |first2=Vei |last3=Lu |first3=Ake T. |last4=Woo |first4=Jennifer S. |last5=Choi |first5=Oi-Wa |last6=Jasinska |first6=Anna J. |last7=Riancho |first7=José A. |last8=Tung |first8=Spencer |last9=Coles |first9=Natalie S. |last10=Braun |first10=Jonathan |last11=Vinters |first11=Harry V. |last12=Coles |first12=L. Stephen |title=The cerebellum ages slowly according to the epigenetic clock |journal=Aging |date=11 May 2015 |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=294–306 |doi=10.18632/aging.100742 |pmid=26000617 |pmc=4468311 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2015syndromeX"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Walker |first1=Richard F. |last2=Liu |first2=Jia Sophie |last3=Peters |first3=Brock A. |last4=Ritz |first4=Beate R. |last5=Wu |first5=Timothy |last6=Ophoff |first6=Roel A. |last7=Horvath |first7=Steve |title=Epigenetic age analysis of children who seem to evade aging |journal=Aging |date=15 May 2015 |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=334–339 |doi=10.18632/aging.100744 |pmid=25991677 |pmc=4468314 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2014obesity"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | last2 = Erhart | first2 = W | last3 = Brosch | first3 = M | last4 = Ammerpohl | first4 = O | last5 = von Schoenfels | first5 = W | last6 = Ahrens | first6 = M | last7 = Heits | first7 = N | last8 = Bell | first8 = JT | last9 = Tsai | first9 = PC | last10 = Spector | first10 = TD | last11 = Deloukas | first11 = P | last12 = Siebert | first12 = R | last13 = Sipos | first13 = B | last14 = Becker | first14 = T | last15 = Roecken | first15 = C | last16 = Schafmayer | first16 = C | last17 = Hampe | first17 = J | year = 2014 | title = Obesity accelerates epigenetic aging of human liver | journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A | volume = 111| issue = 43| pages = 15538–43| doi = 10.1073/pnas.1412759111 | pmid = 25313081 | pmc=4217403| bibcode = 2014PNAS..11115538H }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="ScienceDaily"&gt;{{cite web|last=University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), Health Sciences|title=Scientist uncovers internal clock able to measure age of most human tissues; Women's breast tissue ages faster than rest of body|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/10/131020203006.htm|publisher=ScienceDaily|accessdate=22 October 2013|date=20 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Forbes"&gt;{{cite web|last=University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), Health Sciences|title=Scientists discover new biological clock with age-measuring potential|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/melaniehaiken/2013/10/21/scientists-discover-new-biological-clock-that-measures-aging/|work=Forbes|accessdate=21 October 2013|date=21 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Berdyshev1967"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Berdyshev | first1 = G | last2 = Korotaev | first2 = G | last3 = Boiarskikh | first3 = G | last4 = Vaniushin | first4 = B | year = 1967 | title = Nucleotide composition of DNA and RNA from somatic tissues of humpback and its changes during spawning | url = | journal = Biokhimiia | volume = 31 | issue = 5| pages = 988–993 |pmid=5628601 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Bell2012"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bell | first1 = JT | last2 = Tsai | first2 = PC | last3 = Yang | first3 = TP | last4 = Pidsley | first4 = R | last5 = Nisbet | first5 = J | last6 = Glass | first6 = D | last7 = Mangino | first7 = M | last8 = Zhai | first8 = G | last9 = Zhang | first9 = F | last10 = Valdes | first10 = A | last11 = Shin | first11 = SY | last12 = Dempster | first12 = EL | last13 = Murray | first13 = RM | last14 = Grundberg | first14 = E | last15 = Hedman | first15 = AK | last16 = Nica | first16 = A | last17 = Small | first17 = KS | last18 = Dermitzakis | first18 = ET | last19 = McCarthy | first19 = MI | last20 = Mill | first20 = J | last21 = Spector | first21 = TD | last22 = Deloukas | first22 = P | year = 2012 | title = Epigenome-wide scans identify differentially methylated regions for age and age-related phenotypes in a healthy ageing population | url = | journal = PLoS Genet | volume = 8 | issue = 4| page = e1002629 | doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.1002629| pmid = 22532803 | pmc = 3330116 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Biome2013"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.biomedcentral.com/biome/novel-epigenetic-clock-predicts-tissue-age/ |title=Novel epigenetic clock predicts tissue age |publisher=Biome |date=October 21, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131231083320/https://www.biomedcentral.com/biome/novel-epigenetic-clock-predicts-tissue-age/ |archivedate=December 31, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Collado2007"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Collado | first1 = M | last2 = Blasco | first2 = MA | last3 = Serrano | first3 = M | date = Jul 2007 | title = Cellular senescence in cancer and aging | url = | journal = Cell | volume = 130 | issue = 2| pages = 223–33 | doi=10.1016/j.cell.2007.07.003| pmid = 17662938 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Gibbs2014"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Gibbs | first1 = WT | year = 2014 | title = Biomarkers and ageing: The clock-watcher | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 508 | issue = 7495| pages = 168–170 | doi = 10.1038/508168a | pmid=24717494| bibcode = 2014Natur.508..168G | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="DNAmAgeSoftware"&gt;[http://labs.genetics.ucla.edu/horvath/htdocs/dnamage/ DNA methylation age software]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Bocklandt2011"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bocklandt | first1 = S | last2 = Lin | first2 = W | last3 = Sehl | first3 = ME | last4 = Sánchez | first4 = FJ | last5 = Sinsheimer | first5 = JS | last6 = Horvath | first6 = S | last7 = Vilain | first7 = E | year = 2011 | title = Epigenetic Predictor of Age | journal = PLoS ONE | volume = 6 | issue = 6| page = e14821 | pmid = 21731603 | doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0014821 | pmc=3120753| bibcode = 2011PLoSO...614821B }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Hannum2013"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Hannum | first1 = G | last2 = Guinney | first2 = J | last3 = Zhao | first3 = L | last4 = Zhang | first4 = L | last5 = Hughes | first5 = G | last6 = Sadda | first6 = S | last7 = Klotzle | first7 = B | last8 = Bibikova | first8 = M | last9 = Fan | first9 = JB | last10 = Gao | first10 = Y | last11 = Deconde | first11 = R | last12 = Chen | first12 = M | last13 = Rajapakse | first13 = I | last14 = Friend | first14 = S | last15 = Ideker | first15 = T | last16 = Zhang | first16 = K | year = 2013 | title = Genome-wide methylation profiles reveal quantitative views of human aging rates | journal = Mol Cell | volume = 49 | issue = 2| pages = 359–367 | doi=10.1016/j.molcel.2012.10.016 | pmid=23177740 | pmc=3780611}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Koch2011"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Koch |first1=Carmen M. |last2=Wagner |first2=Wolfgang |title=Epigenetic-aging-signature to determine age in different tissues |journal=Aging |date=26 October 2011 |volume=3 |issue=10 |pages=1018–1027 |doi=10.18632/aging.100395 |pmid=22067257 |pmc=3229965 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2015DownSyndrome"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | last2 = Garagnani | first2 = P | last3 = Bacalini | first3 = MG | last4 = Pirazzini | first4 = C | last5 = Salvioli | first5 = S | last6 = Gentilini | first6 = D | last7 = Di Blasio | first7 = AM | last8 = Giuliani | first8 = C | last9 = Tung | first9 = S | last10 = Vinters | first10 = HV | last11 = Franceschi | first11 = C | date = Feb 2015 | title = Accelerated epigenetic aging in Down syndrome | journal = Aging Cell | volume = 14| issue = 3| pages = 491–95| doi = 10.1111/acel.12325 | pmid = 25678027 | pmc=4406678}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2015HIV"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | last2 = Levine | first2 = AJ | year = 2015 | title = HIV-1 infection accelerates age according to the epigenetic clock | journal = J Infect Dis | volume = 212| issue = 10| pages = 1563–73| doi = 10.1093/infdis/jiv277 | pmid=25969563 | pmc=4621253}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Levine2016menopause"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Levine | first1 = M | date = 2016 | title = Menopause accelerates biological aging| journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci USA | volume = 113| issue = 33| pages =9327–32| pmid= 27457926 | pmc= 4995944| doi=10.1073/pnas.1604558113}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Levine2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Levine |first1=Morgan E |last2=Lu |first2=Ake T |last3=Bennett |first3=David A |last4=Horvath |first4=Steve |title=Epigenetic age of the pre-frontal cortex is associated with neuritic plaques, amyloid load, and Alzheimer's disease related cognitive functioning |journal=Aging |date=18 December 2015 |volume=7 |issue=12 |pages=1198–1211 |doi=10.18632/aging.100864 |pmid=26684672 |pmc=4712342 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Lu2016"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lu | first1 =A | date = 2016 | title = Genetic variants near MLST8 and DHX57 affect the epigenetic age of the cerebellum.| journal = Nature Communications | volume =7 | issue = | pages =10561| doi=10.1038/ncomms10561 | pmid=26830004 | pmc=4740877| bibcode =2016NatCo...710561L }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Lu2017"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lu | first1 =A | date = 2017 | title = Genetic architecture of epigenetic and neuronal ageing rates in human brain regions.| journal = Nature Communications | volume =8 | issue =15353 | pages =15353| doi=10.1038/ncomms15353 | pmid=28516910 | pmc=5454371 | bibcode =2017NatCo...815353L }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Maierhofer2017Werner"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Maierhofer | first1 = A | date = 2017 | title = Accelerated epigenetic aging in Werner syndrome.| journal = Aging| volume =9 | issue = 4| pages =1143–1152| pmid=28377537| pmc= 5425119 | doi=10.18632/aging.101217}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Marioni2015mortality"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marioni | first1 = R | last2 = Shah | first2 = S | last3 = McRae | first3 = A | last4 = Chen | first4 = B | last5 = Colicino | first5 = E | last6 = Harris | first6 = S | last7 = Gibson | first7 = J | last8 = Henders | first8 = A | last9 = Redmond | first9 = P | last10 = Cox | first10 = S | last11 = Pattie | first11 = A | last12 = Corley | first12 = J | last13 = Murphy | first13 = L | last14 = Martin | first14 = N | last15 = Montgomery | first15 = G | last16 = Feinberg | first16 = A | last17 = Fallin | first17 = M | last18 = Multhaup | first18 = M | last19 = Jaffe | first19 = A | last20 = Joehanes | first20 = R | last21 = Schwartz | first21 = J | last22 = Just | first22 = A | last23 = Lunetta | first23 = K | last24 = Murabito | first24 = JM | last25 = Starr | first25 = J | last26 = Horvath | first26 = S | last27 = Baccarelli | first27 = A | last28 = Levy | first28 = D | last29 = Visscher | first29 = P | last30 = Wray | first30 = N | last31 = Deary | first31 = I | year = 2015 | title = DNA methylation age of blood predicts all-cause mortality in later life | journal = Genome Biology | volume = 16 | issue = 1| page = 25 | doi = 10.1186/s13059-015-0584-6 | pmid=25633388 | pmc=4350614}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Marioni2015fitness"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marioni | first1 = R | last2 = Shah | first2 = S | last3 = McRae | first3 = A | last4 = Ritchie | first4 = S | last5 = Muniz-Terrera | first5 = GH | last6 = SE | last7 = Gibson | first7 = J | last8 = Redmond | first8 = P | last9 = SR | first9 = C | last10 = Pattie | first10 = A | last11 = Corley | first11 = J | last12 = Taylor | first12 = A | last13 = Murphy | first13 = L | last14 = Starr | first14 = J | last15 = Horvath | first15 = S | last16 = Visscher | first16 = P | last17 = Wray | first17 = N | last18 = Deary | first18 = I | year = 2015 | title = The epigenetic clock is correlated with physical and cognitive fitness in the Lothian Birth Cohort 1936 | journal = International Journal of Epidemiology | volume = 44| issue = 4| pages = 1388–1396| doi = 10.1093/ije/dyu277 | pmid = 25617346 | pmc=4588858}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Teschendorff2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Teschendorff | first1 = AE | last2 = Menon | first2 = U | last3 = Gentry-Maharaj | first3 = A | last4 = Ramus | first4 = SJ | last5 = Weisenberger | first5 = DJ | last6 = Shen | first6 = H | last7 = Campan | first7 = M | last8 = Noushmehr | first8 = H | last9 = Bell | first9 = CG | last10 = Maxwell | first10 = AP | last11 = Savage | first11 = DA | last12 = Mueller-Holzner | first12 = E | last13 = Marth | first13 = C | last14 = Kocjan | first14 = G | last15 = Gayther | first15 = SA | last16 = Jones | first16 = A | last17 = Beck | first17 = S | last18 = Wagner | first18 = W | last19 = Laird | first19 = PW | last20 = Jacobs | first20 = IJ | last21 = Widschwendter | first21 = M | year = 2010 | title = Age-dependent DNA methylation of genes that are suppressed in stem cells is a hallmark of cancer | journal = Genome Res | volume = 20 | issue = 4| pages = 440–446 | doi=10.1101/gr.103606.109 | pmid=20219944 | pmc=2847747}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Horvath2012"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horvath | first1 = S | last2 = Zhang | first2 = Y | last3 = Langfelder | first3 = P | last4 = Kahn | first4 = R | last5 = Boks | first5 = M | last6 = van Eijk | first6 = K | last7 = van den Berg | first7 = L | last8 = Ophoff | first8 = RA | year = 2012 | title = Aging effects on DNA methylation modules in human brain and blood tissue | journal = Genome Biol | volume = 13 | issue = 10| page = R97 | doi = 10.1186/gb-2012-13-10-r97 | pmid=23034122 | pmc=4053733}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Nordfjall2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Nordfjäll | first1 = K | last2 = Svenson | first2 = U | last3 = Norrback | first3 = KF | last4 = Adolfsson | first4 = R | last5 = Roos | first5 = G | date = Mar 2010 | title = Large-scale parent-child comparison confirms a strong paternal influence on telomere length | journal = Eur J Hum Genet | volume = 18 | issue = 3| pages = 385–89 | doi = 10.1038/ejhg.2009.178 | pmid = 19826452 | pmc=2987222}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Rakyan2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rakyan | first1 = VK | last2 = Down | first2 = TA | last3 = Maslau | first3 = S | last4 = Andrew | first4 = T | last5 = Yang | first5 = TP | last6 = Beyan | first6 = H | last7 = Whittaker | first7 = P | last8 = McCann | first8 = OT | last9 = Finer | first9 = S | last10 = Valdes | first10 = AM | last11 = Leslie | first11 = RD | last12 = Deloukas | first12 = P | last13 = Spector | first13 = TD | year = 2010 | title = Human aging-associated DNA hypermethylation occurs preferentially at bivalent chromatin domains | journal = Genome Res | volume = 20 | issue = 4| pages = 434–439 | doi=10.1101/gr.103101.109 | pmid=20219945 | pmc=2847746}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Wang2012"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wang |first1=Ye |last2=Zang |first2=Xinjie |last3=Wang |first3=Yao |last4=Chen |first4=Peng |title=High expression of p16INK4a and low expression of Bmi1 are associated with endothelial cellular senescence in the human cornea |journal=Molecular Vision |date=2012 |volume=18 |pages=803–15 |pmc=3324359 |pmid=22509111 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="Chen2016"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Chen | first1 = B | last2 = Marioni | first2 = ME | year = 2016 | title = DNA methylation-based measures of biological age: meta-analysis predicting time to death. | journal = Aging | volume = 8 | issue =9 | pages = 1844–1865 | doi= 10.18632/aging.101020 | pmid = 27690265 | pmc=5076441}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pmid24490752&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Weidner |first1=Carola |last2=Lin |first2=Qiong |last3=Koch |first3=Carmen |last4=Eisele |first4=Lewin |last5=Beier |first5=Fabian |last6=Ziegler |first6=Patrick |last7=Bauerschlag |first7=Dirk |last8=Jöckel |first8=Karl-Heinz |last9=Erbel |first9=Raimund |last10=Mühleisen |first10=Thomas |last11=Zenke |first11=Martin |last12=Brümmendorf |first12=Tim |last13=Wagner |first13=Wolfgang |title=Aging of blood can be tracked by DNA methylation changes at just three CpG sites |journal=Genome Biology |date=2014 |volume=15 |issue=2 |pages=R24 |doi=10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r24 |pmid=24490752 |pmc=4053864 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite journal |last1=Aquino |first1=Eunise M. |last2=Benton |first2=Miles C. |last3=Haupt |first3=Larisa M. |last4=Sutherland |first4=Heidi G. |last5=riffiths |first5=Lyn R. G |last6=Lea |first6=Rodney A. |title=Current Understanding of DNA Methylation and Age-related Disease |journal=OBM Genetics |date=12 April 2018 |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=1 |doi=10.21926/obm.genet.1802016 |doi-access=free }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Field |first1=Adam E. |last2=Robertson |first2=Neil A. |last3=Wang |first3=Tina |last4=Havas |first4=Aaron |last5=Ideker |first5=Trey |last6=Adams |first6=Peter D. |title=DNA Methylation Clocks in Aging: Categories, Causes, and Consequences |journal=Molecular Cell |date=September 2018 |volume=71 |issue=6 |pages=882–895 |doi=10.1016/j.molcel.2018.08.008 |doi-access=free }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Bell | first1 = C. G. | last2 = Lowe | first2 = R. | last3 = Adams | first3 = P. D. | last4 = Baccarelli | first4 = A. A. | last5 = Beck | first5 = S. | last6 = Bell | first6 = J. T. | last7 = Ideker | first7 = T. | year = 2019 | title = DNA methylation aging clocks: challenges and recommendations | url = https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-019-1824-y | journal = Genome Biology | volume = 20 | issue = 1| page = 249 | doi = 10.1186/s13059-019-1824-y }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Wang |first1=Meng |last2=Lemos |first2=Bernardo |title=Ribosomal DNA harbors an evolutionarily conserved clock of biological aging |journal=Genome Research |date=March 2019 |volume=29 |issue=3 |pages=325–333 |doi=10.1101/gr.241745.118 |doi-access=free }}
[[Category:Ageing]]
[[Category:Cancer]]
[[Category:Gerontology]]
[[Category:Epigenetics]]
[[Category:Life extension]]</text>
      <sha1>nbpk7aapcxwgaomji7x2w7w20e5rm64</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
