<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>East German balloon escape</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56998952</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961209205</id>
      <parentid>961208900</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-07T06:10:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>195.144.91.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Aftermath */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="24392" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Flight from East Germany by eight people, 1979}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Infobox event
| title                    = 
| image                    = 
| image_size               = &lt;!-- |image_upright= is preferred for most cases, see WP:IMGSIZE --&gt;
| image_upright            = 
| image_alt                = 
| caption                  = 
| native_name              = 
| native_name_lang         = 
| english_name             = 
| time                     = 02:00am (approximate)
| duration                 = 25 minutes
| date                     = {{start date|1979|09|16}}
| venue                    = 
| location                 = [[Bad Lobenstein#districts|Oberlemnitz]], [[East Germany]]&lt;br&gt;(takeoff)&lt;br&gt;[[Naila]], [[West Germany]]&lt;br&gt; (landing)
| coordinates              = {{coord|50|28|59.05|N|11|35|28.82|E|format=dms|display=inline}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Wetzel |first1=Günter |title=Die Nacht der Flucht |url=https://www.ballonflucht.de/flucht.html |website=Ballonflucht.de |accessdate=16 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;(takeoff)&lt;br&gt;{{coord|50|19|N|11|41|E|format=dms|display=inline,title}}&lt;br&gt;(landing)
| also_known_as            = 
| type                     = 
| theme                    = 
| cause                    = 
| motive                   = 
| target                   = 
| first_reporter           = 
| budget                   = 
| patron                   = 
| organisers               = Peter Strelzyk &amp; family&lt;br&gt; Günter Wetzel &amp; family
| filmed_by                = 
| participants             = 8
| outcome                  = Successful escape to West Germany
| casualties1              = 
| casualties2              = 
| casualties3              = 
| reported deaths          = 
| reported injuries        = 2
| reported missing         = 
| reported property damage = 
| burial                   = 
| inquiries                = 
| inquest                  = 
| coroner                  = 
| arrests                  = 
| suspects                 = 
| accused                  = 
| convicted                = 
| charges                  = 
| trial                    = 
| verdict                  = 
| convictions              = 
| sentence                 = 
| publication_bans         = 
| litigation               = 
| awards                   = 
| url                      = 
| blank_label              = &lt;!-- or |blank_data= --&gt;
| blank1_label             = &lt;!-- or |blank1_data= --&gt;
| blank2_label             = &lt;!-- or |blank2_data= --&gt;
| website                  = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
| notes                    = Portrayed in ''[[Night Crossing]]'' (1982) and ''Der Ballon'' (2018)
}}
The '''East German balloon escape''' took place at approximately 2:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. on September 16, 1979.  Two families, with eight members in total, escaped the communist country of [[East Germany]] by crossing the border to [[West Germany]] in a homemade [[hot air balloon]]. The plot to accomplish this was carried out over a period of one and a half years, including an unsuccessful attempt, three different balloons, and various modifications until the successful escape occurred. One failed crossing alerted the government to the plot, but the police were not able to identify the suspects before their flight to the west.

==Background==
[[File:System of gdr border fortification.jpg|thumb|Diagram of border fortifications]]
The [[Eastern bloc]] country of [[East Germany]] was separated from [[West Germany]] by the [[Inner German border]] and the [[Berlin Wall]], which were heavily fortified with [[watchtowers]], [[land mines]], armed soldiers, and various other measures to prevent its citizens from escaping to The West. The [[Border Troops of the German Democratic Republic|East German border patrols]] were instructed by standing order to prevent border penetration by all means including lethal force ([[Schießbefehl]] ("order to fire")).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=|title=Die Todesopfer an der Berliner Mauer 1961–1989. Ein biographisches Handbuch.|last=Hertle|first=Hans-Hermann|last2=Nooke|first2=Maria|publisher=|year=2009|isbn=3-86153-517-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peter Strelzyk, (1942-2017), an electrician and former East German Air Force mechanic, and Günter Wetzel, (born 1955), a bricklayer by trade,{{r|wp1}} were coworkers at a local plastics factory{{r|ds1}} who had been friends for four years. They shared a desire to flee the country and began discussing ways to cross the border. On March 7, 1978, they agreed to work to plan an escape.{{r|pb1}} They considered building a [[helicopter]] but quickly realized they would not be able to acquire an engine capable of powering such a craft. Next, they decided to investigate the idea of constructing a hot air balloon,{{r|pm1}} having been inspired by a television program about ballooning.{{r|wp1}} An alternate account is that they were given a magazine article about the [[Albuquerque International Balloon Fiesta|International Balloon Festival]] in [[Albuquerque, New Mexico]]. by a relative.{{r|pb1}}

==Construction==
The pair began research into balloons. Their plan was to escape with their wives and total of four children (aged 2 to 15). They calculated the weight of the passengers and the craft itself to be around {{convert|750|kg}}. Subsequent calculations determined a balloon capable of lifting this weight would need to hold {{convert|2000|m3|sp=us}} heated to {{convert|100|C}}. The next calculation was the amount of material needed for the balloon, estimated at {{convert|800|m2|sp=us}}.{{r|pm1}}

The pair lived in [[Pößneck]], a small town of about 20,000 where large quantities of cloth would not be available without raising attention. They tried neighboring towns of [[Rudolstadt]], [[Saalfeld]], and [[Jena]] without success.{{r|hn1}} They traveled {{convert|50|km}} to [[Gera, Germany|Gera]] where they purchased {{convert|1|meter}} wide rolls of cotton cloth totaling {{convert|850|meter}} in length at a department store after telling the astonished clerk that they needed the large quantity of material to use as tent lining for their camping club.{{r|pm1|hn1}}

Wetzel spent two weeks sewing the cloth into a balloon shaped bag, {{convert|15|meter}} wide by {{convert|20| meter}} long, on a 40 year old manually-operated sewing machine. Strelzyk spent the time building the gondola and burner assembly. The gondola was made from an iron frame, [[sheet metal]] floor, and clothesline ran around the perimeter every {{convert|150|mm}} for the sides. The burner was made using two {{convert|11|kg|adj=on}} bottles of [[liquid propane]] household gas, hoses, water pipe, a nozzle, and a piece of stove pipe.{{r|pm1}}

==Test==
The team was ready to test the craft in April 1978. After days of searching, they found a suitable secluded forest clearing near [[Ziegenrück]], {{convert|10|km}} from the border and {{convert|30|km}} from Pößneck. After lighting the burner one night, they failed to inflate the balloon. They thought the problem could be because they laid the balloon out on the ground. After weeks of additional searching, they found a {{convert|25|meter|adj=on}} cliff at a rock quarry where they could suspend the balloon vertically before inflation but that was also unsuccessful.{{r|pm1}}

Next they decided to fill the bag first with air at ambient temperature before using the burner to raise the air temperature to provide lift. They constructed a blower with 14-hp {{cvt|250|cc}} motorcycle engine, started with a [[Trabant]] automobile starter power by [[Jump start (vehicle)|jumper cables]] from Strelzyk's [[Moskvitch]] sedan. This engine, quieted by a Trabant [[muffler]], turned {{convert|1|meter}} long fan blades to inflate the balloon. They also used a home-made [[flamethrower]], similar to the gondola's burner, to pre-heat the air faster. With these modifications in place, they returned to the secluded clearing to try again but could still not inflate the balloon. Using the blower did allow them to discover that the cotton material with which they fashioned the balloon was too porous and leaked massively.{{r|pm1}}
 
Their unsuccessful effort cost them 2,400 [[East German mark|DDM]]. Strelzyk disposed of the cloth by burning it in his furnace over several weeks.{{r|pm1}}

==Second attempt==
The pair purchased samples of different fabrics in local stores, including [[umbrella]] material and various samples of [[taffeta]] and [[nylon]]. They used an oven to test the material for [[heat resistance]] and created a test rig from a [[vacuum cleaner]] and a water-filled glass tube to determine which material would allow the vacuum to exert the most suction on the water. This would reveal which material was densest. The umbrella covering performed the best but was also the most expensive. They instead selected a [[synthetic fibers|synthetic]] kind of taffeta.{{r|pm1}}

To purchase a large quantity of fabric without arousing too much suspicion, they again drove to a distant city. This time they traveled over {{convert|160|km}} to a department store in [[Leipzig]]. Their [[cover-up|cover story]] this time was that they were in a sailing club and needed the material to make sails. The quantity they needed had to be ordered, and although they feared the purchase may have been reported to East Germany's [[Stasi|State Security Service]] (Stasi), they returned the next day and picked up the material without incident. They paid 4,800 [[East German mark|DDM]] ({{currency|720|USD}}) for {{convert|800|meter}} of {{convert|1|meter||-wide|adj=mid}} fabric.{{r|pm1}} On the way home, they also purchased an electric motor to speed up the pedal-operated sewing machine they had been using to sew the material into the desired balloon shape.{{r|hn1}}

Wetzel spent the next week sewing the material into another balloon, accomplishing the task faster the second time with the now-electric sewing machine. Soon after, they returned to the forest clearing and had the bag inflated in about five minutes using the blower and flame thrower. The bag arose and held air, but the burner on the gondola was not powerful enough to create the heat needed for lift. They continued experimenting for months, doubling the number of propane tanks and trying different mixtures of fuels. Disappointed with the result, Wetzel decided to abandon the project and instead started to pursue the idea of building a small [[gasoline]] engine-powered [[light aircraft|light airplane]]{{r|pm1}} or a [[glider (aircraft)|glider]].{{r|pb1}}

Strelzyk continued trying to improve the burner. In June 1979, he discovered that with the propane tank inverted, additional pressure caused the liquid propane to gasify which would create a bigger flame. He modified the gondola to mount the propane tanks upside down, and returned to the test site where he found the new configuration produced a {{convert|12|m}} long flame. Strelzyk was ready to attempt an escape.{{r|pm1}}

==First escape attempt==
On July 3, 1979, the weather and wind conditions were favorable. The entire Strelzyk family lifted from a forest clearing at 1:30am and climbed at a rate of {{convert|4|meter}} per second. They reached an altitude of {{convert|6600|ft}} according to an [[altimeter]] Strelzyk had made by modifying a [[barometer]]. A moderate wind was blowing them towards the border and freedom in [[West Germany]]. The balloon entered a cloud, atmospheric [[water vapor]] condensed on the balloon and the added weight of the water caused the balloon to descend. They landed safely approximately {{convert|180|meters}} from the border at the edge of the heavily mined border zone. Unsure of where they were, Strelzyk explored until he found a piece of litter &amp;ndash; a bread bag from a bakery in [[Wernigerode]], an East German town. The family spent nine hours carefully extricating themselves from the {{convert|500|meter}} wide border zone to avoid detection. They also had to travel unnoticed through a {{convert|5|km}} restricted zone before hiking back a total of {{convert|14|km|sp=us}} to their car and all the launch paraphernalia they left there.{{r|pm1}} They made it home just in time to report absent due to sickness from work and school.{{r|hn1}}

The balloon was left where it landed and discovered later that morning. Strelzyk destroyed everything remaining and sold his car fearing that could connect him to the balloon.{{r|pm1}} On August 14, 1979, the Stasi advertised for help finding the "perpetrator of a serious offence" and listed in detail all the items left at the crash site.{{r|wh1}} He felt that the Stasi would eventually trace the balloon to him and the Wetzels. Strelzyk conferred with Wetzel and they agreed their best chance was to quickly build another balloon and get out as soon as possible.{{r|pm1}}

==Successful escape==
[[File:Ballon-flame02.jpg|thumb|Example of balloon gas flame at night]]
The pair decided to double the balloon's size to {{convert|4000|m3|sp=us}} in volume, {{convert|20|meter}} in diameter, and {{convert|25|meter}} in height. They needed {{convert|1250|m2|sp=us}} of taffeta, and purchased the material, in various colors and patterns, all over the country to escape suspicion. Wetzel sewed a third balloon, using over {{convert|6|km|sp=us}} of thread and Strelzyk rebuilt everything else as before. They were ready in six weeks with a {{convert|180|kg|adj=on}} balloon, and a payload of {{convert|550|kg}}, including the gondola, equipment, and cargo (the two families). Confident in their calculations, they found weather conditions right on September 15 when a violent thunderstorm created the correct winds and set off for the launch site in Strelzyk's replacement car (a [[Wartburg (car)|Wartburg]]) and a [[moped]]. Arriving at 1:30 am, they needed just ten minutes to inflate the balloon and three to heat the air.{{r|pm1}}

They lifted off just after 2:00 am and, due to not cutting the tethers holding the gondola to the ground synchronously, it tilted sending the flame towards the fabric which caught fire. After the fire was put out with an extinguisher they had brought for just such an emergency, the balloon climbed to {{convert|2000|meters}} in nine minutes, drifting towards West Germany at {{convert|30|km/h}}. They flew for 28 minutes, with the temperature at {{convert|-8|C}} and no shelter as the gondola was just a railing of clothesline. A design calculation resulted in the burner stovepipe being too long, causing the flame to be too high in the balloon creating excessive pressure which caused the balloon to split. Air rushing out of the split extinguished the burner flame. Wetzel was able to re-light the flame with a match and had to do so several more times before they landed. At one point, they increased the flame to the maximum possible and rose to {{convert|2500|meter}}. They later learned they had been high enough to be detected, but not identified, on [[radar]] by West German [[air traffic controller]]s.{{r|pm1}} They had also been detected on the East German side by a night watchman at the district culture house in [[Bad Lobenstein]]. The report of an [[unidentified flying object]] heading toward the border caused guards to activate search lights, but the balloon was too high and out of reach of the lights.{{r|bm1}}

The tear in the balloon meant they had to use the burner much more often and the distance they could travel was greatly limited. Wetzel later said he thought they could have traveled another {{convert|50|km}} had the balloon remained intact. They made out the border crossing at [[Rudolphstein]] on the [[Bundesautobahn 9|A9]] and saw the search lights. When the propane ran out they descended quickly, landing near the town of [[Naila]], in the West German state of [[Bavaria]] and only {{convert|10|km}} from the border. The only injury was suffered by Wetzel, who broke his leg upon landing.{{r|pm1}} They thought they had made it as they had seen red and yellow colored lights which were not common in East Germany.{{r|wp1}} They also saw small farms, different than the large state-run operations in the east. Another clue was modern farm equipment that was unlike older equipment that was used in East Germany.{{r|tm1}} Two [[Bavarian State Police]] officers saw the balloon's flickering light and headed to where they thought it would land and found Strelzyk and Wetzel who first asked if they had made it to the west, although they noticed the police car was an [[Audi]] – another sign they were in West Germany. Upon learning they had, they happily called for their families to join them.{{r|pm1}}

==Aftermath==
The families decided to initially settle in Naila where they landed. Wetzel worked as an automobile mechanic and Strelzyk opened a TV repair shop in [[Bad Kissingen]]. Due to pressure on them from Stasi spies, the Strelzyks moved to [[Switzerland]] in 1985.{{r|bm1}} After the [[German reunification]] in 1990, they returned to their hometown of Pößneck and to their old home there.{{r|exp1}} The Wetzels remained in Bavaria.{{r|hn1}}

The West German weekly magazine ''[[Stern (magazine)|Stern]]'' paid Strelzyk and Wetzel for exclusive rights to the story.{{r|wp1}}

East Germany immediately increased border security, closed all small airports close to the border, and ordered the planes kept farther inland.{{r|pm1}} Propane gas tanks became registered products and large quantities of fabric suitable for balloon construction could no longer be purchased. Mail from East Germany to the families was prohibited.{{r|gr1}}

Erich Strelzyk learned of his brother's escape on the [[ZDF]] news and was arrested three hours after the landing in his [[Potsdam]] apartment. The arrest of family members was standard procedure to deter others from attempting escape. He was charged with "aiding and abetting escape" as were Strelzyk's sister Maria and her husband who were sentenced to 2½ years. The three were eventually released with the help of [[Amnesty International]].{{r|gr1}}

The escape has been portrayed in two films: ''[[Night Crossing]]'' (1982) and [[Ballon (2018 film)|''Ballon'']] (2018). The former, also called ''With the Wind to the West'' - the English translation of the German title, was an English-language film produced by [[Disney]]. The Strelzyks were reportedly "moved to tears" at the screening of the movie at [[Rockefeller Center]] in [[New York City]].{{r|gr1}}  The latter was a German-language production which "both families welcomed [Director] Herbig’s desire to, as he put it, 'make a German film for an international audience.'" Herbig said in 2018 that both the Strelzeyk and Wetzel families were dissatisfied with the Disney film.&lt;ref name=theguardian/&gt;

Peter Strelzyk died in 2017 at age 74 after a long illness.{{r|exp1}}

In 2017, the balloon was put on permanent exhibition at the [[Haus der Bayerischen Geschichte: Museum]].{{r|bm1}}

==Escapees==
The family members included:{{r|wp1}}
*Peter Strelzyk, age 37
*Doris Strelzyk
*Frank Strelzyk, age 15
*Andreas Strelzyk, age 11
*Günter Wetzel, 24
*Petra Wetzel
*Peter Wetzel, age 5
*Andreas Wetzel, age 2

==Media==
* The [[Disney]] film ''[[Night Crossing]]'' (1982) is an adaptation of the story{{r|exp1}}
* [[Michael Herbig]]'s film [[Ballon (2018 film)|''Ballon'']] (2018) is a German-language adaptation of the story&lt;ref&gt;{{imdb title|tt7125774|Ballon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[BBC]] program ''[[Outlook (radio programme)|Outlook]]'' Fleeing Communism in a Hot Air Balloon{{r|bbc1}}
* [[PBS]] ''[[Nova (American TV series)|Nova]]'' program "History's Great Escapes" (2004){{r|pbs1}}
* Doris Strelzyk, Peter Strelzyk, Gudrun Giese: Destiny Balloon Escape . Quadriga, Berlin 1999, {{ISBN |3-88679-330-3}}
* Jürgen Petschull : With the Wind to the West. The Adventurous Flight from Germany to Germany . Goldmann, Munich 1980, {{ISBN|3-442-11501-9}}
* The [[Netflix]] series ''[[White Rabbit Project (TV Series)|White Rabbit Project]]'', episode 2, "Jailbreak"

==See also==
* [[Winfried Freudenberg]]
* [[Escape attempts and victims of the inner German border]]

==References==
{{reflist|refs=

&lt;ref name="pm1"&gt;{{cite magazine|magazine=[[Popular Mechanics]]|title=The Freedom Balloon|date=Feb 1980|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m9UDAAAAMBAJ|page=100|last=Dornberg|first=John|accessdate=March 22, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="wp1"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Getler|first1=Michael|title=Harrowing Flight From East Germany|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1979/09/28/harrowing-flight-from-east-germany/d71708d0-3d36-4218-b8b9-e93e858c0df9/|accessdate=March 29, 2018|work=The Washington Post|date=September 28, 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="exp1"&gt;{{cite news|title=Man who fled East Germany in a homemade balloon and whose story was made into a film dies|url=https://www.express.co.uk/news/world/779583/Peter-Strelzyk-fled-East-Germany-hot-air-balloon-death|accessdate=March 29, 2018|work=The Express|date=March 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="wh1"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Souerbry|first1=Rachel|title=How Two Families Escaped East Germany In A Homemade Hot Air Balloon|url=https://www.ranker.com/list/families-escaped-east-germany-via-hot-air-balloon/rachel-souerbry|website=ranker.com|accessdate=March 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="tm1"&gt;{{cite news|title=EAST-WEST: The Great Balloon Escape|url=http://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,947451-1,00.html|accessdate=March 29, 2018|work=Time|date=October 1, 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=bbc1&gt;{{cite web|title=Fleeing Communism in a Hot Air Balloon|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p02tf7nb|website=bbc|accessdate=March 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="pbs1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Great Escapes|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/naziprison/escapes2.html|website=pbs.org|accessdate=April 16, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pb1&gt;{{cite book|last=Simpson|first=Paul|title=The Mammoth Book of Prison Breaks|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=V4nABAAAQBAJ|date=July 4, 2013|publisher=Little, Brown Book Group|isbn=978-1-4721-0024-5|page=216}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="bm1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Wetzel und Peter Strelzyk Ballonhülle der Strelzyks|url=https://www.museum.bayern/sammlung/geschichten/peter-strezlyk-und-guenter-wetzel.html|website=museum.bayern|accessdate=March 29, 2018|language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="ds1"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Snow|first1=Philipp|title=Balloon escape from the GDR With hot air to freedom|url=http://www.spiegel.de/einestages/ballonflucht-aus-der-ddr-a-948504.html|language=German|accessdate=March 29, 2018|work=Spiegel Online|date=September 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="hn1"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Overbye|first1=Stine|title=Fathers wanted to escape GDR in a hot air balloon|url=http://historianet.nl/oorlog/tweede-wereldoorlog/huisvaders-wilden-ddr-ontvluchten-in-luchtballon|accessdate=March 30, 2018|work=Historia|date=Apr 13, 2017|language=Dutch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="gr1"&gt;{{cite web|title=The Balloon Escape of Peter Strelzyk|url=http://www.goethe-rutheneum.de/schueler/semifach/flucht/geschis/peter.html|website=goethe-rutheneum.de|accessdate=March 30, 2018|language=German|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20130211024003/http://www.goethe-rutheneum.de/schueler/semifach/flucht/geschis/peter.html|archivedate=February 11, 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="theguardian"&gt;{{citenews|title=Film of daring balloon escape from East revives German identity debate|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/oct/07/east-germany-balloon-escape-film-revives-german-identity-debate|date=Oct 17, 2018|first=Kate|last=Connolly|accessdate=May 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
*[https://www.ballonflucht.de/html/englisch.html Escape by balloon] by Günter Wetzel (participant website)
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ef45Wnf47dc Video of balloon on museum display]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p02tf7nb BBC ''Outlook'' program]
*[http://digital.library.ucla.edu/collections/islandora/object/edu.ucla.library.specialCollections.latimes:4153 Photograph of Güenter Wetzel, Peter and Doris Strelzyk]
*[https://www.museum.bayern/sammlung/geschichten/peter-strezlyk-und-guenter-wetzel.html Photograph of the actual balloon, inflated in 1985 at a festival in Hof, Bavaria]

[[Category:Balloons (aircraft)]]
[[Category:Cold War history of Germany]]
[[Category:Escapes]]
[[Category:1979 in East Germany]]
[[Category:Inner German border]]
[[Category:East German defectors]]
[[Category:Eastern Bloc defectors]]
[[Category:East Germany–West Germany relations]]</text>
      <sha1>ed0l2aaw1e0im0bmtvmu8l558s8i5tp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
