<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.36</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>League of Mayapan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42987234</id>
    <revision>
      <id>962204255</id>
      <parentid>955893343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-06-12T18:00:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:600:8680:2040:A890:9DDD:37C8:EE6C</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hunac Ceel Cauich */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12733" xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=March 2018}}
{{Cite check|date=March 2018}}
{{Infobox country
|conventional_long_name = The League of Mayapan
|common_name = The League of Mayapan
|native_name = ''Luub Mayapan''
[[File:Maya Syllabary Lu 1.jpg|40px]][[File:Maya Syllabary U 3.jpg|40px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Bu 2.jpg|50px]]

[[File:Maya Syllabary Ma 3.jpg|40px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Ya 2.jpg|30px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Pa 2.jpg|40px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Na 2.jpg|40px]]
|era = [[Mesoamerican chronology|post classic period]]
|status = Confederation
|government_type = [[Oligarchy]]
|year_start = 1007&lt;ref&gt;Eggebrecht, A., Eggebrecht, E., Grube, N., Krejci, E., y Seipel, W. (2001) ''Mundo Maya''. Cholsamaj Fundacion [https://books.google.com/books?id=qS9uCyBi3VcC&amp;pg=PA155&amp;dq=liga+de+mayapan+1007&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiUxu38mZDaAhVSzVMKHfvWDqIQ6AEIJzAA#v=onepage&amp;q=liga%20de%20mayapan%201007&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; 
|year_end = 1441&lt;ref&gt;Mesa, O.C. (2011) ''Profecías mayas: Mito y realidad''. Ediciones Nowtilus [https://books.google.com/books?id=TOpzVOdVnykC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;dq=ah+xupan+xiu&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjLrZnPsJDaAhWO7lMKHVeEDZsQ6AEINzAC#v=onepage&amp;q=ah%20xupan%20xiu&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;
|event_start = [[Ah Mekat Tutul Xiu]] unites Chichen Itza, Mayapan, and Uxmal
|date_event1 = 1194
|event1 = [[Hunac Ceel|Hunac Ceel Cauich]] claims divine power and attempts to reform the government
|date_end = 
|event_end = Rebellions by the Tutul Xiu and their allies disintegrate the government
|p1      = Toltec Empire
|flag_p1 = Toltec Emblem.svg
|p2      = Maya collapse
|p3      = Itzá Kingdom (970–987)
|p4      = Ek' Balam
|s1 = Kuchkabal
|s2 = Tabasco (former state)
|s3 = Acalan
|s4 = Itzá Kingdom (1194–1697)
|s5 = Kowoj
|s6 = Yalain
|s7 = Kejache
|s8 = Mopan people{{!}}Mopan
|image_flag = 
|flag = 
|flag_type = 
|image_coat = 
|symbol = 
|symbol_type = 
|image_map = Mayapan 1200.jpg
|image_map_caption = The League of Mayapan at its greatest extent, circa 1200 {{citation needed|date=March 2018}}
|capital = [[Mayapan]], [[Uxmal]], [[Chichen Itza]]
|common_languages = [[Yucatec]], [[Chontal Maya language|Chontal]], [[Itzaʼ language|Itza]], [[Mopan Maya language|Mopan]], [[Lakantun]], [[Q'eqchi' language|Q'eqchi]], [[Ch’orti’ language|Ch'orti']], [[Sakapultek language|Sakapultek]], [[Poqomchiʼ language|Pokomchi]], [[Sakapultec]] [[Uspantek language|Uspantek]] [[Q’anjob’al language|Q'anjob'al]]
|religion = [[Maya religion]]
|deputy1                     = [[Ah Mekat Tutul Xiu]] &lt;small&gt;(first)&lt;/small&gt;
|deputy2                     = [[Ah Xiu Xupan]] &lt;small&gt;(last)&lt;/small&gt;
|year_deputy1                = 987–1007
|year_deputy2                = 1441–1461
|
|today = {{flag|Mexico}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Guatemala}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Belize}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Honduras}}
}}
'''The League of Mayapan''' ([[Yucatec]]: '''Luub Mayapan''' [[Maya glyphs]]: [[File:Maya Syllabary Lu 1.jpg|20px]][[File:Maya Syllabary U 3.jpg|20px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Bu 2.jpg|25px]] [[File:Maya Syllabary Ma 3.jpg|20px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Ya 2.jpg|15px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Pa 2.jpg|20px]][[File:Maya Syllabary Na 2.jpg|20px]]) was a confederation of [[Maya civilization|Maya]] states in the [[Mesoamerican chronology|post classic period]] of [[Mesoamerica]] on the [[Yucatan peninsula]].

The main members of the league were the [[Itza people|Itza]], the [[Tutul-Xiu]], [[Mayapan]], and [[Uxmal]].

Mayapan means flag of the Maya. {{citation needed|date=September 2017}}

== Before the League ==

===The Itza===
The Itza were known as water witches. According to the [[Chilam Balam]] of Chumayel, in 325 they started immigrating to [[Bacalar]] from [[Petén Basin|Peten]]. From there many of them continued northwest, where they conquered the classical Maya city of Uuc Yabnal and renamed it as [[Chichen Itza]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.osea-cite.org/program/chichen_itza.php&lt;/ref&gt; They lived there from 550 to 692. After that for economic and political reasons the Itza moved to [[Chakan Putum]], where they lived until 928 when they returned to Chichen Itza.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Antonio |first= Meliz Bolio|date= 2005|title= Traducción del maya al español de "Libro de Chilam Balam de Chumayel"|trans-title=|url= |language=spanish |location= |publisher= |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Chichen Itza '2010 07.jpg|thumbnail|Chichen Itzá]]

===The Tutul Xiu===
The [[Tutul-Xiu]] were known as overflowing virtue. In the Seventh century they migrated to Yucatan. There their leader [[Ah Suytok Tutul Xiu]], nicknamed Chac Uitzil Hun, founded [[Uxmal]].
The date that this happened is disputed by a codex from [[Tizimín|Tizimin]], and another from [[Maní, Yucatán|Mani]].
In 869 Ah Mekat Tutul Xiu ruler of the Tutul Xius moved to Uxmal from Nonohual.
Nonohual's location is unknown, but was probably in Peten, it also might have been another name for [[Potonchán]] in [[Tabasco]] or [[Tula (Mesoamerican site)|Tula]].
The Tutul Xius were the main group of people forcing the Itzas out of Chichen Itza.
[[File:Uxmal1.jpg|thumbnail|Uxmal]]

===Cocom===
The [[Cocomes|Cocom]] were known as the lineage of the wood pigeon. They lived farther to the west and forced the Itza out of Chakan Putum. The Itzas spent forty years living in the [[rainforest]]. They called it Xulucmul (living under the trees in ash and poverty).

== Foundation ==
Before the foundation of the league, the Toltecs invaded Yucatan. Their leader was the semi-mythical king [[Kukulcan]]. Whether Kukulkan was real or not, the Toltecs had influence over the Maya there.

"''The indians who inhabited Chichen Itza, ruled by a great lord called Kukulcan, and showing this be true named the main building  Kukulcan, and say they came from the west and differing in whether entered before or after the Yzaes or with them, and said they were well prepared and had no wife or children, and say that after his return he was taken into Mexico by one of their gods and called Cezalcuati"
List of things Yucatan, Diego de Landa.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wayeb.org/download/resources/landa.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:YaxchilanDivineSerpent.jpg|thumbnail|[[Kukulkan]]]]

Ah Mekat Tutul Xiu, is considered the ruler who founded The League of Mayapan in 987. He unified Chichen Itza, Mayapan, and Uxmal. Chichen Itza being the main city, with a population of approximately 50,000 people. He continued to incorporate other areas, Zama ([[Tulum]]), Ichpatun, [[Izamal|Itzamal]], and The Cocom region.

== Hunac Ceel Cauich ==
[[File:Chac Xib Chac.jpg|thumbnail|Chac Xib Chac]]
[[File:Cenote en Chichén Itzá. Quintana Roo. México-7.jpg|thumbnail|A Karstik doline known as cenote]]
In 1175 The League began to disintegrate. A Cocom man named [[Hunac Ceel|Ceel Cauich Ah]] was ritually thrown into [[Sacred Cenote|the cenote of Chichen Itza]] ([[cenote]] being the a Spanish term for the Mayan word dzonot, which is a deep, [[karst]]ik sinkhole filled with water). The Sacred Cenote of Chichen Itza was specially considered an entrance to the afterlife and thus a site of pilgrimage. It is 15 meters deep from the ground to the water surface and its very steep walls made almost impossible to climb out if thrown into. But Ceel managed to survive and climbed out, which he used as a sign of his divine right to rule and proclaimed himself [[Ajaw]], a spiritual and political leader. He also renamed himself Hunac Ceel Cauich. The Itzáes did not fall for this ruse and negated to recognize his authority.
Ceel gathered many followers from Mayapan and The Cocom region. In 1194, Hunac Ceel Cauich declared war on [[Chac-Xib-Chac]] one of the ''K'ul Kokom'', the four rulers of Chichén Itzá. The other three ''K'ul Kokom'', and his brothers were Sac Xib Chac, Chac Ek Yuuan and Hun Yuuan Chac (also called uooh Puc). Ah Itzimthul Chac was also one of the Chac brothers, he ruled  Ichcanzihoo also known as T'ho in present-day [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]].

=== Legend of the depopulation of Chichen Itzá ===

Scientific data points to the fact that Chichén Itzá declined before the rise of Mayapan as a regional power, but ongoing research is currently being done in several Maya sites, so there's not any chronological certainty yet.

However, traditional sources (which are often mixed with fantasy and legend) say that Hunac Ceel Cauich had a daughter named [[Sac Nicté]] (in [[Yucatec Maya language|Yucatec Maya]] Sac Nikté' meaning white flower).  Sac Nicté fell in love with a member of the royalty of Chichen Itzá named [[Canek]] (Kaan Ek in Yucatec, meaning black snake). When they met Sac Nicté was 15 and Canek was 21. This was the same day Canek was crowned ruler if the Itzá. The Itzá chose new ruler every Katún Ahau (period of almost 20 years).&lt;ref&gt;http://homepage.univie.ac.at/elisabeth.trinkl/forum/forum0910/forum56navarro.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Based on this Canek became ruler of the Itzá on 22 November 1194. Sac Nicté and Canek instantly fell in love. Sac Nicté was destined, by prearranged marriage, to marry [[Ah Ulil]], ''Batab'' of [[Izamal]]. Canek and Sac Nicté slept together, later Canek stayed awake all night crying because he knew he could not marry Sac Nicté. Ah Ulil and Sac Nicté's wedding was to take place 37 days after Canek's coronation (29 December 1194). Three days before, the wedding fiancés arrived in Uxmal. Gifts from all over Mayeb arrived, Gold, animal tusks, perfume, emeralds, and turtle shells filled with quetzal feather. These gifts came from distant and near cities - except nothing arrived from Chichen Itzá. On the Day of the wedding, Uxmal was decorated with ribbons, feather, plants, and brightly painted bows, the people of the city were dancing and having parties in the street. ''Ajaws, Batabs, Halch Uiniks'', Nobles, and other elites arrived with minstrels. Canek had been invited and he arrived, with him he brought the Itzáes sixty best soldiers. Canek and his warriors ran to the altar where Sac Nicté was being married. Incense was burning and a priest was chanting. Sac Nicté, Canek, and the sixty warriors fled Uxmal, everything had happened so fast that nobody was able to try and stop them. Hunac Ceel, Ah Ulil, and other leaders traveled with a large army to Chichen Itzá only to find the city completely abandoned. Sac Nicté led the Itzá to [[Nojpetén]] where they established a new [[Peten Itza Kingdom|Itza Kingdom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://morgia.blogia.com/2004/102101-la-princesa-sac-nicte-leyenda-maya.php |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-10-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140223181526/http://morgia.blogia.com/2004/102101-la-princesa-sac-nicte-leyenda-maya.php |archivedate=2014-02-23 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Important people ==
*[[Ah Ulil]]
* Ah Itzimthul Chac: a Batab.
*[[Chac-Xib-Chac]]: a ruler of [[Chichen Itza]].
* Hapay Can: was probably a ruler of Chichen Itza.
* Sac Xib Chac: a ruler of Chichen Itza.
* Chac Ek Yuuan: a ruler of Chichen Itza.
* Hun Yuuan Chac (also called uooh Puc): a ruler of Chichen Itza.
* Ix Zacbeliz: a queen of Chichen Itza.
* Zac Xib Chac: Chac-Xib-Chacs brother.
* Uayom-chich: a priest.
* Uxmal Chac: a Batab and a priest.
* Cabal Xiu: a priest.
* [[Hunac Ceel]]
* [[Ah Mekat Tutul Xiu]]: founded the league.
* [[Ah Xiu Xupan]]: started the war that ended the league.
* [[Mo-Chel]]: a nobleman from [[Mayapan]].&lt;ref&gt;http://holybooks.lichtenbergpress.netdna-cdn.com/wp-content/uploads/Book-of-Chilam-Balam-the-of-Chumayel.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ah Yamazi: Batab of Yobain.
* Xkil Itzam Pech: Batab of Kini
* The Pech family
* The Cupul family
* The Cochuah famil
* The Cocom family
* The Xiu family
* The [[Chel family]]: descendants of Mo-Chel
* The Canul family
* The Cauich family

== End of The League ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2018}}
[[File:Cacicazgos mayas - es.svg|thumbnail|The Kuchkabals of Yucatan after the league. The borders closely resemble those of the provinces that were there before. Calotmul was controlled by Tutul Xiu.]]
In 1441  [[Ah Xiu Xupan]], the great ruler of Uxmal, was given the task of making war on the royal family of the Cocom, whom he managed to kill. Only one of the Cocom, who was in Honduras at the time, survived and later founded Tibolón.
The war between Uxmal and Cocom plunged the League into chaos. There was segregation in the provinces and several uprisings broke out. By 1461 the league was completely disintegrated.

After the war Yucatan broke up into seventeen [[Kuchkabal]]s.

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:10th-century establishments in the Maya civilization]]
[[Category:987 establishments]]
[[Category:1461 disestablishments in North America]]
[[Category:15th-century disestablishments in the Maya civilization]]
[[Category:Former confederations|Mayapan, League of]]</text>
      <sha1>gdp1zjlxqt1hpovd8gmoslgbvj8s2nz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
